<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="gllssical" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">
  <brief>
    Perform Radiometric correction on GALILEO-SSI Imaging
  </brief>

  <category>
    <missionItem>Galileo</missionItem>
  </category>

  <description>
    This program is used to radiometrically correct flight images using a linear
    model of the light-transfer function.  This program is specific to the 
    Galileo SSI camera.
    
    References:
    
    1) D-4264 MIPL Software Structural Design for the Instrument Calibration
       of GLL SSI Science Processing.
    
    2) K. Klaasen, "Reduction in Number of Unique SSI Calibration Files",
       29 May 1987.
    
    3) 625-210,"Galileo SSI Calibration Report Part 1", K. Klaasen, H. 
       Breneman, November 1, 1988.
    
    
    This program will radiometrically correct the input image, converting the
    input DN values to some specified radiometric unit.  The program
    requires a radiometric file generated from calibration data acquired at
    the same filter position as the input image, and a dark-current file
    acquired at the same camera gain-state, frame-rate, PNI, and BPM
    settings.  Also, extended exposure mode frames require an
    extended-exposure mode dark-current file.
    
    This program extracts the filter position, exposure time, and frame-rate
    from the label of the input file to determine the required gain file
    to use.  The file $ISIS3DATA/galileo/calibration/gll_gain.sav defines the 
    gain file to use for the given filter, gain state, and frame mode.  The file
    $ISIS3DATA/galileo/calibration/gll_dc.sav defines the DC file to use for the given, gain
    state, frame mode, frame rate, blemish protection mode, clock mode, and
    extended exposure mode.
    
    This program performs the following processing steps on each pixel:
     
     1. The radiometric correction is applied:
    		e = z(d - dc)
        where z is retrieved from the Radiometric File and dc is retrieved 
        from the Dark-Current File.
    
     2. The output pixel is scaled to radiometric units R. 
    
    		           S1 	    K
    		r = e * -------- * --- (D/5.2)**2
    			A1(t-to)    Ko
        where
    
    	S1 = filter-dependent conversion factor from ft-Lamberts to
    	     I/F units for a reference distance of 5.2 AU from the Sun.
    	t  = commanded exposure time of the input image (msec).
            to = line-dependent shutter offset.
            K  = system gain constant for the gain-state of the image.
            Ko = system gain constant for the calibration file gain-state.
    	D  = target distance from the Sun (in AU).
    
     5. The output DN is usually in the range of 
        0.0 to 1.0. 
    
    If the uneven bit weighting correction is enabled, the input DN values (d) 
    will be corrected for uneven-bit-weighting due to the ADC.  If the input 
    dark-current file is in byte format (i.e. an individual dark-current frame), 
    then the correction will be applied to the dark-current as well. The current 
    correction table was supplied by Herb Breneman, 2 Mar 89, and is based on 
    1975 calibration data.
  </description>

  <history>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2008-01-09">
      Original version
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2008-05-13">
      Removed references to CubeInfo 
    </change>
  </history>

  <groups>     
    <group name = "Files">
      <parameter name = "FROM">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>Input file</brief>
        <description>
          Input cube file
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>
    
    <parameter name = "TO">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <pixelType>real</pixelType>
        <brief>Output file</brief>
        <description>
          Output cube file
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Settings">
      <parameter name="BITWEIGHTING">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <brief>
          Correct for uneven bit weighting
        </brief>
        <default><item>false</item></default>
        <description>Correct for uneven bit weighting</description>
       </parameter>
    </group>
  </groups>

</application>
