<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="map2map" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">
  <brief>
    Modify a cube's map projection
  </brief>

  <description>
    This program will alter the projection of a <def link="Cube">cube</def> which is already
    in a <def link="Map Projection">map projection</def> (ISIS <def link="Level2">level2</def> cube).
    Pixels are physically moved using either a nearest neighbor, bilinear, or cubic convolution interpolator.
    Usage examples of this program include:
    <pre>
      1.  Converting from Sinusodial to Mercator or any other
          supported projection
      2.  No projection change but altering projection parameters
          such as center longitude or standard parallels
      3.  No projection change but altering <def link="Pixel Resolution">pixel resolution</def>
      4.  No projection change but altering <def link="Latitude">latitude</def>/ <def link="Longitude">longitude</def> window
      5.  No projection change but altering <def link="Latitude Type">latitude types</def>,
          <def link="Longitude Domain">longitude domains</def>, or <def link="Longitude Direction">longitude direction</def>
      6.  Match the mapping parameters of another ISIS leve2 cube for
          comparison.
    </pre>
    <p>If you need to generate your own map file you can use the <i>maptemplate</i> program or alternatively,
    hand create a file using your favorite editor.  The map file need only specify the ProjectionName
    as defaults will be computed for the remaining map file parameters.
   </p>

   The map file can be an existing map projected (level2) cube.  A level2 cube has <def>PVL</def> labels
   and contains the Mapping group.  Depending on the values of the input parameters, the output
   cube can use some or all of the keyword values of the map file.  For instance, setting
   MATCHMAP = true causes all of the mapping parameters to come from the map file, resulting
   in an output cube having the same number of <def link="Line">lines</def> and
   <def link="Sample">samples</def> as the map file.  If MATCHMAP = true and the map file is missing
   a keyword like PixelResolution, the application will fail with a PVL error.  Setting
   MATCHMAP=false allows for some of the mapping components to be overridden by the user or
   computed from the FROM cube.

   <p>To learn
   more about using map projections in ISIS, refer to the ISIS Workshop
   <a href="https://github.com/USGS-Astrogeology/ISIS3/wiki/Learning_About_Map_Projections">
   "Learning About Map Projections"</a>.
   </p>
  </description>

  <category>
    <categoryItem>Map Projection</categoryItem>
  </category>

  <history>
    <change name="Kay Edwards" date="1986-09-27">
      Original version
    </change>
    <change name="Jeff Anderson" date="2003-01-15">
      Converted to Isis 3.0
    </change>
    <change name="Stuart Sides" date="2003-05-16">
      Modified schema location from astogeology... to isis.astrogeology...
    </change>
    <change name="Stuart Sides" date="2003-05-30">
      Fixed compiler error with uninitialized variable after adding -O1 flag
    </change>
    <change name="Stuart Sides" date="2003-07-29">
      Modified filename parameters to be cube parameters where necessary
    </change>
    <change name="Jacob Danton" date="2005-12-05">
      Added appTest
    </change>
    <change name="Elizabeth Miller" date="2006-05-18">
      Depricated CubeProjection and ProjectionManager to ProjectionFactory
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2007-06-22">
      Fixed typo in user documentation
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2007-06-27">
      Expanded options, fixed conversions when switching measurement systems (such as from planetographic to planetocentric)
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2007-07-31">
      Fixed bug with changing resolutions
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2007-08-09">
      Rewrote resolution handling code to be simpler and fix yet another bug.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2007-08-14">
      Fixed method of getting cube specific projection group parameters, such as the scale and resolution.
    </change>
    <change name="Jeff Anderson" date="2007-11-08">
      Fixed bug trimming longitudes
    </change>
    <change name="Stuart Sides" date="2007-11-16">
        Fixed bug when TRIM option was used and most if not all data was being
        NULLed.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2007-12-05">
        Fixed bug where user-entered resolutions could be ignored
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2008-04-18">
      Added the MATCHMAP option.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2008-05-13">
      Removed references to CubeInfo
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2008-06-13">
      The rotation keyword will no longer automatically propagate
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2008-06-23">
      Added helper button and improved error message
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2008-08-04">
      Changed MATCHMAP to default off and added exclusions. If MATCHMAP is true,
      the ground range and pixel resolution can not be set because they are to be
      taken from the map file.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2008-11-12">
      Moved the MATCHMAP parameter to the "FILES" parameter group. Fixed a problem with this
      program that caused null output images when the input longitude domain was inconsistent
      with the input longitude range in equatorial cylindrical projections.
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2008-12-11">
      Changed the parameters SLAT, ELAT, SLON, ELON to MINLAT, MAXLAT, MINLON,
      MAXLON in correlation with autimos.
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2008-03-12">
      Added a default path as well as a helper function for the MAP parameter.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2010-08-27">
      Made automatic calculation of longitude range more likely to succeed
    </change>
    <change name="Lynn Weller and Debbie A. Cook" date="2012-01-05">
      Updated documentation text, added glossary links, and improved compatability with Isis documentation.
    </change>
    <change name="Tracie Sucharski" date="2012-12-06">
      Changed to use TProjection instead of Projection.  References #775
    </change>
    <change name="David L Miller" date="2015-08-10">
      Fixed bug where map2map fails when missing Scale keyword in the MAP file. Fixes #2151
    </change>
  </history>

  <oldName>
    <item>nuproj</item>
    <item>newmap</item>
    <item>lev2tolev2</item>
  </oldName>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input cube to remap
        </brief>
        <description>
          The specification of the input cube to be remapped.  The cube must
          contain a valid Mapping group in the labels.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="MAP">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          File containing mapping parameters
        </brief>
        <defaultPath>$ISISROOT/appdata/templates/maps</defaultPath>
        <default><item>$ISISROOT/appdata/templates/maps/sinusoidal.map</item></default>
        <description>
          A file containing the desired output mapping parameters in PVL.  This
          file can be a simple label file, hand produced or created via
          the <i>maptemplate</i> program.  It can also be an existing cube or cube label
          which contains a Mapping group.  In the latter case the FROM cube
          will be transformed into the same map projection, resolution, etc.
        </description>
        <helpers>
          <helper name="H1">
            <function>PrintMap</function>
            <brief>View MapFile</brief>
            <description>
              This helper button will cat out the mapping group of the given mapfile to the session log
               of the application
             </description>
            <icon>$ISISROOT/appdata/images/icons/labels.png</icon>
          </helper>
        </helpers>
        <filter>
          *.map *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TO">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Newly mapped cube
        </brief>
        <description>
          This file will contain the results of the remapping.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="MATCHMAP">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>FALSE</item></default>
        <brief>Match the map file</brief>
        <description>
          This forces all of the mapping parameters to come from the
          map file.  Additionally, when the map file is an image the
          TO file will have the same number of lines and samples as
          the map file.
        </description>
        <exclusions>
          <item>PIXRES</item>
          <item>RESOLUTION</item>
          <item>DEFAULTRANGE</item>
          <item>MINLAT</item>
          <item>MAXLAT</item>
          <item>MINLON</item>
          <item>MAXLON</item>
        </exclusions>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Output Map Resolution">
      <parameter name="PIXRES">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>Defines how the pixel resolution in the output map file is obtained</brief>
        <default><item>FROM</item></default>
        <description>
          This parameter is used to specify how the pixel resolution is obtained for the output map
          projected cube.
        </description>
        <list>
          <option value="FROM">
             <brief>Read resolution from input cube</brief>
             <description>
               This option will automatically determine the resolution from the input cube.
             </description>
             <exclusions>
               <item>RESOLUTION</item>
             </exclusions>
           </option>
           <option value="MAP">
              <brief>Read resolution from input map file</brief>
              <description>
                This option will use either the PixelResolution (meters/pixel) or Scale (pixels/degree) in the map file.
              </description>
              <exclusions>
                <item>RESOLUTION</item>
              </exclusions>
            </option>

           <option value="MPP">
              <brief> Get resolution from user in meters per pixel</brief>
              <description>
                This option allows the user to specify the resolution in meters per pixel using the RESOLUTION parameter
              </description>
              <inclusions>
                <item>RESOLUTION</item>
              </inclusions>
            </option>

           <option value="PPD">
              <brief> Get resolution from user in pixels per degree</brief>
              <description>
                This option allows the user to specify the resolution in pixels per degree using the RESOLUTION parameter
              </description>
              <inclusions>
                <item>RESOLUTION</item>
              </inclusions>
            </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="RESOLUTION">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief>Pixel resolution</brief>
        <description>
          Specifies the resolution in either meters per pixel or pixels per degree
        </description>
        <minimum inclusive="no">0.0</minimum>
      </parameter>
    </group>

   <group name="Output Map Ground Range">
      <parameter name="DEFAULTRANGE">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>Defines how the default ground range is determined</brief>
        <default><item>FROM</item></default>
        <description>
          This parameter is used to specify how the default latitude/longitude ground range for the output map projected image
          is obtained.  The ground range can be obtained from the input cube or map file.  Note the user can overide the default
          using the MINLAT, MAXLAT, MINLON, MAXLON parameters.  The purpose of the ground range is to define the coverage of
          the map projected image.  Essentially, the ground range and pixel resolution are used to compute the size (samples
          and line) of the output image.
        </description>
        <list>
          <option value="FROM">
            <brief>Read default range from input cube</brief>
            <description>
              This option will automatically determine the mininum/maximum latitude/longitude from the input cube specified
              using the FROM parameter.
            </description>
          </option>
          <option value="MAP">
            <brief> Read default range from map file</brief>
            <description>
              This option will read the mininum/maximum latitude/longitude from the input map file.
            </description>
          </option>
        </list>
        <helpers>
          <helper name="H1">
            <function>LoadMapRange</function>
            <brief>Calculate Latitude/Longitude Ranges</brief>
            <description>
              This helper button will calculate and convert the latitudes and
              longitudes it finds in the input file if DEFAULTRANGE = FROM. If the
              DEFAULTRANGE = MAP, this will copy the latitudes/longitudes from
              the map files and calculate the unfound ones from the input cube.
             </description>
            <icon>$ISISROOT/appdata/images/icons/exec.png</icon>
          </helper>
        </helpers>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="MINLAT">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief>Minimum Latitude</brief>
        <internalDefault>Use default range</internalDefault>
        <description>
          The minimum latitude of the output map.   If this is entered by the user it will override
          the default input cube or map value.
        </description>

        <minimum inclusive="yes">-90.0</minimum>
        <maximum inclusive="yes">90.0</maximum>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="MAXLAT">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief>Maximum Latitude</brief>
        <internalDefault>Use default range</internalDefault>
        <description>
          The maximum latitude of the ground range.   If this is entered by the user it will override
          the default input cube or map value.
        </description>
        <minimum inclusive="yes">-90.0</minimum>
        <maximum inclusive="yes">90.0</maximum>
        <greaterThan><item>MINLAT</item></greaterThan>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="MINLON">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief>Minimum Longitude</brief>
        <internalDefault>Use default range</internalDefault>
        <description>
          The minimum longitude of the ground range.   If this is entered by the user it will override
          the default input cube or map value.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="MAXLON">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief>Maximum Longitude</brief>
        <internalDefault>Use default range</internalDefault>
        <description>
          The maximum longitude of the ground range.   If this is entered by the user it will override
          the default input cube or map value.
        </description>
        <greaterThan><item>MINLON</item></greaterThan>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TRIM">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>FALSE</item></default>
        <brief>
          Null all pixels outside lat/lon boundaries
        </brief>
        <description>
          If this option is selected, pixels outside the latitude/longtiude
          range will be trimmed or set to null.
          This is useful for certain projections whose lines of latitude and
          longitude are not parallel to image lines and sample columns.
        </description>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Options">
      <parameter name="INTERP">
        <type>string</type>
        <default>
          <item>CUBICCONVOLUTION</item>
        </default>
        <brief>Type of interpolation</brief>
        <description>
          This is the type of interpolation to be performed on the input.
        </description>
        <list>
          <option value="NEARESTNEIGHBOR">
            <brief>Nearest Neighbor</brief>
            <description>
              Each output pixel will be set to the pixel nearest the
              calculated input pixel.
            </description>
          </option>
          <option value="BILINEAR">
            <brief>Bi-Linear interpolation</brief>
            <description>
              Each output pixel will be set to the value calculated by
              a bi-linear interpolation of the calculated input pixel.
            </description>
          </option>
          <option value="CUBICCONVOLUTION">
            <brief>Cubic Convolution interpolation</brief>
            <description>
              Each output pixel will be set to the value calculated by
              a cubic convolution interpolation of the calculated input pixel.
            </description>
          </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>
    </group>
  </groups>
  <examples>
    <example>
      <brief> map2map example demonstrating use of MATCHMAP </brief>
      <description>
        This example shows how to use map2map to match a system LOLA DEM to a
        Clementine 750 base tile available from PDS.
      </description>
      <terminalInterface>
        <commandLine>
          map2map from=/usgs/cpkgs/Isis3/data/base/dems/LRO_LOLA_LDEM_global_128ppd_20100915_0002.cub
          map=clembase_30s135_256ppd.cub matchmap=yes
          to=LOLA_clembase_30s135_256ppd.cub
        </commandLine>
        <description>
          Command line to extract and reproject part of a dem to match a level 2
          image.
        </description>
      </terminalInterface>
      <guiInterfaces>
        <guiInterface>
          <image src="assets/images/map2map_matchmap_image_gui_p1.jpg" width="728" height="428">
            <brief> Top of GUI for map2map MATCHMAP example </brief>
            <description>
              The from file is a system LOLA dem.  The MAP is an Isis level 2
              image.  The output file will be a section of the dem extracted
              out and remapped into the same state as the level 2 image entered
              as MAP.  Because MATCHMAP is checked, all mapping parameters will
              be determined from MAP, and any listed in the GUI are grayed out.
            </description>
            <thumbnail src="assets/thumbs/map2map_matchmap_image_gui_1_thumb.jpg" width="200" height="117" caption="map2map MATCHMAP example GUI top" />
          </image>
        </guiInterface>
        <guiInterface>
          <image src="assets/images/map2map_matchmap_image_gui_p2.jpg" width="728" height="380">
            <brief> Middle of GUI for map2map MATCHMAP example </brief>
            <description>
              This is the middle of the GUI for the <i>map2map</i> MATCHMAP example.
              It shows everything grayed out in the output map ground range box
              because MATCHMAP was checked in the previous image.  The default
              INTERP is selected.
            </description>
            <thumbnail src="assets/thumbs/map2map_matchmap_image_gui_1_thumb.jpg" width="200" height="104" caption="map2map MATCHMAP example GUI top" />
          </image>
        </guiInterface>
        <guiInterface>
          <image src="assets/images/map2map_matchmap_image_gui_p3.jpg" width="728" height="330">
            <brief> Bottom of GUI for map2map MATCHMAP example </brief>
            <description>
              This is the bottom of the GUI for the <i>map2map</i> MATCHMAP example.
              It shows the state of the GUI when the application has completed.
            </description>
            <thumbnail src="assets/thumbs/map2map_matchmap_image_gui_1_thumb.jpg" width="200" height="90" caption="map2map MATCHMAP example GUI top" />
          </image>
        </guiInterface>
      </guiInterfaces>
      <inputImages>
        <image src="assets/images/FromFile_LOLA_global_DEM.jpg" width="496" height="496">
          <brief> FROM for map2map MATCHMAP example </brief>
          <description>
            This is a LOLA global dem stored in the Isis system.  A section of
            this file matching the coverage of MAP will be extracted and
            reprojected to match MAP.
          </description>
          <thumbnail caption="Input image (dem) to be reprojected" src="assets/thumbs/FromFile_LOLA_global_DEM_thumb.jpg" width="200" height="200"/>
          <parameterName>FROM</parameterName>
        </image>
        <image src="assets/images/MatchFile_Clem750_Tile.jpg" width="496" height="496">
          <brief>  MAP for map2map MATCHMAP example </brief>
          <description>
            This is a base tile from the PDS Clementine 750.
          </description>
          <thumbnail caption="Isis level 2 MAP" src="assets/thumbs/MatchFile_Clem750_Tile_thumb.jpg" width="200" height="200"/>
          <parameterName>MAP</parameterName>
        </image>
      </inputImages>
      <outputImages>
        <image src="assets/images/ToFIle_LOLA_Match_Clem750.jpg" width="496" height="496">
          <brief>  TO for map2map MATCHMAP example </brief>
          <description>
            This is a section of the LOLA global dem extracted and remapped to
            match a base tile of the PDS Clementine 750.  Notice how the
            geometry matches the geometry of the second input image above (MAP).
          </description>
          <thumbnail caption="MATCHMAP example  TO" src="assets/thumbs/ToFIle_LOLA_Match_Clem750_thumb.jpg" width="200" height="200"/>
          <parameterName>TO</parameterName>
        </image>
      </outputImages>
    </example>
    <example>
      <brief> map2map example demonstrating projection change, resolution change, and use of TRIM </brief>
      <description>
        In this example the polar portion of a Messenger/Mariner10 global mosaic
        is extracted and transformed to a PolarStereographic projection.  The
        pixel resolution is reduced from 500 m/pix to 1000 m/pix.  Also the trim
        option is exercised to null the pixels outside of the lat/lon boundary
        and generate a circular output image instead of a square.
      </description>
      <terminalInterface>
        <commandLine>
          map2map from=MessengerFlyby_Mariner10_blobal.cub map=npola.map
          to=MessengerFlyby_Mariner10_north_polar.cub pixres=map defaultrange=map
          trim=yes
        </commandLine>
        <description>
          Command line for map2map TRIM example.
        </description>
      </terminalInterface>
      <guiInterfaces>
        <guiInterface>
          <image src="assets/images/map2map_global_to_polar_gui_1.jpg" width="728" height="428">
            <brief> Top of GUI for map2map TRIM example </brief>
            <description>
              The FROM file is a Messenger/Mariner10 global Equirectangular
              mosaic.  The MAP file defines a PolarStereographic projection.
              The TO file will be the polar section of the FROM extracted out
              and transformed into a PolarStereographic projection.  Notice that
              PIXRES specifies that the resolution is to be read from the MAP.
              If the pixel resolution is missing from the map file, the
              application will throw an error.
            </description>
            <thumbnail src="assets/thumbs/map2map_global_to_polar_gui_1_thumb.jpg" width="200" height="117" caption="map2map MATCHMAP example GUI top" />
          </image>
        </guiInterface>
        <guiInterface>
          <image src="assets/images/map2map_global_to_polar_gui_2.jpg" width="728" height="425">
            <brief> Bottom of GUI for map2map TRIM example </brief>
            <description>
              This is the bottom of the GUI for the map2map TRIM example.
              It shows that the default map ground range will be read from the
              MAP.  If the ranges are not in MAP, the application will throw an
              error.  Also notice that the TRIM option has been selected.
            </description>
            <thumbnail src="assets/thumbs/map2map_global_to_polar_gui_2_thumb.jpg" width="200" height="116" caption="map2map MATCHMAP example GUI top" />
          </image>
        </guiInterface>
      </guiInterfaces>
      <dataFiles>
        <dataFile path="assets/IN/npola.map">
          <brief> View PVL mapping file </brief>
          <description>
            The is the mapping file that defines the output map projection.
            Since the default range is set to MAP as well, it also contains
            the desired lat/lon range of the output level 2 image.
          </description>
        </dataFile>
      </dataFiles>
      <inputImages>
        <image src="assets/images/FromFile_MessengerFlyby_Mariner10_global.jpg" width="496" height="496">
          <brief> FROM for map2map TRIM example </brief>
          <description>
            This is a Messenger/Mariner10 global mosaice in an Equirectangular
            map projection.  The north polar section of this file will be
            extracted and transformed to a Polar Stereographic projection and
            trimmed to the exact lat/lon range specified in the map file,
            forming a circle.
          </description>
          <thumbnail caption="Input image (dem) to be reprojected" src="assets/thumbs/FromFile_MessengerFlyby_Mariner10_global_thumb.jpg" width="200" height="200"/>
          <parameterName>FROM</parameterName>
        </image>
      </inputImages>
      <outputImages>
        <image src="assets/images/ToFile_MessengerFlyby_Mariner10_north_polar.jpg" width="496" height="496">
          <brief> TO for map2map TRIM example </brief>
          <description>
            This is the north polar section of the Messenger/Mariner10 global
            mosaic of Mercury in an Polar Stereographic projection and trimmed
            to the exact lat/lon range specified in the map file to form a circle.
          </description>
          <thumbnail caption="Output PolarStereographic projection of north pole" src="assets/thumbs/ToFile_MessengerFlyby_Mariner10_north_polar_thumb.jpg" width="200" height="200"/>
          <parameterName>TO</parameterName>
        </image>
      </outputImages>
    </example>
  </examples>
</application>
