<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="histitch" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">
  <brief>
    Merge a HiRISE channel pair to make a single image
  </brief>

  <description>
      <p>
    The program allows the user to combine two HiRISE channels to form a 
    single CCD image. Histitch will typically be run after radiometric
    correction and prior to geometric processing. The two input files 
    must be the individual channel files (channels 0 and 1) of the 
    same CCD observation.   The program will test to make sure the 
    Observation IDs and CCD IDs of the input cubes match, and that one
    cube is channel 0  and the other is channel 1. The program is clever enough 
     to figure out the channels associated with each input file and correctly
    order them in the output file.  Any ancillary data "blobs" 
    will not be propagated to the output file.  The channel number on 
    the output cube is set to 2 to signify that it is the combination of channels 
    0 and 1.
      </p>
      <p>
     histitch can create a CCD image if when only one channel is provided.
     The proper placement, left half of CCD for channel 1 images, right half for
     channel 0, is determined from the input file and the remainder of the CCD
     is filled with Nulls.
      </p>
  </description>

  <category>
    <missionItem>Mars Reconnaissance Orbiter</missionItem>
  </category>

  <history>
    <change name="Eric Eliason" date="2004-07-31">
      Original version
    </change>
    <change name="Elizabeth Ribelin" date="2005-02-22">
      Added obsevation id, ccd id, and channel number tests
    </change>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2006-02-22">
      Made FROM2 optional and allow creation of full CCD with just one
      channel file.
    </change> 
    <change name="Brendan George" date="2006-08-24">
      Added StitchedChannels keyword to Instrument Group, to identify
      which channels were used.
    </change>
    <change name="Brendan George" date="2006-09-01">
      Added StitchedProductIds keyword to Instrument group, to identify
      which images were used.
    </change>
    <change name="Brendan George" date="2006-09-28">
        Documentation fixes
    </change>
    <change name="Stacy Alley" date="2007-08-16">
        Added the balance option.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2008-05-13">
      Removed references to CubeInfo 
    </change>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2008-10-02">
      Added new EQUALIZE balance option that has utilizes new options WIDTH, 
      FILL, CHANNEL and OPERATOR parameters.  This new option applies a 
      line-by-line equalization of the CCD channels using and addative or 
      multiplicative option.
    </change> 
    <change name="Jeannie Walldren" date="2008-11-05"> 
      Replaced references to DataInterp class with NumericalApproximation.
    </change>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2008-12-08">
      Set  channel 1 (left) as the default to hold instead of channel 0.   
      Added reporting of results to label in the Histitch group.  Also added 
      creation of a Table of data when the EQUALIZE BALANCE option is 
      selected.
    </change> 
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2008-12-23">
      The BALANCE=TRUE option now honors the CHANNEL parameter and applies the 
      coefficient/ratio to the other channel.
    </change> 
    <change name="Steven Lambright &amp; Stacy Alley" date="2009-06-09">
      Added error checking to SKIP and SEAMSIZE parameters. Fixed problem
      with accessing out of array bounds.
    </change>
  </history>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROM1">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          First HiRISE Channel file.
        </brief>
        <description>
          This is the first of a pair of input HiRISE channel
          image files. This file can be either the channel 0
          or 1 file. The pair of input files must correspond
          to the the same observation of a HiRISE CCD.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="FROM2">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <internalDefault>None</internalDefault>
        <brief>
          Second HiRISE Channel file.
        </brief>
        <description>
            <p>
          This is the second of a pair of input HiRISE channel
          image files. This file can be either the channel 0
          or 1 file. The pair of input files must correspond
          to the the same observation of a HiRISE CCD.
            </p>
            <p>
              If the user does not provide a file for the second file, histitch
              will create a full CCD and map the FROM1 file into the proper
              location in the CCD.  This allows creation of the full CCD without
              both channels being required.
            </p>
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TO">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Output HiRISE CCD image.
        </brief>
        <description>
          The output cube is a HiRISE CCD image with the two channel
          files combined. The channel number for this cube is set  to 2.
         </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>
    </group>
    <group name="Balance Channels">
      <parameter name="BALANCE">
        <type>string</type>
        <default><item>FALSE</item></default>
        <brief>Option to balance channel 0 and channel 1</brief>
        <description>
            A feature which calculates the average on each channel and multiplies one side with
            the ratio of the averages
        </description>
       <list>
          <option value="TRUE">
            <brief>Balance On</brief>
            <description>
                Enables balance feature.
            </description>
            <exclusions>
             <item>WIDTH</item>
             <item>FILL</item>
             <item>OPERATOR</item>
            </exclusions>
          </option>
          <option value="FALSE">
            <brief>Balance Off</brief>
            <description>
               Disables balance feature.
            </description>
            <exclusions>
              <item>SEAMSIZE</item>
              <item>SKIP</item>
             <item>WIDTH</item>
             <item>FILL</item>
             <item>CHANNEL</item>
             <item>OPERATOR</item>
            </exclusions>
          </option>
          <option value="EQUALIZE">
            <brief>Line-by-line equalization</brief>
            <description>
                <p>
                    Enables line-by-line equalization feature.  This feature uses 
                    the SEAMSIZE and SKIP parameters to generate an average of each 
                    line for both channels.  These averages can be filtered (using 
                    an LPF) and missing data filled (using spline interpolation).  
                    The results can be subtracted or multiplied to correct for 
                    downtrack differences in the channels.
                </p>
                <p>
                    When this option is selected, an ISIS Table is created 
                    called HistitchStats.  This table contains four fields: 
                    Channel1Original, Channel0Original, Channe1Correction, and 
                    Channel0Correction.  If the MULTIPLY OPERATOR is selected, 
                    then one channel corrected column will be all 1.0.  For the 
                    ADD OPERATOR one column will contain all 0.0.  
                </p>
                <p>
                    The two original columns will contain the results of 
                    averaging the specified window with the values of SEAMSIZE 
                    and SKIP parameters.  The correction columns will contain 
                    the ratio (MULTIPLY) or additive (ADD) component of the 
                    correction that was appled to channel 0 or 1, whichever one
                    is not designated the hold channel  in the CHANNEL 
                    parameter.
                </p>
                <p>
                    The ISIS program <b>tabledump</b> can be used to extract the 
                    contents of this table to an ASCII file.
                </p>
            </description>
           <inclusions>
              <item>SEAMSIZE</item>
              <item>SKIP</item>
             <item>WIDTH</item>
             <item>FILL</item>
             <item>CHANNEL</item>
             <item>OPERATOR</item>
            </inclusions>
          </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="SKIP">
        <type>integer</type>
        <default>
          <item> 7 </item>
        </default>
        <minimum inclusive="true">0</minimum>
        <brief> Number of Pixels to skip on the edges of the image. </brief>
        <description>
          Number of pixels to skip on each side of the seam before the program 
          starts to accumulate pixel DN's to calculate the seam average value.  
        </description>
      </parameter>
    <parameter name="SEAMSIZE">
        <type>integer</type>
        <default>
          <item> 11 </item>
        </default>
        <minimum inclusive="true">1</minimum>
        <brief> Number of Pixels on the seam </brief>
        <description>
          Number of pixels (after skipping 'SKIP' number of pixels) used to 
          compute the averages on each side of the seam.
        </description>
      </parameter> 
      <parameter name="WIDTH">
        <type>integer</type>
        <brief>Width of filter to apply to line averages</brief>
        <default><item>0</item></default>

        <description>
          Specify the width of the filter to apply to both channel line 
          averages.  This is turned off with a value of 0.
        </description>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="FILL">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>true</item></default>
        <brief>
          Apply spline interpolation to channel line averages
        </brief>
        <description>
          Apply a spline interpolation to each line average to fill any gaps 
          that may exist
        </description>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="CHANNEL">
        <type>integer</type>
        <default><item>1</item></default>
        <brief>Specify channel to normalize to (hold as truth)</brief>
        <minimum inclusive="yes">0</minimum>
        <maximum inclusive="yes">1</maximum>
        <description>
          Typically, channel 1, the left channel, is held and channel 0, the 
          right channel, is corrected.  This option allows the user to select 
          which channel to hold.
        </description>
      </parameter>   
      <parameter name="OPERATOR">
        <type>string</type>
        <default><item>MULTIPLY</item></default>
        <brief>Option to balance channel 0 and channel 1</brief>
        <description>
            A feature which calculates the average on each channel and multiplies one side with
            the ratio of the averages
        </description>
       <list>
          <option value="MULTIPLY">
            <brief>Multiply channel line average corrections</brief>
            <description>
                Line average ratio is multiplied to the specified channel to 
                equalize the combined CCD channels.
            </description>
          </option>
          <option value="ADD">
            <brief>Add channel line average corrections</brief>
            <description>
               Line average ratio is added to the specified channel to 
                equalize the combined CCD channels.
            </description>
          </option>
       </list>
      </parameter>
    </group>
  </groups>
  <examples>
    <example>
      <brief> HiRISE image </brief>
      <description>
        This example shows the hiStitch application.
      </description>
      <terminalInterface>
        <commandLine> from1=IN/Channel0.cub from2=IN/Channel1.cub to=OUT/output.cub balance=true skip=7 seamsize=11
        </commandLine>
        <description>
         hiStitch gui example
        </description>
      </terminalInterface>

      <inputImages>
        <image src="assets/image/oldStitch.JPG" width="500" height="500">
          <brief> Input images for hiStitch</brief>
          <description>These are input images stitched together without the balance option on.
          </description>
          <thumbnail caption=" Input HiRISE images" src="assets/thumb/oldStitch.JPG" width="200" height="200"/>
          <parameterName>FROM1,FROM2</parameterName>
        </image>
      </inputImages>

      <outputImages>
        <image src="assets/image/newStitch.JPG" width="500" height="500">
          <brief> Output image for hiStitch</brief>
          <description> This is the output image with the balance option TRUE.
          </description>
          <thumbnail caption="Output image showing results of the hiStitch application." src="assets/thumb/newStitch.JPG" width="200" height="200"/>
          <parameterName>TO</parameterName>
        </image>
      </outputImages>

      <guiInterfaces>
        <guiInterface>
          <image width="741" height="841" src="assets/image/hiStitchGUI.JPG">
            <brief>Example Gui</brief>
            <description>Screenshot of GUI with parameters filled in to perform a hiStitch operation on the input images. </description>
            <thumbnail width="200" height="300" caption="hiStitch Gui" src="assets/thumb/hiStitchGUI.JPG" />
          </image>
        </guiInterface>
      </guiInterfaces>
    </example>
  </examples>
</application>
