<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="mat2cnet" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">
  <brief>
    Converts an ISIS2 match point file to an ISIS control network file.
  </brief>

  <description>
    <p>
      This program converts an ISIS2 match point file to an ISIS control
      network file.  It requires a list file of ISIS2 cubes and corresponding
      list file of ISIS cubes.
      <strong>Note: </strong> In order to identify which ISIS cube
      corresponds to a particular ISIS2 cube, these lists must be the same
      length and ordering.  That is, if the first cube of the ISIS2 list was
      imported from a particular raw image (observation), then the first cube
      of the ISIS list must be imported from the same image (observation),
      and so on for each cube listed.
    </p>
    <p>
      This application also requires a match point file, an output Control
      Network pvl name, a network ID, a target and a description.  The user may
      also choose whether to input a RAND PPP file containing latitude,
      longitude and radius for each corresponding point ID and to create an
      output RAND PPP log.  This program converts the radius values in these
      files from km to meters before adding them to the output control network.
      If a RAND PPP file is not entered, all the points in the MATCH file will
      be set to type Free.  If a RAND PPP is input, then any points not found
      in this file will still be set to Free and the user may choose whether to
      set points found in both the RAND and MATCH files to Fixed or Free.  Any
      points found in the RAND file without measurements in the MATCH file will
      not be included in the output control net.  The corresponding lines from
      the RAND PPP file for these points will be copied to the RAND PPP log.
    </p>
    <p>
      The following indicates how the ISIS2 Class is translated to an ISIS MeasureType
      <ul>
        <li> "T" (Truth) is translated to Reference</li>
        <li> "S" (SubPixel) is tranlated to RegisteredSubPixel</li>
        <li> "M" (Measured) is translated to RegisteredPixel</li>
        <li> "A" (Approximate) is tranlated to Candidate</li>
        <li> "U" (Unmeasured) is translated to Candidate and the measure is set to Ignore</li>
      </ul>
    </p>
  </description>

  <category>
    <categoryItem>Control Networks</categoryItem>
    <categoryItem>Import and Export</categoryItem>
  </category>

  <history>
    <change name="Brendan George" date="2007-08-10">
      Original version
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2007-12-14">
      Now IMAGE_NUMBER will be used before IMAGE_ID for matching files
    </change>
    <change name="Stuart Sides" date="2008-04-15">
      Fixed bug where serial numbers were not correct.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2008-05-19">
      Error message added for missing FSC's
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2008-07-01">
      Added exception message when the given MATCH file's "Matchpoint total"
      keyword is less than the number of actual Match Points in the file.
    </change>
    <change name="Jeannie Walldren" date="2009-11-06">
      Added RAND input parameter and updated documentation.  Added exception
      messages for invalid match point file headers and values. Added 1%
      Progress updates to show potentially slower steps. Added appTests for
      RAND parameter and to catch errors.  Added examples to xml file.
    </change>
    <change name="Jeannie Walldren" date="2009-12-17">
      Modify code to allow use of particular types of edited RAND files.
      Updated description of RAND parameter to reflect this change.
    </change>
    <change name="Jeannie Walldren" date="2010-03-21">
      Convert RAND radius values from kilometers to meters.  Added option to
    </change>
    <change name="Jeannie Walldren" date="2010-04-15">
      Added option to create RAND only points (no measures in the matchpoint
      file) as GROUND points.
    </change>
    <change name="Jeannie Walldren" date="2010-04-19">
      Modified error messages to output filename typed in by user rather than
      entire path.
    </change>
    <change name="Jeannie Walldren" date="2010-06-30">
      Changed CONTROL parameter name to CNET for consistency with other ISIS3
      programs.  Added INPUTPPP parameter. Changed parameter name from RAND to
      PPP for more precise description and modified POINTTYPE parameter usage.
      Added results to GUI log and added output PPPLOG parameter.
    </change>
    <change name="Jeannie Walldren" date="2010-12-01">
      Modified to be compatible with binary control network.  Modified errors app test Makefile.
    </change>
    <change name="Travis Addair" date="2011-04-11">
      Changed CNET to ONET and PPPLOG to LOG as per consistency wiki.
    </change>
    <change name="Debbie A. Cook" date="2011-06-07">
      Changed point types "Ground" to "Fixed" and "Tie" to "Free".
    </change>
    <change name="Jeannie Backer" date="2011-07-20">
      Clarified documentation.  Added POINTLOCK and MEASURELOCK parameters to
      allow the user to determine whether to EditLock points and measures.
      Added appTests for new parameters and gave more meaningful names to
      existing appTests.
    </change>
    <change name="Jeannie Backer" date="2016-04-22">
      Modified to use cube labels to set control net target if unable to set with only the user
      given TARGET. References #3892
    </change>
    <change name="Jesse Mapel" date="2018-07-06">
      Changed to just use the input target name because it is not needed to compute target radii.
      Fixes #5457.
    </change>
  </history>

  <groups>

    <group name="ISIS2 Files">

      <parameter name="LIST2">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          List of ISIS2 input cubes in the match point file.
        </brief>
        <description>
          A text file containing one column of ISIS2 cube file names. Every
          file used in the match point file should be represented in this list.
          <strong>Note: </strong> The cubes must be available for the program
          to open and must be in the same order as the ISIS cubes in LIST3.
          An error will be thrown if the number of files in this list does not
          match the number of files in LIST2, or if the IMAGE_ID and
          IMAGE_NUMBER keywords are not found in any ISIS2 cube.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.lis *.txt *.lst
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="MATCH">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
            ISIS2 match point file
        </brief>
        <description>
          Use this parameter to specify the ISIS2 match point file to be
          converted to an ISIS control network file.  This file must contain a
          two line header.  The first line of the header must have the
          "Matchpoint Total" keyword and a value for the number of measures in
          the match point file.  The second line of the header should be text
          labels for each column.  The match point file has 7 columns: PointID,
          FSC, LINE, SAMP, CLASS, DIAMETER, and Comments.  The Point ID is
          made up of alphanumeric characters,  FSC is an integer, LINE and SAMP
          must be doubles.  CLASS is used to determine the measure type.  Valid
          values include T (set to reference measure, validated manual), M
          (validated manual), S (validated automatic), or U (if line/samp=0/0,
          set unmeasured, otherwise set estimated).   The DIAMETER column is
          used in the case of a crater.  Comments are not read in to this
          application. A match point file may only have one line for a
          particular PointID/FSC combination, otherwise an error will be thrown
          since there is no way to determine which line contains correct values.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.mat *.dat *.txt *.tbl
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="INPUTPPP">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <brief>Input a RAND PPP file</brief>
        <description>
          This parameter indicates whether a RAND PPP (Pole, Point, Picture)
          file will be input.  Valid RAND PPP files for mat2cnet are detailed
          in the PPP parameter description.
        </description>
        <default><item>FALSE</item></default>
        <inclusions>
          <item>PPP</item>
          <item>POINTTYPE</item>
          <item>POINTLOCK</item>
          <item>LOG</item>
        </inclusions>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="PPP">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
            RAND PPP file containing latitude, longitude, and radius values for
            given Point IDs.
        </brief>
        <description>
          Use this parameter to specify the RAND PPP file to assign lat/lon/rad
          values associated with corresponding point IDs from the MATCH file.
          These files do not contain headers and have 4 unlabeled columns:
          LATITUDE, LONGITUDE, RADIUS, and PointID.  The lines of original RAND
          PPP files have exactly 79 characters, and columns are right justified
          with specific lengths, namely, 24, 24, 24, and 7.  The only edited
          RAND PPP files that are valid for this program are those that have a
          single space added between the RADIUS and the PointID. LATITUDE,
          LONGITUDE, and RADIUS values must be doubles and PointID is
          alphanumeric.  If this file contains a Point ID that does not exist
          in the match point file, it will not be added to the ControlNet
          output and the corresponding lines from the RAND PPP file will be
          copied to the LOG output file.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.ppp *.dat
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="POINTTYPE">
        <type>string</type>
        <default><item>FIXED</item></default>
        <brief>
          ControlPoint type for points found in RAND PPP and MATCH files.
        </brief>
        <description>
          This parameter determines the ControlPoint type to which points will
          be set if they are found in the RAND PPP file and have corresponding
          measurements in the MATCH file.  This parameter defaults to Fixed.
          <strong>Note: </strong> All points from the MATCH file not found in
          the RAND PPP file will be set to Free and all points from the RAND PPP
          file not found in the MATCH file will be omitted from the output
          Control Network.
        </description>
        <list>
          <option value = "FIXED">
            <brief>
              Set PointType keyword to Fixed for points in RAND PPP file
            </brief>
            <description>
              If this option is selected, any points in the RAND PPP file that
              has measurements in the MATCH file will have its PointType
              keyword set to Fixed in the output ControlNet.
            </description>
          </option>

          <option value = "FREE">
            <brief>
              Set PointType keyword to Free for points in RAND PPP file
            </brief>
            <description>
              If this option is selected, any points in the RAND PPP file that
              has measurements in the MATCH file will have its PointType
              keyword set to Free in the output ControlNet.
            </description>
          </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="POINTLOCK">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <brief>
          Indicates how to set EditLock keyword for points in RAND PPP file
        </brief>
        <description>
          This parameter indicates whether control points found in the RAND PPP
          file will be locked. That is, if this parameter is set to true,
          then each ControPoint in the output ControlNet that exists in the
          RAND PPP file will have the keyword EditLock set to true. This
          prevents any editing by most ISIS programs (with the exception of
          jigsaw) to the latitude, longitude, and radius values associated to
          the points in the RAND PPP file. Furthermore, the reference measures
          of each of these points will be treated as if they are locked,
          preventing any editing by ISIS programs to the sample and line
          values found in the match point file. This parameter defaults to TRUE
          and can only be used if the INPUTPPP parameter is set to true.
        </description>
        <default><item>TRUE</item></default>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="LOG">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <internalDefault>No Log Output</internalDefault>
        <brief>
          Optional RAND PPP log file.
        </brief>
        <description>
          This file will contain the Point IDs of all control points that were
          found in the RAND PPP file but had no measurements in the MATCH file.
          <strong>Note: </strong> This log is <u>not</u> a typical results log that
          contains the GUI log output.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.log *.txt
        </filter>
      </parameter>

    </group>
    <group name="ISIS3 Files">

      <parameter name="LIST3">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          List of ISIS input cubes in the match point file.
        </brief>
        <description>
          A text file containing one column of ISIS cube file names. Every
          file used in the match point file should be represented in this list.
          <strong>Note: </strong> The cubes must be available for the program to
          open and must be in the same order as the ISIS2 cubes in LIST2.  An
          error will be thrown if the number of files in this list does not
          match the number of files in LIST2.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.lis *.txt *.lst
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="ONET">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <brief>
          ISIS output control network file
        </brief>
        <description>
          Use this parameter to specify the file name of the output ISIS3
          control network.
          </description>
        <filter>
          *.net *.pvl *.ctl *.cnet
        </filter>
      </parameter>

    </group>
    <group name="Control Network Keyword Settings">

      <parameter name="DESCRIPTION">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>
          Set Description keyword to this value in output ControlNet
        </brief>
        <description>
          The Description keyword of the output ControlNet will be set to this
          string value. This should be a brief description of the control
          network file to be created.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="NETWORKID">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>
          Set NetworkId keyword to this value in output ControlNet
        </brief>
        <description>
          The NetworkId keyword of the output ControlNet will be set to this
          string value. The NetworkId is a single word identifier assigned
          to this particular ControlNet file. This string should be unique
          to this output file.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TARGET">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>
          Set TargetName keyword to this value in output ControlNet
        </brief>
        <description>
          The TargetName keyword of the output ControlNet will be set to this
          string value. This is the planetary body targeted in the images in
          the input file lists. The TargetName value should appear in all cubes
          used in the output ControlNet.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="MEASURELOCK">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <brief>
          Indicates how to set EditLock keyword for measures in MATCH file
        </brief>
        <description>
          This parameter indicates whether control measures found in the match
          point file will be locked. That is, if this parameter is set to true,
          then each ControlMeasure in the output ControlNet file will have the
          keyword EditLock set to true. This prevents any editing by ISIS3
          programs to the sample and line values associated to each measure
          found in the match point file. This parameter defaults to FALSE.
        </description>
        <default><item>FALSE</item></default>
      </parameter>

    </group>
  </groups>

  <examples>

    <example>
      <brief>Create control net from match point file</brief>
      <description>
        This example demonstrates how to use the  <strong>mat2cnet </strong>
        application to create a control network from a match point file.  In
        this case, no RAND PPP file is used.
      </description>
      <terminalInterface>
        <commandLine>
          list2=../IN/isis2cubes.lis match=../IN/matchpointfile.mat
          list3=../IN/isis3cubes.lis control=../OUT/controlnet.net
          description="Default Test Network" networkid= TestNet01 target=Titan
        </commandLine>
        <description>
          Run the <strong>mat2cnet</strong> application to create a ControlNet
          file from a match point file with corresponding ISIS2 cubelist and
          ISIS cubelist
        </description>
      </terminalInterface>
      <guiInterfaces>
        <guiInterface>
          <image width="750" height="539" src="assets/images/mat2cnetGuiEx1.jpg">
            <brief>Example Gui</brief>
            <description>
              Screenshot of GUI with parameters filled in to perform the
              <strong>mat2cnet</strong> application.  The RAND PPP parameter is left
              as the default of "None".
            </description>
            <thumbnail width="200" height="144" caption="Mat2cnet Gui using match point file" src="assets/thumbs/mat2cnetGuiThumbEx1.jpg" />
          </image>
        </guiInterface>
      </guiInterfaces>
      <dataFiles>
        <dataFile path="assets/match.mat">
          <brief>Example of match point file.</brief>
          <description>
            This text file is an example of a valid match point file with proper
            header and columns.
          </description>
          <parameterName>
            MATCH
          </parameterName>
        </dataFile>
        <dataFile path="assets/controlnet.net">
          <brief>Example of control net file.</brief>
          <description>
            This pvl file is an example of the output control network created
            from the given match point file.  Notice the NetworkId, TargetName,
            and Description are assigned the values from the command line.
          </description>
          <parameterName>
            CONTROL
          </parameterName>
        </dataFile>
      </dataFiles>
    </example>

    <example>
      <brief>Create control net from match point file and RAND PPP file</brief>
      <description>
        This example demonstrates how to use the  <strong>mat2cnet </strong>
        application to create a control network from a match point file and
        corresponding RAND PPP file.
      </description>
      <terminalInterface>
        <commandLine>
          list2=../IN/isis2cubes.lis match=../IN/matchpt.mat inputppp=true
          ppp=../IN/rand.ppp list3=../IN/isis3cubes.lis
          control=../OUT/control.net description="RAND PPP Test Network"
          networkid= TestNet02 target=Titan
        </commandLine>
        <description>
          Run the <strong>mat2cnet</strong> application to create a ControlNet
          file from a match point file with corresponding ISIS2 cubelist, ISIS3
          cubelist, RAND PPP file with a default point type of fixed.
        </description>
      </terminalInterface>
      <guiInterfaces>
        <guiInterface>
          <image width="750" height="539" src="assets/images/mat2cnetGuiEx2.jpg">
            <brief>Example Gui</brief>
            <description>
              Screenshot of GUI with parameters filled in to perform the
              <strong>mat2cnet</strong> application with a RAND PPP file.
            </description>
            <thumbnail width="200" height="144" caption="Mat2cnet Gui using intensity" src="assets/thumbs/mat2cnetGuiThumbEx2.jpg" />
          </image>
        </guiInterface>
      </guiInterfaces>
      <dataFiles>
        <dataFile path="assets/match.mat">
          <brief>Example of match point file.</brief>
          <description>
            This text file is an example of a valid match point file with proper
            header and columns.
          </description>
          <parameterName>
            MATCH
          </parameterName>
        </dataFile>
        <dataFile path="assets/rand.ppp">
          <brief>Example of RAND PPP file.</brief>
          <description>
            This text file is an example of a valid RAND PPP file.
            Notice that there are 2 points in this file to add.
          </description>
          <parameterName>
            PPP
          </parameterName>
        </dataFile>
        <dataFile path="assets/controlnet_rand.net">
          <brief>Example of control net file.</brief>
          <description>
            This pvl file is an example of the output control network created
            from the given match point file and RAND PPP file.  Notice the
            following: the first point in the RAND PPP file has 3 measures in
            the MATCH file and is written to the control network as type Fixed
            and the second point in the RAND PPP file is not contained in the
            Control Network since there are no measures with this ID in the
            MATCH file.
          </description>
          <parameterName>
            CONTROL
          </parameterName>
        </dataFile>
        <dataFile path="assets/randlog.txt">
          <brief>Example of RAND PPP output log file.</brief>
          <description>
            This text file is an example of the output RAND PPP log created when
            there are points in the RAND PPP file that do not have measures in
            the MATCH file.
          </description>
          <parameterName>
            CONTROL
          </parameterName>
        </dataFile>
      </dataFiles>
    </example>

  </examples>
</application>
