<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="tgocassisrdrgen" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">
  <brief>
    Converts CaSSIS cubes into PDS 4 standard format
  </brief>

  <description>
    "Tgocassisrdrgen" is an app that converts CaSSIS cubes, which are 3D images
    captured by the CaSSIS camera on board the European Space Agency's ExoMars
    Trace Gas Orbiter, into PDS 4 standard format.
  </description>

  <history>
    <change name="Adam Paquette" date="2017-05-23">
      Original Version
    </change>
    <change name="Makayla Shepherd" date="2017-06-01">
      Added detached label.
    </change>
    <change name="Adam Paquette" date="2017-06-02">
      Added the cassis specific translation file for label output.
    </change>
    <change name="Adam Paquette" date="2017-06-04">
      Changed the order that the elements appear in the output label.
    </change>
    <change name="Marjorie Hahn" date="2017-06-05">
      Added a default test to ensure that if the exported PDS4 data is reingested,
      then it is the same as the original cube.
    </change>
    <change name="Marjorie Hahn" date="2017-06-08">
      Moved code to write out .img and .xml PDS4 data to WritePds4 in ProcessExportPds4.
    </change>
    <change name="Kaitlyn Lee" date="2018-05-16">
      Added parameter PRODUCTID to set the ProductId keyword. If the product id is
      not specified by the user, set the ProductId keyword to the observation id.
    </change>
    <change name="Kaitlyn Lee" date="2018-05-21">
      Added the check to see if the input cube is a mosaic. If it is, instead of
      the Instrument group, the cube will have a Mosaic group. So, the ProductId
      will now be written to the Mosaic group.
    </change>
    <change name="Kristin Berry" date="2018-06-12">
      Updated to use the tgoCassisExportMosaic.trn translation file when the input cube is a mosaic.
    </change>
    <change name="Kristin Berry" date="2019-03-01">
      Added TITLE and VERSIONID optional parameters to specify these values in the exported PDS4 label. 
      Fixed bug that disabled reading of mosaics with Archive groups. 
    </change>
    <change name="Kristin Berry" date="2019-06-15">
      Updated logicalID and schema to new values. Add code needed to set the pixel description in the output
      file and to output the focal length without units as required by the cassis schema. 
    </change>
  </history>

  <category>
    <missionItem>ExoMars Trace Gas Orbiter</missionItem>
  </category>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input RDR CaSSIS formated ISIS cube
        </brief>
        <description>
          Input cube that is a CaSSIS formated RDR cube, to be translated into a corresponding .img
          file and associated detached pds4 label. Currently, the cube must be a CaSSIS specific cube to
          be translated at all.
        </description>
        <filter>*.cub</filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TO">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Output IMG file. Also determines XML file name.
        </brief>
        <description>
          Output IMG file where the image data will be. The value that is entered also determines
          the name of the detached XML label, where the .img extension is replaced with .xml.
          Example: test.img is entered, the detached label would be named test.xml
        </description>
        <filter>*.img</filter>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Keywords">
      <parameter name="PRODUCTID">
        <type>string</type>
        <internalDefault>None</internalDefault>
        <brief>
          Product ID value
        </brief>
        <description>
          Update the default Product ID value. This value will be the last section of the PDS4 logical_identifier value.
        </description>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="TITLE">
        <type>string</type>
        <internalDefault>None</internalDefault>
        <brief>
          Product ID value
        </brief>
        <description>
          Update the default Title value. 
        </description>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="VERSIONID">
        <type>string</type>
        <internalDefault>None</internalDefault>
        <brief>
          Product ID value
        </brief>
        <description>
          Update the default Version ID value. 
        </description>
      </parameter>
    </group>

  </groups>
</application>
