<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="barscale" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">

  <brief>
    Creates a bar scale for an image
  </brief>

  <description>
  <p>
    The barscale program creates a horizontal bar scale for a given image. 
  </p>
  <p>
    The bar scale is a bar graphic divided into portions and labeled with a unit
    measurement associated with corresponding ground length. It indicates, for
    example, the scale of an image or map. Many users find bar scales helpful to
    place on maps and images for publication so that observers can make a quick
    assessment of distance relationships.
  </p>
  <p>
  <b><u>How Barscale Works</u></b>
  </p>
  <p>
    This program uses the USGS standard as a guide for producing the bar scale. The USGS
    standard can be viewed at http://pubs.usgs.gov/of/1999/of99-430/of99-430_sec35.pdf.
    The program takes a projected or unprojected image file as input. If the image is
    unprojected, it must be initialized with SPICE information. This can be achieved by
    running the spiceinit program on the unprojected file. The pixel resolution 
    (PIXRES) is obtained either from the CENTER or from a user defined location in the image 
    file (USERLOC). The user determines the desired length of the bar scale and the unit of 
    measurement, either METER or KILOMETER, to employ. The length of the bar scale is 
    controlled using the LEFTLIMIT, LEFTSEGS, RIGHTLIMIT, and RIGHTSEGS parameters. The right 
    side of a bar scale is used to provide larger divisions of measurement and the left side 
    provides smaller divisions of measurement but is not required. The examples below are
    provided to demonstrate how these parameters are used.
  </p>
  <p>
    <u>Example 1:</u> To create a bar scale with no left limit and a right limit of 20 kilometers
    with 4 divisions: LEFTLIMIT=0 LEFTSEGS=0 RIGHTLIMIT=20 RIGHTSEGS=4 UNIT=KILOMETER
  </p>
  <p>
    <u>Example 2:</u> To create a bar scale with a left limit of 10 kilometers with 5 divisions
    and a right limit of 20 kilometers with 2 divisions: LEFTLIMIT=10 LEFTSEGS=5 RIGHTLIMIT=20
    RIGHTSEGS=2 UNIT=KILOMETER
  </p>
  <p>
  <b><u>Important Facts to Remember</u></b>
  </p>
  <p>
  <ul>
    <li>
    Ensure that the bar scale limits are set to a reasonable size based on the resolution of the 
    image. If the limits are set too small, the bar scale will not be useful. For example, if an 
    image has a resolution of 153 meters/pixel, then the result of setting the limit to 10 times 
    greater than the resolution will produce a bar scale that is only 10 pixels wide; this may or 
    may not be considered a useful bar scale. 
    </li>
    <li>
    The vertical height (in pixels) of the bar scale must be provided along with the font size 
    (in pixels).
    </li>
    <li>
    The width of the bar scale is dependent upon the resolution of the image and the RIGHTLIMIT 
    and LEFTLIMIT set by the user. It should be noted that the TEXTHEIGHT provided by the user
    to specify font height does not mean that the characters will be exactly that number of pixels 
    tall. The height of the text will only be about 75% of what is specified. This is because of 
    the way that fonts are defined. Each font has a certain number of pixels devoted to the ascent 
    above its baseline and to the descent below its baseline. Keep this in mind when specifying
    the height of the text for the bar scale.
    </li>
    <li>
    The BACKGROUND of the bar scale can be set to either BLACK or WHITE. 
    </li>
    <li>
    The text that goes with the bar scale can either go ABOVE the bar scale or BELOW it.
    </li>
  </ul>
  </p>
  <p>
  <b><u>How to Place the Bar Scale in the Image File:</u></b>
  </p>
  <p>
    There are two options for placing the bar scale in the image file. 
  </p>
  <p>
    <u>1)</u> Set the PADIMAGE option to false if the bar scale should be placed on the image at a 
    specified line and sample. The CORNERLINE and CORNERSAMPLE parameters need to be set to the upper 
    left corner at the bar scale's insertion point.
  </p>
  <p>
    <u>2)</u> Set the PADIMAGE option to true if the bar scale should be appended to the bottom of 
    the image file. The bar scale will be justified LEFT, CENTER, or RIGHT within the padding 
    depending on the user's choice.
  </p>
  <p>
    Please note that this program is designed to generate bar scales for localized images. This 
    program should not be used to generate a bar scale for a global image because of the drastic 
    resolution changes that occur across the expanse of a global image.
  </p>
  </description>

  <history>
    <change name="Janet Barrett" date="2013-01-22">
      Original version.
    </change>
    <change name="Janet Richie" date="2013-02-22">
      Documentation review.
    </change>
    <change name="Janet Barrett" date="2013-03-07">
      Updated code to meet standards. References #575.
    </change>
  </history>

  <category>
    <categoryItem>Utility</categoryItem>
  </category>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input cube file
        </brief>
        <description>
          This is the input image cube that the bar scale will be created
	  for.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TO">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Output cube file
        </brief>
        <description>
          This is the output file name.  The cube file will contain the bar
          scale.
        </description>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Bar Scale Options">
      <parameter name="PIXRES">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>Specifies the location to calculate pixel resolution</brief>
        <default><item>CENTER</item></default>
        <description>
	  Specifies the location in the image where the pixel resolution will
	  be calculated: the center of the image or a user-defined line and
	  sample in the image.
        </description>
        <list>
          <option value="CENTER">
            <brief>Get the pixel resolution from the center of the image</brief>
            <description>
              The pixel resolution will be obtained from the center line and
              sample of the image.
            </description>
            <exclusions>
              <item>LINE</item>
              <item>SAMPLE</item>
            </exclusions>
          </option>
          <option value="USER">
            <brief>Get the pixel resolution from a user defined line and sample</brief>
            <description>
              The pixel resolution will be obtained from a user defined line and
              sample in the image file.
            </description>
            <inclusions>
              <item>LINE</item>
              <item>SAMPLE</item>
            </inclusions>
          </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>
      
      <parameter name="LINE">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief>Line in image to calculate resolution</brief>
        <description>
          This is the line number in the input image where the pixel
          resolution will be calculated at.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="SAMPLE">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief>Sample in image to calculate resolution</brief>
        <description>
          This is the sample number in the input image where the pixel
          resolution will be calculated at.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="UNITS">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>Specifies the units of measurement to use for scale</brief>
        <default><item>KILOMETER</item></default>
        <description>
	  Specifies the units of measurement to use for the bar scale. Must
	  be METER or KILOMETER.
        </description>
        <list>
          <option value="KILOMETER">
            <brief>Bar scale unit of measurement</brief>
            <description>
              The bar scale will be created using KILOMETER as its unit of
              measurement.
            </description>
          </option>
          <option value="METER">
            <brief>Bar scale unit of measurement</brief>
            <description>
              The bar scale will be created using METER as its unit of
              measurement.
            </description>
          </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="LEFTLIMIT">
        <type>integer</type>
        <brief>Size of left side of scale in UNITS specified</brief>
        <description>
          If this value is greater than zero, then there will be a left
          hand side to the scale and the LEFTLIMIT will be the limit
          in UNITS of that side of the scale.
        </description>
        <minimum inclusive="yes">0</minimum>
        <default><item>0</item></default>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="LEFTSEGS">
        <type>integer</type>
        <brief>Number of segments in left side of scale</brief>
        <description>
          This is the number of segments that the left side of the
          scale will be divided into.
        </description>
        <minimum inclusive="yes">1</minimum>
        <internalDefault>None</internalDefault>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="RIGHTLIMIT">
        <type>integer</type>
        <brief>Size of right side of scale in UNITS specified</brief>
        <description>
          This value must be greater than zero. It is the limit in 
          UNITS of the right side of the scale.
        </description>
        <minimum inclusive="no">0</minimum>
        <default><item>1</item></default>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="RIGHTSEGS">
        <type>integer</type>
        <brief>Number of segments in right side of scale</brief>
        <description>
          This is the number of segments that the right side of the
          scale will be divided into.
        </description>
        <minimum inclusive="yes">1</minimum>
        <default><item>1</item></default>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="CORNERLINE">
        <type>integer</type>
        <brief>Line location of upper left corner of scale in image</brief>
        <description>
          This is the line in the input image file where the upper left
          corner of the bar scale will be placed.
        </description>
        <internalDefault>None</internalDefault>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="CORNERSAMPLE">
        <type>integer</type>
        <brief>Sample location of upper left corner of scale in image</brief>
        <description>
          This is the sample in the input image file where the upper left
          corner of the bar scale will be placed.
        </description>
        <internalDefault>None</internalDefault>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="BARHEIGHT">
        <type>integer</type>
        <brief>Height of bar scale in pixels</brief>
        <description>
          This is the number of pixels that will be used in the vertical 
          dimension of the bar scale. This value has to be at least 5
          to create a bar scale.
        </description>
        <minimum inclusive="yes">5</minimum>
        <default><item>50</item></default>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="BACKGROUND">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>Specifies the background color to use for the scale</brief>
        <default><item>WHITE</item></default>
        <description>
          Specifies the background color to user for the scale bar. If the
          background is black, then the lines and text will be white. If the
          background is white, then the lines and text will be black.
        </description>
        <list>
          <option value="BLACK">
            <brief>Bar scale background will be black</brief>
            <description>
              The bar scale will be created using a background color of black.
              All lines and text used to make the bar scale will be white.
            </description>
          </option>
          <option value="WHITE">
            <brief>Bar scale background will be white</brief>
            <description>
              The bar scale will be created using a background color of white.
              All lines and text used to make the bar scale will be black.
            </description>
          </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TEXTHEIGHT">
        <type>integer</type>
        <brief>Bar scale text height in pixels</brief>
        <description>
          This is the height in pixels of the text that will be written
          above/below the bar scale.
        </description>
        <minimum inclusive="yes">10</minimum>
        <default><item>50</item></default>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TEXTLOC">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>Specifies the location of text in relation to the bar scale</brief>
        <default><item>ABOVE</item></default>
        <description>
          Specifies the location of the text in relation to the bar scale. The
          text can be printed either above or below the bar scale.
        </description>
        <list>
          <option value="ABOVE">
            <brief>Print text above the bar scale</brief>
            <description>
              Print the text above the bar scale.
            </description>
          </option>
          <option value="BELOW">
            <brief>Print text below the bar scale</brief>
            <description>
              Print the text below the bar scale.
            </description>
          </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="PADIMAGE">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>FALSE</item></default>
        <brief>Add padding at bottom of image to hold bar scale</brief>
        <description>
          Determines if the bar scale will be written directly on the 
          image file at the line,sample specified, or if the bar scale
          will be written and appended to the bottom of the image file.
          The user will still need to specify the upper left sample of
          the bar scale. 
        </description>
        <exclusions>
          <item>CORNERLINE</item>
          <item>CORNERSAMPLE</item>
        </exclusions>
        <inclusions>
          <item>PLACEMENT</item>
        </inclusions>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="PLACEMENT">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>Specifies how to place the bar scale in the padding of the image</brief>
        <default><item>LEFT</item></default>
        <description>
          This determines how the bar scale will be placed in the padding that is added
          to the image. The three options are LEFT justified, CENTER, or RIGHT justified.
        </description>
        <list>
          <option value="LEFT">
            <brief>Left justify the bar scale in the padding</brief>
            <description>
              Left justify the bar scale in the padding at the bottom of the image. The
              bar scale will be placed so that the leftmost part of the bar scale (including
              text) is 10 pixels in from the left side of the image.
            </description>
          </option>
          <option value="CENTER">
            <brief>Center the bar scale in the padding</brief>
            <description>
              The bar scale will be placed in the padding at the bottom of the image so that the 
              center of the scale is at the center sample of the image 
            </description>
          </option>
          <option value="RIGHT">
            <brief>Right justify the bar scale in the padding</brief>
            <description>
              Right justify the bar scale in the padding at the bottom of the image. The
              bar scale will be placed so that the rightmost part of the bar scale (including
              text) is 10 pixels in from the right side of the image.
            </description>
          </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>

    </group>
  </groups>
  
</application>
