<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="cnetcombinept" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">

  <brief>
    Combine one to many control networks with common control points.
  </brief>

  <description>
    <p>
      This program will create a control network by combining control points
      from one or more control networks into single points that satisfy image
      distance criteria. It employs a more robust/direct technique than
      <em>cnetmerge</em>. This technique evaluates each control point in all
      input networks by finding all candidate merger control points who have a
      measure within IMAGETOL. Then, for each candidate point, the average
      distance of the measures in the candidate to a measure in the source
      point is computed. If the average distance to any measure in the source
      point is less than IMAGETOL, then the candidate point and source point
      are merged. The candidate control point is disabled so that it will
      never be considered for another merger and the now augmented control
      point is added back to the search pool for further merger considerations,
      which can occur when other common measures are considered.
    </p>
    <p>
       When all control points have been searched and all mergers have taken
       place, a new single combined control network is created.
    </p>
    <p>
        Note that this application can be ran more than once and directly on the
        output of any past run (in other words, you need only provide a single
        network, if desired).
    </p>
  </description>

  <seeAlso>
    <applications>
      <item>cnetmerge</item>
    </applications>
  </seeAlso>

  <history>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2015-10-11">
      Original Version
    </change>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2015-10-22">
      Corrected the count when SAVEMINS=TRUE.
    </change>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2015-11-13">
      Uses modified ControlNet class  which provides the ability to take
      ownership of all points in the control net efficiently. This is needed
      in order to ensure only a single copies of control points are utlized to
      minimize memory overhead.
    </change>
    <change name="Jeannie Backer" date="2016-03-11">
      Added program to ISIS package.
    </change>
    <change name="Jeannie Backer" date="2016-04-22">
      Modified to set the new control net's target and radii by using the input control net's
      values. References #3892
    </change>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2016-12-05">
      Modified merging algorithm and parameters. Fixes #4558.
    </change>
    <change name="Jesse Mapel" date="2016-12-06">
      Created new tests and updated documentation. References #4558.
    </change>
    <change name="Tyler Wilson" date="2017-06-29">
      Modified ControlPointMerger::merge function to properly hand combining control points
      that contain the same control measures in each point.  Fixes #4869.
    </change>
    <change name="Tyler Wilson" date="2017-06-29">
      Modified ControlPointMerger::merge function so that merged control measure types
      are set to candidate (except when they have the same reference measure).  Fixes #4870.
    </change>
    <change name="Tyler Wilson" date="2017-06-29">
      cnetcombinept now properly sets apriori lat/lon values to adjusted values.  Fixes #4772.
    </change>
    <change name="Jesse Mapel" date="2018-07-06">
      Removed calls to set control net target radii because they are no longer needed by
      the control network. Fixes #5457.
    </change>
  </history>

  <category>
    <categoryItem>Control Networks</categoryItem>
  </category>

  <groups>
    <group name="Input">

      <parameter name="CNETBASE">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <internalDefault>None</internalDefault>
        <brief>Master control network file to match</brief>
        <description>
          The base control network file to which others will be matched.
        </description>
        <filter>*.net *.cnet *.ctl</filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="CNETFROM">
         <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <internalDefault>None</internalDefault>
        <brief>Merger control network file</brief>
        <description>
          A control network that will be matched to the base (i.e. master) network.
        </description>
        <filter>*.net *.cnet *.ctl</filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="CNETLIST">
          <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <internalDefault>None</internalDefault>
        <brief>List of merger control network files</brief>
        <description>
          A list of control network file names that will be matched to the base (i.e. master) network.
        </description>
        <filter>*.lis *.txt</filter>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Output">
      <parameter name="ONET">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <internalDefault>None</internalDefault>
        <brief>
          Merged Control Network
        </brief>
        <description>
          The output Control Network, which is the combined result of the input
          networks.
        </description>
        <filter>*.net *.cnet *.ctl</filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TOSN">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <internalDefault>None</internalDefault>
        <brief>
          Write a list of all serial numbers contained in the network
        </brief>
        <description>
           Provided with a filename in this option, all the cube serial numbers
           that are contained in the network are written to this file as soon as
           it is determined in the processing.
        </description>
        <filter>*.lis</filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="NETWORKID">
        <type>string</type>
        <internalDefault>None</internalDefault>
        <brief>The NetworkId keyword value for the merged ControlNet</brief>
        <description>
          The NetworkId keyword for the newly merged ControlNet will be set to
          this given value. The Networkid is a single word identifier or name
          assigned to a Control Network.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="DESCRIPTION">
        <type>string</type>
        <internalDefault>None</internalDefault>
        <brief>The Description keyword value for the merged ControlNet</brief>
        <description>
          The Description keyword for the newly merged ControlNet will be set
          to this given value.  This should be a brief description of the
          purpose of the merged control network.
        </description>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Parameters">
        <parameter name="IMAGETOL">
            <type>double</type>
            <default><item>1.0</item></default>
           <brief>Pixel distance tolerance to determine merge of point</brief>
           <description>
             The acceptable distance, in pixels, for merging points.
           </description>
        </parameter>

        <parameter name="KDNODES">
           <type>integer</type>
           <default><item>10</item></default>
           <brief>Specify the leaf size of the kd-tree</brief>
           <description>
              Number of leaves in the kd-tree structure.
           </description>
        </parameter>

       <parameter name="SETAPRIORIBEST">
           <type>boolean</type>
           <brief>
              Reset the apriori surface point to best available
           </brief>
           <description>
               When TRUE, all points apriori latitude/longitude surface point is
               updated to use the best one available. This is often the
               resulting coordinate after jigsaw has adjusted the surface point.
           </description>
           <default><item>false</item></default>
       </parameter>

       <parameter name="CLEANNET">
           <type>boolean</type>
           <default><item>true</item></default>
           <brief>Remove all invalid or ignored control points/measures</brief>
           <description>
             <p>
                 When true, all invalid or ignored control points and measures
                 are removed from the output control network as one of
                 the main objectives of this application is to remove
                 redundancies and mimimize the size of networks. However, for
                 evaluation purposes, you can set this to false, which will
                 preserve all control points.
             </p>
             <p>
                 When specifying the minimum number of measures/control point
                 using the MINMEASURES parameter, any control point that does
                 not meet this criteria will also be removed from the netwrk
                 when CLEANNET=true, otherwise these points will be set to
                 ignored.
             </p>
           </description>
       </parameter>

       <parameter name="CLEANMEASURES">
           <type>boolean</type>
           <default><item>true</item></default>
           <brief>Remove all invalid or ignored control measures</brief>
           <description>
             <p>
                 When true, all invalid or ignored control points and measures
                 are removed from the output control network as one of
                 the main objectives of this application is to remove
                 redundancies and mimimize the size of networks. However, for
                 evaluation purposes, you can set this to false, which will
                 preserve all control points.
             </p>
             <p>
                 When specifying the minimum number of measures/control point
                 using the MINMEASURES parameter, any control point that does
                 not meet this criteria will also be removed from the netwrk
                 when CLEANNET=true, otherwise these points will be set to
                 ignored.
             </p>
           </description>
       </parameter>

        <parameter name="MINMEASURES">
            <type>integer</type>
            <default><item>0</item></default>
            <brief>Select minimim number of valid measures/point</brief>
            <description>
                 This allows users to disable points that have less than
                 MINMEASURES control measures/control point. For example, if you
                 want to flag all points as ignored with 2 measures or less, set
                 MINMEASURES=3. Points that don't meet this critieria are set to
                 ignore and are subject to the CLEANNET action requested by the
                 user (i.e., all ignored points are removed from the network if
                 CLEANNET=true).
            </description>
        </parameter>

    </group>
  </groups>
</application>
