<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="cnetcombinept" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">

  <brief>
    Combine one to many control networks with common control points.
  </brief>

  <description>
    <p>
      This program will create a control network by combining control points
      from one or more control networks into single points that satisfy either
      ground or image distance criteria. It employs a more robust technique than
      <em>cnetmerge</em>. This technique evaluates
      each control point in the combined network by applying a search of radial 
      spatial distance (in meters) to collect all points that may be of the same feature.
      This search will find a list of <em>candidate</em> control points, i.e. points
      that the algorithm has found might be matches. Distance statistics of common
      control measures from the image are computed using the source point and each
      candidate control point. The MODE parameter for this program specifies the
      maximum distance, in IMAGE (pixel units) or GROUND (meter units), allowed 
      to determine whether the two control points are measurements of the same 
      image feature. If the average of all common measures is less than or equal to
      the distance (in the given IMAGE or GROUND units), then all control 
      measures from the candidate control point are copied to the source control 
      point (increasing image match depth) and the candidate control point is 
      disabled so that it will never be considered for another merger.  The now 
      augmented control point is added back to the search pool for further merger 
      considerations.
    </p>
    <p>
       When all control points have been searched and all mergers have taken
       place, a new single combined control network is created. 
    </p>
    <p>
        Note that this application can be ran more than once and directly on the 
        output of any past run (in other words, you need only provide a single 
        network, if desired). 
    </p>
  </description>

  <seeAlso>
    <applications>
      <item>cnetmerge</item>
    </applications>
  </seeAlso>

  <history>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2015-10-11">
      Original Version
    </change>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2015-10-22">
      Corrected the count when SAVEMINS=TRUE.
    </change>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2015-11-13">
      Uses modified ControlNet class  which provides the ability to take 
      ownership of all points in the control net efficiently. This is needed 
      in order to ensure only a single copies of control points are utlized to 
      minimize memory overhead.
    </change>
    <change name="Jeannie Backer" date="2016-03-11">
      Added program to ISIS package.
    </change>
  </history>

  <category>
    <categoryItem>Control Networks</categoryItem>
  </category>

  <groups>
    <group name="Input">

      <parameter name="CNETBASE">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>           
        <internalDefault>None</internalDefault>
        <brief>Master control network file to match</brief>
        <description>
          The base control network file to which others will be matched. 
        </description>
        <filter>*.net *.cnet *.ctl</filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="CNETFROM">
         <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <internalDefault>None</internalDefault>
        <brief>Merger control network file</brief>
        <description>
          A control network that will be matched to the base (i.e. master) network.
        </description>
        <filter>*.net *.cnet *.ctl</filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="CNETLIST">
          <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <internalDefault>None</internalDefault>
        <brief>List of merger control network files</brief>
        <description>
          A list of control network file names that will be matched to the base (i.e. master) network.
        </description>
        <filter>*.lis *.txt</filter>
      </parameter>


      <parameter name="REFERENCE">
          <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <internalDefault>None</internalDefault>
        <brief>Cube file to use as a reference image for IMAGE mode</brief>
        <description>
          The reference cube for matching by image. 
        </description>
        <filter>*.cub</filter>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Output">
      <parameter name="ONET">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <internalDefault>None</internalDefault>
        <brief>
          Merged Control Network
        </brief>
        <description>
          The output Control Network, which is the combined result of the input
          networks.
        </description>
        <filter>*.net *.cnet *.ctl</filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="NETWORKID">
        <type>string</type>
        <internalDefault>None</internalDefault>
        <brief>The NetworkId keyword value for the merged ControlNet</brief>
        <description>
          The NetworkId keyword for the newly merged ControlNet will be set to
          this given value. The Networkid is a single word identifier or name
          assigned to a Control Network.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="DESCRIPTION">
        <type>string</type>
        <internalDefault>None</internalDefault>
        <brief>The Description keyword value for the merged ControlNet</brief>
        <description>
          The Description keyword for the newly merged ControlNet will be set
          to this given value.  This should be a brief description of the
          purpose of the merged control network.
        </description>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Parameters">
        <parameter name="MODE">
            <type>string</type>
           <default><item>GROUND</item></default>
          <brief>Type of control point merger to apply</brief>
          <description>
            The MODE parameter indicates whether to use ground or image coordinates to determine
            merge points. 
          </description>
            <list>
               <option value="GROUND">
                    <brief>
                        Use ground coordinates to determine merge points 
                    </brief>
                    <description>
                      Measure point distance in ground units (i.e. meters or kilometers).
                    </description>
                    <!--
                    <inclusions>
                      <item>GROUNDTOL</item>
                    </inclusions>
                    !-->
                </option>
               <option value="IMAGE">
                    <brief>
                        Use image coordinates from a specfied named reference 
                        cube 
                    </brief>
                    <description>
                      Measure point distance in pixel units.
                    </description>
                    <!--
                    <inclusions>
                      <item>REFERENCE</item>
                      <item>IMAGETOL</item>
                    </inclusions>
                    !-->
                </option>
            </list>
        </parameter>

        <parameter name="DISTANCE">
           <type>double</type>
           <brief>
               Specifies the radial search distance for merge candidates 
           </brief> 
           <description>
               The radial search range from the source control point to find all 
               candidate control points to consider for merging. This distance is 
               specified in meters. Users must carefully consider this value as 
               it must be large enough to include the maximum uncertainity in the 
               SPICE ephemeris data for all images. Note if the adjusted 
               latitude/longitude coordiate exists in the point, it will be used 
               to determine the ground coordinate, otherwise apriori 
               latitude/longitudes are used to compute distances from each 
               control point. It also should not be so small that it will not 
               find all the points of the same feature.
           </description>
        </parameter>

        <parameter name="IMAGETOL">
            <type>double</type>
            <default><item>1.0</item></default>
           <brief>Pixel distance tolerance to determine merge of point</brief>
           <description>
             The acceptable distance, in pixels, for merging points.
           </description>
        </parameter>

        <parameter name="GROUNDTOL">
            <type>double</type>
            <default><item>0.0</item></default>
          <brief>
             Specifies distance on ground to merge point if no common image measures .
          </brief> 
          <description>
             The acceptable distance, in ground measurements, for merging points.
          </description>
        </parameter>
        
        <parameter name="KDNODES"> 
           <type>integer</type>
           <default><item>10</item></default>
           <brief>Specify the leaf size of the kd-tree</brief> 
           <description>
              Number of leafs in the kd-tree structure.
           </description>
        </parameter>

       <parameter name="SETAPRIORIBEST">
           <type>boolean</type>
           <brief>
              Reset the apriori surface point to best available
           </brief>
           <description>
               When TRUE, all points apriori latitude/longitude surface point is 
               updated to use the best one available. This is often the 
               resulting coordinate after jigsaw has adjusted the surface point.
           </description>
           <default><item>false</item></default>
       </parameter>

       <parameter name="REJECTEDMEASURES">
           <type>string</type>
          <default><item>NOACTION</item></default>
         <brief>Tweek rejected measures</brief>
         <description>
           Determeines how to deal with rejected measures.
         </description>
           <list>
              <option value="NOACTION">
                   <brief>
                       Do not perform any action on non-normal measures
                   </brief>
                   <description>
                     If selected, the program will leave rejected measures with their current settings.
                   </description>
               </option>
              <option value="IGNORE">
                   <brief>  Set (jigsaw) rejected measures to IGNORE</brief>
                   <description>
                     If selected, the program will set rejected measures to Ignore.
                   </description>
               </option>
              <option value="REMOVE">
                   <brief>  Remove (jigsaw) rejected measures from point</brief>
                   <description>
                     If selected, the program will remove rejected measures from the control point.
                   </description>
               </option>
           </list>
       </parameter>

        <parameter name="MINMEASURES">
            <type>integer</type>
            <default><item>0</item></default>
            <brief>Select minimim number of measures that are valid</brief> 
            <description>
                 This allows users to disable (by setting measures as ignored) 
                 points that have less than MINMEASURES control 
                 measures/control point. For example, if you want to flag all 
                 points as ignored with 2 measures or less, set MINMEASURES=3. 
            </description>
        </parameter>

       <parameter name="SAVEMINS">
           <type>boolean</type>
           <brief>
              Save points that have less than the mininum measures
           </brief>
           <description>
               When TRUE, all points found to have the minimum number of            
               measures are set to ignore and written to the output control 
               network. When FALSE, they are excluded(removed) from the output 
               network.
           </description>
           <default><item>false</item></default>
       </parameter>
    </group>
  </groups>
</application>
