<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="Photemplate" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">

  <brief> 
    Create a PVL template for photometric correction
  </brief>

  <description>
    <p>
     This program creates a <def>PVL</def> template file to be used in 
     photometry-based applications, such as 
     <a href="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Application/presentation/Tabbed/photomet/photomet.html">
     <b>photomet</b></a>.  Each planet has different surface and atmospheric 
     properties requiring different model specifications. It is important to 
     set up the models with unique parameter values that apply to a specific 
     planetary body.  There are two types of correction models that can be 
     specified in this program:
     </p>
     <ol>
     <li> Photometric - describes the planetary surface of an image </li>
     <li> Atmospheric - applies to the atmosphere through which an image was acquired</li>
     </ol>
     <p>
     The normalization models are not specified in this program, but only three 
     models (albedoatm, shadeatm, and topoatm) apply atmosperheric correction.  
     Choose an atmospheric model only if one of the three normalization models
     listed above will be applied with the photomet program.  
     </p>
     <p>
     This program allows the use of a PVL file that contains preset parameter names for 
     different photometric and atmospheric models.  
     Within the GUI, the user may select a PVL file and then use the drop-down 
     menu to view the contents of the PVL file or to load the parameter values 
     from the PVL file into the appropriate parameter names in the GUI.  Note:  
     If more than one model for "PhtName" or "AtmName" are in the PVL file, 
     then the parameter values for the first model type encountered by the program 
     will be loaded into the GUI.  Review the parameter names and values to make 
     sure the correct options and values are displayed before executing the program.  
     Below are examples of parameter settings within a PVL file:
     </p>
<pre>
<b>PVL file examples: </b>
     
  Example 1:				Example 2:		  

  Object = PhotometricModel		Object = PhotometricModel
   Group = Algorithm			  Group = Algorithm
      PhtName = Lambert 		    PhtName = Minnaert
    EndGroup				    K = 0.5
  EndObject				  EndGroup
					EndObject
  
	
  Example 3:				Example 4:		     
  
  Object = PhotometricModel		Object = PhotometricModel
    Group  = Algorithm  		  Group  = Algorithm
      PhtName = Hapkehen  		    PhtName = Lunarlambertmcewen
      Wh = 0.52 			  EndGroup
      Hh = 0.0  			EndObject
      B0 = 0.0
      Theta = 30.0
      Hg1 = 0.213
      Hg2 = 1.0
    EndGroup
  EndObject
  Object = AtmosphericModel
    Group = Algorithm
      AtmName = Hapkeatm2
      Hnorm = 0.003
      Tau = 0.28
      Tauref = 0.0
      Wha = 0.95
      Hga = 0.68
    EndGroup
  EndObject
  
  Example 5:
       
  Object = PhotometricModel
  # For Mars red filter images
  # The phase angles at which the coefficient values for the Lunar Lambert 
  # Empirical L and the Minnaert Empirical K approximation are 
  # calculated, along with the brightness (phase curve) values at those
  # points (ALL ON ONE LINE!)

    Group = Algorithm
      PhtName = LunarLambertEmpirical
      PhaseList = "0.,10.,20.,30.,40.,50.,60.,70.,80.,90.,100.,110.,120.,130.,
                  140.,150.,160.,170.,180."
      LList = "0.946,0.748,0.616,0.522,0.435,0.350,0.266,0.187,0.118,0.062,0.018,
              -0.012,-0.027,-0.035,-0.036,-0.037,-0.031,-0.012,-0.010"
      PhaseCurveList = "0.1578,0.1593,0.1558,0.1484,0.1391,0.1292,0.1194,0.1099,
                       0.1008,0.09176,0.08242,0.07234,0.06165,0.05106,0.04091,
		       0.03137,0.02171,0.01038,0."
    EndGroup

    Group = Algorithm
      PhtName = MinnaertEmpirical
      
      # The numbers below are entered on a single line in the text file for each
      # parameter name (see $ISIS3DATA/base/templates/photometry/marsred.pvl).
      
      PhaseList = "0.,10.,20.,30.,40.,50.,60.,70.,80.,90.,100.,110.,120.,130.,
                  140.,150.,160.,170.,180."
      KList = "0.518,0.595,0.660,0.709,0.753,0.796,0.837,0.875,0.904,0.922,
              0.926,0.935,0.954,0.986,1.019,1.063,1.099,1.095,1.090"
      PhaseCurveList = "0.1574,0.1582,0.1546,0.1470,0.1375,0.1273,0.1174,0.1077,
                       0.09797,0.08750,0.07594,0.06466,0.05471,0.04665,0.03935,
		       0.03339,0.02642,0.01482,0."
    EndGroup
  EndObject 
</pre>

    <p>
      Below are equations for some of the photometric model functions, 
      where phase is the <def>phase angle</def>, and u0 and u are the cosines of the 
      <def>incidence angle</def> and <def>emission angle</def>, respectively:
    </p>


<h2><b><center>SURFACE PHOTOMETRIC FUNCTION</center></b></h2>
<br/>
<table border="1">
<caption><b>Available photometric models and equations</b></caption>
<tr>
<th>Photometric Model Name</th>
<th>Function Equation</th>
</tr>    
<tr>
<td> Lambert </td> 
<td> u0 </td> 
</tr>    
<tr>
<td> LommelSeeliger </td>
<td> u0/(u0+u) </td>
</tr>    
<tr>
<td> Minnaert </td>
<td> u0**K * u**(K-1) </td>
</tr>    
<tr>
<td> LunarLambert ("lunar" part is Lommel-Seeliger) </td>
<td> (1-L)*u0 + 2*L*u0/(u0+u) </td>
</tr>    
<tr>
<td> MinnaertEmpirical </td>
<td> B(phase) * u0**K(phase) * u**(K(phase)-1) </td>
</tr>    
<tr>
<td> LunarLambertEmpirical </td>
<td> B(phase) * ((1-L)*u0 + 2*L*u0/(u0+u)) </td>
</tr>    
<tr>
<td> Hapkehen (Hapke-Henyey-Greenstein)</td>
<td> No equation available </td>
</tr>    
<tr>
<td> Hapkeleg (Hapke-Legendre)</td>
<td> No equation available </td> 
</tr>    
<tr>
<td> LunarLambertMcEwen </td>
<td> No equation available </td>
</tr>    
</table>

<pre>
<b>References:</b>

Chandrasekhar, S., 1960.  Radiative Transfer. Dover, 393 pp.
Hapke, B. W., 1981. Bidirectional reflectance spectroscopy 1: Theory. J. 
   Geophys. Res., pp. 86,3039-3054.
Hapke, B., 1984. Bidirectional reflectance spectroscopy3: Corrections for 
   macroscopic roughness. Icarus, 59, pp. 41-59.
Hapke, B., 1986. Bidirectional reflectance spectroscopy 4: The extinction 
   coefficient and the opposition effect. Icarus, 67, pp. 264-280.
Kirk, R. L., Thompson, K. T., Becker, T. L., and Lee, E. M., 2000. 
   Photometric modelling for planetary cartography. Lunar Planet. Sci., XXXI, 
   Abstract #2025, Lunar and Planetary Institute, Houston (CD-ROM).
</pre>

<p>
See <a href="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Application/presentation/Tabbed/photomet/photomet.html">
     <b>photomet</b></a> documetation for additional information.
</p>
  </description>

  <history>
    <change name="Noah Hilt" date="2008-11-18">
      Original version.
    </change>
    <change name="Janet Barrett" date="2011-09-23">
      1) The entire user interface has been redesigned. The previous version of this 
      program made use of radio button lists to allow the user to choose a photometric
      model or an atmospheric model. In order to make the program more compact, the
      radio button lists were replaced with drop down menus. When an option is chosen
      from the drop down menu, the parameters that apply to that option are made visible.
      Parameters that don't apply to that option remain hidden. This helps to make the
      interface look less cluttered than it did when every parameter and every option
      were visible all the time. 
      2) The "NORMALIZATION" option is no longer available in this program. This program's
      main use is to create files with preset photometric and atmospheric values for use
      with various planets. The normalization models are not specific to individual 
      planets like the atmospheric and photometric models are. The normalization mode
      is only used in the photomet program, so this information now needs to be 
      provided through photomet.
      3) The PVL parameter was replaced with the TOPVL parameter. The PHOTOMETRIC
      parameter was replaced with PHTNAME. The ATMOSPHERIC parameter was replaced with
      ATMNAME.
      4) The BHAREF, HGAREF, and WHAREF parameters were removed because they have
      become obsolete.
      5) The Hapke Legendre (HAPKELEG), empirical Minnaert (MINNAERTEMPIRICAL), and
      empirical Lunar Lambert (LUNARLAMBERTEMPIRICAL) photometric functions have
      been added.
      6) Documentation describing the parameters is still central to the photomet
      program. The documentation will be moved into this program in the next ISIS
      release.
      7) Helper buttons were added to the FROMPVL to allow you to View a PVL or to Load
      a PVL. PLEASE NOTE: When loading a Minnaert Empirical or Lunar Lambert Empirical
      model from a PVL, only the first value will be loaded into the GUI. This is
      a known problem and will be fixed in the next patch or release to ISIS.
      8) ***NOTE*** The Minnaert Empirical and Lunar Lambert Empirical models do not
      load properly from a PVL file when using the Load Pvl helper button. This is
      a known problem and will be fixed in the next patch or release of ISIS.
    </change>
    <change name="Sharmila Prasad" date="2011-10-27">
      Added API's to display and output PVL information, specifically for arrays and 
    alphabetically organized the Photometric Model names.
    </change>
    <change name="Ella Mae Lee" date="2012-11-16">
      Improved the documentation, fixes #452.
    </change>
  </history>

  <seeAlso>
    <applications>
      <item>Photomet</item>
    </applications>
  </seeAlso>

  <category>
    <categoryItem>Radiometric and Photometric Correction</categoryItem>
  </category>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROMPVL">
         <type>filename</type>
         <fileMode>input</fileMode>
         <brief>
           Input PVL file with photometric parameters
         </brief>
	 <defaultPath>$base/templates/photometry</defaultPath>
         <internalDefault>None Specified</internalDefault>
         <description>
           Use this parameter to select an existing PVL filename that contains a 
	   description of the photometric properties of a planetary body. The 
	   information in this file will be merged with the information that is 
	   input through the user interface or command line to create the output 
	   PVL file.
         </description>
         <helpers>
          <helper name="H1">
            <function>PrintPvl</function>
            <brief>View Input PVL File</brief>
            <description>
              This helper button will report the information in the given input 
	      PVL file to the session log of the application, see text box at the
	      bottom of the GUI.
             </description>
            <icon>$ISIS3DATA/base/icons/labels.png</icon>
          </helper>
          <helper name="H2">
            <function>LoadPvl</function>
            <brief>Load Input PVL File values into the GUI</brief>
            <description>
              This helper button will take the values in the FROMPVL file and
              load them into their correct locations in the GUI.
             </description>
             <icon>$ISIS3DATA/base/icons/exec.png</icon>
          </helper>
         </helpers>
         <filter>
           *.pvl
         </filter>
       </parameter>
      <parameter name="TOPVL">
         <type>filename</type>
         <fileMode>output</fileMode>
         <brief>
           Output PVL file containing the photometric parameter values
         </brief>
         <description>
           Use this parameter to select or enter the output filename. If the 
	   file already exists it will be overwritten. The ".pvl" extension is 
	   automatically appended to the filename if no extension is entered.
         </description>
         <filter>
           *.pvl
         </filter>
       </parameter>
    </group>
    
    <group name="Photometric Parameters">
      <parameter name="PHTNAME">
        <type>combo</type>
        <brief>
          Photometric model to be used
        </brief>
        <description>
          This is the name of the surface photometric function model to use
	  to apply the photometric correction.  Both the abbreviated names 
	  and the full model names are valid entries.
        </description>
        <internalDefault>FROMPVL</internalDefault>
        <default>
          <item>FROMPVL</item>
        </default>
        <list>
          <option value="FROMPVL">
            <brief>Get photometric model from PVL file</brief>
            <description>
	      Get the photometric model from the PVL file.  Add any missing
	      parameters to the PVL file, or enter the values on the command
	      line or use the GUI to enter the values.
            </description>
            <exclusions>
              <item>THETA</item>
              <item>WH</item>
              <item>HG1</item>
              <item>HG2</item>
              <item>HH</item>
              <item>B0</item>
              <item>BH</item>
              <item>CH</item>
              <item>L</item>
              <item>K</item>
              <item>PHASELIST</item>
              <item>KLIST</item>
              <item>LLIST</item>
              <item>PHASECURVELIST</item>
            </exclusions>
          </option>

          <option value="HAPKEHEN">
            <brief>
              Hapke-Henyey-Greenstein photometric model
            </brief>
            <description>
	      Derive model albedo using complete Hapke model with Henyey-Greenstein 
	      single-particle phase function whose coefficients are hg1 and hg2, 
	      plus single scattering <def>albedo</def> wh, opposition surge parameters hh 
	      and b0, and macroscopic roughness theta.   For a smooth model with opposition
	      effect use theta=0.
            </description>
            <inclusions>
              <item>THETA</item>
              <item>WH</item>
              <item>HG1</item>
              <item>HG2</item>
              <item>HH</item>
              <item>B0</item>
            </inclusions>
            <exclusions>
              <item>BH</item>
              <item>CH</item>
              <item>L</item>
              <item>K</item>
              <item>PHASELIST</item>
              <item>KLIST</item>
              <item>LLIST</item>
              <item>PHASECURVELIST</item>
            </exclusions>
          </option>
          <option value="HAPKELEG">
            <brief>
              Hapke-Legendre photometric model
            </brief>
            <description>
              Derive model albedo using complete Hapke model with Henyey Legendre 
	      two-term Legendre polynomial phase function whose coefficients are bh 
	      and ch, plus single scattering albedo wh, opposition surge parameters 
	      hh and b0, and macroscopic roughness theta.  
            </description>
            <inclusions>
              <item>THETA</item>
              <item>WH</item>
              <item>BH</item>
              <item>CH</item>
              <item>HH</item>
              <item>B0</item>
            </inclusions>
            <exclusions>
              <item>HG1</item>
              <item>HG2</item>
              <item>L</item>
              <item>K</item>
              <item>PHASELIST</item>
              <item>KLIST</item>
              <item>LLIST</item>
              <item>PHASECURVELIST</item>
            </exclusions>
          </option>

          <option value="LAMBERT">
            <brief>
              Lambert photometric model
            </brief>
            <description>
              Simple photometric model which predicts that light incident on 
	      a surface is scattered uniformly in all directions; the total 
	      amount of reflected light depends on the <def>incidence angle</def>
	      of the illumination. This function does not depend upon the
	      outgoing light direction.
            </description>
            <exclusions>
              <item>THETA</item>
              <item>WH</item>
              <item>HG1</item>
              <item>HG2</item>
              <item>HH</item>
              <item>B0</item>
              <item>BH</item>
              <item>CH</item>
              <item>L</item>
              <item>K</item>
              <item>PHASELIST</item>
              <item>KLIST</item>
              <item>LLIST</item>
              <item>PHASECURVELIST</item>
            </exclusions>
          </option>
          <option value="LOMMELSEELIGER">
            <brief>
              Lommel-Seeliger photometric model
            </brief>
            <description>
              This model takes into account the <def>radiance</def> that results from
              single scattering (scattering of collimated incident light) and
	      does not take into account the radiance that results from multiple
	      scattering (scattering of diffuse light which has made its way
	      indirectly to the same position by being scattered one or more
	      times). This model depends on the incidence and emission angles.
	    </description>
            <exclusions>
              <item>THETA</item>
              <item>WH</item>
              <item>HG1</item>
              <item>HG2</item>
              <item>BH</item>
              <item>CH</item>
              <item>HH</item>
              <item>B0</item>
              <item>L</item>
              <item>K</item>
              <item>PHASELIST</item>
              <item>KLIST</item>
              <item>LLIST</item>
              <item>PHASECURVELIST</item>
            </exclusions>
          </option>
          <option value="LUNARLAMBERT">
            <brief>
              Lunar Lambert photometric model
            </brief>
            <description>
              This model combines a weighted sum of the LommelSeeliger and
              Lambert models. Given a suitable value for the LunarLambert
	      function weight, L, this model fits the true <def>reflectance</def> behavior
	      of many planetary surfaces equally well as the Hapke model. This
	      model also depends on the incidence and emission angles.
	    </description>
            <inclusions>
              <item>L</item>
            </inclusions>
            <exclusions>
              <item>THETA</item>
              <item>WH</item>
              <item>HG1</item>
              <item>HG2</item>
              <item>BH</item>
              <item>CH</item>
              <item>HH</item>
              <item>B0</item>
              <item>K</item>
              <item>PHASELIST</item>
              <item>KLIST</item>
              <item>LLIST</item>
              <item>PHASECURVELIST</item>
            </exclusions>
          </option>
          <option value="LUNARLAMBERTEMPIRICAL">
            <brief>
              Lunar Lambert Empirical photometric model
            </brief>
            <description>
              This model combines a weighted sum of the LommelSeeliger and
              Lambert models. Given a suitable value for the LunarLambert
	      function weight, L, this model fits the true reflectance behavior
	      of many planetary surfaces equally well as the Hapke model. 
	      This model also depends on the incidence and emission angles.
            </description>
            <inclusions>
              <item>PHASELIST</item>
              <item>LLIST</item>
              <item>PHASECURVELIST</item>
            </inclusions>
            <exclusions>
              <item>THETA</item>
              <item>WH</item>
              <item>HG1</item>
              <item>HG2</item>
              <item>BH</item>
              <item>CH</item>
              <item>HH</item>
              <item>B0</item>
              <item>K</item>
              <item>L</item>
              <item>KLIST</item>
            </exclusions>
          </option>
          <option value="LUNARLAMBERTMCEWEN">
            <brief>
              Lunar Lambert-McEwen photometric model
            </brief>
            <description>
              This model was developed specifically for use with the Moon to be 
	      used in conjunction with the MoonAlbedo normalization model.
            </description>
            <exclusions>
              <item>THETA</item>
              <item>WH</item>
              <item>HG1</item>
              <item>HG2</item>
              <item>BH</item>
              <item>CH</item>
              <item>HH</item>
              <item>B0</item>
              <item>L</item>
              <item>K</item>
              <item>PHASELIST</item>
              <item>KLIST</item>
              <item>LLIST</item>
              <item>PHASECURVELIST</item>
            </exclusions>
          </option>
          <option value="MINNAERT">
            <brief>
              Minnaert photometric model
            </brief>
            <description>
              This model combines a weighted sum of the LommelSeeliger and
              Lambert models. Given a suitable value for the LunarLambert
	      function weight, L, this model fits the true <def>reflectance</def> behavior
	      of many planetary surfaces equally well as the Hapke model. This
	      model also depends on the incidence and emission angles.  
            </description>
            <inclusions>
              <item>K</item>
            </inclusions>
            <exclusions>
              <item>THETA</item>
              <item>WH</item>
              <item>HG1</item>
              <item>HG2</item>
              <item>BH</item>
              <item>CH</item>
              <item>HH</item>
              <item>B0</item>
              <item>L</item>
              <item>PHASELIST</item>
              <item>KLIST</item>
              <item>LLIST</item>
              <item>PHASECURVELIST</item>
            </exclusions>
          </option>
          <option value="MINNAERTEMPIRICAL">
            <brief>
              Minnaert Empirical photometric model
            </brief>
            <description>
              This model combines a weighted sum of the LommelSeeliger and
              Lambert models. Given a suitable value for the LunarLambert
	      function weight, L, this model fits the true reflectance behavior
	      of many planetary surfaces equally well as the Hapke model. This
	      model also depends on the incidence and emission angles.
            </description>
            <inclusions>
              <item>PHASELIST</item>
              <item>KLIST</item>
              <item>PHASECURVELIST</item>
            </inclusions>
            <exclusions>
              <item>THETA</item>
              <item>WH</item>
              <item>HG1</item>
              <item>HG2</item>
              <item>BH</item>
              <item>CH</item>
              <item>HH</item>
              <item>B0</item>
              <item>K</item>
              <item>L</item>
              <item>LLIST</item>
            </exclusions>
          </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>
    
      <parameter name="THETA">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>
          Macroscopic roughness angle
        </brief>
        <default><item>None Specified</item></default>
        <internalDefault>None Specified</internalDefault>
        <description>
          The "macroscopic roughness" of the surface as it affects
	  the photometric behavior, used for Hapkehen or Hapkeleg.  
	  This is the RMS slope at scales larger than 
	  the distance photons penetrate the surface but smaller than a pixel.
	  The roughness correction, which will be evaluated if theta is given 
	  any value other than 0.0, but is extremely slow. See Hapke (1986).  
        </description>
        <minimum inclusive="yes">0.0</minimum>
        <maximum inclusive="yes">90.0</maximum>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="WH">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>
          Single scattering albedo
        </brief>
        <default><item>None Specified</item></default>
        <internalDefault>None Specified</internalDefault>
        <description>
          The Hapke single scattering <def>albedo</def> of surface particles, 
	  see Hapke (1981).
        </description>
        <minimum inclusive="no">0.0</minimum>
        <maximum inclusive="yes">1.0</maximum>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="HG1">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>
          Hapke Henyey Greenstein coefficient
        </brief>
        <default><item>None Specified</item></default>
        <internalDefault>None Specified</internalDefault>
        <description>
          Asymmetry parameter used in Hapke Henyey Greenstein model
	  for the scattering phase function of single particles in the
	  surface.  See Hapke (1981).  The two-parameter Henyey Greenstein
	  function is:<br/>
          <blockquote>
	  P(phase)=(1-hg2) * (1-hg1**2)/(1+hg1**2+2*hg1*cos(phase))**1.5 
	  + hg2  * (1-hg1**2)/(1+hg1**2-2*hg1*cos(phase))**1.5
	  </blockquote>
        </description>
        <minimum inclusive="no">-1.0</minimum>
        <maximum inclusive="no">1.0</maximum>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="HG2">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>
          Hapke Henyey Greenstein coefficient
        </brief>
        <default><item>None Specified</item></default>
        <internalDefault>None Specified</internalDefault>
        <description>
          The Hapke Henyey Greenstein coefficient for single particle phase
          function.  Second parameter of the two-parameter Henyey-Greenstein
	  model for the scattering phase function of single particles in the 
	  surface.  This parameter controls the proportions in a linear 
	  mixture of ordinary Heneyey Greenstein phase functions with asymmetry 
	  parameters equal to +hg1 and -hg1.  See HG1 for the full formula.
        </description>
        <minimum inclusive="yes">0.0</minimum>
        <maximum inclusive="yes">1.0</maximum>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="BH">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>
          The Hapke Legendre coefficient for single particle phase function.  
        </brief>
        <default><item>None Specified</item></default>
        <internalDefault>None Specified</internalDefault>
        <description>
          The Hapke Legendre coefficient for single particle phase 
          function.  A two-term Legendre polynomial is used for the scattering 
	  phase function of single particles in the surface: <br/>
	  <blockquote>
	  P(phase) = 1 + bh * p1(cos(phase)) + ch * p2(cos(phase)) <br/>
	  </blockquote>
	  Bh is not to be confused with the legendre coefficient bha
	  of the phase function for atmospheric particles, used when 
	  atmname=anisotropic1 or anisotropic2.
        </description>
        <minimum inclusive="no">-1.0</minimum>
        <maximum inclusive="no">1.0</maximum>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="CH">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>
          Hapke Legendre coefficient
        </brief>
        <default><item>None Specified</item></default>
        <internalDefault>None Specified</internalDefault>
        <description>
          The Hapke Legendre coefficient for single particle phase
          function.  A two-term Legendre polynomial is used for the scattering 
	  phase function of single particles in the surface: <br/>
	  <blockquote>
          P(phase) = 1 + bh * p1(cos(phase)) + ch * p2(cos(phase))
	  </blockquote>
        </description>
        <minimum inclusive="no">-1.0</minimum>
        <maximum inclusive="no">1.0</maximum>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="HH">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>
          Hapke opposition surge 
        </brief>
        <default><item>None Specified</item></default>
        <internalDefault>None Specified</internalDefault>
        <description>
          The Hapke opposition surge component.  The width parameter for the 
	  opposition effect for the surface if Hapkehen or Hapkeleg is used.  
	  See Hapke (1984).
        </description>
        <minimum inclusive="yes">0.0</minimum>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="B0">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>
          Hapke opposition surge
        </brief>
        <default><item>None Specified</item></default>
        <internalDefault>None Specified</internalDefault>
        <description>
          The Hapke opposition surge component.  The magnitude of the opposition
	  effect for the surface if Hapkehen or Hapkeleg is used.  See Hapke (1984).
        </description>
        <minimum inclusive="yes">0.0</minimum>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="ZEROB0ST">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>
          Specifies if opposition surge is set to zero under standard conditions
        </brief>
         <default><item>TRUE</item></default>
        <description>
          This specifies if the opposition surge component B0 is set to zero
          during the standard conditions phase.  The program will automatically
	  default to "TRUE" if "ZEROBST" is not defined by the user.
        </description>
        <list>
          <option value="READFROMPVL">
            <brief>
              Get ZEROB0ST value from the FROMPVL file
            </brief>
            <description>
              Retrieve and set the ZEROB0ST parameter from the FROMPVL file. If
              a FROMPVL file is not provided, then an error will occur.
            </description>
          </option>
          <option value="FALSE">
            <brief>
              B0 will not be set to zero for standard conditions phase
            </brief>
            <description>
              This option specifies that the opposition surge B0 will not be set to zero 
              during the standard conditions phase.
            </description>
          </option>
          <option value="TRUE">
            <brief>
              B0 will be set to zero for standard conditions phase 
            </brief>
            <description>
              This option specifies that the opposition surge B0 will be set to zero
              during the standard conditions phase.
            </description>
          </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="L">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>
          Lunar-Lambert function weight
        </brief>
        <default><item>None Specified</item></default>
        <internalDefault>None Specified</internalDefault>
        <description>
          The Lunar Lambert function weight that governs limb-darkening 
	  in the lunar lambert photometric function: 
	  <blockquote>
	  Func=(1-L)*u0 + 2*L*u0/(u0+u)
	  </blockquote>
	  The values generally fall in the range from 0 (Lambert function) to 1 
	  (Lommel-Seeliger or "lunar" function).
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="K">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>
          Minnaert function exponent
        </brief>
        <default><item>None Specified</item></default>
        <internalDefault>None Specified</internalDefault>
        <description>
          The Minnaert function exponent that governs limb-darkening in the 
	  Minnaert photometric function: 
	  <blockquote>
	  Func = u0**K * u**(K-1)
	  </blockquote>
	  The values generally fall in the range from 0.5 ("lunar-like", 
	  almost no limb darkening) to 1.0 (Lambert function).
        </description>
        <minimum inclusive="yes">0.0</minimum>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="PHASELIST">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>
          Empirical functions phase angle list
        </brief>
        <description>
          The Minnaert Empirical and Lunar Lambert Empirical function phase 
	  angle list entered as a comma delimited string describing how the 
	  parameters of the empirical function vary with <def>phase angle</def>.
	  See "$ISIS3DATA/base/templates/photometry/marsred.pvl" for an example.
        </description>
        <default><item>No List</item></default>
        <internalDefault>
          No List
        </internalDefault>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="KLIST">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>
          Minnaert Empirical function limb darkening parameter list
        </brief>
        <description>
          The Minnaert Empirical function exponent list of limb darkening values
	  entered as a comma delimited string that describes how the parameters 
	  of the empirical function vary with phase angle.  
	  See "$ISIS3DATA/base/templates/photometry/marsred.pvl" for an example.
        </description>
        <default><item>No List</item></default>
        <internalDefault>
          No List
        </internalDefault>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="LLIST">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>
          The Lunar Lambert Empirical function limb darkening parameter list  
        </brief>
        <description>
          The Lunar Lambert Empirical function parameter list of limb darkening 
	  values entered as a comma delimited string that describes how the 
	  parameters of the empirical function vary with phase angle.  See 
	  "$ISIS3DATA/base/templates/photometry/marsred.pvl" for an example.
        </description>
        <default><item>No List</item></default>
        <internalDefault>
          No List
        </internalDefault>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="PHASECURVELIST">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>
          Empirical functions phase curve (brightness) value list
        </brief>
        <description>
          The Minnaert Empirical or Lunar Lambert Empirical function phase curve 
	  list of brightness values corresponding to a set of phase angles 
	  defined in the PHASELIST parameter.  See 
	  "$ISIS3DATA/base/templates/photometry/marsred.pvl" for an example.
        </description>
        <default><item>No List</item></default>
        <internalDefault>
          No List
        </internalDefault>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Atmospheric Parameters">
      <parameter name="ATMNAME">
        <type>combo</type>
        <brief>
          Atmospheric model to be used
        </brief>
        <description>
          This is the name of the atmospheric photometric function model to be
	  applied. The models ending with "1" use a first order scattering 
	  approximation. Those ending with "2" use a second order scattering 
	  approximation, and are slower but more accurate than the first order 
	  scattering approximation.  The atmospheric correction can be used with 
	  only three atmospheric normalization models: albedoatm, shadeatm, 
	  and topoatm. See Kirk et al. (2001).
        </description>
        <internalDefault>NONE</internalDefault>
        <default>
          <item>NONE</item>
        </default>
        <list>
          <option value="NONE">
            <brief>No atmospheric model</brief>
            <description>
	      No atmospheric correction will be applied.
            </description>
            <exclusions>
              <item>HNORM</item>
              <item>BHA</item>
              <item>TAU</item>
              <item>TAUREF</item>
              <item>WHA</item>
              <item>HGA</item>
              <item>NULNEG</item>
            </exclusions>
          </option>

          <option value="ANISOTROPIC1">
            <brief>
              Anisotropic 1 atmospheric model
            </brief>
            <description>
              Uses Chandrasekhar's solution for anisotropic scattering described
              by a one term Legendre polynomial. This model uses first order
              scattering approximation.  
            </description>
            <inclusions>
              <item>HNORM</item>
              <item>BHA</item>
              <item>TAU</item>
              <item>TAUREF</item>
              <item>WHA</item>
            </inclusions>
            <exclusions>
              <item>HGA</item>
            </exclusions>
          </option>
          <option value="ANISOTROPIC2">
            <brief>
              Anisotropic 2 atmospheric model
            </brief>
            <description>
              Uses Chandrasekhar's solution for anisotropic scattering described
              by a one term Legendre polynomial. This model uses second order 
              scattering approximation. It is slower but more accurate than 
              Anisotropic1. 
            </description>
            <inclusions>
              <item>HNORM</item>
              <item>BHA</item>
              <item>TAU</item>
              <item>TAUREF</item>
              <item>WHA</item>
            </inclusions>
            <exclusions>
              <item>HGA</item>
            </exclusions>
          </option>
          <option value="HAPKEATM1">
            <brief>
              Hapke 1 atmospheric model
            </brief>
            <description>
              Provides an approximation for strongly anisotropic scattering that
              is similar to Hapke's model for a planetary surface. The 
              Chandrasekhar solution for isotropic scattering is used for the 
              multiple scattering terms, and a correction is made to the singly 
              scattered light for anisotropic particle phase function. A one-term 
	      Henyey Greenstein function is used. This model uses a first 
              order scattering approximation. 
            </description>
            <inclusions>
              <item>HNORM</item>
              <item>HGA</item>
              <item>TAU</item>
              <item>TAUREF</item>
              <item>WHA</item>
            </inclusions>
            <exclusions>
              <item>BHA</item>
            </exclusions>
          </option>
          <option value="HAPKEATM2">
            <brief>
              Hapke 2 atmospheric model
            </brief>
            <description>
              Provides an approximation for strongly anisotropic scattering that
              is similar to Hapke's model for a planetary surface. The 
              Chandrasekhar solution for isotropic scattering is used for the 
              multiple scattering terms, and a correction is made to the singly 
              scattered light for anisotropic particle phase function. A 
	      one-term Henyey Greenstein function is used. This model uses a 
	      second order scattering approximation. It is slower but more 
	      accurate than HAPKEATM1. 
            </description>
            <inclusions>
              <item>HNORM</item>
              <item>HGA</item>
              <item>TAU</item>
              <item>TAUREF</item>
              <item>WHA</item>
            </inclusions>
            <exclusions>
              <item>BHA</item>
            </exclusions>
          </option>
          <option value="ISOTROPIC1">
            <brief>
              Isotropic 1 atmospheric model
            </brief>
            <description>
              Uses Chandrasekhar's solution for isotropic scattering. This 
	      model uses first order scattering approximation.  
            </description>
            <inclusions>
              <item>HNORM</item>
              <item>TAU</item>
              <item>TAUREF</item>
              <item>WHA</item>
            </inclusions>
            <exclusions>
              <item>HGA</item>
              <item>BHA</item>
            </exclusions>
          </option>
          <option value="ISOTROPIC2">
            <brief>
              Isotropic 2 atmospheric model
            </brief>
            <description>
              Uses Chandrasekhar's solution for isotropic scattering. This model
              uses second order scattering approximation. It is slower but more 
              accurate than Isotropic1.  
            </description>
            <inclusions>
              <item>HNORM</item>
              <item>TAU</item>
              <item>TAUREF</item>
              <item>WHA</item>
            </inclusions>
            <exclusions>
              <item>HGA</item>
              <item>BHA</item>
            </exclusions>
          </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>
   
      <parameter name="NULNEG">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>
          Specifies if negative values will be set to NULL
        </brief>
        <default><item>READFROMPVL</item></default>
        <description>
          This specifies if negative values after removal of atmospheric
          effects will be set to NULL.  Negative values are only generated
	  in modes that include atmospheric correction and occur when the
	  optical depth "tau" is overestimated, so that the atmospheric
	  <def>radiance</def> subtracted from the image is brighter than the 
	  darkest observed pixels.  In this case "tau" should be decreased 
	  until no negative values are present in the output file.
        </description>
        <list>
          <option value="READFROMPVL">
            <brief>
              Get NULNEG value from the FROMPVL file
            </brief>
            <description>
              Retrieve and set the NULNEG parameter from the FROMPVL file. 
	      An error is reported if a PVL file is not provided.
            </description>
          </option>
          <option value="NO">
            <brief>
              Do not set negative values to NULL
            </brief>
            <description>
              This option specifies not to set negative values to NULL after 
              the removal of atmospheric effects.
            </description>
          </option>
          <option value="YES">
            <brief>
              Negative values will be set to NULL
            </brief>
            <description>
              This option specifies to set negative values to
              NULL after the removal of atmospheric effects.
            </description>
          </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>
 
      <parameter name="TAU">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>
          Optical depth of atmosphere
        </brief>
        <default><item>None Specified</item></default>
        <internalDefault>None Specified</internalDefault>
        <description>
          The normal optical depth of the atmosphere.
        </description>
        <minimum inclusive="yes">0.0</minimum>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TAUREF">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>
          Reference value of tau
        </brief>
        <default><item>None Specified</item></default>
        <internalDefault>None Specified</internalDefault>
        <description>
          The reference value of tau to which the image will be normalized.  This 
	  would normally be 0.0 unless one is interested in simulating a hazy
	  atmosphere scene.
        </description>
        <minimum inclusive="yes">0.0</minimum>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="HGA">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>
          Henyey Greenstein coefficient
        </brief>
        <default><item>None Specified</item></default>
        <internalDefault>None Specified</internalDefault>
        <description>
          The coefficient of single particle Henyey Greenstein phase
          function.  Henyey-Greenestein asymmetry parameter for atmospheric 
	  particle phase function, used in hapkeatm1 and hapkeatm2 atmospheric models.  
	  Not to be confused with corresponding parameter hg1 for the 
	  surface particles.
        </description>
        <minimum inclusive="no">-1.0</minimum>
        <maximum inclusive="no">1.0</maximum>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="WHA">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>
          Single scattering albedo
        </brief>
        <default><item>None Specified</item></default>
        <internalDefault>None Specified</internalDefault>
        <description>
          The single scattering albedo of atmospheric particles.
        </description>
        <minimum inclusive="no">0.0</minimum>
        <maximum inclusive="yes">1.0</maximum>
      </parameter>
      
      <parameter name="BHA">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>
          Legendre coefficient
        </brief>
        <default><item>None Specified</item></default>
        <internalDefault>None Specified</internalDefault>
        <description>
          The coefficient of the single particle Legendre phase function.
	  Coefficient of P1 (cosine) term of atmospheric particle phase
	  function, used in anisotropic1 and anisotropic2 atmospheric models.
	  Not to be confused with corresponding coefficient bh for the 
	  surface particles.
        </description>
        <minimum inclusive="yes">-1.0</minimum>
        <maximum inclusive="yes">1.0</maximum>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="HNORM">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>
          Atmospheric shell thickness
        </brief>
        <default><item>None Specified</item></default>
        <internalDefault>None Specified</internalDefault>
        <description>
          The atmospheric shell thickness normalized to the planet
          radius, used to modify angles to get more accurate path lengths 
	  near the terminator (Ratio of scale height to the planetary
	  radius).  The hnorm parameter is defined as "0.003" for Mars, 
	  which is the only planet for which the atmospheric modes are 
	  currently used.
        </description>
        <minimum inclusive="yes">0.0</minimum>
      </parameter>
    </group>
  </groups>
  <examples>
     <example>
      <brief>Create a PVL file of photometric parameters</brief>
      <description>
        This example shows the GUI and the parameter name settings.  The helper option
	is used to load the preset parameter values if an existing PVL file is used, 
	and then the required parameter names without any values are manually added.
      </description>
      <terminalInterface>
        <commandLine>
        </commandLine>
        <description>
	 Run photemplate to generate a PVL file with the parameter values for the 
	 selected photometric models.
	</description>
      </terminalInterface>
      <guiInterfaces>
        <guiInterface>
          <image src="assets/images/photemplate_gui.png" width="716" height="969">
            <brief>Photemplate GUI</brief>
            <description>
              Screenshot of GUI version of the application.  The parameter values
	      have been loaded and edited for the output PVL file.
            </description>
            <thumbnail src="assets/thumbs/photemplate_gui_thumb.png" caption="Photemplate GUI" width="222" height="300"/>
          </image>
        </guiInterface>
      </guiInterfaces>
      <dataFiles>
        <dataFile path="assets/hapken_hapkeatm2.pvl">
          <brief>Output PVL file</brief>
          <description>
            The output PVL file will contain the photometric parameters to be applied 
	    to the input cube.  Load the PVL file parameters using the photemplate GUI 
	    and manually enter required parameter names without any values assigned.
          </description>
          <parameterName>
            FROMPVL <br/>
	    TOPVL
          </parameterName>
        </dataFile>
      </dataFiles>
    </example>   
   </examples>
</application>
