<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="cam2cam" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">
  <brief>
    Convert camera image to a different camera image
  </brief>

  <description>
      This program will convert a input camera cube to a different camera geometry.  For example, given overlapping MGS MOC and Odyssey Themis cubes, 
      this program can convert the MOC image to have the same geometric camera characteristics as the Themis cube (or vice versa).  Another use is to align
      bands in a camera cube which has independent bands.  For example, a raw Themis cube (after thm2isis) will not have aligned pixels.  This program can
      be used to align the pixels without going to a map projection.  To prevent pixels from falling off the edge of the cube you can run pad on the cube prior to
      this program.
    </description>

  <category>
    <categoryItem>Cameras</categoryItem>
  </category>

  <history>
    <change name="Jeff Anderson" date="2000-05-10">
      Original version
    </change>
    <change name="Jeff Anderson" date="2004-01-19">
      Converted to Isis 3.0
    </change>
    <change name="Jacob Danton" date="2005-12-05">
      Added an appTest.
    </change>
    <change name="Elizabeth Miller" date="2006-03-23">
      Fixed appTest to reflect changes in all camera models
    </change>
    <change name="Debbie A. Cook" date="2007-06-21">
       Corrected setting of output file labels so that the Spice comes from the match cube and not the input cube
     </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2007-06-22">
       Fixed typo in documentation
     </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2008-01-23">
       Fixed an access on an invalid pointer that caused segmentation faults on 
       cubes in which the camera is band-dependant.
     </change>
    <change name="Jeff Anderson" date="2008-02-12">
       Fixed problems with reference bands on band-dependent instruments
     </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2008-05-12">
          Removed references to CubeInfo 
    </change>
  </history>

  <oldName>
    <item>lev1tolev1</item>
  </oldName>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input camera cube
        </brief>
        <description>
            The camera cube which will be modified
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="MATCH">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Instrument cube to match
        </brief>
        <description>
            This is the camera cube which will be matched.  It must be only one band so use the input attributes to select the band to match.  For example,
            themis.cub+5.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TO">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Output cube
        </brief>
        <description>
          The resultant cube which will have the same camera geometry and image size as the match cube.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Options">
      <parameter name="REFBAND">
        <type>integer</type>
        <internalDefault>middle</internalDefault>
        <brief>Reference Band</brief>
        <description>
            This is the reference band to be used in the MATCH cube.  
            That is, all bands in the FROM cube will be matched to 
            this band.  The default is to use the middle band; however,
            the user can enter any band number which is valid for the
            instrument, regardless of whether the band is in the cube
            or not.  
            This only applies to band dependent camera models such as 
            Themis.
        </description>
        <minimum inclusive="yes">1</minimum>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="INTERP">
        <type>string</type>
        <default>
          <item>CUBICCONVOLUTION</item>
        </default>
        <brief>Type of interpolation</brief>
        <description>
          This is the type of interpolation to be performed on the input.
        </description>
        <list>
          <option value="NEARESTNEIGHBOR">
            <brief>Nearest Neighbor</brief>
            <description>
              Each output pixel will be set to the pixel nearest the
              calculated input pixel.
            </description>
          </option>
          <option value="BILINEAR">
            <brief>Bi-Linear interpolation</brief>
            <description>
              Each output pixel will be set to the value calculated by
              a bi-linear interpolation of the calculated input pixel.
            </description>
          </option>
          <option value="CUBICCONVOLUTION">
            <brief>Cubic Convolution interpolation</brief>
            <description>
              Each output pixel will be set to the value calculated by
              a cubic convolution interpolation of the calculated input pixel.
            </description>
          </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>
    </group>
  </groups>
</application>
