<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="vimscal" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">

  <brief>
    Radiometric correction of Cassini VIMS camera images. 
  </brief>

  <description>
    This program applies a dark current and a flat field correction to images, then converts the output units
    to either specific energy or I/F.

    <br/><br/>
    <b>Dark Current:</b><br/>
    The dark current correction for VIS consists of reading a binary ".tab" file from $cassini/calibration/vims and subtracting
    derived values from this file.<br/>

    The dark current correction for IR consists of reading the sideplane data (stored in a SideplaneIr table in the cube) and
    subtracting this from the input cube. If "CompressorId" is available then the sideplane data was already subtracted from
    the file, but the linear fit capabilities are still available to re-do the dark current with a linear fit instead of the
    default subtraction. If spectral summing is on then no dark current can be applied. If spectral editing is on then the linear
    fit on the dark current can not be applied. Sideplane keywords for IR are as follows:
    <ul>
      <li>None = No dark current subtraction (applied by the instrument)</li>
      <li>Sideplane = Sideplane was subtracted only without fitting a line</li>
      <li>Fit Delta = Sideplane was previously subtracted so the difference between the
    sideplane and linear fit function subtracted</li>
      <li>Fit = A linear fit was applied to the dark current values and the result was subtracted</li>
    </ul>
    <br/><br/>

    <b>Flat Field:</b><br/>
    For both VIS and IR this determines the correct file from $cassini/calibration/vims/flatfield and divides the input data by the
    flat field data.<br /><br />

    <b>Subareas</b><br/>
    The offset and swath keywords will be respected by running "crop" on the calibration files appropriately and using the cropped 
    calibration files.
  </description>

  <history>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2009-06-24">
      Original version
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2009-08-03">
      The solar distance calculation is now much more likely to succeed
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2009-12-16">
      Better error handling - fewer temporary files left around
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2009-12-17">
      Sped up program by not searching a pvl much more than necessary,
      improved error messages
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2010-02-19">
      Now closing calibration files when done with them
    </change>
  </history>

  <category>
    <missionItem>Cassini</missionItem>
  </category>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input Isis cube
        </brief>
        <description>
          Use this parameter to choose an Isis cube to be calibrated.  To ensure 
          that it contains all needed keywords in its label, input cube should 
          have been imported using <strong>vims2isis</strong> and, if "I/F" is chosen, input cube 
          must have been run through <strong>spiceinit</strong> application.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TO">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <pixelType>real</pixelType>
        <brief>
           Output Isis cube
        </brief>
        <description>
           Use this parameter to select the output filename of the calibrated 
           Isis cube.
        </description>
        <filter>
           *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name = "Options">
      <parameter name = "UNITS">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>Output units</brief>
        <description>
        </description>
        <default><item>IOF</item></default>
        <list>
          <option value="SPECENERGY">
            <brief>Specific Energy</brief>
            <description>
              This option indicates that the output is in terms of specific energy (ergs/sec/spectel). 
            </description>
          </option>
          <option value="IOF">
            <brief>I/F</brief>
            <description>
              This option indicates that the output is in terms of solar flux (I/F). 
              Input cube must have been run through the <strong>spiceinit</strong> application.
            </description>
          </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="IRORIGDARK">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <brief>Do not perform IR Dark Current Corrections</brief>
        <description>
          By default Isis will fit a line to the dark current values, on each band, across the lines since
          there is one dark value per line. The linear fit value will be applied correctly even if a dark
          current was applied to this cube beforehand. This disables the line fitting for the dark current.
          This parameter has no effect for VIS cubes.
        </description>
        <default><item>false</item></default>
      </parameter>
    </group>
  </groups>
</application>
