<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="lrowaccal" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">

  <brief>
    This program calibrates LRO WAC images
  </brief>

  <description>
    <p>
      This program applies dark, flat-field, radiometric, and temperature corrections for each
      framelet based on the band's filter number. There is also an optional mask to replace
      special pixels in the calibrated image. In order to output in I/F units, the cube must
      have spice data.
    </p>

    <p>
      Corrections are applied in the following order: Dark, Flat-field, Radiometric, Special pixel mask, and Temperature.
    </p>

    <h3>Dark Correction:</h3>
    <p>
      If the DarkFile parameter is set, the given file(s) will be used for calibration. If DarkFile
      is set to "Default" or not set at all, the dark files will be looked up based on the time and
      temperature in the WAC being calibrated. The parameter,MiddleTemperatureFpa, is used for
      temperature and StartTime for time. This program, lrowaccal, will attempt to find the 2 dark
      files with closest time/temperature and interpolate/extrapolate from them. The method for
      finding dark files is as follows:
      <ul>
      <li>Create filename template based on WAC image offset and type (UV, BW, etc). Example: WAC_UV_Offset68_*C_*T_Dark.????.cub</li>
      <li>Look in $lro/calibration/wac_darks for matching files.</li>
      <li>Sort files on two factors:
        <ol>
          <li>abs(dark temp - WAC temp)</li>
          <li>abs(dark time - WAC time)</li>
        </ol>
        <li>
          Example:
          <div style="font-size:90%; font-family:monospace; margin:5px; margin-left:30px;">
            WAC Temp = 23.33 and WAC Time = 314264519.932493<br/>
            <br/>
            WAC_UV_Offset68_-10C_319412928T_Dark.0005.cub<br/>
            WAC_UV_Offset68_-15C_319412928T_Dark.0005.cub<br/>
            WAC_UV_Offset68_-20C_311632116T_Dark.0005.cub<br/>
            WAC_UV_Offset68_-20C_319412928T_Dark.0005.cub<br/>
            WAC_UV_Offset68_-25C_319412928T_Dark.0005.cub<br/>
            WAC_UV_Offset68_-30C_311632116T_Dark.0005.cub<br/>
            <br/>
            becomes<br/>
            <br/>
            WAC_UV_Offset68_-25C_319412928T_Dark.0005.cub<br/>
            WAC_UV_Offset68_-20C_311632116T_Dark.0005.cub<br/>
            WAC_UV_Offset68_-20C_319412928T_Dark.0005.cub<br/>
            WAC_UV_Offset68_-30C_311632116T_Dark.0005.cub<br/>
            WAC_UV_Offset68_-15C_319412928T_Dark.0005.cub<br/>
            WAC_UV_Offset68_-10C_319412928T_Dark.0005.cub<br/>
          </div>
        </li>
      </li>
      <li>Take the 2 closest temperatures (-25C and -20C in the example).</li>
      <li>Select the closest time for each temperature.
        <div style="font-size:90%; font-family:monospace; margin:5px; margin-left:30px;">
          Example result:<br/>
          <br/>
          WAC_UV_Offset68_-25C_319412928T_Dark.0005.cub<br/>
          WAC_UV_Offset68_-20C_311632116T_Dark.0005.cub<br/>
        </div>
      </li>
      <li>
        If only one temperature is available, the 2 times that are closest to the WAC time will be
        chosen. This will allow WACs to always be calibrated against something, instead of just
        failing.
        <div style="font-size:90%; font-family:monospace; margin:5px; margin-left:30px;">
          Example result:<br/>
          <br/>
          WAC_UV_Offset68_-20C_311632116T_Dark.0005.cub<br/>
          WAC_UV_Offset68_-20C_319412928T_Dark.0005.cub<br/>
        </div>
      </li>
      </ul>
    </p>
    <p>
      Once the dark files are found, the correction is applied:
      <pre>
        output[pixel] -= (dark1[pixel] - dark2[pixel])/(dark1Temp - dark2Temp)*(frameTemp-dark2Temp) + dark2[pixel]
      </pre>
        where
      <pre>
        dark1, dark2 = dark file cubes
        dark1Temp, dark2Temp = temperature of dark1 file and dark2 file
        frameTemp = (WAC EndTemperatureFpa - WAC BeginTemperatureFpa)/WAC NumFramelets * frame + WAC BeginTemperatureFpa
      </pre>
    </p>

    <h3>Flat-field Correction:</h3>
    <p>
      <pre>
        output[pixel] /= flatfield[pixel]
      </pre>

      If FlatfieldFile is not set, flat-field cube is loaded from $lro/calibration/wac_flats/WAC_&lt;wac mode&gt;_Flatfield.????.cub
    </p>

    <h3>Radiometric Correction:</h3>
    <p>
      <pre>
      output[pixel] /= WAC ExposureDuration
      if radiometricType == iof
        output[pixel] *= solarDistance<sup>2</sup> / iofResponsivity[band]
      else
        output[pixel] /= radianceResponsivity[band]
      </pre>
      where
      <pre>
        solarDistance is distance from the Moon to the Sun
      </pre>

      If RadiometricFile is not set, radiometric responsivity is loaded from $lro/calibration/WAC_RadiometricResponsivity.????.pvl
    </p>

    <h3>Special Pixel Mask:</h3>
    <p>
      <pre>
      for each framelet in the output cube
        if specialPixelMask[pixel] is special
          outputFramelet[pixel] = specialPixelMask[pixel]
      </pre>

      If SpecialPixelsFile is not set, special pixel mask is loaded from $lro/calibration/wac_masks/WAC_&lt;wac mode&gt;_&lt;temp&gt;C_SpecialPixels.????.cub. temp is closest temperature to WAC MiddleTemperatureFpa.
    </p>
    <h3>Temperature Correction:</h3>
    <p>
      <pre>
        for each framlet in the output cube
          if output[pixel] is special- leave it alone
          else preform the correction
        </pre>
        Correction:
        <pre>

                inputPixel
            --------------------
             a*(frameTemp) + b

             Where:
               'a' and 'b' are band dependent constants, read in from a file.
             AND
               frameTemp = (WAC EndTemperatureFpa - WAC BeginTemperatureFpa)/WAC NumFramelets * frame + WAC BeginTemperatureFpa
      </pre>
      If TEMPRATUREFILE is not set, the constants are loaded from $lro/calibration/WAC_TempratureConstants.????.pvl
    </p>

    <p>
      The DN level in an uncalibrated image is the sum of the true signal from the scene,
      the bias, the dark current, and random noise in all 3 components. The random noise in
      the true signal and dark current is called shot noise and the random noise in the bias
      is called read noise. The true signal, bias, and dark current are defined as mean
      values so that if the random noise were averaged down to insignificance by taking a
      very large number of images and averaging them, the resulting image would be the true
      scene, bias, and dark current with no systematic error. That implies the statistical
      distribution of the random noise has an average of zero, and therefore the random noise
      has both positive and negative values, except for the trivial case of zero random noise.
    </p>

    <p>
      The calibration equation is:
      <pre>  reportedDN = ObservedDN - MeanBias - DarkCurrent </pre>

        Where:
        <pre>
   ObservedDN = TrueDN + E
   E is a randomly sampled value from (mu, sigma^2) and mu=0
   TrueDN is the signal that would be reported in an idealized case of an instrument with zero noise.</pre>
     </p>

    <p>
      Let's look at the case of a calibrated image for which the true signal
      is zero, a dark image. In calibration the mean bias and dark current are
      subtracted. The random noise term is then randomly sampled from a known
      distribution with a mean of zero. Since the distribution has a mean of
      zero, values for the random noise can be positive or negative.
      Therefore, the addition of random noise to a pixel with true signal near
      zero can result in negative DN values.
    </p>

    <p>
      Negative reported DNs are possible when E &lt; -1 * TrueDN. These are
      pixels in a very dark image that happen to have a strongly negative
      random noise value.
    </p>

    <p>
      Note: ObservedDN and TrueDN both must be greater than or equal to zero.
      For ObservedDN, it's because the hardware is not able to report negative
      DN values . For TrueDN, it's because radiance and reflectivity cannot be
      negative. The dimmest target is one that is completely dark, and for
      that target TrueDN = 0.
    </p>

    <p>
    If run on a non-spiceinited cube, this program requires access to local mission-specific 
    SPICE kernels, in order to find the distance between the sun and the target body. 
    When run on a spiceinited cube, this can be determined using the camera model.
    Using a spiceinited cube as input has the advantage of not requiring that local 
    mission-specific kernels be available. (See spiceinit web=true.)
    </p>

  </description>

  <category>
    <missionItem>Lunar Reconnaissance Orbiter</missionItem>
  </category>

  <history>
    <change name="Jacob Danton" date="2009-07-01">
      Original version
    </change>
    <change name="Dan Clarke" date="2012-08-13">
      Updated use of deprecated methods (use ProcessCube instead
      of Start/EndProcess). Updated documentation/comments.
      Optimized/cleaned up code in Calibrate, GetDark, and GetMask.
      Changed the algorithm for finding dark files in GetDark.
      GetDark will now find the two closest available dark file
      temperatures matching the input WAC cube. Then, it will find
      the dark file at each temperature with the time closest to the
      WAC time. This should prevent failed calibrations from missing
      darks.
    </change>
    <change name="Adam Licht" date="2012-12-18">
      Fixed an error which would apply band 1 corrections to a
      single passed in band, even if that band was not band 1.
    </change>
    <change name="Adam Licht" date="2013-04-16">
      Implemented a temperature based correction to lrowaccal.
      This correction requires constants which are read from a
      pvl file. A file other than the default can be passed in
      via an argument. The correction may also be turned off via
      an argument.
    </change>
    <change name="Stuart Sides" date="2021-02-22">
      Added ability to get the sun distance from the camera.
    </change>
    <change name="Cordell Michaud" date="2022-05-03">
      Refactored lrowaccal to be callable for testing and to remove global 
      variables and helper functions. Added units label "W/m2/sr/um" to 
      RadiometricType keyword in output cube label when RadiometricType is 
      AbsoluteRadiance.
    </change>
  </history>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input Image
        </brief>
        <description>
          This is the non-calibrated, unprojected WAC cube
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TO">
         <type>cube</type>
         <fileMode>output</fileMode>
         <pixelType>real</pixelType>
         <brief>
           Output Image
         </brief>
         <description>
           This is the calibrated WAC cube
         </description>
         <filter>
           *.cub
         </filter>
       </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Dark Options">
      <parameter name="Dark">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>True</item></default>
        <brief>
          Calibrate using a dark file.
        </brief>
        <description>
          Calibrate using a correction based off of a dark file. Please see the Dark Correction
          section at the beginning of this document for a detailed explanation of how the
          correction is applied
        </description>
        <inclusions><item>DarkFile</item></inclusions>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="DarkFile">
        <type>filename</type>
        <default><item>Default</item></default>
        <brief>
          Dark file used for calibration.
        </brief>
        <description>
          Dark file used for calibration. The default is to use the dark file with the closest
          time and temperature to the WAC image being calibrated. See the Dark Correction section
          at the beginning of this document for a detailed explanation of how dark files are
          chosen.
        </description>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Flatfield Options">
      <parameter name="Flatfield">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>True</item></default>
        <brief>
          Calibrate using a flatfield file.
        </brief>
        <description>
          Calibrate using a flatfield file.
        </description>
        <inclusions><item>FlatfieldFile</item></inclusions>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="FlatfieldFile">
        <type>filename</type>
        <default><item>Default</item></default>
        <brief>
          Flatfield file used for calibration.
        </brief>
        <description>
          Flatfield file used for calibration. The default is to use the system defined dark file with
          the highest version number.
        </description>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Radiometric Options">
      <parameter name="Radiometric">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>True</item></default>
        <brief>
          Do radiometric calibration.
        </brief>
        <description>
          Perform a radiometric calibration on the input cub. This type of this correction is
          defined by the RadiometricType parameter.
        </description>
        <inclusions>
          <item>RadiometricType</item>
          <item>RadiometricFile</item>
        </inclusions>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="RadiometricType">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>
          Calibrated output cube units.
        </brief>
        <description>
          Calibrated output cube units. I/F or radiance.
        </description>
        <default><item>IOF</item></default>
        <list>
          <option value="IOF">
            <brief>I/F</brief>
            <description>
            </description>
          </option>
          <option value="RADIANCE">
            <brief>Radiance</brief>
            <description>
            </description>
          </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="RadiometricFile">
        <type>filename</type>
        <default><item>Default</item></default>
        <brief>
          Radiometric constants file used for calibration.
        </brief>
        <description>
          Radiometric constants file used for calibration. The default is to use the system
          defined file with the highest version.
        </description>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Special Pixels Options">
      <parameter name="SpecialPixels">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>True</item></default>
        <brief>

        </brief>
        <description>
          This option will apply a special pixel mask to the input cub. The default is to use the
          system defined mask file with the matching WAC mode and closest Temperature to the input
          cub. Please see the main documentation for a detailed description of the
          Special Pixel Mask correction.
        </description>
        <inclusions><item>SpecialPixelsFile</item></inclusions>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="SpecialPixelsFile">
        <type>filename</type>
        <default><item>Default</item></default>
        <brief>
          This option will apply a special pixel mask to the cub. The default is to use the system
          defined mask file with the matching WAC mode and closest Temperature to the input cub.
          Please see the main documentation for a detailed description of the
          Special Pixel Mask correction.
        </brief>
        <description>
        </description>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Temperature Options">
      <parameter name="Temperature">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>True</item></default>
        <brief>
          Calibrate using temperature base correction.
        </brief>
        <description>
          Calibrate using temperature gain and offset.
          Please see <a href="./assets/documentation/Temperature_Correction.pdf">this</a> document, which outlines how the correction was derived.
        </description>
        <inclusions><item>TemperatureFile</item></inclusions>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="TemperatureFile">
        <type>filename</type>
        <default><item>Default</item></default>
        <brief>
          Temperature gain and offset file.
        </brief>
        <description>
          Temperature gain and offset file. The default is to use the system defined temperature gain and offset file with
          the highest version number.
        </description>
      </parameter>
    </group>

  </groups>
</application>
