<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="cneteditor" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">
  <brief>
    Interactive control network editor
  </brief>

  <description>
    <p>
      Cneteditor allows a user to visualize control point and measure attributes
      and to edit them interactively. The user can toggle between control point
      coordinate and sigma display in Latitude, Longitude, Radius or XYZ format.
      Select keywords from a control network file are imported into a table of
      editable rows and columns. <strong>Always make a backup copy of the input
      file before using this program. There is no "undo" capability yet.</strong>
    </p>
    <p>
      The basic utility of this program is to set control points or control
      measures to "ignore" or "EditLock," and to modify A Priori SP coordinate
      sigma values (in either lat/lon/radius or XYZ format). The control point
      type can be changed to "Constrained," "Fixed," or "Free." There are columns
      such as PointID or Reference which should not be changed. If control points
      or measures are set to "yes" for EditLock, the user is prompted to verify
      updated values.
    </p>
    <p>
      The control network file is loaded either by entering the filename after
      the program name on the command line or by using the file selection menu
      after invoking the program.
    </p>
    <p>
      Command line example:
      <pre>cneteditor control_network_file.net</pre>
    </p>
    <p>
      On the menu bar are drop down menus "File," "Tables," "Coordinate Display,"
      and "Help."  The options under "File" are "Open," "Save," "Save As,"
      "Close," and "Quit." The options under "Tables" are "Freeze Tables" and
      "Enable Sorting." The options under "Coordinate Display" are "X,Y,Z" and
      "Lat,Lon,Radius." The icons are activated only after a control network file
      has been loaded. When the sorting icon is enabled, the <strong>"^"
      (ascending)</strong> or <strong>"v" (descending)</strong> symbol appears in
      the activated column heading. The sort is performed by clicking on the
      symbol or by clicking on a different column of interest while sorting is
      enabled.
    </p>
    <p>
      The "Freeze Tables" icon (ice cube) is used to temporarily turn off the
      filtering function. It freezes the table so that edits to a cell can be
      performed without screen refresh. When the edits are completed, turn off
      the freeze pane by clicking on the icon again. Once the freeze icon is
      off, the edited information is updated in memory but not saved to disk.
      Use the "save" or "save as" options under "File" to save the file to disk.
    </p>
    <p>
      When the tables are not frozen the cells are updated based on the filters
      that have been applied as soon as a cell is edited. If more than one cell
      in a row needs to be edited then freeze the pane before changing any of
      the cells.
    </p>
    <p>
      The "Coordinate Display" icons ("X,Y,Z" and "Lat, Lon, Radius") toggle
      display of coordinates and sigmas between the two formats. Latitude/Longitude
      coordinate units are decimal degrees. Radius and XYZ coordinate units are
      meters. All coordinate sigma units are meters.
    </p>
    <p>
      The filters tabs presently available are "Control Points and Measures" and
      "Images and Points." Filters for points and sigmas correspond to the active
      coordinate display format ("X,Y,Z" or "Lat, Lon, Radius"). The tab for
      "Connections" is displayed but not implemented yet so there are no keyword
      options available when the tab is selected.
    </p>
    <p>
      The results of the filters are displayed in the "Control Point Table,
      "Control Measure Table," and the "Point View" tree.
    </p>
    <p>
      The green "+" icon can be used to add a new filter or a new filter group.
      Click the "+" icon inside the bounding box to add a new filter. Select a
      keyword to filter with such as "PointType." The "And" or "Or" logic type
      radio button must also be selected.
    </p>
    <p>
      Click the "+" icon outside the bounding box to add a new filter group.
      Select a keyword to filter with such as "GoodnessOfFit."  The "And" or
      "Or" logic type radio button must also be selected.
    </p>
    <p>
      The drop-down menu under the filter tabs lists keywords that can be
      selected for the filters. Additional filtering options can be chosen to
      include or exclude specific values by clicking on the radio icons. A text
      box will be displayed for keywords that require text or numbers. <strong>
      Be careful with extra spaces when entering text, verify entry by reading
      the filter statement if the expected result is empty.</strong>
    </p>
    <p>
      The ">=" or "&lt;=" symbols are used to enter the cutoff numbers for
      specific keywords that are stored as numbers, and when selected there may
      be an option to select the "inclusive" or "exclusive" filter.
    </p>
    <p>
      The "Effect" option is used to select "Point" and/or "Measure." The
      default is both "Point" and "Measure" so there is an "X" within the radio
      icons. To turn off one or the other option, click on the desired radio
      icon; "X" means selected and no "X" means not selected.
    </p>
    <p>
      For the "Control Points and Measures" tab, the "Min count for points" is
      used to define how many measures a control point must have for a
      particular filter. The default value is "1" so the filtering is applied to
      control points that have at least one measure. If the "Control point"
      option under "Effect" is turned off, then the min count is not used.
    </p>
    <p>
      <strong>Warning:</strong> Not all filters have the same effect. For
      example, some keywords require minimum and/or maximum values while others
      require text entries. <strong>It is best to read the statement above the
      filter options to see exactly what the options that has been selected is
      performing</strong>.
    </p>
    <p>
      <strong>Editing cells:</strong>
      <br/><br/>
      Click on the cell to type the value, or double-click on the cell to see
      the valid values in the drop-down menu to select from. If no valid values
      exist, then type the text in the cell.
    </p>
    <p>
      <strong>Copying to all cells:</strong>
      <br/><br/>
      Select a cell that has the content that will be copied to all cells under
      a column. Click on the selected cell to activate, and then hold down the
      right icon to select "copy to all cells."
    </p>
    <p>
      For more help click on "What"s This?" under Help, or use Shift+F1. Once
      you see the "?" on the screen, click on the screen to see the information.
    </p>
  </description>

  <category>
    <categoryItem>Control Networks</categoryItem>
    <categoryItem>Display</categoryItem>
  </category>

  <history>
    <change name="Eric Hyer" date="2011-03-07">
      Original version
    </change>
    <change name="Jai Rideout" date="2011-10-07">
      Added documentation in preparation for the October release. Credit goes to
      Janet Richie and Ella Lee for their help in preparing the documentation.
    </change>
    <change name="Jai Rideout" date="2012-01-04">
      No longer crashes if unknown column titles are found in cneteditor
      QSettings. Fixes #616.
    </change>
    <change name="Jai Rideout" date="2012-01-20">
      Added measure type, line, and sample filters. Added a couple of existing
      filters to the image-point filter selector and fixed typos in a few of the
      filter description strings. Fixes #645.
    </change>
    <change name="Jai Rideout" date="2012-01-20">
      Added Eric Hyer's final changes to this application that allow users to
      load a cube list and have cube filenames display instead of cube serial
      numbers. "Cube serial number" filter is now called "Image ID", as users
      may be either filtering on cube serial numbers or cube filenames. Fixes
      #304.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright and Jai Rideout" date="2012-03-28">
      Edit-locked points and measures now appear non-editable in the point and
      measure tables. Fixes #356.
    </change>
    <change name="Jai Rideout" date="2012-03-28">
      Points with any edit-locked measures can no longer be deleted. Fixes #621.
    </change>
    <change name="Jai Rideout and Steven Lambright" date="2012-04-09">
      Sorting is now configurable through a sorting dialog, including the
      ability to enable/disable sorting and set table size limits for automatic
      enabling of sorting on either the point or measure table. Fixes #360.
    </change>
    <change name="Jai Rideout" date="2012-05-02">
      Added several new filters for filtering points/measures, as well as
      images/points. The new filters include: a priori/adjuted lat/lon/radius,
      a priori/adjusted lat/lon/radius sigma, jigsaw rejected points, jigsaw
      rejected measures, sample and line shift. Fixes #367.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright and Kim Oyama" date="2012-05-30">
      Improved user interface for the new sorting options to be (hopefully)
      extremely obvious what the options are, how they work, and why your
      tables are not sorting (when they aren't sorting). Fixes #838.
    </change>
    <change name="Ian Humphrey" date="2015-10-07">
      Updated icons. Fixes #1041.
    </change>
    <change name="Ian Humphrey" date="2015-11-16">
      Fixed a couple missing icons. References #1041.
    </change>
    <change name="Ken Edmundson" date="2024-02-23">
      Added 1) capability to display point coordinates and sigmas in either
      lat/lon/radius or XYZ format; 2) menu items and menu bar icons to toggle
      between coordinate formats; 3) new filters for the XYZ coordinate format;
      4) updated documentation. References #5421.
    </change>
  </history>
</application>
