<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Id: mdisddr.xml,v 1.3 2009/09/08 21:35:48 kbecker Exp $ -->

<application name="mdisddr" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">
  <brief>
    Creates a MESSENGER DDR PDS product from an MDIS image
  </brief>
  <description>
      <p>
        <b>mdisddr</b> will process a Messenger MDIS NAC or WAC image cube and 
        export it to PDS/DDR format.  The resulting file will have a PDS 
        compliant label and data object according to the description in SIS 
        document, mdis_crd_rdrsis.pdf.  This file can be found in the PDS data 
        archive CDROM under the <i>document</i> directory.  
        <b>mdisddr</b> assumes the input file has been run through at a minimum
        mdis2isis and spiceinit. This will ensure that proper values of the 
        PRODUCT_ID and SOURCE_PRODUCT_ID are included in the output DDR 
        label.
      </p>
      <p>
          The Derived Data Record (DDR) data set consists of files that parallel 
          CDRs in their directory structure. Each DDR has 5 layers of data 
          containing geometric information (latitude, longitude, incidence angle, 
          emission angle, phase angle) as 32-bit PC_REAL or IEEE_REAL. This 
          information is derived from pixel spatial coordinates and associated SPICE 
          files. A DDR label is attached and points to a single multiband image in 
          the DDR.  x, y dimensions = 1024/(MESS:FPU_BIN * MESS:PIXELBIN)
      </p>
      <p>
          The sequence of processing that creates a DDR is as follows. Gimbal 
          positions are extracted from the gimbal C kernel. Using that and other 
          SPICE kernels, the equipotential surface intercept is calculated for 
          each spatial pixel. The angles of this pixel relative to the 
          equatorial plane and reference longitude constitute the latitude and 
          longitude of the pixel. For that latitude and longitude, solar 
          incidence, emission, and phase angles are determined.  This is the 
          order in which the bands are written to the output PDS image file.
      </p>
      </description>

  <history>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2009-06-24">
        Original Version
    </change>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2009-09-08">
        Added additional documentation.
    </change>
  </history>

  <category>
    <missionItem>Messenger</missionItem>
  </category>

  <groups>

    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>Input MESSENGER cube</brief>
        <description>
          Input filename of a MESSENGER cube file to be exported into a PDS DDR 
          image.  The minimum requirement is that it must be initalized with 
          SPICE (using the <B>spiceinit</B> application). 
        </description>
        <filter> *.cub </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TO">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
          <internalDefault>Derived</internalDefault>
        <brief>Name of output file</brief>
        <description>
            <p>
                 Output filename, by default the filename will be generated from the
                input file contents using the PRODUCT_ID.   The user can specify the 
                name if desired here, but to ensure consistancy with SIS 
                specifications, the name of the file will be derived by the program.  
                See the OPATH parameter for additional options of where the output 
                file will be written.
            </p>
            <p>
                The format of the derived filename will be of the form
                DN0131770878M_DE_0.IMG where 'D' indicates it is a derived data 
                product, the second letter will be 'N' for MDIS/NAC or 'W' for 
                MDIS/WAC instrument;  the next ten characters will be numbers 
                indicating the mission elasped time (MET) of the image;  the 
                following character is the filter - 'M' for monochrome or the 
                NAC, letters 'A' -'L' for WAC filters;  the two characters after 
                the first underscore is always 'DE' indicating it is a derived 
                data type;  and the last number after the second underscore is 
                the version number.  The customary IMG extension is standard for
                most all PDS image data products.
            </p>
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="OPATH">
        <type>string</type>
          <internalDefault>Current</internalDefault>
          <brief> Path to write output DDR file to when TO is not given</brief>
          <description>
            This parameter is provided to be used instead of the TO parameter if 
            the filename convention is to be followed.  If TO is not given, then 
            output filename is derived internally according to the description in 
            the SIS and the output file is placed in the OPATH directory.  The 
            default is to write it to the current directory.
          </description>
      </parameter>

    </group>

    <group name="Stretch">

      <parameter name="TYPE">
        <type>string</type>
        <default><item>AUTOMATIC</item></default>
        <brief>
          Select the type of stretch
        </brief>
        <description>
          This parameter is used to select one of two ways to stretch output
          pixels.  The are AUTOMATIC or MANUAL.
        </description>
        <list>
          <option value="AUTOMATIC">
            <brief>Sets it to well defined angular ranges</brief>
            <description>
                This program computes geometric and photometric angles that have 
                well defined/behaved ranges.  Selecting AUTOMATIC, in effect, 
                will result in the range -360 to +360 no matter what the data 
                ranges are in the file.
            </description>
            <exclusions>
              <item>MIN</item> 
              <item>MAX</item>
            </exclusions>
          </option>
          <option value="MANUAL">
            <brief>User defined stretch</brief>
            <description>
              Enables the user defined stretch for the output IMG.
            </description>
          </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="MIN">
          <type>double</type>
          <brief>
              Lower bound of the stretch
          </brief>
          <description>
             Lower bound for the manually specified stretch.
          </description>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="MAX">
          <type>double</type>
          <brief>
              Upper bound of the stretch
          </brief>
          <description>
              Upper bound for the manually specified stretch.
          </description>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Output Controls">

        <parameter name="BITS">
          <type>integer</type>
          <default><item>32</item></default>
          <brief>
            Number of bits for the output DN
          </brief>
          <description>
            The number of bits to compress the input data to. The valid data as
            well as the five special pixel values (NULL, LIS, LRS, HIS, HRS) will be
            compressed into this number of bits. The output data type will be
            automaticity choosen using this value. A value of 8 will create 
            unsigned byte output files. Values from 9 to 16 will create unsigned
            word output files. Unused bits in the unsigned word output file will be
            set to zero.
          </description>
          <minimum inclusive="yes">8</minimum>
          <maximum inclusive="yes">32</maximum>
        </parameter>
      </group>
  </groups>
</application>

