<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="kaguyami2isis" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">

  <brief>Import PDS formatted Kaguya MI image cube into Isis format cube</brief>

  <description>
    This program will import a PDS formatted Kaguya MI VIS and NIR level 1 (EDR) 
    image into an Isis cube.
  </description>

  <history>
    <change name="Janet Barrett" date="2011-05-09">
      Original version
    </change>
    <change name="Janet Barrett" date="2012-05-02">
      At this time, there is no camera model for the Kaguya MI data. In order to
      be able to perform photometry on the Kaguya MI data, the SubSolarLongitude
      and SubSolarLatitude information needed to be calculated. These calculations 
      are done by using the aaplus library developed by P J Naughter at 
      http://www.naughter.com. This library can only be distributed in binary form,
      so it has to stay in the local directory of ISIS where it will not be 
      distributed. The formulae used to do the calculations were taken from Meeus 
      "Astronomical Algorithms" (1st Ed). This code can be removed as soon as a camera 
      model is available for the Kaguya MI camera. The start and stop times for these 
      images are very close, so the start time is used to calculate the SubSolar lat/lon
      information.
    </change>
    <change name="Lynn Weller" date="2012-01-23">
      Application category name changed from Import and Export to Kaguya.  Fixes mantis ticket #951.
    </change>
    <change name="Janet Barrett" date="2013-06-13">
      Fixed code so that it sets the NaifFrameCode appropriately according to the base band specified
      in the labels.  Fixes mantis tickets #1167 and #1680.
    </change>
  </history>

  <category>
    <missionItem>Kaguya</missionItem>
  </category>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input PDS formatted Kaguya MI VIS or NIR file
        </brief>
        <description>
          Use this parameter to select the Kaguya MI VIS or
	  NIR EDR filename. This file must contain the PDS 
          labels.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.img *.IMG
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TO">
         <type>cube</type>
         <fileMode>output</fileMode>
         <brief>
           Output Isis cube
         </brief>
         <description>
           Use this parameter to select the output filename
         </description>
         <filter>
           *.cub
         </filter>
      </parameter>
    </group>
  </groups>
</application>
