<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="equalizer" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">

  <brief>
      Tone matches map projected cubes
  </brief>

  <description>
      <p>
        This program can be used to tonematch or equalize the brightness and/or 
        contrast of a list of input cubes prior to mosaicking.  All the input 
        cubes, which can include mosaics, must be in a common map projection as 
        this program will use the mapping information to gather statistics in 
        overlapping areas. This statistic gathering is done on a band-by-band 
        basis.  The statistics are used in a least squares solution to 
        determine multiplicative (GAIN or MULT) and additive (OFFSET or BASE) 
        corrections for each image. In addition to simply calculating corrective 
        factors and applying said factors to each image in one run of the 
        program, the user has the option to stop the processing and examine the 
        gathered statistics in a text file. The program can then be run again, 
        using the file containing those statistics as an input, to apply 
        correction to any or all of the images without the need to recalculate 
        corrective factors. The actual equation to be used for equalization on 
        each band in each cube is:
        <pre>
            newdn(s,l,b)   =   (olddn(s,l,b) - avg(b)) * GAIN(b) + avg(b) + OFFSET(b)
        </pre>
        where
        <pre>
            s = sample index
            l = line index
            b = band index
        </pre>
      </p>

      <p>
        Prior to equalizing, the user can choose whether to adjust the brightness and/or contrast of the cubes. 
        The default is to adjust both, however, if the brightness (average) of all the cubes is the same,
        then simply adjusting the contrast may suffice.   Likewise, if the standard deviation of all the 
        cubes is similar, then a contrast adjustment is not necessary.  Adjusting for contrast only implies
        the OFFSET values will be held to zero.  Similarly, adjusting for 
        brightness implies the GAIN values will be held to one.
      </p>

      <p>
          The OFFSET and GAIN values are computed independently for each image, therefore we have two
          least squares computations with N unknowns, where N is the number of cubes to be equalized.
          The overlaps, M, between all the cubes are computed, and in some cases 
          M &lt; N.  This implies an underdetermined system, and the program 
          will report an error if this occurs.  You can hold one or more images 
          to alleviate this problem.  Holding an image forces GAIN and OFFSET to 
          1.0 and 0.0 for that image, respectively. 
      </p>

      <p>
         If the the user chooses to apply correction to the images, then a list
         of output file names can be specified with the TOLIST parameter.  If no
         TOLIST is specified, the equalized cubes will be named the same as the 
         input cubes with the addition of a '.equ' prior to the '.cub' 
         extension, and placed in the same directories as their input files.
      </p>

      <p>
          For the sake of efficiency, the user may choose to set the "sampling 
          percent" to be less than its default value of 100.0.  By doing so, the
          program will likely perform its statistic gathering noticeably faster,
          but at the risk of losing accuracy in the results.  It should 
          be noted that the user also runs the risk of encountering an error if
          decreasing the sampling percent results in the amount of valid data in
          the calculated overlaps being less than the minimum set by the
          MINCOUNT parameter (default value of 1000).  Sampling percent must be 
          a decimal value between 0.0 (exclusive) and 100.0 (inclusive).
      </p>
  </description>

  <category>
    <categoryItem>Mosaicking</categoryItem>
  </category>

<oldName>
    <item>b4equal</item>
    <item>equalizer</item>
</oldName>

  <history>
    <change name="Kay Edwards" date="1994-05-24">
      Original version
    </change>
    <change name="Elizabeth Ribelin" date="2005-06-25">
      Ported to Isis 3.0
    </change>
    <change name="Elizabeth Ribelin" date="2005-10-04">
        Changed categoryItem to Photometry and Radiometry 
    </change>
    <change name="Brendan George" date="2005-11-07">
        Added application test
    </change>
    <change name="Elizabeth Miller" date="2006-01-12">
      Made SD default contrast mode (PCA may have errors)
    </change>
    <change name="Jeff Anderson" date="2007-07-16">
      Fixed memory leak
    </change>
    <change name="Jeff Anderson" date="2008-04-09">
      Modified to solve system using QRD which is faster the SVD
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2008-05-12">
      Removed references to CubeInfo 
    </change>
    <change name="Tracie Sucharski" date="2008-06-12">
      Modified call LeastSquares Solve due to change to LeastSquares
      Solve method.
    </change>
    <change name="Travis Addair" date="2009-03-12">
      Added user feedback during statistic gathering, modified existing progress
      information, and moved error checking on number of bands and projection 
      parameters to be done prior to statistic gathering    
    </change>
    <change name="Travis Addair" date="2009-06-24">
      Refactored for use with the new OverlapNormalization class, thus removing
      the option to use the broken PCA contrast mode; the PVL output has been
      modified to print all normalization information for a cube in one group
      with OverlapStatistics information coming last in the file; added an
      option to decrease the percentage of lines sampled in statistic gathering
    </change>
    <change name="Travis Addair" date="2009-07-17">
      Added a TOLIST parameter, allowing the user to specify a unique output 
      file name and location for each input file.  The default is now to 
      place each output file in the same directory as its input file, not in 
      the current working directory.
    </change> 
     <change name="Travis Addair" date="2009-07-30">
      Added functionality allowing the user to run the program applying 
      corrections based off of previously gathered statistics obtained from 
      the program's output PVL file.  The output PVL has also been changed 
      from "PVL" to "OUTSTATS".  Results will now be placed into the print 
      file.
     </change>
     <change name="Travis Addair" date="2009-11-19">
      Updated documentation and examples to reflect the most recent changes to 
      using the program.
     </change>
  </history>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
        <parameter name="FROMLIST">
          <type>filename</type>
          <fileMode>input</fileMode>
          <brief>
              List of cubes to equalize
          </brief>
          <description>
              A list of map projected cubes to equalize.  The Mapping groups 
              must match in order to do the equalization. 
          </description>
        </parameter>

        <parameter name="HOLDLIST">
            <type>filename</type>
            <fileMode>input</fileMode>
            <brief>
                List of filenames to hold 
            </brief>
            <description>
                List of cubes that are to be held in the equalization.  
                An additive and a multiplicative factor of 0 and 1 will be applied 
                to all cubes that were held.  All cubes listed in this file must 
                also be contained in FROMLIST.
            </description>
            <internalDefault>None</internalDefault>
            <filter>
              *.txt *.lis *.lst
            </filter>
        </parameter>  

        <parameter name="TOLIST">
          <type>filename</type>
          <fileMode>input</fileMode>
          <brief>
            List of the equalized cubes to be created
          </brief>
          <description>
            This list of output files must contain a file name to correspond to 
            each input file in the FROMLIST.  Input files will be associated 
            with output files by index, so that the equalized product of the 
            first file in the FROMLIST will be written to the name and location 
            of the first file in the TOLIST, and so on.  Each output file will 
            be written to the exact location with the exact name specified, 
            unless the location and name happen to be identical to those of its 
            corresponding input file, in which case an error will be thrown.  If 
            this list is not specified, but the APPLY option is still selected, 
            the output files will be placed in the directories of their input 
            files, and named the same with the exception of an added ".equ" 
            extension (e.g. "foobar.cub" becomes "foobar.equ.cub").
          </description>
          <internalDefault>Automatic</internalDefault>
        </parameter>

        <parameter name="OUTSTATS">
          <type>filename</type>
          <fileMode>output</fileMode>
          <brief>
               Output text file containing thorough equalization-related 
               statistics
          </brief>
          <description>
               This file will contain the statistics of all of the overlapping areas 
               in every band along with the computed equalizing factors 
               (OFFSET and GAIN).  Specifying this output file is optional.  
          </description>
          <internalDefault>None</internalDefault>
          <filter>
            *.txt *.pvl *.lis *.lst
          </filter>
        </parameter>

        <parameter name="INSTATS">
          <type>filename</type>
          <fileMode>input</fileMode>
          <brief>
               Input text file containing thorough equalization-related 
               statistics, used for applying correction
          </brief>
          <description>
               This file must contain the statistics of all of the overlapping 
               areas in every band along with the computed equalizing factors 
               (OFFSET and GAIN) for every image in the FROMLIST.  
          </description>
          <filter>
            *.txt *.pvl *.lis *.lst
          </filter>
        </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="ProcessingOptions">                           
        <parameter name="PROCESS">
            <type>string</type>
            <brief>
               Calculate statistics, apply correction, or do both 
            </brief>
            <description>
                This option allows the user to decide whether they want to do the 
                equalization calculations and then go on to apply correction 
                afterwards, apply correction to the images off of previously 
                gathered statistics, or do the calculations but not apply 
                correction.  If the APPLY option is not selected, you must 
                specify an OUTSTATS file.  If it is selected you can still 
                optionally specify an OUTSTATS file and the GAIN/OFFSET values 
                will be applied to each input cube.  The names and locations of 
                the output cubes are specified by the TOLIST file.  
            </description>
            <default><item>BOTH</item></default>
            <list>
                <option value="BOTH">
                    <brief>
                       Calculate statistics and apply correction 
                    </brief>
                    <description>
                        This option will calculate statistics on the images, 
                        then apply correction off of those results. 
                    </description>
                    <exclusions>
                        <item>INSTATS</item>
                    </exclusions>
                </option>
                <option value="CALCULATE">
                    <brief>
                        Calculate statistics only
                    </brief>
                    <description>
                        This option will calculate statistics on the images and 
                        print them to an output PVL file, but not correct them.
                    </description>
                    <inclusions>
                        <item>OUTSTATS</item>
                    </inclusions>
                    <exclusions>
                        <item>TOLIST</item>
                        <item>INSTATS</item>
                    </exclusions>
                </option>
                <option value="APPLY">
                    <brief>
                        Apply correction only
                    </brief>
                    <description>
                        This option will use previously generated statistics to 
                        apply correction to the images.
                    </description>
                    <inclusions>
                        <item>INSTATS</item>
                    </inclusions>
                    <exclusions>
                        <item>HOLDLIST</item>
                        <item>OUTSTATS</item>
                        <item>ADJUST</item>
                        <item>MINCOUNT</item>
                        <item>WEIGHT</item>
                        <item>PERCENT</item>
                    </exclusions>
                </option>
                               
            </list>
        </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="CalculationOptions">                           
        <parameter name="ADJUST">
            <type>string</type>
            <brief>
                Algorithm type used to adjust the pixel values.
            </brief>
            <description>
                Choose the fit option to select the algorithm to use to
                adjust the pixel values.  The BRIGHTNESS mode will equalize 
                using only an offset (the gain will be set to 1.0), and the 
                CONTRAST mode will equalize using only a gain (the offset will
                be set to 0.0).  The BOTH option will equalize using both an 
                offset and a gain.  In most cases this option will give 
                you the best results.
            </description>
            <default><item>BOTH</item></default>
            <list>
                <option value="BOTH">
                    <brief>
                        Adjust the Brightness and Contrast of the images.
                    </brief>
                    <description>
                        This option will use an algorithm that equalizes
                        both the brightness and contrast of the images.
                    </description>
                </option>
                <option value="BRIGHTNESS">
                    <brief>
                        Adjust the Brightness of the images only
                    </brief>
                    <description>
                        This option will use an algorithm that only equalizes
                        the brightness of the images.  This option should be
                        used only if the variance/standard deviation of the
                        images is close.
                    </description>
                </option>
                <option value="CONTRAST">
                    <brief>
                        Adjust the Contrast of the images only
                    </brief>
                    <description>
                        This option will use an algorithm that only equalizes
                        the contrast of the images.  This option should only
                        be used if the brightness of the images are already
                        close.
                    </description>
                </option>                
            </list>
        </parameter>

        <parameter name="MINCOUNT">
            <type>integer</type>
            <brief>
                Minimum number of points in overlapping area required to be used
                in the solution
            </brief>
            <description>
                If the number of points in the overlapping area meets or exceeds
                this value, the area will go into the least-squares solution as 
                a "known".  Otherwise it will not be included in the 
                calculations.
            </description>
            <default><item>1000</item></default>
        </parameter>

        <parameter name = "WEIGHT">
            <type>boolean</type>
            <brief>
                Whether or not overlaps should be weighted
            </brief>
            <description>
                This option allows the user to decide whether they want to  
                weight the least squares solution based on how large the overlap 
                area is, or if they want no weighting at all.  If this parameter 
                is set to "true", then larger overlapping areas will have more 
                of an impact on the corrective factors than smaller overlaps.
            </description>
            <default><item>FALSE</item></default>
        </parameter>

        <parameter name="PERCENT">
            <type>double</type>
            <brief>
                Percentage of the lines to consider when gathering overall cube
                statistics and overlap statistics
            </brief>
            <description>
                The percentage of the lines in each area to consider in the 
                process-by-line solutions for finding overall cube statistics 
                and overlap statistics.  This value must be a decimal value 
                between 0.0 (exclusive) and 100.0 (inclusive).
            </description>
            <default><item>100.0</item></default>
        </parameter>
    </group>
  </groups>

  <examples>
    <example>
      <brief>Calculate Statistics and Apply Correction</brief>
      <description>
        This example shows the most typical use of the equalizer application.  
        The defaults are to perform both calculation and adjustment for both the
        gain and offset.
      </description>
      <terminalInterface>
        <commandLine> fromlist= FromList.lst holdlist= HoldList.lst
        </commandLine>
        <description>
          Specify a list of images to equalize along with a holding list that enables the necessary
          calculations to be performed.  All other options are at default
          values.
        </description>
      </terminalInterface>

      <guiInterfaces>
        <guiInterface>
          <image width="614" height="750" src="assets/images/bothGui.jpg">
            <brief>
              Example GUI
            </brief>
            <description>
              Screenshot of the GUI with parameters set to calculate the gain 
              and offset, and then apply corrections.  Because the TOLIST 
              parameter is set to its default value of "Automatic", each output 
              image will be placed into the directory of its corresponding input
              image.  Also, because the OUTSTATS parameter is set to its default 
              value of "None", a record of the calculations performed will not 
              be written anywhere but to the print file.
            </description>
            <thumbnail width="164" height="200" caption="equalizer gui" src="assets/thumbs/bothGui.jpg" />
          </image>
        </guiInterface>
      </guiInterfaces>

      <inputImages>
        <image src="assets/images/nonEqualizedMosaic.jpg" width="512" height="512">
          <brief> Mosaic of the input images for equalizer</brief>
          <description>
              This is a a small section of the input images for the equalizer example mosaicked together.
          </description>
          <thumbnail caption=" Mosaic of unequalized input images" src="assets/thumbs/nonEqualizedMosaic.jpg" width="200" height="200"/>
          <parameterName>FROMLIST</parameterName>
        </image>
      </inputImages>

      <dataFiles>
          <dataFile path="assets/FromList.lst">
              <brief>Click here to see the list of input images to be equalized</brief>
              <description>
                  This list contains the names of three files to calculate 
                  statistics upon, and then equalize.  The file names are
                  separated by new lines.
              </description>
          </dataFile>
          <dataFile path="assets/HoldList.lst">
              <brief>Click here to see the list of input images to be held</brief>
              <description>
                  This list contains the name of one file from the FROMLIST to 
                  be held during calculations.  When multiple images are held, 
                  their file names are likewise separated by new lines.  
              </description>
          </dataFile>
      </dataFiles>

      <outputImages>
        <image src="assets/images/EqualizedMosaic.jpg" width="512" height="512">
          <brief> Mosaic of the output images for equalizer</brief>
          <description> 
              This is a small section of the equalized output images mosaicked together.
          </description>
          <thumbnail caption="Mosaic showing results of the equalizer application." src="assets/thumbs/EqualizedMosaic.jpg" width="200" height="200"/>
          <parameterName>TOLIST</parameterName>
        </image>
      </outputImages>
    </example>

    <example>
      <brief>Calculate Statistics</brief>
      <description>
        This example shows the use of the equalizer application for calculating 
        equalization statistics and writing them to a file, and not applying the 
        correction to the input images.
      </description>
      <terminalInterface>
        <commandLine> fromlist= FromList.lst holdlist=/HoldList.lst 
            outstats= stats.pvl process= calculate
        </commandLine>
        <description>
          In addition to specifying a fromlist and a holdlist, we must also 
          specify a location to write the output statistics pvl, and set the 
          process type to "calculate".  Since no output images will be created, 
          we do not (and can not), specify a tolist.  All other options are at 
          default values.
        </description>
      </terminalInterface>

      <guiInterfaces>
        <guiInterface>
          <image width="614" height="750" src="assets/images/calcGui.jpg">
            <brief>
              Example GUI
            </brief>
            <description>
              Screenshot of the GUI with parameters set to calculate 
              equalization statistics on a set of input images.
            </description>
            <thumbnail width="164" height="200" caption="equalizer gui" src="assets/thumbs/calcGui.jpg" />
          </image>
        </guiInterface>
      </guiInterfaces>

      <inputImages>
        <image src="assets/images/nonEqualizedMosaic.jpg" width="512" height="512">
          <brief> Mosaic of the input images for equalizer</brief>
          <description>
              This is a a small section of the input images for the equalizer example mosaicked together.
          </description>
          <thumbnail caption=" Mosaic of unequalized input images" src="assets/thumbs/nonEqualizedMosaic.jpg" width="200" height="200"/>
          <parameterName>FROMLIST</parameterName>
        </image>
      </inputImages>

      <dataFiles>
          <dataFile path="assets/FromList.lst">
              <brief>Click here to see the list of images to calculate statistics upon</brief>
              <description>
                  This list contains the names of three files to calculate 
                  statistics upon.  The file names are
                  separated by new lines.
              </description>
          </dataFile>
          <dataFile path="assets/HoldList.lst">
              <brief>Click here to see the list of input images to be held</brief>
              <description>
                  This list contains the name of one file from the FROMLIST to 
                  be held during calculations.  When multiple images are held, 
                  their file names are likewise separated by new lines.  
              </description>
          </dataFile>
          <dataFile path="assets/stats.pvl">
              <brief>Click here to see the output text file containing statistics for equalizing</brief>
              <description>
                  This pvl contains thorough equalization-related statistics 
                  that can be used for applying correction to any or all images 
                  used to generate this file.  
              </description>
          </dataFile>
      </dataFiles>
    </example>

    <example>
      <brief>Apply Correction</brief>
      <description>
        This example shows the use of the equalizer application for applying 
        correction to a subset of the images used to produce a specified input 
        statistics file.
      </description>
      <terminalInterface>
        <commandLine> fromlist= Input.lst tolist= Output.lst instats= 
            stats.pvl process= apply 
        </commandLine>
        <description>
          Specify a fromlist that is a sublist of the fromlist from Example 2.  
          Because calculations have already been performed, no holdlist is 
          specified, and since we want to place the output images in a specific
          location with specific names, a tolist is specified. Finally, we set
          the value of the instats parameter to be the output statistics file
          generated in Example 2, and set the process to "apply".  All other 
          options are at default values.
        </description>
      </terminalInterface>

      <guiInterfaces>
        <guiInterface>
          <image width="614" height="750" src="assets/images/applyGui.jpg">
            <brief>
              Example GUI
            </brief>
            <description>
              Screenshot of the GUI with parameters set to apply correction to a
              subset of the images used to produce a specified input statistics 
              file.
            </description>
            <thumbnail width="164" height="200" caption="equalizer gui" src="assets/thumbs/applyGui.jpg" />
          </image>
        </guiInterface>
      </guiInterfaces>

      <dataFiles>
          <dataFile path="assets/Input.lst">
              <brief>Click here to see the list of images to be equalized</brief>
              <description>
                  This list contains the names of two files to equalize.  Both 
                  file names appear in the FROMLIST file from the previous 
                  example, and both file names have calculated gain and offset
                  coefficients calculated for them in the INSTATS file. Since we
                  do not wish to create a new file for the held image, however,
                  we chose not to include it in this new list.  The file names 
                  are separated by new lines.
              </description>
          </dataFile>
          <dataFile path="assets/Output.lst">
              <brief>Click here to see the list of images to write after equalization</brief>
              <description>
                  This list contains the names of two files to be written as 
                  outputs from the equalization process.  The index of each file 
                  name corresponds to the index of a file from this example's 
                  FROMLIST file.  Here, the output images retain their original 
                  names, but are written to the current directory.
              </description>
          </dataFile>
          <dataFile path="assets/stats.pvl">
              <brief>Click here to see the input text file containing statistics for equalizing</brief>
              <description>
                  This pvl contains thorough equalization-related statistics for 
                  applying correction to any or all images used to generate this 
                  file.  In this example, two of the three files used to 
                  generate these statistics have been selected for equalization.
              </description>
          </dataFile>
      </dataFiles>

      <outputImages>
        <image src="assets/images/EqualizedMosaic.jpg" width="512" height="512">
          <brief> Mosaic of the output images for equalizer</brief>
          <description> 
              This is a small section of the equalized output images and the 
              held image from Example 2 mosaicked together.  Note that since we 
              only chose to omit the held image from Example 2 when 
              applying correction, that the results are the same as those in 
              Example 1.
          </description>
          <thumbnail caption="Mosaic showing results of the equalizer application." src="assets/thumbs/EqualizedMosaic.jpg" width="200" height="200"/>
          <parameterName>TOLIST</parameterName>
        </image>
      </outputImages>
    </example>
  </examples>
</application>
