<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="trackextract" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">
  <brief>
    Removes the tracking band from a mosaic and places it into a new tracking cube.
  </brief>

  <description>
    <p>
      Updates a mosaic cube with tracking information that was created using older versions of ISIS
      (prior to 3.6.0) to be up to date with ISIS version 3.6.0 and above. Removes the tracking
      band and the InputImages table from the input mosaic cube and places them into a separate
      tracking cube. A reference to the tracking cube is then added to the mosaic label. In the
      copying process, if a pixel in the tracking band of the input mosaic is not associated with
      any of the original input images, a NULL value is written to that pixel in the tracking cube.
      The mosaic cube's bit type remains the same, but the tracking cube's bit type will always be
      unsigned integer. 
    </p>
    <p>
      <b>Please Note: This application only works for 32-bit ("Real") mosaics as both 8-bit and
      16-bit mosaics created prior to ISIS version 3.6.0 are considered to be corrupted.</b>
    </p>
    
  </description>

  <category>
    <categoryItem>Utility</categoryItem>
  </category>

  <history>
    <change name="Kaitlyn Lee" date="2018-07-20">
      Original version
    </change>
    <change name="Summer Stapleton" date="2018-09-06">
      Updated code to throw user error if input mosaic is anything other than 32-bit ("Real") as
      it has been decided that 8-bit and 16-bit mosaics are corrupted. Updated documentation for
      this. Also fixed the NULL value being written to the tracking cube as LRS was originally
      being written instead.
    </change>
    <change name="Kaitlyn Lee" date="2018-10-16">
      Removed FLOAT_MAX because it was not being used in the code and was causing build warnings 
      on MacOS 10.13. References #5520.
    </change>
  </history>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input cube with tracking band
        </brief>
        <description>
          The mosaic created prior to ISIS version 3.6.0 that contains the tracking band
          and InputImages table to be extracted. <b>Please Note: This mosaic cube must be of
          bit-type "Real" as both 8-bit and 16-bit mosaics created before ISIS version 3.6.0 are
          considered to be corrupted.</b>
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TO">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Output mosaic and tracking cube
        </brief>
        <description>
          The output mosaic cube name that will be up to date with isis version 3.6.0 and above. 
          This cube will no longer have the tracking band or the InputImages table, but a tracking
          cube will be created in the same location with this information. This tracking cube will
          have the same base name as the mosaic, but will end in "_tracking.cub".
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>
    </group>
  </groups>
</application>
