<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="isisui" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">
  <brief>
    Outputs the command line of any ISIS application
  </brief>

  <description>
    <p>
      This program allows its user to output a validated command line for any
      ISIS application. The parameters will be validated using the application's
      xml file. Command line arguments will be used to initialize the
      application's parameters.
    </p>
    <p>
      If the GUI flag is not present on the command line, the
      parameters will be validated and the command line will be output if no
      errors were detected.
    </p>
    <p>
      If the GUI flag is present on the command line, the GUI parameters fields
      will be initilized using the command line arguments. The user will then
      be able to change parameter values and supply values for ones not on the
      command line. When the GUI is told to process the parameters, a validation
      check is done. If there were errors, a message will be displayed and the
      user will be allowed to correct the problem. If the validation succeeds
      the command line will be output, and the GUI will be taken down.
    </p>
  </description>

  <category>
    <categoryItem>Scripting</categoryItem>
  </category>

  <history>
    <change name="Stuart Sides" date="2003-03-13">
      Original version
    </change>
    <change name="Stuart Sides" date="2003-05-16">
      Modified schema location from astogeology... to isis.astrogeology..."
    </change>
    <change name="Stuart Sides" date="2003-05-30">
      Added modifications to apptest by Kim
    </change>
    <change name="Brendan George" date="2006-09-28">
        Documentation fixes
    </change>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2009-11-27">
        Changed the call to Application to provide compatability withg Qt 
        startup requirements.
    </change>

  </history>

  <groups>
    <group name="Command Line">
      <parameter name="arg1">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>
          An ISIS application
        </brief>
        <description>
          The ISIS application you need the command line for.
          Note: This must be the first command line option!
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="arg2">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <brief>
          Flag for starting the Isis GUI
        </brief>
        <description>
          If this flag is present anywhere on the command line, the Isis GUI
          will be started. All application parameters from the other arguments
          will be inserted into the correct fields.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="arg3-n">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>
          Arguments to the application named in arg1
        </brief>
        <description>
          These arguments are specific to the application named in arg1. Their
          formats and values are dependant on the application.
        </description>
      </parameter>
    </group>
  </groups>

  <examples>
    <example>
      <brief>
        Display GUI for the program crop.
      </brief>
      <description>
        Display the GUI for the application "crop". Since there are no
        parameter arguments for crop the fields will be initially empty.
      </description>
      <terminalInterface>
        <commandLine>
          crop GUI
        </commandLine>
        <description>
          This example deminstrates how to get the GUI for the ISIS application
          "crop" to be displayed. The parameters for crop will initially be
          empty.
        </description>
      </terminalInterface>
    </example>

    <example>
      <brief>
        Display GUI for program ratio.
      </brief>
      <description>
        Display the GUI for the application "ratio". The arguments "num",
        "den" and "to" will be used to fill in the corresponding parameter
        values when the GUI is displayed.
      </description>
      <terminalInterface>
        <commandLine>
          ratio GUI num=$WORK/numerator.cub:3
            den=denominated.cub:1 to=result.cub
        </commandLine>
        <description>
          This example deminstrates how to get the GUI for the ISIS application
          "ratio" to be displayed. The parameters for ratio will initially be
          set to the values from the command line.
        </description>
      </terminalInterface>
    </example>

    <example>
      <brief>
        Check the command line argument to ratio for validity without the GUI.
      </brief>
      <description>
        The argument "num" will be filled in when the GUI is displayed.
      </description>
      <terminalInterface>
        <commandLine>
          ratio num=$WORK/numerator.cub:3
        </commandLine>
        <description>
          This example deminstrates how to validate the parameters given on
          the command line. No GUI will be displayed. This example will fail
          with an error message since values were not specified for all the
          required parameters. It will also set the exicution status to a non
          zero (failes) value.
        </description>
      </terminalInterface>
    </example>
  </examples>
</application>

