<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="mical" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">

  <brief>
     Radiometrically calibrates a Mars Exploration Rover (MER) 
     Microscopic Imager(MI) image
  </brief>

  <description>
  <p>
    mical performs radiometric corrections to images acquired by the MER
    MI camera.  MI images taken during science operations have 1024 samples
    and 1024 lines and are single bands.  The pre calibration images are signed 
    word or 16 bit images.  Subareas can be aquired but this was rarely done during 
    the mission.<br/>

    mical has a number of parameters required to process MER MI image
    data.  Most of these parameters are read from an ISIS parameter defaults
    file located in the mer directory specified in the IsisPreference file.  
    This file has the form:
     <pre>    
      $mer/calibration/mical.ker.xxx
    
      where "xxx" is a positive number.
     </pre>  
    mical will search for the parameter file with the highest number and
    load all its defaults needed to process MI images.  Note that the
    caller may explicity provide an alternative ISIS parameter defaults
    file name in the "CALKERNEL" input parameter if they have their own
    set of defaults that applies to MI data.  See an existing calibration
    file for details on how to configure this file.
  </p>  
<p>
    The level of calibration output can be selected.  by choosing one of the
    output options, the user can choose to dark current correct, dark current and 
    flat field, or dark current, flat field and output in I/F values.
  </p>

  <p>
    The dark current correction equation mical implements is as follows:
    <pre>
      r = dn - (rpi + rpv) + (zei * zev) + (aai * aav)
    </pre>

    Where: 
            r is the aver signal being generated at the focal plane
            dn is the input pixel value
            rpi is the referance pixel dn 
            rpv is the referance pixel correction value
            zei is the zero exposure pixel dn
            zev is the zero exposure correction value
            aai is the active area pixel dn
            aav is the active area correction value

     The user can choose to not correct for the reference pixel, zero exposure
     or active area  by selecting or deselecting the RPCORRECTION, ZECORECTION,
     or AACORRECTION checkbox.  The program will also determain if these 
     corrections should be applied.  If the ShutteEffectCorrectionFlag is set to "TRUE"
     in the image labels, the reference pixel, and zero exposure will not be applied.<br/>

     If a flat fielded output is chosen:
     <pre>
       r = dn / f
     </pre>

       where:
       r is the corrected output value
       dn is the input pixel that has been dark current corrected
       f is a flat field pixel<br/>

       if the "ShutteEffectCorrectionFlag is false and the exposure duration is greater
       them zero and less them 1000 and the image is mot equal to 1024 samples, a 
       image smear correction is applied.
</p>




  </description>

  <history>
    <change name="Robert Sucharski" date="2007-02-16">
      Original version
    </change>
  </history>

  <category>
    <missionItem>Mars Exploration Rover</missionItem>
  </category>

  <seeAlso>
    <applications>
      <item>mer2isis</item>
    </applications>
  </seeAlso>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Level 0 MER MI image
        </brief>
        <description>
          An uncalibrated MER MI image.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub *.CUB
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TO">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <pixelType>real</pixelType>
        <brief>
          Level 1 MER MI image
        </brief>
        <description>
          The resultant radiometrically calibrated cube
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub *.CUB
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="CALKERNEL">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          PVL kernel containing calibration prameters
        </brief>
        <internalDefault>Internal Default </internalDefault>
        <description>
          If you do not enter a file, mical will search for a file with the form:
          <pre>
            $mer/calibration/mical.kernel.xxx

            where "xxx" is a positive number.
          </pre>
          the kernel with the highest version (xxx) will be used.
          See an existing calibration 
          file for details on how to configure this file.
        </description>
        <helpers>
          <helper name="H1">
            <function>helperButtonLogCalKernel</function>
            <brief>View Calibration Kernel in the log area</brief>
            <description>
              This button will display the callibration kernel in the log area.
              If no file is entered in the CALKERNEL parameter then the system
              file will be displayed.
            </description>
            <icon>$ISIS3DATA/base/icons/view_text.png</icon>
          </helper>
        </helpers>
     </parameter>

     <parameter name="REFPIXIMAGE">
       <type>cube</type>
       <fileMode>input</fileMode>
       <brief>
         Referance Pixel image (ERP)
       </brief>
       <description>
         At times, a referance pixel image was aquired when image data was 
         taken.  If a referance pixel image was acquired, it can be used in the 
         calibration.  A referance pixel image uses the designation "ERP" rather 
         then "EFF" in the file name.
       </description>
       <filter>
         *.cub *.CUB
       </filter>
       <internalDefault>Use Model Value</internalDefault>
     </parameter> 
      <parameter name="FLATFIELD">
         <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          The flat field image used in correction
        </brief>
        <description>
          User can enter a flat field image that will be used in the correction.  
          If no value is entered, then the file listed in the calibration kernel 
          will be used.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub *.CUB
        </filter>
        <internalDefault> Use value in kernel </internalDefault>
      </parameter>
    </group>
    <group name="Output Options">
      <parameter name="CALSTAGE">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>
          The calibration stage to process
        </brief>
        <description>
          This parameter allows the user to control what calibration step will 
          be applied to the input image.  if "DARK" is selected, then only a 
          dark current correction is preformed.  If "FLAT" is selected, the 
          image is corrected for dark current and a flat field correction is 
          applied.  if "IOF" is chosen then the final outut will in refiectance 
          values.
        </description>
        <default>
          <item>IOF</item>
        </default>
        <list>
          <option value="DARK">
            <brief>
              Dark Current correction
            </brief>
            <description>
              The output file will be a dark current corrected file.
            </description>
          </option>
          <option value="FLAT">
            <brief>
              Dark Current and Flat Field correction
            </brief>
            <description>
              The output will be a dark current corrected and flat field 
              corrected.  This is the "CFD" image in the PDS archive.
            </description>
          </option>
          <option value="IOF">
            <brief>
              Convert Dark current and Flat Field  corrected image to I/F values
            </brief>
            <description>
              The output file will be a flat field corrected image that has been 
              converted to refiectance.  This is the "IFF" file in the PDS 
              archive.
            </description>
          </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Entry Option">
      <parameter name="CCDtemp">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief>
          CCD temperature
        </brief>
        <description>
          A user defined CCD temperature that will be used in calculations that use
          the CCD temperature.  If entered, this value will be used rather then the 
          temperature in the image labels.
        </description>
        <internalDefault>Temperature from Labels</internalDefault>
      </parameter>

     <parameter name="PCBtemp">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief>
          PCB temperature
        </brief>
        <description>
          A user defined PCB temperature that will be used in calculations that use
          the PCB temperature.  If entered, this value will be used rather then the 
          temperature in the image labels.          
        </description>
        <internalDefault>Temperature from labels</internalDefault>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="RPCORRECTION">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <brief>
          Correct for Referance Pixel
        </brief>
        <description>
          If this option is selected, the reference pixel correction will be applied.  
          if the ShutteEffectCorrectionFlag is set to TRUE then the reference pixel
          correction is not applied, even if this parameter is set to true.  The 
          default is true which will apply the correction.
        </description>
        <default><item>TRUE</item></default>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="ZECORRECTION">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <brief>
          Correct for Zero Exposure
        </brief>
        <description>
          If this option is selected, the zero exposure correction will be applied.  
          if the ShutteEffectCorrectionFlag is set to TRUE then the zero exposure
          correction is not applied, even if this parameter is set to true.  The 
          default is true which will apply the correction.
        </description>
        <default><item>TRUE</item></default>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="AACORRECTION">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <brief>
          Correct for Active Area
        </brief>
        <description>
          If this option is selected, the active area. correction will be applied.  
          The default is true which will apply the correction.
        </description>
        <default><item>TRUE</item></default>
      </parameter>
      </group>
   </groups>
</application>

