<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="demprep" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">
  <brief>
    This program prepares DEMs for use as shape models. It is not valid to run this program on anything but a DEM.
  </brief>

  <description>
    This program performs the necessary preparation of a DEM file so that it can be used as a shape model. The
    method used to find the intersection of a look vector with a DEM surface has recently changed (9/2010) to
    take care of problems that were encountered at the poles of the DEM file that were caused by artifacts
    generated near the poles when the DEM was produced. This new intersection algorithm requires that the DEM
    have a padded line at any pole that exists in the DEM file. If the DEM is a global DEM, then the left and
    right edges are also padded with a single column of pixels. The padding allows the bilinear interpolation
    to work properly at the poles. The new algorithm also requires that the DEM have a table blob in its labels
    ("ShapeModelStatistics") which contains the minimum and maximum radii that occcur in the DEM file. This
    information is required in order to bracket the solution where the look vector intersects the DEM. This 
    information helps to make the algorithm run much faster. The DEM is required to be a Planetocentric file
    in Simple Cylindrical projection. If it is not, then the demprep program will fail. This program will first
    check to see if the DEM has been padded. If padding has already occurred, then no further padding will be
    added. It is not valid to run this program on anything but a DEM.

    This program can be run on files with non-Equatorial projections. If the file is non-Equatorial, then it
    cannot be padded. However, the program will add the ShapeModelStatistics table blob to the DEM file labels.
  </description>

  <history>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2008-09-15">
      Original version (demwrap)
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2008-10-03">
      Added additional checks for valid projections and fixed the implementation
      of the north and south poles.
    </change>
    <change name="Janet Barrett" date="2010-09-09">
      Original version (demprep) Used the demwrap program as a model for the demprep program.
    </change>
    <change name="Janet Barrett" date="2011-02-18">
      The padding at the poles is no longer set to the average value of the line below or above the padded line.
      In order for the ray tracing routine in the Sensor class to converge when it is right at the poles, the
      padding had to be changed in the following way: At the north pole, the average of the pixels that lie in
      the first line of the file is calculated. Then, each pixel in the top padded line is set to 2*average - 
      the pixel below it. At the south pole, the average of the pixels that lie in the last line of the file
      is calculated. Then, each pixel in the bottom padded line is set to 2*average - the pixel above it. This
      change only applies to those DEM files that cover the poles.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2011-03-18">
      Fixed handling of special pixels. Now reports the min/max radius
      encountered. A negative radius will now cause this program to fail.
    </change>
    <change name="Janet Barrett" date="2011-07-05">
      Modified the program so that it works with files that have non-Equatorial projections. These types
      of files will not be padded. They will only have the ShapeModelStatistics table blob added to their
      labels. Several programs are looking for the ShapeModelStatistics table blob to determine if the
      file is a DEM.
    </change>
    <change name="Debbie A. Cook" date="2012-12-10">
      Changed to use TProjection instead of Projection.  References #775
    </change>
    <change name="Kristin Berry" date="2014-05-30">
      Fixed padding for special pixels. References #1010
    </change>
  </history>

  <category>
    <categoryItem>System</categoryItem>
  </category>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input DEM cube
        </brief>
        <description>
  	      The DEM cube which will be padded
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TO">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Output padded DEM cube
        </brief>
        <description>
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>
    </group>
  </groups>
</application>
