<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="qmos" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">

  <brief>
    Display and analyze cube footprints
  </brief>

  <description>
    This is a tool for visualizing image footprints for a mosaic.

    <p/>qmos is designed specifically for visualizing large amounts of images,
    how images overlap, where control points lie on the images, and how
    jigsaw has moved control points.

    <p/>qmos only supports files which have latitude and longitude information
    associated with them. Global projections are also not supported. If your
    files meet these requirements, it is beneficial to run a couple of Isis
    programs on your files before loading them into qmos. The programs you
    should run are:
    <ul>
      <li>
        <i>
          camstats from=future_input_to_qmos.cub attach=true
          sinc=... linc=...
        </i>
      </li>
      <br/>
      This enables qmos to give you the emission angle, incidence angle, and
      resolution in the <b>File List</b>
      <li>
        <i>
          footprintinit from=future_input_to_qmos.cub sinc=... linc=...
        </i>
      </li>
      <br/>
      This enables qmos to use the given footprints instead of trying to
      calculate its own. The 'linc' and 'sinc' parameters can have a significant
      effect on your image's footprint. Also, images without footprints cannot
      be opened more than one at a time. Running footprintinit will
      significantly speed up loading images into qmos.
    </ul>

    To see more documentation, launch qmos and go to "Help -> qmos Help."
  </description>

  <category>
    <categoryItem>Display</categoryItem>
  </category>

  <history>
    <change name="Stacy Alley" date="2009-05-20">
      Original version
    </change>
    <change name="Eric Hyer" date="2010-03-22">
      Discontinued forcing of gui style to windows
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2011-09-28">
      Rewrote the underlying functionality and re-factored the majority of the
      code base to make a quicker, more-intuitive and more maintainable
      program. Updated user documentation to be much more complete.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2011-10-05">
      Improved documentation in preparation for the October release. Working
      with me to help figure out the best ways to document qmos were Orrin
      Thomas and Trent Hare. Fixes #427
    </change>
    <change name="Kimberly Oyama and Steven Lambright" date="2012-07-26">
      Added the 'Auto Grid' functionality, an options dialog, the option to select
      the source of the latitude and longitude extents, and an 'Auto Apply' option to
      update the grid as parameters are changed to the grid tool. Also changed the
      draw and clear grid buttons to a single 'Show Grid' check button. Updated the
      documentation to include these changes. Fixes #604.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2012-12-27">
      Added a 'Phase Angle' column to the list of opened files. This column behaves exactly
      like the other camera angle columns with respect to visibility and sorting. Fixes #1093.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2013-01-09">
      Added some color coding options for the jigsaw movement arrows in the control network
      tool. You can now color code this arrows on the number of measures in a point or on the
      maximum residual magnitude of the measures in the point. Fixes #479.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2013-02-01">
      Fixed a bug that caused qmos to sometimes freeze, in the grid tool, when the maximum longitude
      was set to a negative value. Fixes #1060.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2013-02-12">
      Improved map file capabilities. Please see the help pages inside of qmos (Help -> qmos Help)
      for descriptions and explanations of the new functionality. Fixes #1034.
    </change>
  </history>
</application>
