<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="qmos" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">

  <brief>
    Display and analyze cube footprints
  </brief>

  <description>
    This is a tool for visualizing image footprints for a mosaic.

    <p/>qmos is designed specifically for visualizing large amounts of images,
    how images overlap, where control points lie on the images, and how
    jigsaw has moved control points.

    <p/>qmos is designed specifically for visualizing large amounts of images,
    how images overlap, where control points lie on the images, and how
    jigsaw has moved control points.

    <p/>qmos only supports files which have latitude and longitude information
    associated with them. Global projections are also not supported. If your 
    files meet these requirements, it is beneficial to run a couple of Isis 
    programs on your files before loading them into qmos. The programs you
    should run are:
    <ul>
      <li>
        <i>
          camstats from=future_input_to_qmos.cub attach=true
          sinc=... linc=...
        </i>
      </li>
      <br/>
      This enables qmos to give you the emission angle, incidence angle, and
      resolution in the <b>File List</b>
      <li>
        <i>
          footprintinit from=future_input_to_qmos.cub sinc=... linc=...
        </i>
      </li>
      <br/>
      This enables qmos to use the given footprints instead of trying to
      calculate its own. The 'linc' and 'sinc' parameters can have a significant
      effect on your image's footprint. Also, images without footprints cannot
      be opened more than one at a time. Running footprintinit will
      significantly speed up loading images into qmos.
    </ul>

    To see more documentation, launch qmos and go to "Help -> qmos Help."
  </description>

  <category>
    <categoryItem>Display</categoryItem>
  </category>

  <history>
    <change name="Stacy Alley" date="2009-05-20">
      Original version
    </change>
    <change name="Eric Hyer" date="2010-03-22">
      Discontinued forcing of gui style to windows
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2011-09-28">
      Rewrote the underlying functionality and re-factored the majority of the
      code base to make a quicker, more-intuitive and more maintainable
      program. Updated user documentation to be much more complete.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2011-10-05">
      Improved documentation in preparation for the October release. Working
      with me to help figure out the best ways to document qmos were Orrin
      Thomas and Trent Hare. Fixes #427
    </change>
  </history>
</application>
