<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="csspckgen"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">

  <brief>
    Creates a new Cassini PCK SPICE DB file for the latest date-versioned PCKs
  </brief>

  <description>
    <p>
      This program creates the latest PCK SPICE DB file for the Cassini
      missions.  The Cassini mission continually refines its approximations of
      planetary constants, and so regularly releases their latest PCK with each
      SPK release.  There are only two PCKs that need to be considered: a
      general Cassini PCK and a Jupiter PCK.  Each file is versioned with a date
      string.
    </p>
    <p>
      New version of Isis are capable of resolving this date string and
      grabbing the latest PCK from the data area.  In an effort to support
      legacy versions of Isis 3, this program adds Selection groups for the
      direct paths to the latest PCK files, and is called by the makedb script
      within the Cassini PCK directory in order to always contain the latest
      PCKs.
    </p>
    <p>
      When initializing a file, spiceinit will grab the last PCK in the DB file
      that it can use for the given coverage period.  With this in mind, the
      date-versioned filenames should be placed below the direct filenames such
      that new versions of Isis will resolve the latest PCK at runtime.  This
      way, in case a user is missing the directly specified PCK, they could fall
      back to whatever happens to be the latest PCK in their data area.
      Unfortunately, in legacy versions of Isis 3, spiceinit only looks at the
      coverage time, and does not consider whether a file exists when
      determining if it is usable, thus the date-versioned filenames must be
      placed above the direct filenames, and will thus not be used until legacy
      support is dropped.
    </p>
    <p>
      Once all supported versions of Isis contain the date-versioning logic,
      these direct filenames should no longer be added by this program, and
      removed from all future DB files.
    </p>
  </description>

  <history>
    <change name="Travis Addair" date="2012-04-03">
      Original version
    </change>
  </history>

  <category>
    <categoryItem>System</categoryItem>
  </category>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input PCK kernel.????.db file
        </brief>
        <description>
          The PCK PVL group DB file used to generate the new db file. Defaulted
          to use the versioned pattern
          $ISISDATA/cassini/kernels/pck/kernels.????.db.
        </description>
        <internalDefault>
          Automatic
        </internalDefault>
        <filter>
          *.db
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TO">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Output PCK kernel.????.db file
        </brief>
        <description>
          The new DB file that is the matching PCK file.  Defaulted to use a new
          version of the patterned filename
          $ISISDATA/cassini/kernels/pck/kernels.????.db.
        </description>
        <internalDefault>
          Automatic
        </internalDefault>
        <filter>
          *.db
        </filter>
      </parameter>
    </group>
  </groups>
</application>
