<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="chan1m32isis" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">

 <brief>
    Import Chandrayaan-1 Moon Mineralogy Mapper (M3) images into ISIS cubes
 </brief>

 <description>
    This program imports Chandrayaan-1 Moon Mineralogy Mapper (M3) Level 1B (L1B) or Level 0 (L0) PDS
    products into ISIS cubes.
    <p>
      The level 1B PDS data files have been processed to have north up and east to the right. This processing
      is removed during the import of the data into ISIS. If the level 1B file is missing lines, the program will add 
      lines of data containing the special pixel value NULL to pad the image to the correct number of lines. The
      location of missing lines is determined by looking for time differences between adjacent records of the 
      UTC_TIME table greater than the exposture duration. 
    </p>
    <p>
      Chandrayaan-1 M3 L1B PDS data products consist of:
      <ul>
        <li> A detached PDS label file </li> 
        <li> A multiple-band image file containing the calibrated spectral radiance image data in units 
      of (W/m^2/µm/sr)</li>
        <li> A 3-band image file containing pixel location data </li>
        <li> A 10 band image file containing observation geometry </li>
      </ul>
    </p>
    <p>
      The level 0 PDS data files were not flipped or mirrored from the orientation they were in when collected. The level
      0 files are missing the same lines as the level 1B files, but they do not contain the necessary information to add
      NULL lines as do the level 1B products.
    </p>
    <p>
      Chandrayaan-1 M3 L0 PDS data products consist of:
      <ul>
        <li> An detached PDS label file </li>
        <li> A multi-band file containing the raw data </li>
        </ul>
    </p>

 </description>

  <history>
    <change name="Steven Lambright and Tracie Sucharski" date="2013-03-12">
      Original version
    </change>
    <change name="Stuart Sides" date="2014-04-03">
      Updated documentation after reviews
    </change>
    <change name="Stuart Sides" date="2014-04-18">
      Added missing line detection and correction based on the TIM table for level 1B products.
    </change>
  </history>

  <category>
    <missionItem>Chandrayaan 1</missionItem>
  </category>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input detached PDS formatted Chandrayaan-1 M3 label file
        </brief>
        <description>
          This file is a detached PDS formatted label which contains pointers to the following files:
          <ul>
            <li>Multi-band image of calibrated spectral radiance level 1B data or raw level 0 data (*_RDN.IMG, *_L0.IMG) </li>
            <li>Three band image containing position of each image pixel on the Moon (*_LOC.IMG). Not used for L0 label files.</li>
            <li>Ten band image containing observation geometry (*_OBS.IMG). Not used for L0 label files.</li>
          </ul>
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.LBL
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TO">
         <type>cube</type>
         <fileMode>output</fileMode>
         <brief>
           Output calibrated spectral radiance image cube
         </brief>
         <description>
           Output ISIS cube containing calibrated spectral radiance pixels (units of W/m^2/µm/sr) or level 0 raw data.
         </description>
         <filter>
           *.cub
         </filter>
       </parameter>

       <parameter name="LOC">
         <type>cube</type>
         <fileMode>output</fileMode>
         <internalDefault>None</internalDefault>
         <brief>
           Optional output file containing lunar surface location of all radiance image pixels.
         </brief>
         <description>
           This is an optional output file containing location information for the center of all pixels 
           contained in the radiance image file (L1B) created from the "TO" parameter. The output 
           ISIS cube will 3 band containing the following:
           <ol>
             <li>Planetocentric latitude in decimal degrees</li>
             <li>Longitude in decimal degrees</li>
             <li>Radius in meters from the Moon center</li>
           </ol>
           If the "TO" parameter is not an L1B product then this keyword will be ignored.  
         </description>
         <filter>
           *.cub
         </filter>
       </parameter>

       <parameter name="OBS">
         <type>cube</type>
         <fileMode>output</fileMode>
         <internalDefault>None</internalDefault>
         <brief>
           Optional output file containing observation geometry information for all radiance image pixels.
         </brief>
         <description>
           This is an optional output file containing observation geometry information for each
           pixel in the  radiance image. The output ISIS cube with have ten bands containing the following:
           <ol>
             <li> To-sun azimuth angle (decimal degrees, clockwise from local north)</li>
             <li> To-sun zenith angle (incidence angle in decimal degrees, zero at zenith)</li>
             <li> To-sensor azimuth angle (decimal degrees, clockwise from local north)</li>
             <li> To-sensor zenith angle (emission angle in decimal degrees, zero at zenith)</li>
             <li> Observation phase angle (decimal degrees, in plane of to-sun and to-sensor rays)</li>
             <li> To-sun path length (decimal au with scene mean subtracted and noted in PDS label)</li>
             <li> To-sensor path length (decimal meters)</li>
             <li> Surface slope from DEM (decimal degrees, zero at horizontal)</li>
             <li> Surface aspect from DEM (decimal degrees, clockwise from local north)</li>
             <li> Local cosine i (unitless, cosine of angle between to-sun and local DEM facet normal vectors)</li>
           </ol>
           If the "TO"  parameter is not an L1B product then this keyword will be ignored.  
         </description>
         <filter>
           *.cub
         </filter>
       </parameter>
    </group>
  </groups>
</application>

