<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="nocam2map" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">

  <brief>
    Map project a cube without a camera model
  </brief>

  <description>
    <p>
      This program will map project a raw instrument cube without a camera
      model. However, the lack of a camera model requires latitude/longitude
      information at each pixel in the raw cube. This must be facilitated 
      through a latitude image and longitude image with the same size as the raw
      instrument cube.
    </p>

    <p>
      The procedure to project the input cube is output driven. That is, we
      create an output map cube (as specified by the user) and at each output
      pixel, compute its projected latitude/longitude using the projection
      parameters. Using this coordinate we must search for that position in
      the two input cubes (latitude/longitude). If found, we will have a
      sub-pixel location that has a 1-1 correspondence with the raw instrument
      pixel. An interpolator (nearest neighbor, bilinear, or cubic convolution)
      is then used to compute a value for the output pixel.
    </p>

    <p>
      Therefore the root of the problem is finding the latitude/longitude in the 
      two input cubes as it is a 2-dimensional search. We do this by first
      creating two polynomial functions of a user-specified order (DEGREE), one
      for sample and one for line. These functions, f(lat,long) = sample and
      g(lat,long) = line, are dervied using a least-squares computation by
      collecting a sparse set of control points (line,samp)-to-(lat,long). The
      sparseness is controlled by the SINC and LINC. Unfortunately the
      polynomial is not accurate enough to supply the mapping to sub-pixel
      accuracy. The level of errors (between control points and the equations
      derived) can be written to the RESIDUAL file for examination.
    </p>

    <p>
      To achieve sub-pixel accuracy, we use the polynomials to get us close
      (generally within 6 pixels). Using this estimated location, two affine
      transforms are computed by collecting a small 3x3 window of control
      points. These equations are used to further refine the estimated location.
      We iterate this process until our estimated sample/line is within an
      acceptable tolerance (TOLERANCE) of latitude/longitude values contained in
      the two cubes (LATCUB/LONCUB) or until the number of iterations is 
      exceeded (ITERATIONS).
    </p>

    <p>
      Defining the output map is controlled as follows:
      <ul>
        <li>ProjectionName - Should be specified by the map file</li>
        <li>TargetName -  Will be searched for in the FROM cube or can be
          specified by the user.
        </li>
        <li>EquatorialRadius and PolarRadius- Will be automatically computed
          from NAIF kernels or can be specified by the user.
        </li>
        <li>LatitudeType - Will be read from the map if available,
          otherwise will be set to the latitude type of the LATCUB</li>
        <li>LongitudeDirection - Will be read from the map if available,
          otherwise will be set to the longitude direction of the LONCUB</li>
        <li>LongitudeDomain - 0-360 by default.</li>
        <li>MinimumLatitude - Can be computed from the LATCUB, read from the map
          file or user specified.</li>
        <li>MaximumLatitude - Can be computed from the LATCUB, read from
          the map or user specified.</li>
        <li>MinimumLongitude - Can be computed from the LONCUB, read from
          the map or user specified.</li>
        <li>MaximumLongitude - Can be computed from the LONCUB, read from
          the map or user specified.</li>
        <li>Scale or PixelResolution - Can be computed<sup>1</sup> from the
           input, read from the map, or user specified in either meters/pixel
          (PixelResolution) or pixels/degree (Scale)</li>
      </ul>
    </p>

      <pre>
<sup>1</sup>To compute the scale we find the number of pixels from point (1, 1) to point (nsamples, nlines) in the input cube:
  sqrt[(nsamples-1)<sup>2</sup> + (nlines-1)<sup>2</sup>]
 And the angle across this line:
  acos(cos(latitude_point1) * cos(latitude_point2) * cos(longitude_point1 - longitude_point2) + sin(latitude_point1) * sin(latitude_point2))
 The scale is equal to the number of pixels divided by the angle in pixels per degree.
      </pre>

  </description>

  <category>
    <categoryItem>Map Projection</categoryItem>
  </category>

  <history>
    <change name="Noah Hilt" date="2008-08-01">
      Original Version
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2009-01-27">
      Fixed parameter names
    </change>
    <change name="Noah Hilt" date="2009-03-02">
      The min/max longitude/latitude are now converted from the input domain to 
      the map file's domain if necessary.
    </change>
    <change name="Travis Addair" date="2009-08-10">
      Mapping group parameters are now placed into the print file.
    </change>
  </history>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input cube to be mapped
        </brief>
        <description>
          This will specify the raw instrument cube to be mapped.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="LATCUB">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input cube to read latitude values
        </brief>
        <description>
          The DN values from this cube will be used as the latitude values for
          the input cube, samples and lines must match the FROM cube.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="LATTYPE">
        <type>string</type>
        <default>
          <item>PLANETOCENTRIC</item>
        </default>
        <brief>The latitude type</brief>
        <description>
          Specify the latitude type, either in planetographic or planetocentric 
          coordinates.
        </description>
        <list>
          <option value="PLANETOCENTRIC">
            <brief>Planetocentric Latitude</brief>
            <description>
              Sets the latitude to be in planetocentric coordinates.
            </description>
          </option>
          <option value="PLANETOGRAPHIC">
            <brief> Planetographic latitude</brief>
            <description>
              Sets the latitude to be in planetographic coordinates.
            </description>
          </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="LONCUB">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input cube to read longitude values
        </brief>
        <description>
          The DN values from this cube will be used as the longitude values for
          the input cube, samples and lines must match the FROM cube.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="LONDIR">
        <type>string</type>
        <default>
          <item>POSITIVEEAST</item>
        </default>
        <brief>The longitude direction</brief>
        <description>
          Specify the longitude direction, either positive east or positive
          west.
        </description>
        <list>
          <option value="POSITIVEEAST">
            <brief>Positive East Longitude</brief>
            <description>
              Sets the longitude direction to be positive east.
            </description>
          </option>
          <option value="POSITIVEWEST">
            <brief>Positive West Longitude</brief>
            <description>
              Sets the longitudedirection to be positive west.
            </description>
          </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>

        <parameter name="TO">
          <type>cube</type>
          <fileMode>output</fileMode>
          <brief>
            Newly mapped cube
          </brief>
          <description>
            This file will contain the results of the remapping.
          </description>
          <filter>
            *.cub
          </filter>
        </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name ="Polynomial Fit">
      <parameter name ="DEGREE">
        <type>integer</type>
          <default>
            <item>3</item>
          </default>
          <brief>Degree of polynomial functions</brief>
          <description>
             The order of the polynomial functions to compute sample/line from 
             latitude/longitude.
            </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name ="SINC">
        <type>integer</type>
          <internalDefault>
            Computed
          </internalDefault>
          <brief>Sample Increment</brief>
          <description>
              The number of samples skipped over when adding points to the
              polynomial functions.
            </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name ="LINC">
        <type>integer</type>
          <internalDefault>
            Computed
          </internalDefault>
          <brief>Line Increment</brief>
          <description>
              The number of lines skipped over when adding points to the
              polynomial functions.
            </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name ="RESIDUALS">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
          <internalDefault>
            none
          </internalDefault>
          <brief>File to write residuals to</brief>
          <description>
              If a file is specified, residuals for each point (line, sample) 
              are written to the file for examination.
            </description>
      </parameter>

     <parameter name="NOWARP">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>false</item></default>
        <brief>Specify whether or not to warp the image</brief>
        <description>
          If set to true, the image will not be processed and warped, and will
          only calculate the polynomial fit with errors.
        </description>
        <exclusions>
          <item>TO</item>
          <item>MAP</item>
          <item>PIXRES</item>
          <item>RESOLUTION</item>
          <item>TARGET</item>
          <item>EQURADIUS</item>
          <item>POLRADIUS</item>
          <item>DEFAULTRANGE</item>
          <item>MINLAT</item>
          <item>MAXLAT</item>
          <item>MINLON</item>
          <item>MAXLON</item>
          <item>TOLERANCE</item>
          <item>ITERATIONS</item>
          <item>INTERP</item>
        </exclusions>
      </parameter>
      </group>

    <group name="Mapping">
      <parameter name="MAP">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          File containing mapping parameters
        </brief>
        <defaultPath>$base/templates/maps</defaultPath>
        <default><item>$base/templates/maps/sinusoidal.map</item></default>
        <description>
          A file containing the desired output mapping parameters in PVL form.  This
          file can be a simple hand produced label file.  It can also be an existing cube label
          which contains a Mapping group.  You can produce map file using the "maptemplate" program.
        </description>
        <helpers>
          <helper name="H1">
            <function>PrintMap</function>
            <brief>View MapFile</brief>
            <description>
              This helper button will cat out the mapping group of the given mapfile to the session log
               of the application
             </description>
            <icon>$ISIS3DATA/base/icons/labels.png</icon>
          </helper>
        </helpers>
        <filter>
          *.map *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="PIXRES">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>Defines how the pixel resolution in the output map file is obtained</brief>
        <default><item>COMPUTE</item></default>
        <description>
          This parameter is used to specify how the pixel resolution is obtained for the output map
          projected cube.
        </description>

        <helpers>
          <helper name="H1">
            <function>ComputePixRes</function>
            <brief>Compute Pixel Resolution </brief>
            <description>This helper button will compute the pixel
              resolution from the input</description>
            <icon>$ISIS3DATA/base/icons/exec.png</icon>
          </helper>
          <helper name="H2">
            <function>LoadMapRes</function>
            <brief>Load Map File Resolution </brief>
            <description>This helper button will load the default resolution from the map file</description>
          </helper>
        </helpers>

        <list>
           <option value="COMPUTE">
              <brief>Compute resolution from input cube</brief>
              <description>
                This option will automatically determine the resolution from the
                input. The scale in pixels per degree is computed by calculating 
                the angle from point (1,1) to point (nsamples, nlines) across 
                the input cube and dividing the number of pixels across the line 
                from point (1,1) to point (nsamples, nlines) by the angle.
              </description>
              <exclusions>
                <item>RESOLUTION</item>
              </exclusions>
            </option>

           <option value="MAP">
              <brief>Read resolution from input map file</brief>
              <description>
                This option will use either the PixelResolution (meters/pixel) or Scale (pixels/degree) in the map file.
              </description>
              <exclusions>
                <item>RESOLUTION</item>
              </exclusions>
            </option>

           <option value="MPP">
              <brief> Get resolution from user in meters per pixel</brief>
              <description>
                This option allows the user to specify the resolution in meters per pixel using the RESOLUTION parameter
              </description>
              <inclusions>
                <item>RESOLUTION</item>
              </inclusions>
            </option>

           <option value="PPD">
              <brief> Get resolution from user in pixels per degree</brief>
              <description>
                This option allows the user to specify the resolution in pixels per degree using the RESOLUTION parameter
              </description>
              <inclusions>
                <item>RESOLUTION</item>
              </inclusions>
            </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="RESOLUTION">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief>Pixel resolution</brief>
        <description>
          Specifies the resolution in either meters per pixel or pixels per degree
        </description>
        <minimum inclusive="no">0.0</minimum>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TARGET">
        <type>string</type>
        <internalDefault>Read from FROM cube</internalDefault>
        <brief>The target planet to map from/to</brief>
        <description>
          This will specify the target planet to map from/to, i.e. Mars, Venus,
          etc.
        </description>
      </parameter>

       <parameter name ="EQURADIUS">
         <type>double</type>
         <internalDefault>Read from PCK file</internalDefault>
         <brief>Equatorial radius of target</brief>
         <description>
             The equatorial radius can be read using the NAIF routines to get
             the radius from the specified target planet, or read from the user.
          </description>
         <minimum inclusive="no">0.0</minimum>
         <inclusions>
           <item>POLRADIUS</item>
         </inclusions>
        </parameter>

        <parameter name ="POLRADIUS">
          <type>double</type>
          <internalDefault>Read from PCK file</internalDefault>
          <brief>Polar radius of target</brief>
          <description>
             The polar radius can be read using the NAIF routines to get
             the radius from the specified target planet, or read from the user.
           </description>
           <minimum inclusive="no">0.0</minimum>
           <inclusions>
             <item>EQURADIUS</item>
           </inclusions>
        </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Output Map Ground Range">
      <parameter name="DEFAULTRANGE">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>Defines how the default ground range is determined</brief>
        <default><item>COMPUTE</item></default>
        <description>
          This parameter is used to specify how the default latitude/longitude ground range for the output map projected image
          is obtained.  The ground range can be obtained from the camera or map file.  Note the user can overide the default using the MINLAT, MAXLAT, MINLON, MAXLON parameters.
          The purpose of the ground range is to define the coverage of the map projected image.  Essentially, the ground range and
          pixel resolution are used to compute the size (samples and line) of the output image.
        </description>

        <helpers>
          <helper name="H1">
            <function>ComputeInputRange</function>
            <brief>Compute Input Ground range </brief>
            <description>This helper button will load the default ground range
              from the input</description>
            <icon>$ISIS3DATA/base/icons/exec.png</icon>
          </helper>
          <helper name="H2">
            <function>LoadMapRange</function>
            <brief>Load Map File Ground Range </brief>
            <description>This helper button will load the default ground range from the map file</description>
          </helper>
        </helpers>

        <list>
           <option value="COMPUTE">
              <brief> Compute default range from input cube</brief>
              <description>
                This option will automatically determine the mininum/maximum latitude/longitude from the input camera model cube specified
                using the FROM parameter.
              </description>
            </option>

           <option value="MAP">
              <brief> Read default range from map file</brief>
              <description>
                This option will read the mininum/maximum latitude/longitude from the input map file.  All four values are expected to be defined.
              </description>
            </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="MINLAT">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief>Starting latitude</brief>
        <internalDefault>Use default range</internalDefault>
        <description>
          The minimum latitude of the ground range.   If this is entered by the user it will override the default camera or map value.  By default,
          planetocentric latitudes are assumed unless the MAP file specifies otherwise.
        </description>

        <minimum inclusive="yes">-90.0</minimum>
        <maximum inclusive="yes">90.0</maximum>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="MAXLAT">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief>Ending latitude</brief>
        <internalDefault>Use default range</internalDefault>
        <description>
          The maximum latitude of the ground range.   If this is entered by the user it will override the default camera or map value.
          By default, planetocentric latitudes are assumed unless the MAP file specifies otherwise.
        </description>
        <minimum inclusive="yes">-90.0</minimum>
        <maximum inclusive="yes">90.0</maximum>
        <greaterThan><item>MINLAT</item></greaterThan>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="MINLON">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief>Starting longitude</brief>
        <internalDefault>Use default range</internalDefault>
        <description>
          The minimum longitude of the ground range.   If this is entered by the user it will override the default camera or map value.
           By default, positive east longitudes in the range of 0 to 360 are assumed unless the MAP file specifies otherwise.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="MAXLON">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief>Ending longitude</brief>
        <internalDefault>Use default range</internalDefault>
        <description>
          The maximum longitude of the ground range.   If this is entered by the user it will override the default camera or map value.
           By default, positive east longitudes in the range of 0 to 360 are assumed unless the MAP file specifies otherwise.
        </description>
        <greaterThan><item>MINLON</item></greaterThan>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Affine Correction">
      <parameter name="TOLERANCE">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief>Geometric tolerance in pixels</brief>
        <default>
          <item>1.0</item>
        </default>
        <description>
          When computing the sample/line to be mapped from input->output, the
          sample and line are determined from the polynomial fit function. The
          transform then calculates the pixel differences in stereographically
          projected latitude/longitude from the input at sample/line to
          the output's stereographically projected latitude/longitude. If this
          difference is greater than the tolerance, then an affine
          transformation is iteratively used until the difference is less than
          the tolerance or is set to null after a set number of iterations.
        </description>
        <minimum inclusive="no">0.0</minimum>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name ="ITERATIONS">
        <type>integer</type>
        <default>
          <item>10</item>
        </default>
        <brief>The number of iterations to meet tolerance</brief>
        <description>
          If the tolerance has not been met in the number of iterations
          specified, then the pixel is not mapped to the output.
        </description>
        <minimum inclusive="yes">1</minimum>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Interpolation">
      <parameter name="INTERP">
        <type>string</type>
        <default>
          <item>CUBICCONVOLUTION</item>
        </default>
        <brief>Type of interpolation</brief>
        <description>
          This is the type of interpolation to be performed on the input.
        </description>

        <list>
          <option value="NEARESTNEIGHBOR">
            <brief>Nearest Neighbor</brief>
            <description>
              Each output pixel will be set to the pixel nearest the
              calculated input pixel.
            </description>
          </option>

          <option value="BILINEAR">
            <brief>Bi-Linear interpolation</brief>
            <description>
              Each output pixel will be set to the value calculated by
              a bi-linear interpolation of the calculated input pixel.
            </description>
          </option>

          <option value="CUBICCONVOLUTION">
            <brief>Cubic Convolution interpolation</brief>
            <description>
              Each output pixel will be set to the value calculated by
              a cubic convolution interpolation of the calculated input pixel.
            </description>
          </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>
    </group>
  </groups>
</application>
