<?xml version="1.0"?>
<application name="hidestripe" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">
  <brief>
    Corrects a known striping pattern in HiRISE images.
  </brief>

  <description>
    <p>
    In mixed mode HiRISE images, there is a tendency for every other line in the 
	 ccd with the lower binning mode to be significantly darker or lighter than 
	 normal image data would suggest. This program attempts to correct that 
	 problem. 2 passes through a cube are necessary to perform the correction. The 
	 first pass gathers information on each line of the cube to determine if the 
	 striping phenomenon occurs in odd numbered lines or in even numbered lines, and
	 also gathers information to perform the actual correction.
	 </p>
	 The second pass through the data performs the actual correction, of which there
	 are two different types. The default, an additive correction, is of the following
	 form for each pixel
	 
	 <pre>
    					     
                                         ((Line[i-1]) + Line[i+1])
                Pixel[i,j] - Line[i] +   --------------------------
                                                      2
    </pre>
	 
	 The other correction, a multiplicative correction of a similar style, is of
	 the form
	 
    <pre>
                Pixel        ((Line[i-1]) + Line[i+1])
               -------   *  ---------------------------
               Line[i]                    2
    </pre>
	 <p>
	 It should finally be noted that the striping pattern has been observed to
	 be most prevalent in a certain quardrant of the image, though that phase
	 is not the same for all images. In order to address this irregularitiy, the 
	 line averages shown above are not for the entire line, but only for the 
	 quarter of the line in which sample i exists. 
	 </p>
	 <p>
	 Caution should be taken when running hidestripe: it should only be run on
	 images where different CCDs are run at different binning modes. Of those,
	 only channels that are not used in the highest binning mode of the image
	 should be corrected. For example, if an image has binning modes 1, 2, and 4
	 the CCDs with modes 1 and 2 may be hidestripe'd, but in an image that is 
	 only binned in modes 1 and 2, the bin 1 CCDs are the only ones that need 
	 the hidestripe correction.
	 </p>
  </description>

  <category>
    <missionItem>Mars Reconnaissance Orbiter</missionItem>
  </category>

  <history>
    <change name="Drew Davidson" date="2006-05-30">
      Original version
    </change>
	 <change name="Drew Davidson" date="2006-07-29">
      Changed to calculate phase limits differently for Channel 1
    </change>
	 <change name="Drew Davidson" date="2006-08-17">
      Added capability to process bin 2 data
    </change>
    <change name="Drew Davidson" date="2007-01-05">
	   Allowed users to specify odd or even correction
	 </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2008-05-13">
      Removed references to CubeInfo 
    </change>
  </history>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Single hirise channel in cub form
        </brief>
        <description>
		    input channel file. The file must have a number of samples divisible
			 by four so that it may be equally divided into phases. Also, the
			 image should exibit the horizontal striping problem addressed above.
			 Otherwise, this program will do an unwanted normalization.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TO">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Output cube to contain cub with correction.
        </brief>
        <description>
		    This image will have the hidestripe correction applied to it. 
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>
    </group>
	 
	 <group name="Correction Type">
	   <parameter name="CORRECTION"> 
		  <type>string</type>
		  <brief>Type of correction to apply</brief>
		  <description>
          A correction that is either multiplicative or additive in nature.
			 For more specific information on the nature of the correction, see
			 the general program description
		  </description> 
		  <default><item>ADD</item></default>
		  <list>
		    <option value="ADD">
			   <brief>Additive correction</brief>
				<description>
				  Correct by subtracting the average of the line needing correction
				  from every pixel on that line and then adding the average of the 
				  line above and below that line.
				</description>
			  </option>
			  <option value="MULTIPLY">
			    <brief>Multiplicative correction</brief>
				 <description>
				  Correct by dividing the average of the line needing correction
				  from every pixel on that line and then multiplying the average
				  of the line above and below that line.
				 </description>
			  </option>
		  </list>
		</parameter>
     </group>
	  
 <group name="Correction Start">
      <parameter name="PARITY">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>Specify line stripes as an even or odd pattern</brief>
        <default>
          <item>AUTO</item>
        </default>
        <description>
        </description>
        <list>
          <option value="AUTO">
            <brief>Automatically determine what parity to correct</brief>
            <description>
				
            </description>
          </option>
          <option value="EVEN">
            <brief>Apply correction to even lines (2,4,6 ...)</brief>
            <description>
            </description>
          </option>
          <option value="ODD">
            <brief>Apply correct to odd lines (1,3,5 ...)</brief>
            <description>
            </description>
          </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>
    </group>
  </groups>
  
  <examples>
    <example>
      <brief> Additive correction </brief>
      <description>
        This example shows the default additive correction applied to a binned
		  1 image in an image that is mixed and includes binning modes 1 and 4
      </description>
      <terminalInterface>
        <commandLine> 
		    from=HiRISE/cubs/RED5_bin1.cub to=HIRISE/cubs/RED5_bin1_corrected.cub
        </commandLine>
        <description>
		    Note that the defaults are not changed, and thus the additive 
			 correction is applied.
        </description>
      </terminalInterface>

      <inputImages>
        <image src="assets/image/in1.jpg" width="500" height="500">
          <brief> Input image before hidestripe</brief>
          <description>
			   The image before the correction is applied. Note the horizontal 
				stripes.
          </description>
          <thumbnail caption="Before correction" src="assets/thumb/in1.jpg" width="200" height="200"/>
          <parameterName>FROM</parameterName>
        </image>
      </inputImages>

      <outputImages>
        <image src="assets/image/out1.jpg" width="500" height="500">
          <brief> Output image after hidestripe</brief>
          <description>
			   The same image has now been smoothed such that the horizontal
				stripes are removed.
          </description>
          <thumbnail caption="After correction" src="assets/thumb/out1.jpg" width="200" height="200"/>
          <parameterName>TO</parameterName>
        </image>
      </outputImages>

      <guiInterfaces>
        <guiInterface>
          <image width="441" height="221" src="assets/image/gui1.jpg">
            <brief>Example Gui</brief>
            <description>
				  Parameters set to perform additive correction. No options have
				  been changed from their defaults (though required TO/FROM have).
            </description>
            <thumbnail width="200" height="100" caption="Default Gui" src="assets/thumb/gui1.jpg" />
          </image>
        </guiInterface>
      </guiInterfaces>
    </example>
  </examples>

</application>
