<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="bandnorm" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">

  <brief>
    Normalize bands in a cube
  </brief>

  <description>
    <p/>
    The program accomplishes the fairly straightforward task of taking an input
    cube and outputting normalized values. 
    <p/>
    Normalization may be done with respect to each band or the entire cube.
    If the user were to normalize by band, the program would take a pass through
    the data in order to determine the average of each band. Bandnorm will then
    pass through each band again and normalize each one based on the average
    of the given band.  If normalizing by the entire cube, the first pass would compute
    the average of the cube, and the second pass would normalize each band using
    this average.  Bandnorm can use a text file as the input for the average 
    value of each band. 
    <p/>
  </description>

  <history>
    <change name="Elizabeth Miller" date="2006-07-18">
      Original version
    </change>
    <change name="Chris Austin" date="2007-12-27">
      Added Spectral Pencil option.
    </change>
    <change name="Chris Austin" date="2008-01-23">
      Modified Spectral Pencil option to be more flexible with the structure of 
      its Spectral files, namely, allowing for more than one column, and 
      specifying which column to use durring normilization.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2008-05-12">
          Removed references to CubeInfo 
    </change>
  </history>

  <category>
    <categoryItem>Math and Statistics</categoryItem>
  </category>

  <seeAlso>
    <applications>
      <item>divfilter</item>
    </applications>
  </seeAlso>

  <groups>

    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input cube
        </brief>
        <description>
          This file will be the input cube that gets normalized.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TO">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Output cube
        </brief>
        <description>
         Output file that will be created using average values from 
         the input cube to normalize.
        </description>
      </parameter>
   </group>

    <group name="Normalization option">
      <parameter name="AVERAGE">
         <type>string</type>
         <default><item>BAND</item></default>
         <brief>Direction in which statistics and operations operate</brief>
         <description>
        	This is the the average to be used during normalization. If the user chooses
        	to use band averages, they intend to take in an entire band of data 
            and normalize based on the average of that band for each pixel in
            that band. If they choose to use the average from the entire cube, 
        	they intend to take in an entire cube of data and normalize each 
            pixel in each band based on the average of the entire cube.  If they 
            choose pencil, they intend to use a file containing the averages of 
            each band to normalize each pixel in correlating band.  This file is 
            best obtained using Qview's plot tool.
         </description>
         <list>
           <option value="BAND">
            <brief>Divide by Band Average </brief>
            <description>
              Get the average of each band separately to use in the normalization
            </description>
             <exclusions>
               <item>SPECTRUM</item>
               <item>METHOD</item>
               <item>NUMBER</item>
               <item>NAME</item>
            </exclusions>
            </option>
           <option value="CUBE">
            <brief>Divide by Cube Average</brief>
            <description>
	           Get the average of the entire cube to use in the normailization
            </description>
             <exclusions>
               <item>SPECTRUM</item>
               <item>METHOD</item>
               <item>NUMBER</item>
               <item>NAME</item>
            </exclusions>
            </option>
            <option value="PENCIL">
            <brief>Divide by Spectral Pencil</brief>
            <description>
              Use the given file as the source of the values used to normalize 
              each band separately.
            </description> 
            <inclusions>
              <item>SPECTRUM</item>
              <item>METHOD</item>
              <item>NUMBER</item>
              <item>NAME</item>
            </inclusions>
            </option>
         </list>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="SPECTRUM">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>Spectral Pencil</brief>
        <description>
          The file with the spectrum data for each band to be normalized with.  
          It assumes this file was aquired using Qview's plot tool. The first 
          line of the spectrum file MUST be composed of titles, and the
          following lines MUST be the data desired (in most cases the average) 
          of each band in sequential order, starting with the first band. Extra 
          lines are ignored.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.txt *.lis
        </filter>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="METHOD">
        <type>string</type>
        <default><item>BYNAME</item></default>
        <brief>The mothod used to determine desired column</brief>
        <description>
          The method used to determine the correct data column of the spectrum
          file wished to be used in creating the normalized cube.
        </description>
        <list>
          <option value="BYNUMBER">
            <brief>Specify the column of the spectrum file to be used by 
              column number</brief>
            <description>
              Allows one to specify by column number within the given 
              spectrum file, the column data to be used to create the normalized 
              cube.
            </description>
            <inclusions>
              <item>NUMBER</item>
            </inclusions>
            <exclusions>
              <item>NAME</item>
            </exclusions>
          </option>
          <option value="BYNAME">
            <brief>Specify the column of the spectrum file to be used by 
              column name</brief>
            <description>
              The name of the column within the specified spectrum file, used to 
              create the normalized cube.
            </description>
            <inclusions>
              <item>NAME</item>
            </inclusions>
            <exclusions>
              <item>NUMBER</item>
            </exclusions>
          </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="NUMBER">
        <type>integer</type>
        <default><item>1</item></default>
        <brief>Specifies column used by number</brief>
         <description>
          Allows one to specify by column number within the given 
          spectrum file, the column data to be used to create the normalized 
          cube.
        </description>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="NAME">
        <type>string</type>
        <default><item>Average</item></default>
        <brief>Specifies column used by name</brief>
         <description>
          Allows one to specify by column name within the given 
          spectrum file, the column data to be used to create the normalized 
          cube.
        </description>
      </parameter>
    </group>

  </groups>

</application>
