<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="himos" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">
  <brief>
    Produce an output mosaic of HiRISE CCD images from the same observation and filter.
  </brief>

  <description>
    <p>
  ** The output from this program is required by hirdrgen ** <br/>
  If the final product wil not be an RDR, mapmos or automos can be used to produce a mosaic.  
  This program produces a mosaic and adds keywords to the label group "Mosaic" that are required 
  by hirdrgen. <br/>

  The  input cubes  to this program must be from the same observation, same filter, and map projected.<br/>  

   A new label group, required by hirdrgen, called "Mosaic"  is added to the image labels of 
   the output cube.  The original label blob is also propagated from the first file in the input list.<br/>
   </p>

<p>
  <b> processing sequence for single filter products that will become RDRs </b><br/>
         <b>cam2map</b> - project the cube.  hicolormos requiers a map projected cube.<br/>
         <b>himos</b> - mosaic files and add keywords to the mosaic group.<br/>
         <b>hirdrgen</b> - produce a RDR product.<br/>
</p>

 </description>

  <category>
    <missionItem>Mars Reconnaissance Orbiter</missionItem>
  </category>

  <history>
    <change name="Robert Sucharski" date="2006-07-19">
      Original version,
    </change>
    <change name="Elizabeth Miller" date="2007-02-20">
        Changed OriginalLabel name to IsisCube
    </change>
    <change name="Robert Sucharski" date="2007-04-18">
        Added NothAzimuth, SubSolarAzimuth, and SpecialProcessingFlag keywords
         to the output mosaic group
    </change>
    <change name="Rovert Sucharski" date="2007-10-18">
      Added code to get the avg line and sample for gathering camera infomation if using the avg latitude and longitude fails.
      We contine to use the latitude and logitude so that we are backwards compatible.  We added this new code because 
      the camera could not find an itersect for some images (polar) if we used projection latitude and longitude to "setGround".
     </change>
  </history>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROMLIST">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input list of files
        </brief>
        <description>
          A single colume list of HiRISE CCD  files that will be mosaiced together.  The input
          files must be from the some observation and be from the same filter.  The files must also
          be map projected.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.lis *.lst *.txt
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TO">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Output mosaic
        </brief>
        <description>
          the output mosaic cube with the new mosaic label group added..
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="PRIORITY">
        <type>string</type>
        <default>
          <item>ONTOP</item>
        </default>
        <brief>The priority of pixel placement</brief>
        <description>
          This parameter is used to select one of two ways to masaic the
          pixels in areas of overlap.
        </description>

        <list>
          <option value="ONTOP">
            <brief>Input cube will be placed on top of the mosaic </brief>
            <description>
              When the input pixel is not Null, the input pixel
              value will be written to the output cube.
            </description>
          </option>
          <option value="BENEATH">
            <brief>Input cube will be placed beneath the mosaic</brief>
            <description>
              When the mosaic pixel is not Null it will be left unchanged.
            </description>
          </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>
    </group>
  </groups>
</application>
