<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="cnetedit" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">

  <brief>
    Edit control networks
  </brief>

  <description>
    <p>
      This application applies a series of edits to a <def>control network</def>
      based on the <def>control point</def> IDs and <def>control measure</def>
      cube filenames specified in various edit lists.  All edit operations are
      optional, and performed in a sequential order that cannot be changed.  If
      the user wises to perform any edit operations in a different order, it is
      suggested that they run the application multiple times in a pipeline
      fashion.
    </p>
    <p>
      The primary, and most typical, function of this application is to
      selectively delete unwanted points and measures from a network by flagging
      them as "ignored".  Other operations are generally in place to facilitate
      this purpose, but can also be used on their own.
    </p>
    <p>
      The available operations are as follows:
      <ol>
        <li>Unlock</li>
        <li>Ignore</li>
        <li>Delete</li>
        <li>Lock</li>
      </ol>
      Before any points or measures are ignored and deleted, the listed points
      and measures can be unlocked if edit locked in the input.  Listed points
      and measures can then be ignored, and subsequently any ignored points and
      measures can be deleted from the network.  The deletion operation deletes
      all ignored points and measures, not just those specified in the lists.
      Finally, any listed points or measures can be locked to prevent further
      modification.
    </p>
    <p>
      Additional options include the ability to preserve points with less than a
      single valid measure, ability to retain the <def link="Reference
        Measure">reference</def> (even if not validated or exists in an ignore
      list), and the ability to print detailed logging results to a text file.
    </p>
  </description>

  <history>
    <change name="Tracie Sucharski" date="2008-08-14">
      Original version
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2008-12-29">
      Added options, including EXCLUDELIST and DELETE
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2009-01-09">
      Renamed EXCLUDELIST to IGNORELIST and made other similar name changes.
    </change>
    <change name="Sharmila Prasad" date="2009-07-17">
      Renamed IGNORELIST to FROMLIST and made other similar name changes
      Added options HOLD and UNHOLD
      Set the default as FALSE for DELETE Ignored Control Points and Measures
    </change>
    <change name="Sharmila Prasad" date="2009-07-24">
      Renamed IGNORELIST to FROMLIST and  reverted back to previous format
    </change>
    <change name="Sharmila Prasad" date="2009-08-11">
      Set the default as FALSE for DELETE Ignored Control Points and Measures
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2009-08-11">
      Fixed an out of index bug.
    </change>
    <change name="Sharmila Prasad" date="2009-08-25">
      Added parameter LOG to write logs into the file if explicitly stated,
      parameter POINTLIST to read Control Point ID's from a file
      reverted DELETE default to be TRUE
    </change>
    <change name="Sharmila Prasad" date="2009-09-14">
      Added parameter PRESERVE with default FALSE. If set the Control Points with
      Measures equal to one are not deleted
    </change>
    <change name="Travis Addair" date="2010-11-24">
      Added optional measure validity check, removed a redundant deletion
      pass, and fixed a bug causing points to be deleted before all measures
      had been checked.
    </change>
    <change name="Travis Addair" date="2010-11-29">
      Changed parameter FROMLIST to CUBELIST and ALLFROMLIST to FROMLIST.
    </change>
    <change name="Travis Addair" date="2010-11-30">
      Added progress bar for validity checking and automatic logging of the
      DEFFILE to the print file when entered.
    </change>
    <change name="Travis Addair" date="2010-12-08">
      Added check to ensure that ignored reference measures are not deleted,
      but that the entire point is deleted instead, by setting the containing
      point to ignored whenever the reference is.
    </change>
    <change name="Travis Addair" date="2010-12-20">
      Added information to the log file pertaining to each point and measure
      ignored/deleted with an associated reason why.
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2011-01-18">
      Altered to compile with the new Control redesign.
    </change>
    <change name="Sharmila Prasad" date="2011-05-14">
      Validate DefFile before processing. Added ability to validate measure
      by sample/line residuals or Residual Magnitude
    </change>
    <change name="Sharmila Prasad" date="2011-05-23">
      Helper function to be able to edit the Deffile.
    </change>
    <change name="Sharmila Prasad" date="2011-06-02">
      Added option RETAIN_REFERENCE to retain reference even if not validated or
      if it is in the ignore CubeList
    </change>
    <change name="Debbie A. Cook and Tracie Sucharski" date="2011-06-07">
      Changed point type "ground" to "fixed"
    </change>
    <change name="James Alexander Crough" date="2011-07-13">
      Changed output of ignored points to show EditLocked points as ignored.
    </change>
    <change name="James Alexander Crough" date="2011-07-14">
      Changed output again this time in order to seperate skipping EditLocked
      points into their own PVL objects.
    </change>
    <change name="Travis Addair" date="2012-02-24">
      Changed from ignoring/deletion program to a series of sequential
      and optional operations (unlock, ignore, delete, lock).  Added MEASURELIST
      to allow editing specific measures.  Updated documentation.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2012-05-03">
      Added "IGNOREALL" option. Fixes #293.
    </change>
  </history>

  <category>
    <categoryItem>Control Networks</categoryItem>
  </category>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">

      <parameter name="CNET">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input control network
        </brief>
        <description>
          A control network generated from programs such as autoseed or qnet.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.net
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="ONET">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Output control network
        </brief>
        <description>
          Updated control network with the applied edits.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.net
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="LOG">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <internalDefault>
          None
        </internalDefault>
        <brief>
          Log of all ignored or deleted points and measures
        </brief>
        <description>
          This file provides a PVL record of all points and measures ignored or
          deleted from the input network.  It also makes note of points and
          measures that could not be ignored or deleted, and provides rationales
          for each.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.pvl *.txt
        </filter>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Edit Lists" >
       <parameter name="POINTLIST">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <internalDefault>None</internalDefault>
        <brief>
          List of IDs mapping to points to be edited
        </brief>
        <description>
          The given edit operations will be applied to all the points in the
          control network mapped by the IDs in this list.  Each entry in this
          list should be a control point ID on its own line.  Operations such as
          unlocking, ignoring, and locking will only be applied at the point
          level (e.g. locking lat/lon but not measurements).  Deleting a point,
          however, will remove it and all its measures from the network.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.lis
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="CUBELIST">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <internalDefault>None</internalDefault>
        <brief>
          List of cube filenames to be edited
        </brief>
        <description>
          The given edit operations will be applied to all the measurements
          taken on a cube in this list.  This information is derived from the
          measurement's cube serial number, mapping to a filename in this list.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.lis
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="MEASURELIST">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <internalDefault>None</internalDefault>
        <brief>
          List of paired Point IDs and cube filenames
        </brief>
        <description>
          A file containing a list of paired Point IDs and cube filenames,
          uniquely identifying specific measures to be edited.  Each pairing
          must be on its own line and have the Point ID and filename separated
          by a comma (',').
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.lis *.csv
        </filter>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Edit Operations">
      <parameter name="UNLOCK">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>False</item></default>
        <brief>
          Unlock listed points and measures
        </brief>
        <description>
          Any listed point or measure will have its edit lock removed if it has
          one in the input network.  If not, nothing will happen to the point or
          measure and processing will continue.  Unlocking a point does not
          automatically unlock its measurements, except for the reference.
        </description>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="IGNORE">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>True</item></default>
        <brief>
          Ignore listed points and measures
        </brief>
        <description>
          Any listed point or measure will be ignored.  Ignoring a point does
          not automatically ignore its measurements, except for the reference.
          Ignoring can sometimes fail, for example, if the point or measure is
          edit locked, and the UNLOCK operation is not enabled.
        </description>
        <inclusions>
          <item>CHECKVALID</item>
        </inclusions>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="DELETE">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>TRUE</item></default>
        <brief>
          Delete ignored points and measures
        </brief>
        <description>
          Any ignored point or measure will be deleted, regardless of whether
          or not it is present in an edit list.  Deleting a point will delete
          all its measurements in the process.  If any control point has less
          than two remaining measures after all measurement deletions have been
          performed, then that point will be deleted as well.  This can be
          prevented by enabling the PRESERVE option.  Furthermore, the
          RETAIN_REFERENCE option can be enabled to prevent reference measures
          from being deleted under any circumstance.
        </description>
        <inclusions>
          <item>PRESERVE</item>
          <item>RETAIN_REFERENCE</item>
        </inclusions>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="LOCK">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>False</item></default>
        <brief>
          Lock listed points and measures
        </brief>
        <description>
          Any listed point or measure will have its edit lock set if it does not
          already have one in the input network.  Otherwise, nothing will happen
          to the point or measure and processing will continue.  Locking a point
          does not automatically lock its measurements, except for the
          reference.
        </description>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Validity Check" >
      <parameter name="CHECKVALID">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>False</item></default>
        <brief>
          Ignore all control measures outside user-specified tolerances
        </brief>
        <description>
          If enabled, the application will check the validity of each control
          measure against the tolerances set in the relevant definition file
          (DEFFILE).  Because validity checking requires camera information not
          contained within the control measure itself, a list of all cubes in
          the network is necessary (FROMLIST), and could result in a noticeably
          more time-intensive run of the program.  For the aforementioned
          reasons, this option is disabled by default.
        </description>
        <inclusions>
          <item>FROMLIST</item>
          <item>DEFFILE</item>
        </inclusions>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="FROMLIST">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          List of all Input cubes in the control network
        </brief>
        <description>
          This parameter specifies a list of cube names corresponding to the
          serial numbers for every control measure in the input control
          network.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.lis
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="DEFFILE">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          PVL file containing the description of the Validity Keywords
        </brief>
        <description>
          This parameter specifies a PVL file containing descriptions for the
          validity keywords when the user chooses to perform a validity check
          on each of the measures in the input control network.  Invalid control
          measures will be ignored and, unless otherwise specified, removed.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.def
        </filter>
        <helpers >
          <helper name="H1">
            <function>PrintTemp</function>
            <brief>View DefFile</brief>
            <description>
              This helper button will print the definition file to the session
              log of the application
            </description>
            <icon>$ISIS3DATA/base/icons/labels.png</icon>
          </helper>
          <helper name="H2">
            <function>EditDefFile</function>
            <brief>Edit DefFile</brief>
            <description>
              This helper button opens an editor to able to edit the DefFile
            </description>
            <icon>$ISIS3DATA/base/icons/labels.png</icon>
          </helper>
        </helpers>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Deletion Options">
      <parameter name="PRESERVE">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>FALSE</item></default>
        <brief>
          Preserve points with only one remaining measure
        </brief>
        <description>
          This option will prevent the DELETE operation from removing control
          points that only have one control measure remaining at the end of the
          deletion process.
        </description>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="RETAIN_REFERENCE">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>False</item></default>
        <brief>
          Never delete a reference measure unless the entire point is removed
        </brief>
        <description>
          When enabled, the DELETE operation will retain reference measures
          under all circumstances.  Consequently, if a reference measure is
          ignored, in an edit list, or invalidated, it will still show up in the
          output network.
        </description>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="IGNOREALL">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>False</item></default>
        <brief>
          Ignore all measures in the point when the reference measure is ignored
        </brief>
        <description>
          When enabled, any time a point or the reference measure is ignored the remaining measures
          in a point will also be ignored. Occassionally the reference measure has the highest error
          and we don't want to retain it, but the rest of the measures are also unreliable so it's
          helpful to ignore them also.
        </description>
      </parameter>
    </group>

  </groups>

</application>
