<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="tgocassismos" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">
  <brief>
    Produce an output mosaic of TGO CaSSIS images from the same observation and filter.
  </brief>

  <description>
    <p>
    If the final product wil not be an RDR, mapmos or automos can be used to produce a mosaic.
    This program produces a mosaic and adds keywords to the label group "Mosaic". <br/>

    The  input cubes  to this program must be from the same observation, same filter, and map projected.<br/>

    A new label group, required by tgocassisrdrgen, called "Mosaic"  is added to the image labels of
    the output cube.  The original label blob is also propagated from the first file in the input list.<br/>
    
    This application will produce two cubes. The first cube (that you set with the "TO" parameter) 
    will be your mosaic. A tracking cube will also be created at the same level with tracking
    information for the original cubes (that you set with the "FROMLIST" parameter). This cube will
    have the same base name as the mosaic, but will end in "_tracking.cub".<br/>
    </p>

<p>
  <b> processing sequence for single filter products that will become RDRs </b><br/>
         <b>cam2map</b> - project the cube.<br/>
         <b>tgocassismos</b> - mosaic files and add keywords to the mosaic group.<br/>
         <b>tgocassisrdrgen</b> - produce a RDR product.<br/>
</p>

 </description>

  <category>
    <missionItem>Trace Gas Orbiter</missionItem>
  </category>

  <history>
    <change name="Makayla Shepherd" date="2018-05-09">
      Original version.
    </change>
    <change name="Adam Goins" date="2018-05-17">
      Added SpacecraftName and InstrumentId to mosaic group.
    </change>
    <change name="Kristin Berry" date="2018-06-12">
      Removed the "_filtername" from the ProductId. 
    </change>
    <change name="Kristin Berry" date="2018-06-16">
      Update to read the ObservationId from the Archive Group. 
    </change>
    <change name="Jeannie Backer" date="2018-08-10">
      Added option to allow user to choose ground range. 
    </change>
    <change name="Summer Stapleton-Greig" date="2019-02-28">
      Added the "tracking=true" parameter to tgocassismos' call to automos resulting in automatic
      tracking cube creation. 
    </change>
    <change name="Kristin Berry" date="2019-03-01">
      Added the StopTime keyword to the output Mosaic PVL group, as stop_date_time is required for 
      PDS4 export. 
    </change>
  </history>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROMLIST">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input list of files
        </brief>
        <description>
          A single colume list of TGO CaSSIS files that will be mosaiced together.  The input
          files must be from the some observation and be from the same filter.  The files must also
          be map projected.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.lis *.lst *.txt
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TO">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Output mosaic
        </brief>
        <description>
          The output mosaic cube with the new mosaic label group added.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="PRIORITY">
        <type>string</type>
        <default>
          <item>ONTOP</item>
        </default>
        <brief>The priority of pixel placement</brief>
        <description>
          This parameter is used to select one of two ways to masaic the
          pixels in areas of overlap.
        </description>

        <list>
          <option value="ONTOP">
            <brief>Input cube will be placed on top of the mosaic </brief>
            <description>
              When the input pixel is not Null, the input pixel
              value will be written to the output cube.
            </description>
          </option>
          <option value="BENEATH">
            <brief>Input cube will be placed beneath the mosaic</brief>
            <description>
              When the mosaic pixel is not Null it will be left unchanged.
            </description>
          </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>
    </group>
    <group name="Ground Range">
      <parameter name="GRANGE">
      <type>string</type>
      <default><item>AUTO</item></default>
      <brief>Ground Range Options</brief>
      <description>
        AUTO is the default for this parameter. By default the ground range is
        calculated automatically based on the list of input cubes.  The user can
        override this default. If the USER option is selected, values must be
        entered for the MINLAT, MAXLAT, MINLON, and MAXLON parameters.
      </description>
      <list>
        <option value="AUTO">
          <brief>Automatically Calculate Range</brief>
          <description>
            The program will automatically calculate the ground range for the
            mosaic by examining that latitude and longitude range of all the
            cubes contained in the list passed to FROMLIST.  This is the
            default option.
          </description>
          <exclusions>
            <item>MINLAT</item>
            <item>MAXLAT</item>
            <item>MINLON</item>
            <item>MAXLON</item>
          </exclusions>
        </option>
        <option value="USER">
          <brief>User Entered Range</brief>
          <description>
            The program will apply the ground range values you entered for
            the mosaic.
          </description>
          <inclusions>
            <item>MINLAT</item>
            <item>MAXLAT</item>
            <item>MINLON</item>
            <item>MAXLON</item>
          </inclusions>
        </option>
      </list>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="MINLAT">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief>Minimum Latitude</brief>
        <description>
          The minimum latitude value boundary extent for the output mosaic.
        </description>
        <helpers>
          <helper name="H1">
            <function>helperButtonCalcRange</function>
            <brief>Calculate Ranges using FROMLIST</brief>
            <description>
              This button will calculate the latitude and longitude range using the files in the
              FROMLIST.
            </description>
            <icon>$ISIS3DATA/base/icons/exec.png</icon>
          </helper>
        </helpers>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="MAXLAT">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief>Maximum Latitude</brief>
        <description>
          The maximum latitude value boundary extent for the output mosaic.
        </description>
        <greaterThan>
            <item>MINLAT</item>
        </greaterThan>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="MINLON">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief>Minimum Longitude</brief>
        <description>
          The minimum longitude value boundary extent for the output mosaic.
        </description>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="MAXLON">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief>Maximum Longitude</brief>
        <description>
          The maximum longitude value bounary extent for the output mosaic.
        </description>
        <greaterThan>
            <item>MINLON</item>
        </greaterThan>
      </parameter>
    </group>
  </groups>
</application>
