<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="socetframesettings" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">
  <brief>
    Create a SOCET SET Framing Camera or USGSAstro FrameOffAxis settings file.
  </brief>

  <description>
    This is an ISIS to SOCET SET (trademark BAE Systems) translation program for Framing Camera
    images.  It calculates keyword values specific to SOCET SET's Framing Camera Settings files
    and generates the settings file for input to USGSAstro SOCET SET program 'import_frame.' <br/>
    <br/>
    The input cube must be a "level1" image <b>with SPICE data attached to the label</b> (see
    spiceinit). <br/>
    <br/>
    The following are supported instruments:
    <pre>
       CASSINI ISS
       CLEMENTINE 1 UVVIS
       GALILEO SSI
       MESSENGER NAC
       MESSENGER WAC
       OSIRIS-REX MapCam
       OSIRIS-REX PolyCam
       VIKING ORBITER
<!--
       APOLLO 15 METRIC
       APOLLO 16 METRIC
       APOLLO 17 METRIC
       MEX-SRC
       THEMIS-VIS
-->
    </pre>

  </description>

  <category>
    <categoryItem>SOCET Set Translation</categoryItem>
  </category>

  <seeAlso>
    <applications>
      <item>spiceinit</item>
    </applications>
  </seeAlso>

  <history>
    <change name="Philip Martinez" date="2010-07-12">
      Original version
    </change>
    <change name="Elpitha Howington-Kraus" date="2010-10-14">
      Modified documentation in GUI. Changed OUPUTPNAME to INPUT_DATA_PATH, added CAM_CALIB_PATH
    </change>
    <change name="O. Thomas" date="2012-08-23">
      Renamed program from calc_frame_settingsfile to socetframesettings, restructured program to
      use SpiceRotation class, added Messenger, began modifications to meet ISIS coding standards.
    </change>
    <change name="E. Howington-Kraus" date="2013-02-25">
      Completed modifications to meet ISIS coding standards for formal installation into ISIS.
      Added check for needed SPICE data (blobs) attached to the cube label. Added parameter TO for
      user control over output settings file name (previously the program generated the output file
      name based on the base name of the FROM cube).  Temporarily removed support for APOLLO METRIC,
      MEX-SRC, and THEMIS-VIS sensors until testing can be completed.  References #1526.
    </change>
    <change name="Raad A. Saleh" date="2013-09-09">
      Added support for CLEMENTINE1 UVVIS instrument and updated documentation to reflect the
      changes. Reference #1749.
    </change>
    <change name="Jeannie Backer" date="2016-12-24">
      Added support for OSIRIS-REx instrument and updated documentation to reflect the
      changes. Fixes #3898.
    </change>
    <change name="Brian Carcich" date="2018-03-07">
      Fixed rotations for OSIRIS-REX instruments. Added documentation and cleaned up
      variable names. References #5235.
    </change>
    <change name="Jesse Mapel" date="2018-10-11">
      Changes to better match coding standards and clarify
      documentation. Added OREX test cases. References #5235.
    </change>

</history>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Filename of a "level 1" frame camera cube
        </brief>
        <description>
          Level 1 input Framing Camera cube with SPICE data attached. Supported instruments are
          CASSINI SSI, CLEMENTINE 1 UVVIS, GALILEO ISS, MESSENGER NAC, MESSENGER WAC,
          OSIRIS-REX MapCam, OSIRIS-REX PolyCam, and VIKING ORBITER.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TO">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <brief>SOCET SET Framing Camera Settings file</brief>
        <internalDefault>None</internalDefault>
        <description>
          Output SOCET SET Framing Camera Settings file. This is a text file that must have a file
          extension of ".set." This file is one of the input files to USGSAstro SOCET SET program
          'import_frame.'
        </description>
      </parameter>

    </group>

    <group name="SOCET SET Parameters">

      <parameter name="SS_PROJECT">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>SOCET SET Project name</brief>
        <description>
          Name of the SOCET SET project that you will be importing this image into. Including the
          ".prj" extension is optional. As an example, for SOCET SET project named TEST, enter
          SS_PROJECT=TEST.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="SS_IMG_LOC">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>
        Destination of SOCET SET images as shown in the first column of SOCET SET's location.list
        file
       </brief>
        <description>
          The "logical" location of the SOCET images as shown in the first column of SOCET SET
          internal database file DEVICE/location.list.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="SS_INPUT_PATH">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>
          Full path to location of input images and Framing Camera settings files on the SOCET SET
          machine
        </brief>
        <description>
          Full path on SOCET SET machine where raw images (*.raw) and Framing Camera settings
          files (*.set) will reside for import into SOCET SET, <b><i>with the ending file path
          delimiter included.</i></b> This is typically in the SOCET SET project's images directory.
          <br/>
          <br/>
          Entering the file path delimiters (forward slash for UNIX systems, backslash for Windows
          systems) is straight forward when entering your path into the dialog box. However, special
          handling is required when running this program at the command line or in processing
          scripts.
          <pre>
          For SOCET SET running on Windows, an example input path would be

          E:\images\test

          To enter a path in the dialog box, enter the path as it normally appears. For this
          example, enter

          E:\images\test\

          To enter a path on the command line, or in a script, use the escape character (which is a
          backslash) to pass the delimiters to the program.  For this example, enter

          SS_INPUT_PATH=E:\\IMAGES\\TEST\\ </pre>
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="SS_CAM_CALIB_PATH">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>
          Full path to SOCET SET's camera calibration directory
        </brief>
        <description>
          Full path to SOCET SET's internal database camera calibration directory, <b><i>with the
          ending file path delimiter included.</i></b>
          <pre>
          For SOCET SET running on Windows, an example path would be

          C:\SOCET_SET_5.6.0\internal_dbs\CAM

          To enter a path in the dialog box, enter the path as it normally appears. For this
          example, enter

          C:\SOCET_SET_5.6.0\internal_dbs\CAM\

          To enter a path on the command line, or in a script, use the escape character (which is a
          backslash) to pass the delimiters to the program.  For this example, enter

          SS_CAM_CALIB_PATH=C:\\SOCET_SET_5.6.0\\internal_dbs\\CAM\\ </pre>
        </description>
      </parameter>

    </group>
  </groups>
</application>
