<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="csminit" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">
  <brief>
    Attach a CSM model state to a cube.
  </brief>

  <description>
    <p>
      This program takes Instrument Support Data (ISD) and attempts to create a
      valid Community Sensor Model (CSM) state string using models from the
      loaded CSM Libraries. If a single state string can be created, it is
      attached to the cube in the CSMState BLOB for later use. If there are
      multiple models that create valid state strings, then this program will
      error and return a list of possible models. The user will then have to
      re-run this program using the PLUGINNAME and/or MODELNAME parameters to
      select a specific model.
    </p>
    <p>
      Information about the CSM model will also be added to the CsmInfo group on
      the cube label. These are just for users to reference and are not used
      programmatically.
    </p>
    <p>
      This program can be run on any Cube file, but if the Cube has spice data
      from spiceinit then it will be removed so that there is no ambiguity
      between the ISIS and CSM model.
    </p>
    <p>
      See the Plugins group in the IsisPreferences file for information about
      how to load CSM Libraries for use with this and other ISIS applications.
    </p>
  </description>

  <category>
    <categoryItem>Cameras</categoryItem>
  </category>

  <history>
    <change name="Jesse Mapel" date="2020-11-18">
      Original Version
    </change>
    <change name="Jesse Mapel and Stuart Sides" date="2021-02-03">
      Modified to always add a TargetName and Instrument group to the label for the camera model.
    </change>
    <change name="Kristin Berry and Stuart Sides" date="2021-02-10">
      Modified to revert label and Cube changes on failure.
    </change>
    <change name="Kristin Berry and Stuart Sides" date="2021-02-12">
      Added the ability to take a state string instead of an ISD.
    </change>
  </history>

  <groups>
    <group name="Input Files">
      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          The input cube that the state string will be attached to.
        </brief>
        <description>
          The input cube that the state string will be attached to. Any kernels
          specified in the kernels group and any attached SPICE tables will be
          removed when the model state is attached.
        </description>
        <filter>*.cub</filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="ISD">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <internalDefault>none</internalDefault>
        <brief>
          The Instrument Support Data (ISD) file that will be used.
        </brief>
        <description>
          The Instrument Support Data (ISD) file that will be used to create the
          model state string. The ISD can be just a filename ISD or a NITF2.1 ISD.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="STATE">
        <type>filename</type>
        <internalDefault>none</internalDefault>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          A Community Sensor Model (CSM) state string
        </brief>
        <description>
          A file containing a Community Sensor Model (CSM) state string that will be used to create the
          model for the input cube.
        </description>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Target Specification">
      <parameter name="TARGETNAME">
        <type>string</type>
        <internalDefault>Current TargetName in input label or Unknown if not present.</internalDefault>
        <brief>
          The name of the body observed by the image.
        </brief>
        <description>
          The name of the body observed by the image.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="SHAPEMODEL">
        <type>filename</type>
        <internalDefault>none</internalDefault>
        <brief>
          The shapemodel to represent the surface of the observed body.
        </brief>
        <description>
          The shapemodel to represent the surface of the observed body. If none
          is entered, then a bi-axial ellipsoid is used. The radii are defined
          by the CSM model.
        </description>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Model Specification">
      <parameter name="PLUGINNAME">
        <type>string</type>
        <internalDefault>none</internalDefault>
        <brief>
          The name of the plugin to use.
        </brief>
        <description>
          The name of the plugin to use. The loaded CSM Libraries will be
          searched for a plugin that has this name. If no such plugin is found
          an error will be returned.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="MODELNAME">
        <type>string</type>
        <internalDefault>none</internalDefault>
        <brief>
          The name of the model to use.
        </brief>
        <description>
          The name of the model to use. The loaded CSM Libraries will be
          searched for a model that has this name. If no such model is found an
          error will be returned.
        </description>
      </parameter>
    </group>
  </groups>
</application>
