<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="seedgrid" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">

  <brief>
    Creates a control network for a Lat/Lon range
  </brief>

  <description>
    <p>
      This program creates a control network for a latitude/longitude range on a
      specified target planet. The control network that is created is a grid
      of evenly-spaced control points.  The control network generated will have
      no control measures, but will instead have a known latitude and longitude
      for each control point. The resulting control network can then have images
      added to it by using the
      <a href="../cnetadd/cnetadd.html" target="_blank">cnetadd</a>
      application.
    </p>
  </description>

  <category>
    <categoryItem>Control Networks</categoryItem>
  </category>

  <history>
    <change name="Stacy Alley" date="2009-07-27">
      Original version
    </change>
    <change name="Travis Addair" date="2009-08-27">
      Fixed error when calculating X/Y range and added application test.
    </change>
    <change name="Travis Addair" date="2009-09-11">
      Added parameter allowing user to enter in projection type to use in seeding process.
    </change>
    <change name="Travis Addair" date="2009-09-14">
      Changed means of entering projection type to be a map file so as to allow
      for more customization and accepted projection types.
    </change>
    <change name="Travis Addair" date="2009-09-24">
      Added option to use lat/lon spacing when seeding points; fixed bug causing
      points to be seeded outside the lat/lon range; added a default projection
      type and reinstated the TARGET parameter so the user does not need to edit
      a projection file in order to run the program.
    </change>
    <change name="Travis Addair" date="2010-06-07">
      Added progress bar.
    </change>
    <change name="Tracie Sucharski" date="2010-10-26">
      Changed for new Control Network format.
    </change>
    <change name="Travis Addair" date="2011-04-11">
      Changed parameters PROJECTION to MAP and TO to ONET for consistency.
    </change>
    <change name="Travis Addair" date="2011-07-08">
      Added error checking for latitude and longitude ranges
    </change>
    <change name="Jai Rideout" date="2011-09-30">
      Updated documentation with Janet Richie and Laszlo Kestay for release and
      added example.
    </change>
    <change name="Debbie A. Cook" date="2012-12-10">
      Changed to use TProjection instead of Projection.  References #775
    </change>
    <change name="Jeannie Backer" date="2016-04-22">
      Cleaned up duplicate code. Added error message to alert to the user when the program fails
      to find TargetRadii. Added errors appTest. References #3892
    </change>
    <change name="Jesse Mapel" date="2018-07-06">
      Changed to get the target radii directly from the Target class instead of the control network
      because the control network no longer has them. Fixes #5457.
    </change>
  </history>

  <groups>
    <group name="Target/Range">
      <parameter name="TARGET">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>
          Target planet for the Lat/Lon range
        </brief>
        <description>
          This is the planet on which the Lat/Lon range resides.  The target
          can be specified in one of two ways: by typing the name of a planet
          for this parameter, or by including the TargetName in the MAP file.
          If the user specifies both, then the TARGET parameter will be used
          instead of the TargetName in the MAP file.  If neither is specified,
          the program will throw an error.
        </description>
        <internalDefault>From MAP file</internalDefault>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="MAP">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          File containing mapping parameters
        </brief>
        <defaultPath>$base/templates/maps</defaultPath>
        <default><item>$base/templates/maps/sinusoidal.map</item></default>
        <description>
          A file containing the mapping parameters in PVL form.  This file can
          be a simple PVL file or an existing cube label that contains a
          Mapping group.  By default, the program will use a
          standard map template for a Sinusoidal projection.  If the keyword
          TargetName is not in this mapping file, then the user must specify
          a value for the TARGET parameter. You can produce map files using the
          <a href="../maptemplate/maptemplate.html"
            target="_blank">maptemplate</a> program.
        </description>
        <helpers>
          <helper name="H1">
            <function>PrintMap</function>
            <brief>View MapFile</brief>
            <description>
              This helper button will write the mapping group of the given
              mapfile to the session log of the application.
             </description>
            <icon>$ISIS3DATA/base/icons/labels.png</icon>
          </helper>
        </helpers>
        <filter>
          *.map *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="MINLAT">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief>
          Minimum Latitude
        </brief>
        <description>
          This is the minimum latitude for the Lat/Lon range. Control points are
          added to the control network starting from this latitude.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="MAXLAT">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief>
          Maximum Latitude
        </brief>
        <description>
          This is the maximum latitude for the Lat/Lon range.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="MINLON">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief>
          Minimum Longitude
        </brief>
        <description>
          This is the minimum longitude for the Lat/Lon range. Control points
          are added to the control network starting from this longitude.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="MAXLON">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief>
          Maximum Longitude
        </brief>
        <description>
          This is the maximum longitude for the Lat/Lon range.
        </description>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Step Size">
      <parameter name="SPACING">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>
          Whether the generated control points should be spaced by meter
          increment, or by latitude/longitude increment
        </brief>
        <description>
            This option allows the user to specify the type of spacing the
            program will use when generating the control points.  Selecting
            METER spacing will use a projection to attempt to place control
            points every XSTEP meters within the longitude range, and every
            YSTEP meters within the latitude range.  Conversely, LATLON spacing
            will simply place control points every LATSTEP and LONSTEP within
            the range.
        </description>
        <default><item>METER</item></default>
        <list>
            <option value="METER">
                <brief>
                   Space control points in the range by meter increments.
                </brief>
                <description>
                    This option will space control points in the range by a
                    specified XSTEP and YSTEP given in meters on the planet's
                    surface.  If this option is selected, the user must also
                    specify a MAP file, but not necessarily a value for
                    TARGET if the projection contains the TargetName keyword.
                </description>
                <inclusions>
                    <item>MAP</item>
                    <item>XSTEP</item>
                    <item>YSTEP</item>
                </inclusions>
                <exclusions>
                    <item>LATSTEP</item>
                    <item>LONSTEP</item>
                </exclusions>
            </option>
            <option value="LATLON">
                <brief>
                    Space control points in the range by latitude and longitude
                    increments.
                </brief>
                <description>
                    This option will space control points in the range by a
                    specified LATSTEP and LONSTEP, given in terms of the
                    planet's degrees latitude and longitude, respectively. If
                    this option is selected, the user must specify a TARGET
                    name, but not a MAP file. The lat/lon coordinates are in
                    universal format: the longitude domain is 0-360, the
                    longitude direction is positive east, and the latitude
                    coordinate system is planetocentric.
                </description>
                <inclusions>
                    <item>TARGET</item>
                    <item>LATSTEP</item>
                    <item>LONSTEP</item>
                </inclusions>
                <exclusions>
                    <item>MAP</item>
                    <item>XSTEP</item>
                    <item>YSTEP</item>
                </exclusions>
            </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="XSTEP">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief>
            Step Size in the x direction in meters
        </brief>
        <description>
            Points will be placed on the grid in the longitude range in the
            step described here in meters.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="YSTEP">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief>
            Step Size in the y direction in meters
        </brief>
        <description>
            Points will be placed on the grid in the latitude range in the step
            described here in meters.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="LATSTEP">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief>
            Step Size in the north/south direction
        </brief>
        <description>
            Points will be placed on the grid in the latitude range in the
            step described here in degrees latitude.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="LONSTEP">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief>
            Step Size in the east/west direction
        </brief>
        <description>
            Points will be placed on the grid in the longitude range in the
            step described here in degrees longitude.
        </description>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Control">
      <parameter name="NETWORKID">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>
            Name of this control network
        </brief>
        <description>
            The ID or name of the control network that is created. This string
            should be unique.
        </description>
        <internalDefault>
          No Id
        </internalDefault>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="POINTID">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>
            The pattern to be used to create point ids
        </brief>
        <description>
            A string with one and only one set of question marks ("?").
            This string will be used to create unique IDs for each control
            point created by this program. The question marks will be replaced
            with a number beginning with zero. For example the pattern
            "User????" would create point IDs "User0001" through
            "User9999". Note: Make sure there are enough "?"s for all the
            control points that may be created during this run. If all question
            marks are exausted the program will throw an error.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="DESCRIPTION">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>
            The description of the network
        </brief>
        <description>
            A string describing the purpose of this control network. For
            example, a description might be "LROC NAC MareSmythii GRID NETWORK".
            This description indicates that the control network is for the LROC
            mission using the narrow angle camera instrument, and the feature of
            interest is Mare Smythii. The description string can be literally
            anything, but it is helpful to make it something that is descriptive
            of the control network.
        </description>
        <internalDefault>
          No Description
        </internalDefault>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="ONET">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Output control network
        </brief>
        <description>
          This file will contain the control network that is created.
        </description>
      </parameter>
    </group>
  </groups>

  <examples>
    <example>
      <brief>Seeding Mars</brief>
      <description>
        This example illustrates how to generate a control network for the
        target planet Mars. The resulting control net is named 'out.net', and
        has control points seeded from -90 to +90 latitude, 0 to 360 longitude
        with a spacing of 20 degrees between each point.
      </description>
      <terminalInterface>
        <commandLine>
          TARGET=mars LATSTEP=20 LONSTEP=20 MINLAT=-90 MAXLAT=90 MINLON=0
          MAXLON=360 ONET=out.net SPACING=latlon POINTID='id????'
        </commandLine>
        <description>
          The command to use for this example.
        </description>
      </terminalInterface>

      <dataFiles>
        <dataFile path="assets/out.net">
          <brief>The resulting control network</brief>
          <description>
            This is the control network that is created by seedgrid.
          </description>
          <parameterName>ONET</parameterName>
        </dataFile>
      </dataFiles>

      <outputImages>
        <image src="assets/image/point_distribution.png" width="448"
          height="366">
          <brief>Point Distribution Visualization</brief>
          <description>
            This image is a visualization of the point distribution within the
            control network. This is projected using a sinusoidal projection.
            Please note that this image is not an output of the seedgrid
            application. It is included as a visual aid only.
          </description>
          <thumbnail caption="Resulting distribution of points in the network"
            src="assets/thumb/thumb_point_distribution.png" width="150"
            height="123"/>
        </image>
      </outputImages>
    </example>
  </examples>
</application>
