<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="remrx" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">
  <brief>
    Removes Reseaus from an image
  </brief>

  <description>
    This program will remove Reseaus from Viking, Voyager, and Mariner images.  
    The Reseaus are removed using either bilinear interpolation of the 
    surrounding pixels or by simply putting NULLs in the portion of the 
    image around the Reseau location of the input image.  The ACTION 
    parameter is used to tell the program which of these two actions to 
    take.  The user should input the size of the box around the Reseau that 
    will be modified.  SDIM and LDIM are the sample and line dimensions of 
    the box around the reseau.  RESVALID is used to determine whether the
    program will check the reseau valid flag for nominal reseaux before
    removing the reseau.  If RESVALID is NO, the program will not check
    the reseau valid flag for nominal reseaux and all the reseaux will be
    removed except invalid nominal positions.  If RESVALID is YES, the 
    program will check the reseau valid flag that is output from the 
    findrx program.  If the flag is 0, the program will not remove that
    reseau.  If the flag is 1, the reseau will be removed.  If the flag is
    -1, indicating an invalid nominal position, the reseau will not be
    removed in any case.   The output cube file can be written over the
    input file or a new output cube can be created.  To overwrite the input
    file, the TO parameter should be set to blank, " ".  The "findrx"
    program, which writes the Reseau locations, Reseau type, and a valid
    flag to the cube file label, must be run before "remrx".
  </description>

  <category>
    <missionItem>Viking</missionItem>
    <missionItem>Voyager</missionItem>
    <missionItem>Mariner</missionItem>
  </category>

  <seeAlso>
    <applications>
      <item>findrx</item>
    </applications>
  </seeAlso>

  <history>
    <change name="Elizabeth Ribelin" date="2005-05-02">
      Original version
    </change>
    <change name="Elizabeth Miller" date="2005-10-24">
        Added truth file for gala
    </change>
    <change name="Elizabeth Miller" date="2005-11-15">
      Modified appTest input path (viking testData areas split)
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2008-05-13">
      Removed references to CubeInfo 
    </change>
  </history>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input file reseaus will be removed from
        </brief>
        <description>
          The cube the reseaus will be removed from.  All reseaus in the cube 
          will be removed.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TO">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Output cube
        </brief>
        <description>
          The resultant cube containing the data with reseaus removed.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Dimensions">
        <parameter name="SDIM">
            <type>integer</type>
            <brief>
                Samples to remove around each reseau
            </brief>
            <description>
                The number of samples to remove around each reseau. Defaults to 9.0
            </description>
            <default><item>9</item></default>
            <odd />
        </parameter>

        <parameter name="LDIM">
            <type>integer</type>
            <brief>
                Lines to remove around each reseau
            </brief>
            <description>
                The number of lines to remove around each reseau. Defaults to 9.0
            </description>
            <default><item>9</item></default>
            <odd />
        </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Options">
        <parameter name="ACTION">
            <type>string</type>
            <brief>
                The way the reseaus will be removed
            </brief>
            <description>
                There are 2 options for removing the Reseaus.  The program 
                can replace pixels inside the SDIM x LDIM box with Null or 
                bilinear interpolation. Defaults to BILINEAR.
            </description>
            <default><item>BILINEAR</item></default>
            <list>
                <option value="BILINEAR">
                    <brief>
                       Replace values with bilinear interpolation
                    </brief>
                    <description>
                        This option uses bilinear interpolation to create new DN
                        values for the pixels inside the SDIM x LDIM box.
                    </description>
                </option>
                <option value="NULL">
                    <brief>
                       Replace values with NULLs
                    </brief>
                    <description>
                       This option will replace each value inside the SDIM x LDIM
                       box with the Isis::NULL value.  This allows the user to run 
                       another filter program to replace the NULL values.
                    </description>
                </option>
            </list>
        </parameter>

        <parameter name="RESVALID">
            <type>boolean</type>
            <brief>
                Check Reseau Valid Flag?
            </brief>
            <description>
                If this parameter is TRUE, the reseau valid flag will be
                checked before the reseau is removed.  If the reseau 
                valid flag is a 0 or -1, the reseau will not be removed.
                If the reseau valid flag is a 1, the reseau will be
                removed.  Reseaus with a valid flag=-1 are never removed.
                This flag indicates an invalid nominal position.
                If RESVALID is FALSE, the reseau valid flag will not be 
                checked for nominals and all the reseaus will be removed,
                except the invalid nominals. Defaults to FALSE.
            </description>
            <default><item>FALSE</item></default>
        </parameter>
    </group>
  </groups>

  <examples>
      <example>
        <brief> Reseaus replaced with Bilinear Interpolation </brief>
        <description>
          This example shows the remrx application with the BILINEAR action option.  The SDIM and LDIM default to 9, 
          and RESVALID defaults to false.
        </description>
        <terminalInterface>
          <commandLine> f=../inputRemrx.cub t=out-bilinear.cub
          </commandLine>
          <description>
            Uses bilinear interpolation to fill in missing data around each reseau.
          </description>
        </terminalInterface>

        <inputImages>
          <image src="assets/image/inputRemrx.JPG" width="500" height="500">
            <brief> Input image for mirror</brief>
            <description>This is the 800 by 800 input image for the remrx examples.
            </description>
            <thumbnail caption=" Input Io image" src="assets/thumb/inputRemrx.JPG" width="200" height="200"/>
            <parameterName>FROM</parameterName>
          </image>
        </inputImages>

        <outputImages>
          <image src="assets/image/IoRemrxBilinear.JPG" width="500" height="500">
            <brief> Output image for bilinear interpolation remrx</brief>
            <description> This is the 800 by 800 output image that results.
            </description>
            <thumbnail caption="Output image showing results of the remrx application with bilinear interpolation option." src="assets/thumb/IoRemrxBilinear.JPG" width="200" height="200"/>
            <parameterName>TO</parameterName>
          </image>
        </outputImages>

        <guiInterfaces>
          <guiInterface>
            <image width="441" height="221" src="assets/image/IoRemrxGui.JPG">
              <brief>Example Gui</brief>
              <description>
                  Screenshot of GUI with parameters filled in to perform a bilinear interpolation remrx operation on the input image. 
              </description>
              <thumbnail width="200" height="100" caption="Remrx Gui" src="assets/thumb/IoRemrxGui.JPG" />
            </image>
          </guiInterface>
        </guiInterfaces>
      </example>

      <example>
        <brief> Reseaus replaced with Nulls </brief>
        <description>
          This example shows the remrx application with the NULL action option, using the same input image as the above
          example.  The SDIM and LDIM default to 9, and RESVALID defaults to false.
        </description>
        <terminalInterface>
            <commandLine> f=../inputRemrx.cub t=out-null.cub
          </commandLine>
          <description>
            Nulls out 9x9 boxes around each reseau.
          </description>
        </terminalInterface>

        <outputImages>
          <image src="assets/image/IoRemrxNull.JPG" width="500" height="500">
            <brief> Output image for null remrx</brief>
            <description> This is the 800 by 800 output image that results.
            </description>
            <thumbnail caption="Output image showing results of the remrx application with null option." src="assets/thumb/IoRemrxNull.JPG" width="200" height="200"/>
            <parameterName>TO</parameterName>
          </image>
        </outputImages>

      </example>
   </examples>
</application>

