<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="voycal" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">

  <brief>
    Radiometric correction of Voyager 1 and 2 planetary images
  </brief>

  <description>
    <p>
      VOYCAL performs radiometric corrections to planetary images acquired by the  
      Viking orbiter and Voyager spacecraft vidicon cameras. VOYCAL performs a  
      radiometric correction in two steps. First, VOYCAL corrects for the varying  
      response of the vidicon across the field-of-view of the camera.  
      Multiplicative  and additive correction coefficients, as a function of line 
      and sample position,  are applied to an image array to produce the results 
      of an 'ideal' camera.   Optionally, for Voyager cameras, a non-linearity 
      correction can be additionally  applied to the image data.  Secondly, VOYCAL 
      converts the image data to radiance factor values.  The radiance factor is 
      defined as the ratio of the observed radiance and the radiance of a white 
      screen, normal to the incident rays of the sun.
    </p>
    <br>EQUATIONS</br> 
    <br>-----------------</br> 
    <p>
      The sensitivity of a vidicon camera varies across the field of view of an 
      image frame.  VOYCAL performs an additive, mutiplicative, and non-linearity 
      radiometric correction to an image to 
      correct for the varying sensitivity of the camera.  For information on the 
      radiometric properties of a vidicon camera, see the references; 
    </p>

    <p>"Inflight Performance of the Viking Visual Imaging Subsystem"
     Klassen, Thorpe, and Morabito; Applied Optics, Vol. 16, No. 12,
     December 1977.
    </p>
    <p>"Radiometric Performance of the Voyager Cameras" Danielson,
     Kuperman, Johnson, and Soderblom; Journal of Geophysical
     Research, Vol. 86, No. A10, Pages 8683-8689, September
     30, 1981.
    </p>
    <p>General equations applied to data for radiometric correction are
    indicated below:
    </p>
    <pre>Let: i,j    = line and sample position of pixel in an image
    DI(i,j) = Result of correction.  This value is known as the
              (Radiance factor)*10000. The output of VOYCAL is
              defined as the ratio of the observed radiance and
              the radiance of a white screen, normal to the incident
              rays of the sun. DI(i,j) = 10000 for an ideal 100%
              lambertian reflector with the sun and camera orthoganal
              to the planet surface.
    DR(i,j) = Raw input density number
    DC(i,j) = Camera shading dark current. This is a value from a file
              which provides the additive correction.
    G(i,j)  = Camera shading gain. This is a value from a file which
              provides the multiplicative correction.
    EXP     = Exposure time (seconds)
    W0      = Sensitivity of camera with sun-distance correction at
              standard distance from the sun.  This value is equivalent
              to the density number of a one second exposure of the
              camera for the standard distance of the planet from the
              sun.
    DIST0   = Standard distance of planet.  The W0 value was determined
              for a standard planet-sun distance. For Mars, the
              standard distance is 1.63 AU, the mean distance Mars from
              the Sun.  For Voyager image data, the standard distance
              is the distance of the planet (Jupiter, Saturn, Uranus)
              at the time of the Voyager encounter.
    W1      = Sensitivity of camera with planet-sun distance
              correction at actual distance of planet from the sun.
              This value is equivalent to the density number of a one
              second exposure of the camera for the planet-sun distance.
    DIST1   = actual distance of planet from the sun at time image was
              recorded
    GAIN    = Camera gain state constant
    OFF     = Camera state offset condition value

    W1 = W0*((DIST0**2)/DIST1**2))

    DI(i,j) = (1.0/(EXP*W1))*G(i,j)*(GAIN*DR(i,j)+DC(i,j)+OFF)*10000
  </pre>
  <p>The linearity correction to the DN values is performed before the gain
and offset correction is applied. If the linearity option is chosen, and
the voylin.pvl file has a table entry for the mission camera of the data being 
processed, or the user has provided TAE input for the coefficients B,K,LINORM, 
then a linearity correction will be made. The
result of the linearity correction is fed into the equation shown
above.  Thus, the result of the linearity correction is called DL(i,j).
The following linearity equation is used:</p>
    <pre>DL(i,j) = A*(DR(i,j)+DC(i,j)) + B*(((DR(i,j)+DC(i,j))/LINORM)**K)

      B = coefficient of linearity
      K = power of linearity fit (usually 4)
      LINORM = linearizer normalization (usually 128)
      A = (LINORM-B)/LINORM
    </pre>
  </description>

  <history>
    <change name="Mackenzie Boyd" date="2010-08-10">
      Original version - Converted from Isis2
    </change>
    <change name="Debbie A. Cook" date="2012-07-06">
       Updated Spice members to be more compliant with Isis coding standards. References #972.
    </change>
  </history>

  <category>
    <missionItem>Voyager</missionItem>
  </category>

  <seeAlso>
    <applications>
      <item>voyramp</item>
    </applications>
  </seeAlso>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input cube for radiometric correction
        </brief>
        <description>
          The cube to use for radiometric correction, must be a Voyager image.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TO">
         <type>cube</type>
         <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <pixelType>real</pixelType>
         <brief>
          Output cube
         </brief>
         <description>
           The output cube which will contain the radiometrically corrected 
           data.
         </description>
         <filter>
           *.cub
         </filter>
       </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Options">
      <parameter name="LINEAR">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>TRUE</item></default>
        <brief>
          Option for Linear correction
        </brief>
        <description>
          Option to apply Linear correction to cube. Must have matching data in 
          voylin.pvl. Equation can be viewed in general description.   
        </description>
      </parameter> 
    </group>
  </groups>
</application>
