<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="tabledump" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">
  <brief>
      Program to output a selected table to a file
  </brief>

  <description>
      <p>
          This program takes a cube with one or more table blobs in it, and, through
          input provided by the user, outputs a selected table to an ASCII file,
          with formatting determined by user input.
      </p>

      <p>
          Helper button has been provided in the GUI mode for the NAME 
          parameter.  The helper button will sequentially fill in the name of 
          each table when pressed, clear the field to blank after the last table
          has been reached, and then wrap back to the beginning.
      </p>
  </description>

  <category>
      <categoryItem>Import and Export</categoryItem>
  </category>

  <history>
      <change name="Brendan George" date="2006-10-26">
          Original version
      </change>
      <change name="Brendan George" date="2006-12-18">
          Fixed helper button
      </change>
      <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2007-07-27">
          Changed category from Utility to Import and Export 
      </change>
      <change name="Steven Koechle" date="2008-05-20">
          Changed TO parameter to function like other applications in ISIS.
          It now defaults to console output when no TO file is enterd.
      </change>
      <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2008-06-19">
          Fixed string representation and display.
      </change>
      <change name="Travis Addair" date="2009-03-03">
          Changed helper button to only place one table name into the 
          NAME parameter each time it is pressed
      </change>
  </history>

  <groups>
      <group name="Files">
          <parameter name="FROM">
              <type>cube</type>
              <fileMode>input</fileMode>
              <brief>
                  Input Cube
              </brief>
              <description>
                  This is the cube containing the table to be output.
              </description>
              <filter>*.cub</filter>
          </parameter>

          <parameter name="TO">
              <type>filename</type>
              <fileMode>output</fileMode>
              <brief>
                  Output file
              </brief>
              <description>
                  This is the output file where the table will be written.
              </description>
              <internalDefault>
                No Output file will be created
              </internalDefault>
              <filter>*.txt</filter>
          </parameter>
      </group>

      <group name="Specifications">
          <parameter name="NAME">
              <type>string</type>
              <brief>
                  The name of the table
              </brief>
              <description>
                  This is the name of the table to be output. The name is found
                  in the labels, in the relevant object, as the value of the
                  Keyword "Name." This value is set by the program creating
                  the table, and is standardized to certain conventions.
              </description>
              <helpers>
                <helper name="H1">
                  <function>helperButtonGetTableList</function>
                  <brief>Retrieve Table names</brief>
                  <description>
                     This button will, each time it is pressed, generate the 
                     name of a table in the input cube and put it in the 
                     appropriate field in the GUI, clearing the field to blank 
                     and wrapping back to the top after the last table is hit.  
                  </description>
                  <icon>$ISIS3DATA/base/icons/exec.png</icon>
               </helper>
            </helpers>
          </parameter>

          <parameter name="DELIMIT">
              <type>string</type>
              <brief>
                  The character to be inserted between table entries
              </brief>
              <description>
                  This option will determine which character will be used to
                  separate table entries, with the default option as a comma.
                  The other options are space, to separate with a single
                  space, or "OTHER," which allows the user to input whatever
                  they wish as the delimiter character.
              </description>
              <default><item>COMMA</item></default>
              <list>
                  <option value="COMMA">
                      <brief>Separate with commas</brief>
                      <description>
                          This option will cause the table entries to be
                          separated by commas.
                      </description>
                      <exclusions>
                          <item>CUSTOM</item>
                      </exclusions>
                  </option>
                  <option value="SPACE">
                      <brief>Separate with spaces</brief>
                      <description>
                          This option will cause the table entries to be
                          separated by single space when output.
                      </description>
                      <exclusions>
                          <item>CUSTOM</item>
                      </exclusions>
                  </option>
                  <option value="OTHER">
                      <brief>Separate with user-defined characters</brief>
                      <description>
                          This option allows the user to determine what
                          character is used to separate entries. When this
                          option is selected, the CUSTOM parameter is used
                          to determine what will be used. Whatever string the
                          user enters will be used in between the entries.
                      </description>
                      <inclusions>
                          <item>CUSTOM</item>
                      </inclusions>
                  </option>
              </list>
          </parameter>
          <parameter name="CUSTOM">
              <type>string</type>
              <brief>User-defined delimiter</brief>
              <description>
                  This parameter is only used if the user has selected "OTHER"
                  as a delimiter. The user then enters something into this
                  parameter to use as a delimiter.
              </description>
          </parameter>
      </group>
  </groups>
</application>
