<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="hirdr2isis" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">

  <brief>Import PDS formatted HiRISE RDR image cube into Isis format cube</brief>

  <description>
      <p> 
          This program will import a PDS formatted HiRISE RDR image into an Isis
     cube.  The normal generic application is <b>pds2isis</b>, however HiRISE 
     images require special consideration.  These considerations are based upon 
     requirements placed on the process of converting original HiRISE ISIS 
     products into PDS archive format and back again.  The HiRISE team requires 
     a certain level of preservation so that science analysis on the PDS 
     archived product, particularly in the ISIS system, is not compromised.
      </p>
      <p>
          One consequence of the PDS storage requirements is the conversion of 
          ISIS data to unsigned 16-bit integers.  This data storage type is not 
          support inherently in the ISIS system, but this application converts 
          it to the best data representation possible - 32-bit floating point 
          values.  Comparisons of the conversion process falls within acceptable 
          precision loss (approximately 1.0E-6).
      </p>
      <p>
          Much of what this program does is ensure labels are properly copied 
          and translated from PDS archival form that is consistant and highly 
          comparable to the original ISIS product.  The strictest requirement is
          label integrity which applies mainly to geometric datum contained in 
          the ISIS labels.  The goal is to ensure geometric behavior is within 
          acceptable limits of the original product.
      </p>
  </description>

  <history>
    <change name="Janet Barrett" date="2007-08-17">
      Original version
    </change>
      <change name="Kris Becker" date="2007-12-05">
          The following modifications where made to more closely adhere to the
          orginal ISIS himos source:  map the PDS Archive group back to the
          ISIS Mosaic group; PDS NULL values of -9998 are mapped back to
          ISIS Null; order of the groups are written in the same order as the 
          ISIS input file;  Target radius values are updated for the 
          Equirectangular projection only such that the existing 
          (EquatorialRadius) radius value is copied to the CenterLatitudeRadius 
          keyword and the actual NAIF radii replace EquatorialRadius and 
          PolarRadius values if it is a valid NAIF target; the order of the 
          values in keywords cpmmTdiFlag, cpmmSummingFlag and 
          SpecialProcessingFlag are reordered according to CPMM order as it is 
          in the original source; and added a bit more documentation.
      </change>
      <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2008-05-13">
        Removed references to CubeInfo 
      </change>
  </history>

  <category>
    <missionItem>Mars Reconnaissance Orbiter</missionItem>
  </category>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input PDS formatted HiRISE RDR file
        </brief>
        <description>
          Use this parameter to select the HiRISE RDR filename. This 
          file must contain the PDS labels.  This file must have been generated 
          by the ISIS <b>hirdrgen</b> application.  These files are assumed to 
          be projected products.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.img *.IMG
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TO">
         <type>cube</type>
         <fileMode>output</fileMode>
         <brief>
           Output Isis cube
         </brief>
         <description>
           Use this parameter to select the ISIS output filename.  This file 
           will compare very closely with the original input file to the ISIS 
           <b>hirdrgen</b> application.
         </description>
         <filter>
           *.cub
         </filter>
       </parameter>
    </group>
  </groups>
</application>
