<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="mask" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">

  <brief>
    Set pixels to NULL using a mask cube
  </brief>

  <description>
    This program masks (or NULLs) pixels in an input cube.  The input cube is
    NULLed using a mask cube.  This is done by specifying a minimum/maximum
    pixel range in the mask cube.  Pixels which fall outside the range in
    the mask will be set to NULL in the output cube.  Pixels inside the range
    will be propagated from the input cube to the output.  An option exists to
    reverse the masking process so that pixels outside the range are preserved,
    and pixels inside the range are NULLed.
  </description>

  <history>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="1990-12-03">
      Original version
    </change>

    <change name="Tracie Sucharski" date="2002-06-19">
      Ported to Isis 3.0
    </change>
    <change name="Kim Sides" date="2003-05-13">
      Added application test
    </change>
    <change name="Stuart Sides" date="2003-05-16">
      Modified schema location from astogeology... to isis.astrogeology..."
    </change>
    <change name="Stuart Sides" date="2003-07-29">
      Modified filename parameters to be cube parameters where necessary
    </change>
   <change name="Sharmila Prasad" date="2009-08-24">
      Set Internal Default for "MASK" to be "FROM" 
    </change>
  </history>

  <category>
    <categoryItem>Trim and Mask</categoryItem>
  </category>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input cube to mask
        </brief>
        <description>
          Use this parameter to select the filename. All bands within the file
          will be masked.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="MASK">
         <type>cube</type>
         <fileMode>input</fileMode>
         <brief>
           Mask cube
         </brief>
         <description>
           Use this parameter to select the filename to be used as the mask.
           If this parameter is not explicitly entered, it will default to the
           same filename as FROM
         </description>
        <internalDefault>
          FROM
        </internalDefault>
         <filter>
           *.cub
         </filter>
       </parameter>

      <parameter name="TO">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Output cube
        </brief>
        <description>
          This file will contain the results of the masked cube
        </description>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Mask Options">
      <parameter name="MINIMUM">
        <type>double</type>
        <internalDefault>
          ISIS minimum
        </internalDefault>
        <lessThanOrEqual>
          <item> MAXIMUM </item>
        </lessThanOrEqual>
        <brief>Minimum value of range to mask</brief>
        <description>
          This defines the minimum range of valid data in the mask cube.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="MAXIMUM">
        <type>double</type>
        <internalDefault>
          ISIS maximum
        </internalDefault>
        <greaterThanOrEqual>
          <item> MINIMUM </item>
        </greaterThanOrEqual>
        <brief>Maximum value of range to mask</brief>
        <description>
          This defines the maximum range of valid data in the mask cube.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="PRESERVE">
        <type>string</type>
        <default>
          <item>INSIDE</item>
        </default>
        <brief>Indicates whether to preserve pixels inside or outside of range.</brief>
        <description>
          This parameter indicates whether the pixels chosen to mask are within the range given
          or outside of the range given.  If INSIDE,  pixels inside of given range will be masked.
          If OUTSIDE, pixels outside the range will be masked.
        </description>
        <list>
          <option value="INSIDE">
            <brief> Mask inside range </brief>
            <description>
              If the mask pixel is inside the given range (indicated with the MINIUMUM
              and MAXIMUM parameters), the input pixel will be preserved in the output
              cube, otherwise it will be NULLed.
            </description>
          </option>
          <option value="OUTSIDE">
            <brief> Mask outside range </brief>
            <description>
              If the mask pixel is outside the given range (indicated with the MINIMUM
              and MAXIMUM parameters), the input pixel we be preserved in the output
              file, otherwise it will be NULLed.
            </description>
          </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Special Pixels">
      <parameter name="SPIXELS">
	<type>string</type>
	<default>
	  <item>NULL</item>
	</default>
	<brief>Special pixels to include as mask</brief>
	<description>
	  This indicates which special pixel values are to be included as valid
      pixels in the mask.  For example, a NULL in the mask cube will cause
      the output to be NULL if the NULL or ALL option is selected.  If NONE
      was selected, then the input pixel would be propagated to the output
      cube.
	</description>
	<list>
	  <option value="NONE">
	    <brief> None </brief>
	    <description>
	      No special pixels are considered valid in the mask.
	    </description>
	  </option>

	  <option value="NULL">
	    <brief> Null pixels </brief>
	    <description>
	      Null pixels will be included in the mask.
	    </description>
	  </option>

	  <option value="ALL">
	    <brief> All special pixels </brief>
	    <description>
	      All special pixels included in the mask range
	    </description>
	  </option>
	</list>
      </parameter>
    </group>

  </groups>
</application>
