<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="findimageoverlaps" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">
  <brief>
    Uses the input image footprints to find their intersections and writes these
    intersections to a file for used in other programs such as autoseed.
  </brief>

  <description>
    Several programs in Isis have an input parameter "OVERLAPLIST." This program
    is designed to produce the OVERLAPLIST for other Isis programs to use.<br />
    <br />

    An overlap list is a file describing how the images in a file list intersect
    each other. The output contains encoded information that describes
    how many cubes overlap in a particular latitude/longitude area. For example,
    it might define "lub0454d.342.cub and lub0421c.342.cub overlap in longitudes
    262.2 degrees to 270.3 degrees and latitudes -58.3 degrees to -60.3
    degrees." The information in the file is much more precise than that, but
    the general idea of the data is the same. Having image intersection
    information is key for problems such as initial control point placement
    <br /><br />

    The overlap list is generated using the footprints of the input images. A
    requirement to running this program is running footprintinit on all
    of your input files. The precision of the footprints directly affects the
    precision of the overlap list/intersection information. If you
    re-spiceinit or in any way change the SPICE data of an image then you should
    re-run footprintinit and this program to update your image intersection
    information. Programs that do not change SPICE data (for example,
    calibration) do not require you to re-run this program.<br /><br />

    The algorithm for finding these overlaps is:
    <ol>
      <li>
        Create a list of the image footprints
      </li>
      <li>
        For each combination of items in the list (in the order of 1,2 1,3
        1,4 2,3 2,4 3,4) where the first item is the left hand side and the
        second item is the right hand side, do the following:
        <ol>
          <li>
            If the left and right hand side have overlapping serial numbers
            associated with them then move on to the next combination of items
            in the list.
          </li>
          <li>
            If the lat/lon area associated with the left and right hand side are
            identical, then copy the serial numbers from the right hand side
            into the left hand side and delete the right hand side.
          </li>
          <li>
            If the right hand side is empty or extremely tiny then delete it.
          </li>
          <li>
            Intersect the left and right hand side.
            <ol>
              <li>
                If the intersection is empty or extremely tiny then move on to the
                next combination of items in the list.
              </li>
              <li>
                If the intersection is equal to the left hand side, then update
                the right hand side to be itself minus the intersection. Update
                the left hand side to have the right hand side's serial numbers.
                Move on to the next combination of items in the list.
              </li>
              <li>
                If the intersection is equal to the right hand side, then update
                the left hand side to be itself minus the intersection. Update
                the right hand side to have the left hand side's serial numbers.
                Move on to the next combination of items in the list.
              </li>
              <li>
                Subtract the intersection from the left hand side. If this fails,
                try to subtract the right hand side from the left hand side to
                automatically correct. Update the left hand side. Add the
                intersection as a new item in the list with the serial numbers
                of the left hand side.
              </li>
            </ol>
          </li>
        </ol>
      </li>
    </ol>
  </description>

  <category>
    <categoryItem>Control Networks</categoryItem>
  </category>

  <history>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2008-11-03">
      Original version
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2008-11-24">
      Added the "DETAILED" and "ERRORS" parameters.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2009-01-07">
      Added the number of errors to the results output
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2009-05-27">
      Uses different method call to ImageOverlapSet for optimization
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2009-05-28">
      The input list will be internally sorted by serial number so that
      one list of input images will always produce the same results regardless 
      of the sort order.
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2010-03-26">
      Added an error when no new overlaps are calculated. (i.e. All overlaps
      contain only a single Serial Number)
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2010-09-27">
      Moved the above error handling to ImageOverlapSet.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2011-09-26">
      Improved documentation in preparation for the October release. Working
      with me to document findimageoverlaps was Ra'ad Saleh and Bob Sucharski.
    </change>
    <change name="Marjorie Hahn" date="2016-08-05">
      Fixed a bug where ImageOverlapSet was not recording overlaps where 
      one image is fully enveloped within another. Fixes #2199.
    </change>
  </history>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROMLIST">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          List of input cubes to be intersected
        </brief>
        <description>
          Use this parameter to specify the cubes for which we will find the
          intersections of. If you are working with a control network then this
          is the list of files associated with the control network.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.lis
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="OVERLAPLIST">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Output overlap list
        </brief>
        <description>
          This file will contain the intersected image footprints in a non-human
          readable format.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="ERRORS">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <internalDefault>No Error Output</internalDefault>
        <brief>
          Error list file for errors generated when making the overlap list
        </brief>
        <description>
          This file will contain the errors that occurred while calculating the
          image overlaps. These errors are typically caused by complicated
          math involving arbitrary polygons failing to produce an understandable
          result and can often be alleviated by simplifying the input polygons.
          Basically, the errors might be fixed by reducing the precision of
          your image footprints; but increasing precision might fix them too.
        </description>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Settings">
      <parameter name="DETAILED">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <brief>
          Output detailed error information
        </brief>
        <description>
          When this is set to true, and there is an errors file, the maximum
          amount of information about each error is printed to the errors file.
          When this is false, only filenames will be reported in the errors
          file.
        </description>
        <default><item>false</item></default>
      </parameter>
    </group>
  </groups>
</application>
