<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="cnetcheck" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">

  <brief>
    Checks the validity of a control network
  </brief>

  <description>
    <p>
      This program checks for the validity of a <def>Control Network</def>.  It
      is recommended to run cnetcheck before running jigsaw (can use the same
      input image cube list and control network) in order to catch a choice of
      potential issues with the control network and the corresponding input
      image cube list.
    </p>
    <p>
      The default primary function of cnetcheck is to idenify any
      <def link="Control Islands">Islands</def> within the control network
      (CNET).  Each identified 'Island' will have an output file associated with
      it ("PREFIX"_Island.#, where #=sequential number id).  The output Island
      files contain the list of images connected together as a group, the file
      includes the cube filenames and corresponding
      <def link="Serial Number">serial numbers</def>.
    </p>
    <p>
      NOTE1: If a serial number is identified as a single image island and the
      corresponding image cube file name is not listed within the FROMLIST, then
      the image cube filename will not be included in the appropriate island
      file.
    </p>
    <p>
      NOTE2: If it is discovered that a known island is missing an output island
      file (i.e., output list not created as expected), it is possible that the
      image cube file name(s) were not listed in the input list (FROMLIST).
    </p>
    <p>
      All output files are created in the working directory where cnetcheck is
      initiated.
    </p>
  </description>

  <history>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2008-07-09">
      Original version
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2008-07-10">
      Fixed output files to only show filenames and usage of c_str.
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2008-07-28">
      Fixed NoLatLon option.
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2008-08-01">
      Added Control Point IDs to the NoLatLon flat file.
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2008-10-28">
      Greatly optimized the NoLatLon option.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2008-11-24">
      Renamed parameters: "LIST" is now "FROMLIST" and "CONTROL" is now "NETWORK"
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2009-04-07">
      Added the IGNORE option, which ignores ignored Control Points.
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2009-04-23">
      Added a results group that correlates parameter names to keywords,  fixed
      the newline character outputs, and changed NOMATCH to NOCONTROL.
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2009-05-15">
      Fixed the island detecting to disregard ignored control points and other
      bug fixes.
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2009-06-03">
      Fixed a bug with ignored Control Measures, changed NETWORK to CNET,
      changed the output formats to be more useful and consistant.
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2009-08-21">
      Cleaned up syntax and improved readability.
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2009-09-18">
      Added the SINGLECUBE parameter, renaming SINGLE to SINGLEMEASURE as a consequence.
    </change>
    <change name="Mackenzie Boyd" date="2010-05-28">
      Modified functionality of NOLATLON option to check all measures, not just
      each cube.
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2009-06-08">
      Added the DELIMIT parameter
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2010-10-06">
      Fixed for binary cnet conversion.
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2011-01-18">
      Altered to compile with the new Control redesign.
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2011-02-10">
      Swapped the order of to serial number and filename in the NOCONTROL
      output file.
    </change>
    <change name="James Alexander Crough and Eric Hyer" date="2011-06-15">
      Added ability to check the ratio between the convex hull of the cnet and
      its parent cube.
    </change>
    <change name="Travis Addair" date="2011-08-10">
      Added LOWCOVERAGE option to make convex hull check optional.
    </change>
    <change name="Tammy Becker" date="2011-11-17">
      Modified documentation and changed Tolerance default from 0.0 to 1.0.
    </change>
  </history>

  <category>
    <categoryItem>Control Networks</categoryItem>
  </category>

  <groups>
    <group name="Input Files">
      <parameter name="FROMLIST">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          List of input cube file names in the Control Network
        </brief>
        <description>
          A text file containing one column of ISIS image cube file names.
          Every image cube file used in the control network should be included
          in this list.  The input images are required to be a <def>Level0</def>
          or <def>Level1</def> cube with a successful 'spiceinit' applied
          previously.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.txt *.lis *.list
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="CNET">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input Control Network file
        </brief>
        <description>
          Use this parameter to specify the input Control Network file for
          validation.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.net
        </filter>
      </parameter>

    </group>

    <group name="Output Options">

      <parameter name="DELIMIT">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>
          The character to be inserted between output file field entries
        </brief>
        <description>
          This option determines which character will be used to separate
          the output file field entries, with the default option as a tab.
          Other options are comma, single space, or "OTHER," which allows
          the user to input whatever they wish as the delimiter character.
        </description>
        <default><item>TAB</item></default>
        <list>
          <option value="TAB">
            <brief>Separate with tabs</brief>
            <description>
              This option will cause the output file field entries to be
              separated by tabs.
            </description>
            <exclusions>
              <item>CUSTOM</item>
            </exclusions>
          </option>
          <option value="COMMA">
            <brief>Separate with commas</brief>
            <description>
              This option will cause the output file field entries to be
              separated by commas.
            </description>
            <exclusions>
              <item>CUSTOM</item>
            </exclusions>
          </option>
          <option value="SPACE">
            <brief>Separate with spaces</brief>
            <description>
              This option will cause the output file field entries to be
              separated by single 'white' space.
            </description>
            <exclusions>
              <item>CUSTOM</item>
            </exclusions>
          </option>
          <option value="OTHER">
            <brief>Separate with user-defined characters</brief>
            <description>
              This option allows the user to determine what
              character is used to separate field entries. When this
              option is selected, the CUSTOM parameter contains the
              user-defined string that will be used between the output
              file field entries.
            </description>
            <inclusions>
              <item>CUSTOM</item>
            </inclusions>
          </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="CUSTOM">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>User-defined delimiter</brief>
        <description>
          This parameter is only used if the user has selected "OTHER"
          as a delimiter. The user enters a string into this
          parameter to use as the output delimiter.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="PREFIX">
        <type>string</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Output result filename prefix
        </brief>
        <description>
          The results of the validity check are placed in output file names with
          the given prefix.
          <p>
            For example, PREFIX=CHK_, will result in an output filename
            CHK_Island.1 or CHK_NoControl.txt
          </p>
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="IGNORE">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>True</item></default>
        <brief>
          Disregard 'Ignored' Control Points when checking the Control Network
        </brief>
        <description>
          When Ignore=TRUE, any <def link="Control Point">control points</def>
          and <def link="Control Measures">control measures</def> that are
          flagged as invalid within the network (IGNORE=TRUE), are NOT
          considered links across images/groups when identifying islands.
          <p>
            Ignore=TRUE is the default for consistency with other apps, such as
            jigsaw, that do NOT consider invalid points or measures.
          </p>
          <p>
            When Ignore=FALSE, all valid and invalid control points and control
            measures are considered for links between images and groups.
          </p>
        </description>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Checks">
      <parameter name="NOCONTROL">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>True</item></default>
        <brief>
          Check for images in the FROMLIST that are not in the Control Net
        </brief>
        <description>
          NOCONTROL=True, given the input image cube file name list (FROMLIST),
          any files (and their corresponding <def>serial number</def>) that are
          not found in the input control network (CNET) are considered images
          without control.  These filenames and serial numbers will be listed in
          the output file named [PREFIX]NoControl.txt (with a field delimiter
          [DELIMIT]).
          <p>
            No output file will be created if all images are controlled.
          </p>
          <p>
            NOCONTROL=False will turn off this testing of images without
            control.
          </p>
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="NOCUBE">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>True</item></default>
        <brief>
          Checks for images in the Control Network that are not in the FROMLIST
        </brief>
        <description>
          NOCUBE=True, an output file named [PREFIX]NoCube.txt will be created,
          which will list all <def link="Serial Number">serial numbers</def>
          encountered in the input Control Network (CNET) that do not have a
          corresponding image cube file name in the provided list (FROMLIST).
          <p>
            No output file will be created if all serial numbers match to an
            image cube file name.
          </p>
          <p>
            NOCUBE=False will turn off the testing for matching serial number
            and input image file names.
          </p>
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="SINGLEMEASURE">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>True</item></default>
        <brief>
          Check for Control Points that contain only a single Control Measure
        </brief>
        <description>
          SINGLEMEASURE=True, a file named [PREFIX]SinglePointCubes.txt will be
          created, which will list all image cube file names that exist as the
          single Control Measure in any Control Point within the provided
          Control Network.
          <p>
            Note: In general and when possible, a control point should have more
            than one control measures (more than three).
          </p>
          <p>
            If there are no such single Control Measures, then no file is
            created.
          </p>
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="DUPLICATE">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>True</item></default>
        <brief>
          Check for Control Points containing same image in multiple Measures
        </brief>
        <description>
          When true, a file named [PREFIX]DuplicateMeasures.txt will be created,
          which will list all image cube filenames that exist in more than one
          Control Measure in a single Control Point.
          <p>
            Images under this scenario must be resolved before running jigsaw.
            A single image must not have more than one measure to the same
            control point.
          </p>
          <p>
            If there are no such duplicate Control Measures, then no file is
            created.
          </p>
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="SINGLECUBE">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>True</item></default>
        <brief>
          Check for images that are measured to only one Control Point
        </brief>
        <description>
          When true, a file named [PREFIX]SingleCubes.txt will be created,
          that will list all image cube filenames that are measured to only
          one control point.
          <p>
            These images would have a convex hull value near zero, meaning there
            are not enough control points.  Where possible, any image should
            have measures to multiple control points along the image plane
            boundaries (convex hull value near 1.0 for a full distribution).
            Refer to the Tolerance parameter for a distrubution test.
          </p>
          <p>
            If there are no such single Cubes, then no file is created.
          </p>
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="NOLATLON">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>True</item></default>
        <brief>
          Check for measures whose latitudes and longitudes cannot be computed
        </brief>
        <description>
          When true, a file named [PREFIX]NoLatLon.txt will be created, which
          will list all Serial Numbers within the given Control Network and
          FROMLIST which a latitude and longitude value cannot be computed at
          their respective image measure coordinate.
          <p>
            These identified Serial Numbers and image cube filenames will be
            followed by the Control Point IDs where the latitude and longitude
            could not be computed at the associated measures.
          </p>

          <p>
            If there are no such serial numbers, then no file is created.
          </p>

          <p>
            Only image cubes included in both the FROMLIST and CNET are checked.
          </p>
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="LOWCOVERAGE">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>True</item></default>
        <brief>
          Check for the distribution of Control Points across each image
        </brief>
        <description>
          <p>
            The main purpose of this test is to isolate the images that have an
            insufficient distribution of control point measures.  This is
            performed by constructing a convex hull from all Control Measures
            located on the image in "image pixel space".  The convex hull gives
            a rough estimation of the distributed coverage of Control Points in
            the input control network across each image.  By enabling this
            option, a file named [PREFIX]LowCoverage.txt will be created
            containing all images (with corresponding serial numbers) whose
            convex hull coverage is less than the given user-specified
            TOLERANCE.  A third column will also be output, showing the actual
            coverage value for each reported image.
          </p>
          <p>
            The default of 1.0 for a max tolerance will effectively cause
            nearly every image to be reported, as it is highly unlikely that
            a convex hull will cover 100% of it's corresponding image.
            With a tolerance of 0.25, any image whose convex hull covers less
            than a quarter of the image area will be reported.  A minimal
            tolerance of 0.0 effectively makes the test meaningless, allowing
            images to "pass" this test without having ay control point coverage.
          </p>
          <p>
            Only cubes in both the FROMLIST and CNET are checked.
          </p>
        </description>
        <inclusions>
          <item>TOLERANCE</item>
        </inclusions>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TOLERANCE">
        <type>double</type>
        <default><item>1.0</item></default>
        <minimum inclusive="yes">0.0</minimum>
        <maximum inclusive="yes">1.0</maximum>
        <brief>
          Minimum ratio of convex hull coverage to cube area allowed
        </brief>
        <description>
          Given the area of the convex hull, generated from all measures in an
          image, divide by the total area of the image.  The resulting value
          from 0.0 to 1.0 shows roughly what percentage of the image is covered
          by its measures.  If this coverage value is less than the tolerance
          specified by this parameter, then the image will fail the LOWCOVERAGE
          check and be reported as such.  This value must be between 0.0 and
          1.0, inclusive.
        </description>
      </parameter>
    </group>
  </groups>
</application>
