<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="cnetcheck" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">

  <brief>
    Checks for validity of a Control Net file.
  </brief>

  <description>
    Checks for the validity of a Control Net file given a cube list.  Its primary
    function is to check and find islands of the Control Net.  These islands
    are then written to seperate files, which lists the cubes and their
    corresponding serial number.  If a serial number's cube is not listed in
    the input list, than that cube will NOT be listed within the appropriate
    island file.  If an island file is missing altogether, it is due to the fact
    that all of that islands cubes were not listed in the input list.

    cnetcheck should be ran from the directory you wish for the output files to 
    be written to.
  </description>

  <history>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2008-07-09">
      Original version
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2008-07-10">
      Fixed output files to only show filenames and usage of c_str.
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2008-07-28">
      Fixed NoLatLon option.
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2008-08-01">
      Added Control Point IDs to the NoLatLon flat file.
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2008-10-28">
      Greatly optimized the NoLatLon option.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2008-11-24">
      Renamed parameters: "LIST" is now "FROMLIST" and "CONTROL" is now "NETWORK"
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2009-04-07">
      Added the IGNORE option, which ignores ignored Control Points.
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2009-04-23">
      Added a results group that correlates parameter names to keywords,  fixed
      the newline character outputs, and changed NOMATCH to NOCONTROL.
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2009-05-15">
      Fixed the island detecting to disregard ignored control points and other
      bug fixes.
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2009-06-03">
      Fixed a bug with ignored Control Measures, changed NETWORK to CNET,
      changed the output formats to be more useful and consistant.
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2009-08-21">
      Cleaned up syntax and improved readability.
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2009-09-18">
      Added the SINGLECUBE parameter, renaming SINGLE to SINGLEMEASURE as a consequence.
    </change>
    <change name="Mackenzie Boyd" date="2010-05-28">
      Modified functionality of NOLATLON option to check all measures, not just 
      each cube.
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2009-06-08">
      Added the DELIMIT parameter
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2010-10-06">
      Fixed for binary cnet conversion.
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2011-01-18">
      Altered to compile with the new Control redesign.
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2011-02-10">
      Swapped the order of to serial number and filename in the NOCONTROL
      output file.
    </change>
  </history>

  <category>
    <categoryItem>Control Networks</categoryItem>
  </category>
  
  <groups>
    <group name="Input Files">
      <parameter name="FROMLIST">
          <type>filename</type>
          <fileMode>input</fileMode>
          <brief>
            List of ISIS3 input cubes in the Control Network
          </brief>
          <description>
          A text file containing one column of ISIS3 cube file names. Every file
          used in the match point file should be represented in this list.
          </description>
          <filter>
            *.txt *.lis *.list
          </filter>
        </parameter>

        <parameter name="CNET">
          <type>filename</type>
          <fileMode>input</fileMode>
          <brief>
             Isis3 input Control Network file
          </brief>
          <description>
            Use this parameter to specify the control network file containing
            the information to be validated
            </description>
          <filter>
            *.net
          </filter>
        </parameter>

    </group>

    <group name="Output Options">

      <parameter name="DELIMIT">
          <type>string</type>
          <brief>
              The character to be inserted between file entries
          </brief>
          <description>
              This option will determine which character will be used to
              separate file entries, with the default option as a tab.
              The other options are comma, to separate with a single
              space, or "OTHER," which allows the user to input whatever
              they wish as the delimiter character.
          </description>
          <default><item>TAB</item></default>
          <list>
            <option value="TAB">
                <brief>Separate with tabs</brief>
                <description>
                    This option will cause the file entries to be
                    separated by tabs.
                </description>
                <exclusions>
                    <item>CUSTOM</item>
                </exclusions>
            </option>
              <option value="COMMA">
                  <brief>Separate with commas</brief>
                  <description>
                      This option will cause the file entries to be
                      separated by commas.
                  </description>
                  <exclusions>
                      <item>CUSTOM</item>
                  </exclusions>
              </option>
              <option value="SPACE">
                  <brief>Separate with spaces</brief>
                  <description>
                      This option will cause the file entries to be
                      separated by single space when output.
                  </description>
                  <exclusions>
                      <item>CUSTOM</item>
                  </exclusions>
              </option>
              <option value="OTHER">
                  <brief>Separate with user-defined characters</brief>
                  <description>
                      This option allows the user to determine what
                      character is used to separate entries. When this
                      option is selected, the CUSTOM parameter is used
                      to determine what will be used. Whatever string the
                      user enters will be used in between the entries.
                  </description>
                  <inclusions>
                      <item>CUSTOM</item>
                  </inclusions>
              </option>
          </list>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="CUSTOM">
          <type>string</type>
          <brief>User-defined delimiter</brief>
          <description>
              This parameter is only used if the user has selected "OTHER"
              as a delimiter. The user then enters something into this
              parameter to use as a delimiter.
          </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="PREFIX">
        <type>string</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Outputs results
        </brief>
        <description>
	        The result of the validity check is placed in output files with the 
          given prefix.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="IGNORE">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>True</item></default>
        <brief>
          Ignores ignored Control Points when checking the Control Net.
        </brief>
        <description>
  	       When true, all ignored Control Points and all ignored Control
           Measures provided by the Control Net will be discarded during
           calculations.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="NOCONTROL">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>True</item></default>
        <brief>
          Check for Cubes in the FROMLIST which are not in the Control Net.
        </brief>
        <description>
  	       When true, a file named [PREFIX]NoMatch.txt will be created, which 
           will list all of the cubes, and their corresponding Serial Number 
           which do not exist within the provided Control Net.  If there are no 
           such cubes, then no file is created.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="NOCUBE">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>True</item></default>
        <brief>
          Checks for cubes in the Control Net that are not listed in the FROMLIST.
        </brief>
        <description>
            When true, a file named [PREFIX]NoCube.txt will be created, which 
            will list all of the Serial Numbers in the given Control Net which 
            do not have a corresponding Cube in the proveded List.  If there are 
            no such Serial Numbers, then no file is created.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="SINGLEMEASURE">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>True</item></default>
        <brief>
          Check for Control Points which contain a single Control Measure.
        </brief>
        <description>
          When true, a file named [PREFIX]SinglePointCubes.txt will be created, 
          which will list all of the Cubes which exist as a single Control 
          Measure in any Control Point within the provided Control Net.  If there 
          are no such single Control Measures, then no file is created.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="DUPLICATE">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>True</item></default>
        <brief>
          Check for Control Points which contain the same cube in more than one Control Measure.
        </brief>
        <description>
          When true, a file named [PREFIX]DuplicateMeasures.txt will be created, 
          which will list all of the cubes which exist in more than one Control 
          Measure in a single Control Point within the provided Control Net.  If 
          there are no such duplicate Control Measures, then no file is created.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="SINGLECUBE">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>True</item></default>
        <brief>
          Check for Cubes which have only a single Control Measure.
        </brief>
        <description>
          When true, a file named [PREFIX]SingleCubes.txt will be created, 
          which will list all of the Cubes which exist in only a single Control 
          Measure within the entire Control Net.  If there 
          are no such single Cubes, then no file is created.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="NOLATLON">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>True</item></default>
        <brief>
          Check for measures for which latitudes and longitudes cannot be 
          computed for. 
        </brief>
        <description>
          When true, a file named [PREFIX]NoLatLon.txt will be created, which
          will list all of the serial numbers which are within the given Control
          Net and listed in the input list which cannot compute a latitude and
          longitude.  These serial numbers will be followed by the Control Point
          IDs in which they could not compute their latitudes and longitudes.
          If there are no such serial numbers, then no file is created.

          Only cubes in both the FROMLIST and CNET are checked.
        </description>
      </parameter>
    </group>
  </groups>
</application>
