<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="noseam">
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">

  <brief>Create a mosaic with little to no seams using a list of map projected
      cubes</brief>

  <description>
    This program, noseam, creates a mosaic using an algorithm that minimizes seams.
    The user will enter a text-based list of cubes that must be 1) in the same map projection
    and 2) contain equivalent projection parameters such as PixelResolution, CenterLongitude, and 
    LatitudeSystem. More help is given in the Parameter Groups and with examples at the end of 
    this document. 

    To generate the mosaic, noseam uses the automos application. The FROMLIST and MATCHBANDBIN 
    parameters are taken from noseam and forwarded to automos as well as the remainder of the 
    parameters except with their default values. To learn more about <def link="automos">automos</def> parameters,
    see the automos application documentation.
  </description>

  <category>
    <categoryItem>Mosaicking</categoryItem>
  </category>

  <history>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2008-1-03">
      Original version
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2008-10-24">
      This program was using the input folder as a temporary folder, instead of looking
      up the user's preferences to find the correct temporary folder. This program will now
      use the correct temporary folder.
    </change>
    <change name="Kelvin Rodriguez" date="2016-6-29">
      Added a short description of how noseam utilizes automos in the documentation. 
    </change>
    <change name="Makayla Shepherd" date="2016-8-18">
      The noseam parameters HNS HNL LNS and LNL, which correspond to the size of the 
      boxcar for the highpass and lowpass filters, have been condensed down to two 
      parameters, SAMPLES and LINES as the size of the boxcars must be the same. Fixes #258.
    </change>
    <change name="Ken Edmundson" date="2024-8-25">
      Converted noseam to callable app. Also converted Makefile test to gtest format.
    </change>
  </history>

  <groups>

    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROMLIST">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          List of cubes to mosaic
        </brief>
        <description>
          A list of map projected cubes to mosaic seamlessly.  The Mapping
          groups must match in order to mosaic the cubes.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.txt *.lis *.lst
        </filter>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="TO">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Mosaic output cube
        </brief>
        <description>
          The resulting mosaic, which will be created from the listed cubes.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Filter Sizes">
      <parameter name="SAMPLES">
        <type>integer</type>
        <brief>
              Number of samples for the boxcar filters
        </brief>
        <description>
          This is the total number of samples in the boxcar dimension applied using the highpass 
          and lowpass filters. The number must be odd and cannot exceed twice the number of samples 
          in the input cubes. The smaller the boxcar dimension, the more confined the filtered 
          results are near the image seams, which will remain similar to the original mosaic.
          The larger the boxcar dimension, the greater the extent of the filter effects are beyond 
          the seams. 
        </description>
        <odd />
        <minimum inclusive="yes">1</minimum>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="LINES">
        <type>integer</type>
        <brief>
                Number of lines for the boxcar filters
        </brief>
        <description> 
          This is the total number of lines in the boxcar dimension applied using the highpass 
          and lowpass filters. The number must be odd and cannot exceed twice the number of lines 
          in the input cubes. The smaller the boxcar dimension, the more confined the filtered 
          results are near the image seams, which will remain similar to the original mosaic.
          The larger the boxcar dimension, the greater the extent of the filter effects are beyond 
          the seams. 
        </description>
        <odd />
        <minimum inclusive="yes">1</minimum>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="BandBin Option">
      <parameter name="MATCHBANDBIN">iString(match)
        <type>boolean</type>
        <brief>Enforce BandBin Group Match</brief>
        <description>
          This option causes the application to fail if the input bandbin group does not
          match the mosaic bandbin group.
        </description>
        <default><item>TRUE</item></default>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Intermediate Data">
      <parameter name="REMOVETEMP ">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>TRUE</item></default>
        <brief>Destroy intermediate data</brief>
        <description>
          Multiple cube images as well as lists are created during the
          production of the final seamless mosaic.  If this parameter is changed
          to false, those temporary cubes and lists will not be destroyed.
          
          <p>
          If REMOVETEMP=NO:
          <ul>
            <li>OriginalMosaic.cub - This file is the mosaic result (automos) of the input cubes listed 
              in FROMLIST. </li>
            <li>LowpassMosaic.cub  - This file is the low pass filter (samples x lines) applied to the 
              OriginalMosaic.cub. </li>
            <li>HighpassMosaic.cub - This file is the mosaic result (automos) of the high pass filtered 
              input cubes listed in FROMLIST. </li>
            <li>HighPassList.lis - This single column list contains the individual highpass filter image 
              results and filenames. </li>
            <li>_highpass.cub - Every image in the fromlist will have a high pass filter 
              (samples x lines) output result. This is the suffix filename appended the original input 
              filenames. </li>
            <li>LowpassMosaic.cub + HighpassMosaic.cub = TO (noseam output filename) </li>
          </ul>
        </p>

        </description>
      </parameter>
    </group>

  </groups>

  <examples>

    <example>
      <brief>No Seam Result</brief>
        <description>
           This example shows how noseam works upon a small mosaic and
           compares that result to an automos output.
        </description>

        <terminalInterface>
            <commandLine>FROMLIST=cubes.lis
              TO=final.cub SAMPLES=73 LINES=73</commandLine>
            <description>
                Runs noseam with a 73x73 highpass filter and a 73x73 lowpass 
                filter.
            </description>
        </terminalInterface>

        <dataFiles>
          <dataFile path="assets/cubes.lis">
            <brief>cubes.lis</brief>
            <description>
              This is a text-based file that lists all of the cubes to mosaic.
              This list as well as the cubes to be mosaicked must
              be within the current directory when noseam is executed.
            </description>
            <parameterName>FROMLIST</parameterName>
          </dataFile>
        </dataFiles>

        <inputImages>
            <image src="assets/images/cube1.jpg" width="204" height="550">
                <brief>First listed cube</brief>
                <description>
                    This is the first cube listed in cubes.lis.
                </description>
                <thumbnail caption="cube1.cub" src="assets/images/cube1.jpg" width="74" height="200"/>
            </image>
            <image src="assets/images/cube2.jpg" width="223" height="550">
                <brief>Second listed cube</brief>
                <description>
                    This is the second cube listed in cubes.lis.
                </description>
                <thumbnail caption="cube2.cub" src="assets/images/cube2.jpg" width="81" height="200"/>
            </image>
            <image src="assets/images/cube3.jpg" width="241" height="550">
                <brief>Third listed cube</brief>
                <description>
                    This is the third cube listed in cubes.lis.
                </description>
                <thumbnail caption="cube3.cub" src="assets/images/cube3.jpg" width="87" height="200"/>
            </image>
        </inputImages>

        <outputImages>
          <image src="assets/images/result.jpg" width="404" height="550">
                <brief>The resulting mosaic</brief>
                <description>
                    This is the resulting mosaic final.cub.
                </description>
                <thumbnail caption="final.cub" src="assets/images/result.jpg" width="147" height="200"/>
                <parameterName>TO</parameterName>
            </image>
            <image src="assets/images/original.jpg" width="404" height="550">
                <brief>Automos result (NOT AN OUTPUT OF NOSEAM)</brief>
                <description>
                    This is the same mosaic created using automos.  Notice
                    the difference between automos.cub and final.cub.  The
                    seams that existed between the original images in automos
                    are nearly invisible in final.cub.
                </description>
                <thumbnail caption="automos.cub" src="assets/images/original.jpg" width="147" height="200"/>
            </image>
        </outputImages>

    </example>

  </examples>

</application>
