<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Id: mdiscal.xml 6403 2015-10-23 19:32:20Z jwbacker@GS.DOI.NET $ -->

<application name="mdiscal" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">
  <brief>
    Calibrates  MESSENGER/MIDS EDR/RDR products
  </brief>

  <description>
    This program calibrates images from the Messenger mission's MDIS instrument.
    The input image is corrected for the following, in order, during 
    calibration: <br />
    <ul>
      <li><a href="#DarkCurrent">Step 1: Dark current correction</a ></li>
      <li><a href="#Linearity">Step 2: Linearity correction</a ></li>
      <li><a href="#Smear">Step 3: Readout smear correction</a ></li>
      <li><a href="#Uniformity">Step 4: Uniformity (flat field) correction</a ></li>
      <li><a href="#AbsoluteCoefficient">Step 5: Absolute coefficient correction</a ></li>
      <li><a href="#ConvertIOF">Step 6: Conversion to I over F</a ></li>
      <li><a href="#EmpiricalCorrection">Step 7: Empirical correction</a ></li>
    </ul>

    <p>
      <h1><a id="DarkCurrent">Step 1: Dark current correction:</a ></h1>
      <table border = "1">
        <tr>
          <th>Option</th>
          <th>Description</th>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <TD>None</TD>
          <TD>
            No dark current correction is performed.
          </TD>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <TD>Standard</TD>
          <TD>
            Messenger images have a strip of dark current data on the left-hand side. 
            This will take a median of the first three sample columns (for unbinned 
            data) and use it for the dark current on a line by line basis.
          </TD>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <TD>Linear</TD>
          <TD>
            This will fit a line across the first column of data, which is dark 
            current data, and use the line to determine the dark current correction.
          </TD>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <TD>Model</TD>
          <TD> 
            There are independent dark models, developed on-ground. This will use the 
            most recent of these models to correct the dark current.
          </TD>
        </tr>
      </table>
    </p>
    <p>
      There are times when the user selections for dark current correction will be rejected
      and altered by the program. In these cases a warning message will be printed to alert the
      user to the change. Below is an explanation of what happens in some special cases:
      <table border = "1">
        <tr>
          <th>DARKCURRENT parameter value</th>
          <th>Valid dark pixels exist**</th>
          <th>Exposure duration exceeds 1 second</th>
          <th>Outcome</th>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <th>STANDARD</th>
          <th>No</th>
          <th>No</th>
          <th>
            Dark current correction method is changed to MODEL. The program prints a warning message.
          </th>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <th>STANDARD</th>
          <th>No</th>
          <th>Yes</th>
          <th>
            Dark current correction is turned off, but the rest of the calibration is performed.
            The program prints a warning message.
          </th>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <th>STANDARD</th>
          <th>Yes</th>
          <th>Yes or No</th>
          <th>
            Dark current correction is performed with the original user input MODEL option.
            No warning message is needed.
          </th>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <th>LINEAR</th>
          <th>No</th>
          <th>No</th>
          <th>
            Dark current correction method is changed to MODEL. The program prints a warning message.
          </th>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <th>LINEAR</th>
          <th>No</th>
          <th>Yes</th>
          <th>
            Dark current correction is turned off, but the rest of the calibration is performed.
            The program prints a warning message.
          </th>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <th>LINEAR</th>
          <th>Yes</th>
          <th>Yes or No</th>
          <th>
            Dark current correction is performed with the original user input MODEL option.
            No warning message is needed.
          </th>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <th>MODEL</th>
          <th>Yes or No</th>
          <th>No</th>
          <th>
            Dark current correction is performed with the original user input MODEL option.
            No warning message is needed.
          </th>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <th>MODEL</th>
          <th>No</th>
          <th>Yes</th>
          <th>
            Dark current correction is turned off, but the rest of the calibration is performed.
            The program prints a warning message.
          </th>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <th>MODEL</th>
          <th>Yes</th>
          <th>Yes</th>
          <th>
            Dark current correction method is changed to STANDARD.
            The program prints a warning message.
          </th>
        </tr>
      </table>
      ** Note, there are two binning mode codes in the Instrument group of the input cube's labels,
      the FpuBinningMode and the PixelBinningMode. The number of valid dark pixels referred to in
      the table above is determined by using these values. If the sum of these two binning modes is
      greater than one, then there are no valid dark pixels.
    </p>
    <p>
      <h1><a id="Linearity">Step 2: Linearity correction:</a ></h1>
      Linearity measures the variability of a camera's DN level per unit 
      exposure time and radiance, as a function of variation in exposure time or 
      radiance. Using dark-corrected, desmeared DN values (DCDSI) taken from the 
      center quarter of the images, response linearity was measured with both the 
      NAC and WAC binned and not-binned.
    </p>
    <p>
      <h1><a id="Smear">Step 3: Smear correction:</a ></h1>
      Frame transfer smear corrections for MDIS follow the technique described for  
      NEAR MSI image by Murchie et al. (1999). In brief, an image is exposed for a  
      nominal integration time and is then transferred in 3.84 ms to a memory zone 
      on  the CCD, from which the analog signal is digitized line-by-line. 
      Accumulation  of signal continues during the finite duration of frame 
      transfer, inducing a  streak or frame-transfer smear in the wake of an 
      illuminated object in the  field of view, parallel to the direction of frame 
      transfer. Note that the frame transfer occurs in the calibration pixels as
      well as on the imaging pixels. mdiscal accounts for the frame transfer smear
      contributed from the 16 calibration lines (removed from the PDS-archived images).
    </p>
    <p>
      <h1><a id="Uniformity">Step 4: Uniformity (flat field) correction:</a ></h1>
      Response uniformity, or flat field, is a measure of pixel-to-pixel
      variations  in responsivity. Measurements of response uniformity of the WAC 
      and NAC were  conducted in the OCF, at room temperature and while cold, by 
      imaging the integrating sphere with the two 45W bulbs illuminating the 
      interior.
    </p>
    <p>
      <h1><a id="AbsoluteCoefficient">Step 5: Absolute coefficient correction:</a ></h1>
      This converts the DN values from responsivity to radiance values.
    </p>
    <p>
      <h1><a id="ConvertIOF">Step 6: Convert units to I over F:</a ></h1>
      This converts the DN values radiance values to I over F.
    </p>
    <p>
      <h1><a id="EmpiricalCorrection">Step 7: Empirical correction:</a ></h1>
      Performs an empirical correction on the DN values by scaling them using the 
      EmpiricalCorrectionFactor. Note this correction is only applied to WAC images.
    </p>
    <p>
      <h1>Output units</h1>
      The output units of the DNs will depend on which calibration flags are turned on.
      <ul>
        <li>If IOF=TRUE, output units are measured in I/F</li>
        <li>Otherwise if RADIOMETRIC=TRUE, output units are measured in W/(m**2 micrometer sr)</li>
        <li>If RADIOMETRIC=FALSE, output units are DNs</li>
      </ul>
    </p>
    <p>
      <h1>General calibration limitations</h1>
      This program will throw an error and exit in the following circumstances:
      <ul>
        <li>The input cube is multiband.</li>
        <li>The input cube has less than 2 samples per line.</li>
        <li>The input cube is not unlutted.</li>
        <li>PixelBinningMode > 0 and unable to reduce.</li>
      </ul>
    </p>
    <p>
      <h1>MESSENGER MDIS calibration document excerpt</h1>
      The following is an excerpt from the MESSENGER MDIS calibration document 
      on this process
    </p>
    <pre>
        USAGE
        =====

        Raw units are of DN converted to the physical units
        of radiance or I/F, following the calibration equation:

        L(x,y,f,T,t,b) = Lin[DN(x,y,f,T,t,b,MET) - Dk(x,y,T,t,b,MET) - 
        Sm(x,y,t,b)] / {Flat(x,y,f,b) * t * [Resp(f,b,T)/Correct(f,MET)]}

        where:

        L(x,y,f,T,t,b) is radiance in units of W / (m**-2 microns**-1 sr**-1),
        measured by the pixel in column x, row y, through filter f, at CCD
        temperature T and exposure time t, for binning mode b,

        DN(x,y,f,T,t,b,MET) is the raw DN measured by the pixel in column x, row
        y, through filter f, at CCD temperature T and exposure time t, for binning
        mode b, and Mission Elapsed Time (MET),

        Dk(x,y,T,t,b,MET) is the dark level in a given pixel, derived from
        a model based on exposure time and CCD temperature,

        Sm(x,y,t,b) is the scene-dependent frame transfer smear for the pixel,

        Lin is a function that corrects small nonlinearity of detector response,

        Flat(x,y,f,b) is the non-uniformity or 'flat-field' correction,

        Resp(f,b,T) is the responsivity, relating dark-, flat-, and
        smear-corrected DN per unit exposure time to radiance,

        Correct(f,MET) is a time-variable correction to responsivity
        describing a sudden decrease in transmission of the WAC optics
        on 24 May 2011 and subsequent recovery to normal values, 
        interpreted as due to contamination associated with MESSENGER's
        first periapse season over Mercury's hot pole and the subsequent
        bake-off of the contaminant, 

        and

        t is the exposure time.

        The above equation assumes that data are in the native 12-bit format in
        which they were read off the CCD, and that onboard application of 12-to-8
        bit lookup tables (LUTs) has been inverted.

        This correction is done step-wise using the calibration tables and
        images in this directory as follows.


        (1) Inversion of 12 to 8 bit Compression
        ========================================

        8-to-12 bit inversion of DN values is required when the value of
        MESS:COMP12_8 is 1 (when the data are 8-bit). There are 8 inverse lookup
        tables (LUTs). The table to use is indicated by the value of MESS:COMP_ALG
        from 0 through 7. An 8-bit value (in a row of the table) is inverted by
        replacing it with the 12-bit value in the column corresponding to a
        particular LUT.

        The inversion tables are given in the product MDISLUTINV_0.


        (2) Subtraction of modeled dark level
        =====================================

        Two methods are used for subtraction of the dark level, one for 
        exposure times greater than 1 sec and one for exposure times less than 1 sec.

        In the method for exposure times less than 1 sec, the DN values are valid
        columns in the masked 'dark strip' at the edge of the CCD are fitted
        linearly as a function of line in the image. Then the fits are subtracted
        from the pixels in each line of the CCD.

        In the method for exposure times greater than 1 sec, a model is used which accounts
        for variations in column (sample) in the image, which the previous 
        method cannot do. However if the model were applied to longer exposures,
        it would yield larger residuals than the previous method.

        There are four separate models of dark level (dark current plus
        electronics bias), for the MDIS-WAC and MDIS-NAC (as indicated by the
        keyword INSTRUMENT_ID), and for each camera, without pixel binning turned
        on (MESS:FPU_BIN = 0) or with pixel binning turned on (MESS:FPU_BIN = 1).
        The models estimates the dark level Dk(x,y,t,T) as a function of column
        position x, row position y, exposure time t in milliseconds (as indicated 
        by the keyword MESS:EXPOSURE or EXPOSURE_DURATION), and CCD temperature T 
        (as indicated by the keyword MESS:CCD_TEMP):

        Dk(x,y,t,T) = C(T) + D(T) + [E(T) + F(T) * t] * y + {O(T) + P(T) * t +
         [Q(T) + S(T) * t] * y} * x

        Variables C(T), D(T), E(T), F(T), O(T), P(T), Q(T), and S(T) are all
        third-order functions of CCD temperature, for example:

        C(T) = H0 + H1 * T + H2 * T**2 + H3 * T**3

        In all cases x or y is in the range 0-1023 for a not-binned image (as
        indicated by the keyword MESS:FPU_BIN = 0) or 0-511 for a binned image (as
        indicated by the keyword MESS:FPU_BIN = 1). t is in units of milliseconds,
        and T is in UNCALIBRATED raw counts of CCD temperature.

        For each pixel in column x and row y of an image, application of the
        correction is:

        DN_dark(x,y,t,T) = DN(x,y,t,T) - Dk(x,y,t,T)

        where

        DN(x,y,t,T) is DN in 12-bit format,

        Dk(x,y,t,T) is the predicted DN level from the dark modeldark model, and

        DN_dark(x,y,t,T) is dark-corrected DN.

        The eight sets of coefficients for the WAC not-binned, WAC binned, NAC
        not-binned, and NAC binned dark models are given in the products
        MDISWAC_NOTBIN_DARKMODEL_0, MDISWAC_BINNED_DARKMODEL_0,
        MDISNAC_NOTBIN_DARKMODEL_0, and MDISNAC_BINNED_DARKMODEL_0 respectively.

        (3) Frame Transfer Smear Correction
        ===================================

        Accumulation of signal continues during the finite duration
        of frame transfer induces a streak or frame-transfer smear in the wake
        of an illuminated object in the field of view, parallel to the direction
        of frame transfer. This smear is approximated as:

        Sm(x,y,t,b,f) = SUMM(1,y-1) { t2/t * [DN_dark(x,y,t,b) -
        Sm(x,y,t,b,f)] / Flat(x,y,b,f)}

        where

        Sm(x,y,t,b,f) is the smear in column x and row y at exposure time t
        in binning mode b and filter f,

        Dk_dark (x,y,t,b) is dark-corrected DN in column x and row y at
        exposure time t and temperature T in binning mode b,

        Flat(x,y,b,f) is the flat-field correction in column x and row y in
        binning mode b and filter f,

        t is exposure time in milliseconds, and

        t2 is the time for frame transfer (about 3.4 ms) divided by the number of
        lines in the image in the direction of frame transfer, 1024 for
        full-frame images (when MESS:FPU_BIN = 0) or 512 for binned images (when
        MESS:FPU_BIN = 1).

        For each pixel in column x and row y of an image, application of the
        correction is :

        DN_dark_smear(x,y,t,b,f) = DN_dark(x,y,t,b,f) - Sm(x,y,t,b,f)

        where

        DN_dark_smear(x,y,t,b,f) is dark- and smear- corrected DN,

        DN_dark(x,y,t,b,f) is dark-corrected DN, and

        Sm(x,y,t,b,f) is the smear calculated as shown above.


        (4) Correction for CCD non-linearity
        ====================================

        To remove effects of nonlinearity in WAC image data, the following
        corrections should be applied after correction of dark current, bias,
        and smear.

        For DN_dark_smear > 1
        DN_lin = DN_dark_smear/[0.008760 * Ln(DN_dark_smear) + 0.936321]

        For DN_dark_smear less than or equal to 1
        DN_lin = DN_dark_smear/0.936321

        To remove effects of nonlinearity in NAC image data, the following
        procedure should be applied after correction of dark current, bias,
        and smear.

        For DN_dark_smear > 1
        DN_lin = DN_dark_smear/[0.011844 * Ln(DN_dark_smear) + 0.912031]

        For DN_dark_smear less than or equal to 1
        DN_lin = DN_dark_smear/0.912031

        where

        DN_dark_smear is the input dark- and smear-corrected DN, and

        DN_lin is linearized dark- and smear-corrected DN.


        (5) Flat-field correction
        =========================

        The flat field correction removes pixel to pixel differences in detector
        responsivity, so that the responsivity coefficients can be expressed as
        scalars for each filter. There is a separate flat-field image for MDIS-WAC
        and MDIS-NAC (as indicated by the keyword INSTRUMENT_ID), without pixel
        binning turned on (MESS:FPU_BIN = 0) or with pixel binning turned on
        (MESS:FPU_BIN = 1), for each separate filter (as indicated by the keyword
        FILTER_NUMBER). All of the files are in the 'FLAT' directory.

        For each pixel in column x and row y of an image, application of the
        correction is

        DN_flat(x,y,f,b) = DN_lin(x,y,f,b) / Flat(x,y,f,b)

        where

        DN_flat(x,y,f,b) is flat-fielded, linearized, dark- and smear-corrected
        DN,

        DN_lin(x,y,f,b) is linearized dark- and smear-corrected DN, and

        Flat(x,y,f,b) is the value in the appropriate flat-field image.


        (6) Conversion from DNs to radiance
        ===================================

        The value that relates corrected DN's measured per unit time to radiance
        is the responsivity. Responsivity is modeled as a function of which camera
        is being used (MDIS-WAC or MDIS-NAC as indicated by the keyword
        INSTRUMENT_ID), its binning state (as indicated by the keyword
        MESS:FPU_BIN), and in the case of the WAC the filter number (as indicated
        by the keyword FILTER_NUMBER). The coefficients used to calculate the
        responsivity are in the 'RESPONSIVITY' directory. For a camera, binning
        state, and filter, the responsivity is calculated from uncalibrated CCD
        temperature (as indicated by the keyword MESS:CCD_TEMP) as follows:

        Resp(f,T,b) = R(f,t=-30.3C,b) * [correction_offset(f,b) + T(CCD) * 
        correction_coef1(f,b) + T(CCD)^2 * correction_coef2(f,b)]

        where 

        Resp(f,T,b) is responsivity in filter f at CCD temperature T in binning 
        state b, 

        T(CCD) is raw CCD temperature in units of DNs, 

        R(f,t=-30.3C,b) is responsivity in filter f in binning state b at CCD 
        temperature of 1060 DN (-30.3C), 

        correction_offset(f,b) is camera- and filter-dependent temperature 
        correction offset for filter f and binning state b, 

        correction_coef1(f,b) is the camera- and filter-dependent temperature 
        correction first-order coefficient for filter f and binning state b.

        correction_coef2(f,b) is the camera- and filter-dependent temperature 
        correction second-order coefficient for filter f and binning state b.

        To apply responsivity to obtain radiance L, the expression is

        L(f) = DN_flat(f) / (t * Resp(f,T,b) * Correct(f, MET))

        where

        L is radiance in units of W / (m**2 microns**1 sr**1),

        DN_flat is dark-, smear-, linearity-, and flat field-corrected DN,

        t is the exposure time in seconds, 

        Resp(f,T,b) is the responsivity in filter f at CCD temperature T and
        binning state b, and 

        Correct(f, MET) is the temporal correction to responsivity for 
        filter f at time MET.


        (7) Conversion from radiance to I/F
        ===================================

        To convert from radiance to I/F (also known as radiance factor, the ratio
        of measured radiance to that which would be measured from a white
        perfectly Lambertian surface), the following expression should be applied:

        I_over_F(f) = L(f) * pi * (SOLAR_DISTANCE/149597870.691)**2 / F(f)

        where

        L(f) is calibrated radiance calculated as described above for some filter
        f,

        SOLAR_DISTANCE is that value for distance of the target object from the
        center of the sun in kilometers (as indicated by the keyword
        SOLAR_DISTANCE)

        149597870.691 is the number of kilometers in 1 AU

        F(f) is effective average solar irradiance sampled under the filter
        bandpass.

        The effective average solar radiance for each camera and bandpass is given
        in the SOLAR directory.
    </pre>
    <p>
    If run on a non-spiceinited cube, this program requires access to local mission-specific 
    SPICE kernels, in order to find the distance between the sun and the target body. 
    When run on a spiceinited cube, this can be determined using the camera model.
    Using a spiceinited cube as input has the advantage of not requiring that local 
    mission-specific kernels be available. (See spiceinit web=true.)
    </p>
  </description>

  <category>
    <missionItem>Messenger</missionItem>
  </category>

  <seeAlso>
    <applications>
      <item>mdis2isis</item>
    </applications>
  </seeAlso>

  <history>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2007-11-27">
      Original version
    </change>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2007-12-20">
      Added computation of I/F reflectance for valid NAIF target bodies.
    </change>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2008-01-19">
      Corrected a bug that prevented the I/F correction from ever being 
      applied.  The exposure time must be expressed throughout as seconds and 
      not milliseconds (engineering units) with the exception being the dark 
      current model, which requires them to be in engineering units.  There 
      were incorrect values for the nominal filter wheel encoder values in the 
      file $messenger/calibration/mdisCalibration.trn that incorrectly 
      identified the filter.  This has been corrected, but it was also 
      determined that the validation of the proper filter wheel should take 
      place in mdis2isis.  Added loading of external file values as comma 
      separated values (CSV) files.  This includes the absolute response and 
      solar irradiance constants. 
    </change>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2008-02-29">
      Added filter dependant smear component support.  These values are 
      externally maintained in calibration/responsivity directory.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2008-05-13">
      Removed references to CubeInfo 
    </change>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2008-07-11">
      The dark current model does not support exposure times greater than 2 
      seconds. In these cases, apply the STANDARD dark current processing and 
      report this to the user as an error but complete processing.    Users can 
      always select a different model.
    </change>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2008-09-03"> 
      Corrected determination of dark column count; corrected computation of 
      dark current correction based upon valid/good columns;  added computation 
      of dark strip mean after calibration as a sanity check on the process;  
      updated ProductID and SourceProductId in the Archive group; Corrected 
      units of resulting calibration;  made filter characteristics of name, 
      wavelength and width compliant with CDR SIS specifications;  added program 
      name and versions to RadiometricCalibration group; reworked how the dark 
      model and flatfield are applied to support pixel binning.
    </change>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2008-09-09"> 
      Added additional tests for extreme observing conditions that do not allow 
      the image to be calibrated.
    </change>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2008-09-18"> 
      Very minor change of watts unit expressed as W instead of w.
    </change>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2008-11-19"> 
      Changed the exposure threshold for the dark current model from 2 seconds 
      to 1 second and it now uses the LINEAR model instead of the STANDARD 
      model in this case;  Implemented new quadratic responsivity equation for
      both WAC and NAC instruments that adds an additional term to the 
      responsivity files; updated documentation.
    </change>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2008-11-25"> 
      Corrected inclusion of dark current model file to SourceProductId when 
      applicable; bumped the version number to 3.
    </change>
    <change name="Mackenzie Boyd" date="2009-09-03">
      Added parameter to the usage of reduce to accommodate changes to reduce.
    </change> 
    <change name="Mackenzie Boyd" date="2011-02-04">
      Fixed reduce parameters to use MODE instead of REDUCTION_TYPE. Fixed typo in docs.
    </change> 
    <change name="Mackenzie Boyd" date="2011-02-09">
      Removed a cout, fixed calibration for images with nonzero pixel binning. 
    </change> 
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2011-04-20">
      Added FLATFIELD and RADIOMETRIC parameters so that users can create 
      several different products.  When asking for dark columns to not be kept 
      (KEEPDARK=FALSE), extra columns may be nulled as additional binning 
      and  compression introduces artifacts in adjacent columns; added new 
      keyword (LeftSamplesNulled) to the RadiometricCalibration group 
      indicating the number of NULLed columns.  These changes result in 
      version number 4 of the output calibration file.
    </change> 
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2011-04-29">
      Removed the From keyword from the RadiometricCalibration group created 
      by this application.  Added ValidDarkColumns to this group.  This 
      value indicates the number of samples used to compute the  
      DarkStripMean.
    </change>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2011-04-29">
      Set the version back to 3 as it was deemed not neccessary to change the 
      version after discussion with the MESSENGER team.
    </change>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2012-10-23">
      Several select calibration files were updated.  New flat fields are  
      MDISWAC_BINNED_FLAT_FIL03_5.cub, MDISWAC_NOTBIN_FLAT_FIL03_5.cub, 
      MDISWAC_BINNED_FLAT_FIL06_5.cub and  MDISWAC_NOTBIN_FLAT_FIL06_5.cub.  
      Also updated was the frame transfer file MDISWAC_FRAME_TRANSFER_02.TAB.  
      Added specific corrections for WAC images for a contamination event 
      starting on May 24, 2011 through January 3, 2012  As a result, added new 
      keywords to the RadiometricCalibration group to log this new correction. 
      These keywords are: ContaminationEventFile, ContaminationEventDate and 
      ContaminationEventFactor.  Also corrected computation of dark strip 
      average to properly report 0 when all these pixels are NULL pixels.  
      Software version number is now 1.4.
    </change>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2012-10-24">
      Incremented the CDR version number from 3 to 4 per the request by the
      MESSENGER team.
    </change>
    <change name="Moses Milazzo" date="2014-11-14">
      Updated the smear correction to account for the 16 lines of calibration data
      that are not on the PDS images but still contribute to frame transfer smearing.
      Also updated the calibration tables (MDISWAC_FRAME_TRANSFER_??.TAB) with the 
      correct frame transfer speed. Documentation was updated as well.
      Software version number is now 1.5.
    </change>
    <change name="Jeannie Backer" date="2015-08-31">
      Added ECFACTOR option so that the user can decide whether to apply the empirical correction 
      factor. Changed label keywords in Radiometric Calibration group from ContaminationEvent to 
      EmpiricalCorrection. Increased software version number to 1.6. Increased CDR version to 5. 
      Made code more compliant with ISIS coding standards. Fixes #2332
    </change>
    <change name="Jeannie Backer" date="2015-09-15">
      Modified code so that linearity, responsivity (absolute coefficient), and smear corrections 
      are always performed. Previously these were only applied if the flat field correction
      was applied.  This will change the output DNs for any images where FLATFIELD=false. 
      Updated documentation. Fixes #2338
    </change>
    <change name="Kristin Berry" date="2021-02-26">
      Updated to use camera for the target-sun distance and clock time to ET conversion, if possible.
      This enables the program to be run without local spice kernels (the spice server can be used for spiceinit.)
    </change>
  </history>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input cube
        </brief>
        <description>
          This is the ISIS cube from the Messenger mission to be calibrated.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="TO">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Output cube
        </brief>
        <description>
          This is the output file. The output cube will be a radiometrically calibrated version 
          of the input cube.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>
    </group>
    
    <group name="Options">
      <parameter name="DARKCURRENT">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>Dark current calibration method</brief>
        <description></description>
        <default><item>MODEL</item></default>
        <list>
          <option value="NONE">
            <brief>No correction</brief>
            <description>
              No dark current correction will be applied
            </description>
          </option>
          <option value="STANDARD">
            <brief>Do a median dark current correction</brief>
            <description>
              This will use the median of the three leftmost pixels as the dark current, on a
              line by line basis. 
            </description>
          </option>
          <option value="LINEAR">
            <brief>Use a linear fit</brief>
            <description>
              This will fit a line to the leftmost pixel values, which should be dark current data,
              through the lines. The equation derived from these pixels will be used to calculate
              the dark current correction, on a line by line basis.
            </description>
          </option>
          <option value="MODEL">
            <brief>Use pre-developed model</brief>
            <description>
              Messenger has independent dark models, developed on-ground. This will use the most
              recent of these models to correct the dark current. Note: this method cannot be used
              if the exposure duration of the image exceeds one second.
            </description>
          </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="KEEPDARK">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>false</item></default>
        <brief>Do not set dark current data to null</brief>
        <description>
          <p>
            If this is selected, the dark current data are set to null in the output image. 
          </p>
          <p>
            Binning affects the number of columns that are determined to be set to null.
            Thus, KEEPDARK is overloaded in terms of any columns that contain artifacts that are
            generated by binning (or wavelet compression). These columns are set to null as well.
          </p>
          <p>
            If no binning is applied, then four columns are set to null.  If 
            any combination of DPU or MP (essentially on-board processing) 
            binning is applied, three columns will be set to null.  When DPU 
            and MP 2x2 binning occurs (essentially a 4x4 summing) three 
            columns will be set to null.  All other combinations of binning will 
            have one column set to the null pixel value.
          </p>
          <p>
            If KEEPDARK = TRUE, then no columns are set to null on output.
          </p>
        </description>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="FLATFIELD">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>True</item></default>
        <brief>
          Apply flat field correction
        </brief>
        <description>
          This parameter allows the user to selectively apply 
          the flatfield correction.  This parameter can be used in conjunction 
          with DARKCURRENT and RADIOMETRIC to produce additional output 
          products such as DNs (all parameters DARKCURRENT=MODEL and  
          RADIOMETRIC=FALSE).
        </description>        
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="RADIOMETRIC">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>True</item></default>
        <brief>
          Apply radiometric correction
        </brief>
        <description>
          This parameter allows the user to selectively apply the radiometric
          correction.  This parameter can be used in conjunction with DARKCURRENT and FLATFIELD
          to produce additional output products such as DNs (all parameters DARKCURRENT=MODEL and
          FLATFIELD=FALSE). However, if RADIOMETRIC=FALSE, then  the program will turn IOF=FALSE.
        </description>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="IOF">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>True</item></default>
        <brief>
          Convert to I/F units
        </brief>
        <description>
          <p>
            This option, when set, will convert the output to I/F from radiance values. To convert
            from radiance to I/F (also known as radiance factor, the ratio of measured radiance to
            that which would be measured from a white perfectly Lambertian surface), the following
            expression is applied: 
            <pre>
I_over_F(f) = L(f) * PI * (SOLAR_DISTANCE/149597870.691)**2 / F(f)                
            </pre> 
            where L(f) is calibrated radiance calculated for some filter f,
            SOLAR_DISTANCE is that value for distance of the target object from
            the center of the sun in kilometers (as indicated by the keyword
            SOLAR_DISTANCE), 149597870.691 is the number of kilometers in 1 AU
            and F(f) is effective average solar irradiance sampled under the
            filter bandpass.
          </p>
          <p>
            If the observed target is not of a valid body as recognized by 
            NAIF, the output is left in radiance.
          </p>
        </description>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="ECFACTOR">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>True</item></default>
        <brief>
          Apply empirical correction factor
        </brief>
        <description>
          This parameter is provided to allow the user to selectively apply the empirical
          correction.
        </description>
      </parameter>
    </group>
  </groups>

  <examples>
    <example>
      <brief>
        Calibrating an MDIS image
      </brief>
      <description>
        This example shows the calibration process of a MDIS image
      </description>
      <terminalInterface>
        <commandLine>FROM=EW0089565626A.cub 
          TO=EW0089565626A.calib.cub DARKCURRENT=MODEL</commandLine>
        <description>Calibration process of a MDIS image, using the MODEL dark 
          current option
        </description>
      </terminalInterface>
      <guiInterfaces>
        <guiInterface>
          <image src="assets/images/mdiscal.jpg" width="608" height="550">
            <brief>Calibrate an MDIS image</brief>
            <description>
              This is the GUI for mdiscal when converting the uncalibrated cube 
              EW0089565626A.cub to the calibrated cube EW0089565626A.calib.cub.
            </description>
            <thumbnail caption="Calibrating EW0089565626A.cub" src="assets/thumbs/mdiscal.jpg" width="200" height="181" />
          </image>
        </guiInterface>
      </guiInterfaces>
      <inputImages>
        <image height="512" width="512" src="assets/images/EW0089565626A.jpg">
          <brief>Input Cube</brief>
          <description>
            This is EW0089565626A.jpg before calibration.
          </description>
          <thumbnail src="assets/thumbs/EW0089565626A.jpg" width="200" height="200" caption="Input Image" />
        </image>
      </inputImages>
      <outputImages>
        <image width="550" height="550" src="assets/images/EW0089565626A.model.jpg">
          <brief>Output With Dark Model</brief>
          <description>
            This is the output generated by the default options.
          </description>
          <thumbnail src="assets/thumbs/EW0089565626A.model.jpg" width="200" height="200" caption="Output Image With Dark Model" />
        </image>
      </outputImages>
    </example>
  </examples>
</application>
