<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Id: mdiscal.xml,v 1.15 2009/09/04 17:59:06 mboyd Exp $ -->

<application name="mdiscal" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">
  <brief>
    Calibrates  MESSENGER/MIDS EDR/RDR products
  </brief>

  <description>
    Messenger images are corrected for the following, in order, during 
    calibration: <br />
    <ul>
      <li>
        Dark Current
      </li>
      <li>
        Linearity
      </li>
      <li>
        Smear
      </li>
      <li>
        Uniformity (flat field)
      </li>
      <li>
        Absolute coefficient
      </li>
    </ul>
    <br />
    Dark current correction:
    <ul>
      <li>
        None
      </li>
      No dark current correction is performed.
      <li>
        Standard
      </li>
      Messenger images have a strip of dark current data on the left-hand side. 
      This will take a median of the first three sample colums (for unbinned 
      data) and use that for the dark current on a line by line basis.
      <li>
        Linear
      </li>
      This will fit a line across the first column of data, which is dark 
      current data, and use the line to determine the dark current correction.
      <li>
        Model
      </li> 
      There are independent dark models, developed on-ground. This will use the 
      most recent of these models to correct the dark current.
    </ul>
    Linearity Correction: <br />
    Linearity is the measure of how variable is each camera's DN level per unit 
    exposure time and radiance, as a function of variation in exposure time or 
    radiance. Using dark-corrected, desmeared DN values (DCDSI) taken from the 
    center quarter of the images, response linearity was measured with both the 
    NAC and WAC binned and not-binned. <br /><br />

    Smear Correction: <br />
    Frame transfer smear corrections for MDIS follow the technique described for  
    NEAR MSI image by Murchie et al. (1999). In brief, an image is exposed for a  
    nominal integration time and is then transferred in 3.84 ms to a memory zone 
    on  the CCD, from which the analog signal is digitized line-by-line. 
    Accumulation  of signal continues during the finite duration of frame 
    transfer, inducing a  streak or frame-transfer smear in the wake of an 
    illuminated object in the  field of view, parallel to the direction of frame 
    transfer.<br /><br />
    Uniformity Correction:<br />
    Response uniformity, or flat field, is a measure of pixel-to-pixel
    variations  in responsivity. Measurements of response uniformity of the WAC 
    and NAC were  conducted in the OCF, at room temperature and while cold, by 
    imaging the integrating sphere with the two 45W bulbs illuminating the 
    interior. <br /><br />
    Absolute Coefficient Correction:<br />
    This converts the DN values from responsivity to radiance values.
      <p>
          The MODEL dark current option cannot be used if the exposure time 
          exceeds 1 second.  In this case, the LINEAR model is selected and a 
          message is issued to the user.
      </p>
    <p>
      Note that there are some extreme cases where an image could not be 
      radiometrically calibrated.  When there is more than two factors of 
      binning, FPU or PIXEL, then there are no valid dark pixel colums.  For 
      this case, calibrations using STANDARD or LINEAR cannot be used, however, 
      the MODEL can.  But, the MODEL cannot be used if the exposure time is 
      exceeds 1 seconds.  And in this case, the image cannot be calibrated.  
      When these conditions are detected, a message is issued, but calibration 
      continues using either the MODEL or NONE as the calibration mode.
    </p>
    <p>
      The following is an excerpt from the MESSENGER MDIS calibration document 
      on this process
    </p>
    <PRE>
Raw units are of DN converted to the physical units
of radiance or I/F, following the calibration equation:

L(x,y,f,T,t,b) = Lin[DN(x,y,f,T,t,b,MET) - Dk(x,y,T,t,b,MET) -
Sm(x,y,t,b)] / [Flat(x,y,f,b) * t * Resp(f,b,T)]

where:

L(x,y,f,T,t,b) is radiance in units of W / (m**-2 microns**-1 sr**-1),
measured by the pixel in column x, row y, through filter f, at CCD
temperature T and exposure time t, for binning mode b,

DN(x,y,f,T,t,b,MET) is the raw DN measured by the pixel in column x, row
y, through filter f, at CCD temperature T and exposure time t, for binning
mode b, and Mission Elapsed Time (MET),

Dk(x,y,T,t,b,MET) is the dark level in a given pixel, derived from
a model based on exposure time and CCD temperature,

Sm(x,y,t,b) is the scene-dependent frame transfer smear for the pixel,

Lin is a function that corrects small nonlinearity of detector response,

Flat(x,y,f,b) is the non-uniformity or 'flat-field' correction,

Resp(f,b,T) is the responsivity, relating dark-, flat-, and
smear-corrected DN per unit exposure time to radiance,

and

t is the exposure time in milliseconds.

The above equation assumes that data are in the native 12-bit format in
which they were read off the CCD, and that onboard application of 12-to-8
bit lookup tables (LUTs) has been inverted.

This correction is done step-wise using the calibration tables and
images in this directory as follows:

(1) Inversion of 12 to 8 bit Compression
========================================

8-to-12 bit inversion of DN values is required when the value of
MESS:COMP12_8 is 1 (when the data are 8-bit). There are 8 inverse lookup
tables (LUTs). The table to use is indicated by the value of MESS:COMP_ALG
from 0 through 7. An 8-bit value (in a row of the table) is inverted by
replacing it with the 12-bit value in the column corresponding to a
particular LUT.

The inversion tables are given in the product MDISLUTINV_0.


(2) Subtraction of modeled dark level
=====================================

There are four separate models of dark level (dark current plus
electronics bias), for the MDIS-WAC and MDIS-NAC (as indicated by the
keyword INSTRUMENT_ID), and for each camera, without pixel binning turned
on (MESS:FPU_BIN = 0) or with pixel binning turned on (MESS:FPU_BIN = 1).
The models estimates the dark level Dk(x,y,t,T) as a function of column
position x, row position y, exposure time t (as indicated by the keyword
MESS:EXPOSURE or EXPOSURE_DURATION), and CCD temperature T (as indicated
by the keyword MESS:CCD_TEMP):

Dk(x,y,t,T) = C(T) + D(T) + [E(T) + F(T) * t] * y + {O(T) + P(T) * t +
 [Q(T) + S(T) * t] * y} * x

Variables C(T), D(T), E(T), F(T), O(T), P(T), Q(T), and S(T) are all
third-order functions of CCD temperature, for example:

C(T) = H0 + H1 * T + H2 * T**2 + H3 * T**3

In all cases x or y is in the range 0-1023 for a not-binned image (as
indicated by the keyword MESS:FPU_BIN = 0) or 0-511 for a binned image (as
indicated by the keyword MESS:FPU_BIN = 1). t is in units of milliseconds,
and T is in UNCALIBRATED raw counts of CCD temperature.

For each pixel in column x and row y of an image, application of the
correction is:

DN_dark(x,y,t,T) = DN(x,y,t,T) - Dk(x,y,t,T)

where

DN(x,y,t,T) is DN in 12-bit format,

Dk(x,y,t,T) is the predicted DN level from the dark modeldark model, and

DN_dark(x,y,t,T) is dark-corrected DN.

The eight sets of coefficients for the WAC not-binned, WAC binned, NAC
not-binned, and NAC binned dark models are given in the products
MDISWAC_NOTBIN_DARKMODEL_0, MDISWAC_BINNED_DARKMODEL_0,
MDISNAC_NOTBIN_DARKMODEL_0, and MDISNAC_BINNED_DARKMODEL_0 respectively.


(3) Frame Transfer Smear Correction
===================================

Accumulation of signal continues during the finite duration
of frame transfer induces a streak or frame-transfer smear in the wake
of an illuminated object in the field of view, parallel to the direction
of frame transfer. This smear is approximated as:

Sm(x,y,t,b,f) = SUMM(1,y-1) { t2/t * [DN_dark(x,y,t,b) -
Sm(x,y,t,b,f)] / Flat(x,y,b,f)}

where

Sm(x,y,t,b,f) is the smear in column x and row y at exposure time t
in binning mode b and filter f,

Dk_dark (x,y,t,b) is dark-corrected DN in column x and row y at
exposure time t and temperature T in binning mode b,

Flat(x,y,b,f) is the flat-field correction in column x and row y in
binning mode b and filter f,

t is exposure time in ms, and

t2 is the time for frame transfer (about 3.4 ms) divided by the number of
lines in the image in the direction of frame transfer, 1024 for
full-frame images (when MESS:FPU_BIN = 0) or 512 for binned images (when
MESS:FPU_BIN = 1).

For each pixel in column x and row y of an image, application of the
correction is :

DN_dark_smear(x,y,t,b,f) = DN_dark(x,y,t,b,f) - Sm(x,y,t,b,f)

where

DN_dark_smear(x,y,t,b,f) is dark- and smear- corrected DN,

DN_dark(x,y,t,b,f) is dark-corrected DN, and

Sm(x,y,t,b,f) is the smear calculated as shown above.


(4) Correction for CCD non-linearity
====================================

To remove effects of nonlinearity in WAC image data, the following
corrections should be applied after correction of dark current, bias,
and smear.

For DN_dark_smear &gt; 1 
 DN_lin = DN_dark_smear/[0.008760 * Ln(DN_dark_smear) + 0.936321]

For DN_dark_smear &lt;= 1 
 DN_lin = DN_dark_smear/0.936321

To remove effects of nonlinearity in NAC image data, the following
procedure should be applied after correction of dark current, bias,
and smear.

For DN_dark_smear &gt; 1 
 DN_lin = DN_dark_smear/[0.011844 * Ln(DN_dark_smear) +
0.912031]

For DN_dark_smear &lt;= 1
 DN_lin = DN_dark_smear/0.912031

where

DN_dark_smear is the input dark- and smear-corrected DN, and

DN_lin is linearized dark- and smear-corrected DN.


(5) Flat-field correction
=========================

The flat field correction removes pixel to pixel differences in detector
responsivity, so that the responsivity coefficients can be expressed as
scalars for each filter. There is a separate flat-field image for MDIS-WAC
and MDIS-NAC (as indicated by the keyword INSTRUMENT_ID), without pixel
binning turned on (MESS:FPU_BIN = 0) or with pixel binning turned on
(MESS:FPU_BIN = 1), for each separate filter (as indicated by the keyword
FILTER_NUMBER). All of the files are in the 'FLAT' directory.

For each pixel in column x and row y of an image, application of the
correction is

DN_flat(x,y,f,b) = DN_lin(x,y,f,b) / Flat(x,y,f,b)

where

DN_flat(x,y,f,b) is flat-fielded, linearized, dark- and smear-corrected
DN,

DN_lin(x,y,f,b) is linearized dark- and smear-corrected DN, and

Flat(x,y,f,b) is the value in the appropriate flat-field image.


(6) Conversion from DNs to radiance 
 ===================================
The value that relates corrected DN's measured per unit time to radianceis the
responsivity. Responsivity is modeled as a function of which camera is being
used (MDIS-WAC or MDIS-NAC as indicated by the keyword INSTRUMENT_ID), its
binning state (as indicated by the keyword MESS:FPU_BIN), and in the case of the
WAC the filter number (as indicated by the keyword FILTER_NUMBER). The
coefficients used to calculate the responsivity are in the 'RESPONSIVITY'
directory. For a camera, binning state, and filter, the responsivity is
calculated from uncalibrated CCD temperature (as indicated by the keyword
MESS:CCD_TEMP) as follows:
 
Resp(T,b) = R(t=-30.3C,b) * [correction_offset(b) + T(CCD) * correction_coef1(b)
+ T(CCD)^2 * correction_coef2(b)]

where

Resp(T,b) is responsivity at CCD temperature T in binning state b,

T(CCD) is raw CCD temperature in units of DNs,

R(t=-30.3C,b) is responsivity in binning state b at CCD temperature of 1060 DN
(-30.3C),

correction_offset(b) is the camera-dependent temperature correction offset for
binning state b,

correction_coef1(b) is the camera-dependent temperature correction first-order
coefficient for binning state b.

correction_coef2(b) is the camera-dependent temperature correction second-order
coefficient for binning state b.

The temperature correction defaults to unity at CCD temperature of 1060 DN
(-30.3C).

To apply responsivity to obtain radiance L, the expression is

L = DN_flat / (t * Resp(T,b))

where

L is radiance in units of W / (m**2 microns**1 sr**1),

DN_flat is dark-, smear-, linearity-, and flat field-corrected DN,

t is the exposure time in milliseconds, and

Resp(f,T,b) is the responsivity in filter f at CCD temperature T and
binning state b.


(7) Conversion from radiance to I/F
===================================

To convert from radiance to I/F (also known as radiance factor, the ratio
of measured radiance to that which would be measured from a white
perfectly Lambertian surface), the following expression should be applied:

I_over_F(f) = L(f) * pi * (SOLAR_DISTANCE/149597870.691)**2 / F(f)

where

L(f) is calibrated radiance calculated as described above for some filter
f,

SOLAR_DISTANCE is that value for distance of the target object from the
center of the sun in kilometers (as indicated by the keyword
SOLAR_DISTANCE)

149597870.691 is the number of kilometers in 1 AU

F(f) is effective average solar irradiance sampled under the filter
bandpass.

The effective average solar radiance for each camera and bandpass is given
in the SOLAR directory.
    </PRE>
  </description>

  <category>
    <missionItem>Messenger</missionItem>
  </category>

  <seeAlso>
    <applications>
      <item>mdis2isis</item>
    </applications>
  </seeAlso>

  <history>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2007-11-27">
      Original version
    </change>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2007-12-20">
        Added computation of I/F reflectance for valid NAIF target bodies.
    </change>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2008-01-19">
        Corrected a bug that prevented the I/F correction from ever being 
        applied.  The exposure time must be expressed throughout as seconds and 
        not milliseconds (engineering units) with the exception being the dark 
        current model, which requires them to be in engineering units.  There 
        were incorrect values for the nominal filter wheel encoder values in the 
        file $messenger/calibration/mdisCalibration.trn that incorrectly 
        identified the filter.  This has been corrected, but it was also 
        determined that the validation of the proper filter wheel should take 
        place in mdis2isis.  Added loading of external file values as comma 
        separated values (CSV) files.  This includes the absolute response and 
        solar irradiance constants. 
    </change>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2008-02-29">
        Added filter dependant smear component support.  These values are 
        externally maintained in calibration/responsivity directory.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2008-05-13">
      Removed references to CubeInfo 
    </change>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2008-07-11">
      The dark current model does not support exposure times greater than 2 
      seconds. In these cases, apply the STANDARD dark current processing and 
      report this to the user as an error but complete processing.    Users can 
      always select a different model.
    </change>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2008-09-03"> 
      Corrected determination of dark column count; corrected computation of 
      dark current correction based upon valid/good columns;  added computation 
      of dark strip mean after calibration as a sanity check on the process;  
      updated ProductID and SourceProductId in the Archive group; Corrected 
      units of resulting calibration;  made filter characteristics of name, 
      wavelength and width compliant with CDR SIS specifications;  added program 
      name and versions to RadiometricCalibration group; reworked how the dark 
      model and flatfield are applied to support pixel binning.
    </change>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2008-09-09"> 
      Added additional tests for extreme observing conditions that do not allow 
      the image to be calibrated.
    </change>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2008-09-18"> 
      Very minor change of watts unit expressed as W instead of w.
    </change>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2008-11-19"> 
        Changed the exposure threshold for the dark current model from 2 seconds 
        to 1 second and it now uses the LINEAR model instead of the STANDARD 
        model in this case;  Implemented new quadratic responsivity equation for
        both WAC and NAC instruments that adds an additional term to the 
        responsivity files; updated documentation.
    </change>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2008-11-25"> 
        Corrected inclusion of dark current model file to SourceProductId when 
        applicable; bumped the version number to 3.
    </change>
    <change name="Mackenzie Boyd" date="2009-09-03">
        Added parameter to the usage of reduce to accomidate changes to reduce.
    </change> 
  </history>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input cube
        </brief>
        <description>
          This is the Isis Cube to be calibrated.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="TO">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Output cube
        </brief>
        <description>
          This is the output file. The output cube will be a calibrated version 
          of the input cube.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>
    </group>
    
    <group name="Options">
      <parameter name="DARKCURRENT">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>Dark current calibration method</brief>
        <description></description>
        <default><item>MODEL</item></default>
        <list>
          <option value="NONE">
            <brief>No correction</brief>
            <description>
                No dark current correction will be applied
              </description>
          </option>
          <option value="STANDARD">
            <brief>Do a median dark current correction</brief>
              <description>
                  This will use the median of the three leftmost pixels to as 
                  the dark current, on a line by line basis. 
              </description>
          </option>
          <option value="LINEAR">
            <brief>Use a linear fit</brief>
            <description>
              This will fit a line to the leftmost pixel values, which should be 
              dark current data, through the lines. The equation derived from 
              these pixels will be used to calculate the dark current 
              correction, on a line by line basis.
            </description>
          </option>
          <option value="MODEL">
            <brief>Use pre-developed model</brief>
             <description>
               Messenger has independent dark models, developed on-ground. 
               This will use the most recent of these models to correct the dark
               current.
              </description>
          </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="KEEPDARK">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <brief>Do not set dark current data to null</brief>
        <description>
          If this is checked, the dark current data (assumed to be the first
          three columns) are not removed from the image and also undergo the
          calibration process.
          </description>
        <default><item>false</item></default>
      </parameter>
     <parameter name="IOF">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>True</item></default>
        <brief>
          Convert to I/F units
        </brief>
        <description>
            <p>
            This option when set wil convert the output to I/F from radiance values.  
            To convert from radiance to I/F (also known as radiance factor, the ratio 
            of measured radiance to that which would be measured from a white 
            perfectly Lambertian surface), the following expression should is applied: 
            <PRE>
I_over_F(f) = L(f) * PI * (SOLAR_DISTANCE/149597870.691)**2 / F(f)                
            </PRE> 
            where L(f) is calibrated radiance calculated for some filter f,
            SOLAR_DISTANCE is that value for distance of the target object from
            the center of the sun in kilometers (as indicated by the keyword
            SOLAR_DISTANCE), 149597870.691 is the number of kilometers in 1 AU
            and F(f) is effective average solar irradiance sampled under the
            filter bandpass.
            </p>
            <p>
                If the observed target is not of a valid body as recognized by 
                NAIF, the output is left in radiance.
            </p>
        </description>
      </parameter>
    </group>
  </groups>

  <examples>
    <example>
      <brief>
        Calibrating an MDIS image
      </brief>
      <description>
        This example will show the calibration process of a MDIS image
      </description>
      <terminalInterface>
        <commandLine>FROM=EW0089565626A.cub 
          TO=EW0089565626A.calib.cub DARKCURRENT=MODEL</commandLine>
        <description>Calibration process of a MDIS image, using the MODEL dark 
          current option</description>
      </terminalInterface>
      <guiInterfaces>
        <guiInterface>
          <image src="assets/images/mdiscal.jpg" width="608" height="550">
            <brief>Calibrate an MDIS image</brief>
            <description>
              The is the GUI for mdiscal when converting the uncalibrated cube 
              EW0089565626A.cub to the calibrated cube EW0089565626A.calib.cub.
            </description>
            <thumbnail caption="Calibrating EW0089565626A.cub" src="assets/thumbs/mdiscal.jpg" width="200" height="181" />
          </image>
        </guiInterface>
      </guiInterfaces>
      <inputImages>
        <image height="512" width="512" src="assets/images/EW0089565626A.jpg">
          <brief>Input Cube</brief>
          <description>
            The is EW0089565626A.jpg before calibration
          </description>
          <thumbnail src="assets/thumbs/EW0089565626A.jpg" width="200" height="200" caption="Input Image" />
        </image>
      </inputImages>
      <outputImages>
        <image width="550" height="550" src="assets/images/EW0089565626A.model.jpg">
          <brief>Output With Dark Model</brief>
          <description>
            The is the output generated by the default options
          </description>
          <thumbnail src="assets/thumbs/EW0089565626A.model.jpg" width="200" height="200" caption="Output Image With Dark Model" />
        </image>
      </outputImages>
    </example>
  </examples>
</application>
