<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="moccal" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">

  <brief>
    Radiometrically calibrates a MOC image
  </brief>

  <description>
    <p>
    moccal performs radiometric corrections to images acquired by the Mars
    Global Surveyor (MGS) MOC camera.  MOC has one Narrow Angle (NA)
    detector and 2 Wide Angle (WA) detectors.  It also has two camera
    systems, A and B.  The B camera system is a backup and currently has
    very little or no radiometric calibration information.  It is supported
    to a very limited extent but is not in use at this time.
    </p>
    
    <p>
    The MGS MOC NA detector has a total of 2048 pixels.  The WA Red and WA
    Blue detectors have a total of 3456 pixels.  Images from MOC may or may
    not include all pixels in the acquired image.  There are special summing
    modes that are utilized on-board the spacecraft to average detector
    pixels to combine them into a single output pixel value.  Both NA and WA
    detectors can utilize crosstrack (sample) and downtrack (line) summing
    modes.  The value of these modes indicate the number of samples and
    lines, respectively, that were summed and averaged to result in the
    pixel values stored in the input file to moccal specified in the FROM
    parameter.  These values are stored in the ISIS labels as
    CROSSTRACK_SUMMING and DOWNTRACK_SUMMING, respectively.  Note that this
    will reduce the number of samples in the output image by a factor of at
    most the crosstrack summing mode value.  The NA is restricted to modes
    of 1 through 8 for both crosstrack and downtrack summing.  Furthermore,
    the crosstrack and downtrack modes must be the same.  For both WA
    detectors, crosstrack and downtrack modes range from 1 to 127.  Unlike
    NA, WA crosstrack and downtrack summing modes can differ.  There are two
    additional special WA crosstrack summing modes.  These modes are
    indicated by crosstrack summing mode values of 13 and 27.  Both of these
    modes use specially configured tables to indicate the relative detector
    hardware pixels involved in computing the output pixel value.  These
    modes are intended to maintain approximately equal spatial resolution
    from nadir to limb.  Crosstrack summing mode 13 has a resolution of
    7.5 km/pixel and maximum number of output pixels of 768; mode 27 has
    a resolution of 3.75 km/pixel with the maximum number of output pixels
    of 384.  moccal recognizes both these modes and applies appropriate
    measures to radiometrically correct them.
    </p>
    <p>
    The MOC camera has the ability to acquire images of differing sizes in
    both line and sample.  The starting hardware detector pixel for the
    acquired image is specified by the ISIS label keyword,
    FIRST_LINE_SAMPLE.  The first pixel in the detector is indicated by a
    value of 1.  (Note that in the original PDS image products this is the
    EDIT_MODE_ID keyword and is 0-based.  In ISIS, FIRST_LINE_SAMPLE is a
    PDS standard and is 1 plus this value, a 1-based numbering scheme.)
    Note that all corrections are applied relative to the actual hardware
    pixel.
    </p>
    
    moccal has a number of parameters required to process MGS MOC image
    data.  Most of these parameters are read from an ISIS parameter defaults
    file located in the the mgs directory specified in the IsisPreference file.  
    This file has the form:
     <pre>    
      $mgs/calibration/moccal.kernel.xxx
    
      where "xxx" is a positive number.
     </pre>  
    moccal will search for the parameter file with the highest number and
    load all its defaults needed to process MOC images.  Note that the
    caller may explicity provide an alternative ISIS parameter defaults
    file name in the "CALKERNEL" input parameter if they have their own
    set of defaults that applies to MOC data.  See an existing calibration
    file for details on how to configure this file.
    
    <p>
    The MOC response equation (without pixel-to-pixel variation terms) is as
    follows:
    </p>
    
    <pre>
           dn = a * (r * ex + dc * ex + g) + (z - off)
    
      where r is the average signal being generated at the focal
      plane (in DN/msec at minimum gain), z is the fixed zero
      offset, off is the commanded variable offset, dc is the dark
      current term (in DN/msec at minimum gain), g is the gain-
      dependent offset (in DN at minimum gain), a is the commanded
      system gain (where minimum gain is 1 and all other gains
      are &gt;1) and ex is the exposure time in milliseconds.
    </pre>
    
    moccal computes "r" from "dn" at every pixel in the input MOC image.
    Hence, the actual equation moccal implements is as follows:
    
    <pre>
           r = ((dn - z + off) / a - g) / ex - dc
    </pre>
    
   <p>
    Additional pixel-to-pixel variations are corrected by a detector
    coefficient file also specified in the parameter defaults file.  This
    file has been provided after analysis of the calibration data taken
    prior to and after the launch of MGS.  Certain detectors may not have
    these coefficients derived and thus will not have this correction
    applied.  If these files do exist, they are typically taken from the
    mgs directory specified in the IsisPreference file.  The coefficent file is expected to contain any number of
    comments indicated by a '#' as the first character in a line.  The
    first non-blank or uncommented line must contain the number of values
    (i.e., one per line) of pixel coefficients for this detector.  This
    must be the exact number of pixels in the given detector, 2048 for the
    MOC NA detector and 3456 for the MOC WA Red and Blue detectors.  All
    non-blank, uncommented lines after the detector count expects two values
    per line.  The first is a multiplicative value followed by an additive
    value.  These values are applied to the value "r" computed in the above
    equation to correct for individual pixel variation.  Note that some
    detectors, namely WA Blue, may not have a pixel variation correction
    derived.  For these cases, moccal will apply the
    calibration equation without pixel-to-pixel variation applied. 
   </p>
    
    <p>  
    Prior to MGS MOC mapping phases, MOC NA downtrack summing modes
    greater than 1 was implemented differently in onboard camera software.
    A software patch was made at some point prior to normal mission
    mapping phase that would be used throughout the mapping and extended
    phases for the rest of the mission.  moccal applies the following
    algorithm for all MOC NA images:  *ALL* NA images have the exposure
    times multiplied by the downtrack summing mode.  All NA images prior
    to mapping phases has the recoreded GAIN mode value divided by the
    downtrack summing mode and a new GAIN value is looked up in the table
    that is closest to this value.  It is substituted in the calibration
    equation for the commanded gain value (a).  The critical piece of
    information needed for this algorithm is the time (spacecraft clock
    count or SCLK) when this patch was uploaded to the spacecraft.  This
    time has been determined to be just prior to the first image acquired
    in the normal mapping phase.  This is image m0000001.imq and its SCLK
    is 607568463:128 which corresponds to April 3, 1999, 01:00:40.4405 UTC.
    None of the MOC WA images are affected by this algorithm.
   </p>

    <pre>
    References:
    
    "MOC2 Calibration Report, October 1997 [SCCS 10/17/97 version 1.3]"
    
    "Software Interface Specification, Narrow Angle and Wide Angle
       Standard Data Products (September 1999 (revised for MGS)
       (formatted April 7, 2000))"
    </pre>
  </description>

  <history>
    <change name="Tracie Sucharski" date="1998-04-06">
      Original version
    </change>
    <change name="Jeff Anderson" date="2003-12-18">
      Converted to Isis 3.0
    </change>
    <change name="Jeff Anderson" date="2003-12-18">
      Fixed buffer overflow
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2008-05-13">
      Removed references to CubeInfo 
    </change>
    <change name="Jeannie Walldren" date="2008-11-05">
      Changed MocLabels references from IsNarrowAngle(), IsWideAngleBlue(), 
      IsWideAngleRed() to NarrowAngle(), WideAngleBlue(), WideAngleRed(), 
      respectively.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Koechle" date="2009-05-14">
      Fixed calls to AddComment.  Removed "/*" that should not have been there.
    </change>

  </history>

  <category>
    <missionItem>Mars Global Surveyor</missionItem>
  </category>

  <seeAlso>
    <applications>
      <item>mocevenodd</item>
      <item>mocnoise50</item>
    </applications>
  </seeAlso>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Level 0 MOC image
        </brief>
        <description>
          A uncalibrated MOC image.  If the image is from the narrow angle camera, it should be run through mocevenodd
          and mocnoise50 prior to moccal.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TO">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <pixelType>real</pixelType>
        <brief>
          Level 1 MOC image
        </brief>
        <description>
          The resultant radiometrically calibrated cube
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="CALKERNEL">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          PVL kernel containing calibration parameters
        </brief>
        <internalDefault>Internal Default</internalDefault>
        <description>
          If you do not enter a file, mocal will search for a file with the form:
         <pre>    
          $mgs/calibration/moccal.kernel.xxx
        
          where "xxx" is a positive number.
         </pre>  
          The kernel with the highest version (xxx) will be used.
          See an existing calibration
          file for details on how to configure this file.
        </description>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Calibration Parameters">
      <parameter name="IOF">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>True</item></default>
        <brief>
          Convert to I/F
        </brief>
        <description>
           The user has the option to request the output of moccal to be in
           either units of percent reflectance (IOF="YES") or in average signal
           level at the focal plane (IOF="NO") in DN/msec.  moccal has a set of
           default I/F (percent reflectance) factors for each detector, NA and both
           WA.  Should they not have this value, a W0 of 0.0 will be detected and
           I/F cannot be generated.  moccal will detect occurances of W0=0.0 and
           report this to the user whilst functioning as if IOF="NO" irregardless
           of what may have been provided by the user for IOF.  Conversion to I/F 
           takes place after calibration and pixel-to-pixel variation correction.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="NULLWAGO">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>False</item></default>
        <brief>
          Null lines near WA gain/offset changes
        </brief>
        <description>
          <p>
           The MOC WA camera has an additional capability to change the commanded
           gain state (a) and offset (off) at any time during image acquistion.
           The approximate time these changes are made is provided in a file called
           "wago.tab".  This file can be found on all MOC CDROM products under the
           "index" directory.  This table, called a "WAGO" (Wide Angle Gain Offset)
           table, contains one entry per line of four fields.  All fields are
           double quoted.  The first field is the WA detector for which the gain
           and offset change occurs, the second is the SCLK time of the change, the
           third is the hexidecimal code of the new gain mode identifier and the
           fourth is the offset mode identifier.  The WA detector will be either
           "RED" or "BLUE".  The SCLK is the spacecraft clock count of the time at
           which the command to change gain and offset was initiated.  The gain
           mode identifier indicates a gain value that is stored in a table of
           gain values.  The offset mode identifier is actually specified in
           factors of 5 DN.  Hence, if the commanded offset mode is "5", then "off"
           in the above calibration equation is set to 25 (5 * 5 = 25).  Any number
           of these WAGO changes can occur during WA image acquisition.  WAGO
           changes are apparent as an abrupt change in brightness at a particular
           line.  Beware, not all changes are WAGOs as this is also a
           characteristic of dropped data.
          </p>

          <p>
           As the timing knowledge of the gain-offset changes is only accurate to
           1/8 of a second, and the WA line rate is somewhat faster than this and
           not an even multiple of 1/8 second, the line on which the brightness
           discontinuity occurs may not match precisely the line computed from the
           image start time, line rate, and known time of state change.  In
           addition, changes in highly-summed images (such as global map swaths)
           may result in summed output lines having been created in the instrument
           from unsummed input lines taken in different states.  moccal attempts to
           detect lines that exhibit this signature and corrects them using a
           brightness matching algorithm.  With the WA line rate at 75ms, for a
           downtrack summing mode of 1, the change should occur no more than two
           lines before or after the computed line of the change.  moccal looks in
           this window of transition lines and applies an averaging techinque to
           correct them if NULLWAGO="NO".  If NULLWAGO="YES", then these lines are
           assigned the ISIS NULL value and can be handled later using alternative
           processing techniques.
          </p>
        </description>
      </parameter>
    </group>
  </groups>
</application>
