<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="voyramp" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">

  <brief>
    Corrects Voyager 1 Io images from plasma torus irradiation
  </brief>

  <description>
    <p>
      Removes parabolic (top to bottom) additive error from Voyager
      800 x 800 frames.
    </p>

    <p>
      Calculate the DN offset values for each line to correct additional dark current 
      buildup on the vidicon detectors on Voyager 1 during a 15 hour passage through 
      the Io plasma torus.  The additive error increased from top to bottom of each 
      frame and is directly related to the spacecraft event time. Three 
      two-dimensional [DN offset/Spacecraft event] plots (ICARUS 73,385-426(1988) 
      Global Color and Albedo Variations on IO, by Alfred S. McEwen) reveal the DN 
      offset values based on hour by hour event times, one for top of the frame, 
      middle and bottom. 
      
      Full 16 hour points have been identified of each plot and loaded into 
      three arrays. The event time is given to this routine in GMT hour, minutes 
      and seconds. The arrays are referenced by the whole integer hour passed. 
      Two points are identified by x1 = hour and y1 = array(hour); x2 = hour + 1 
      and y2 = array(hour + 1); where x = event time and y = * DN value.  The 
      hour, minute and seconds of the event time are also converted to a real 
      value and then all is passed on to a routine which will perform a linear 
      interpolation between the two points and return the associated DN value 
      for the real event time. 
      
      This program is meant to be run after voycal has been 
      run on the image, as it provides additional corrections for a specific 
      time period. 
    </p>
  </description>

  <history>
    <change name="Mackenzie Boyd" date="2010-09-08">
      Original version - Converted from Isis2
    </change>
  </history>

  <category>
    <missionItem>Voyager</missionItem>
  </category>

  <seeAlso>
    <applications>
      <item>voycal</item>
    </applications>
  </seeAlso>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input cube, must be a calibrated Voyager 1 cube
        </brief>
        <description>
          The input cube which must be Voyager 1, calibrated, and within the 
          correct time range, of Io.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TO">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <pixelType>real</pixelType>
        <brief>
          Output cube
        </brief>
        <description>
          A further calibrated cube corrected for plasma torus irradiation near 
          the moon Io.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>
    </group>

  </groups>
</application>
