<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="vikcal" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">
  <brief>
    Radiometric correction of VIKING Planetary images
  </brief>

  <description>
    <p>
    VIKCAL performs radiometric corrections to planetary images acquired by
    the Viking orbiter cameras. VIKCAL performs a radiometric correction in
    two steps. First, VIKCAL corrects for the varying response of the
    vidicon across the field of view of the camera.  Multiplicative and
    additive correction coefficients, as a function of line and sample
    position, are applied to an image array to produce the results of an
    'ideal' camera.  VIKCAL converts the image data to radiance factor
    values.  The radiance factor is defined as the ratio of the observed
    radiance and the radiance of a white screen, normal to the incident rays
    of the Sun.
    </p>
    <p>
    If run on a non-spiceinited cube, this program requires access to local mission-specific 
    SPICE kernels, in order to find the distance between the sun and the target body. 
    When run on a spiceinited cube, this can be determined using the camera model.
    Using a spiceinited cube as input has the advantage of not requiring that local 
    mission-specific kernels be available. (See spiceinit web=true.)
    </p>

  </description>

  <category>
    <missionItem>Viking</missionItem>
  </category>

  <seeAlso>
    <applications>
      <item>viknosalt</item>
      <item>viknopepper</item>
      <item>vikfixtrx</item>
    </applications>
  </seeAlso>

  <history>
    <change name="Elizabeth Ribelin" date="2005-05-18">
      Original version - Converted from Isis2
    </change>
    <change name="Elizabeth Miller" date="2005-11-15">
      Fixed problems caused by the split of the viking data area
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2007-08-21">
      Fixed poutput pvl to not have spaces in the keyword names
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2008-05-13">
      Removed references to CubeInfo
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2010-06-16">
      Fixed pvl comments
    </change>
    <change name="Stuart Sides" date="2021-02-22">
      Added ability to calibrate using the camera instead of direcly using SPICE kernels
    </change>
  </history>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input cube file name
        </brief>
        <description>
          The cube to be calibrated.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TO">
        <type>cube</type>
        <pixelType>real</pixelType>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Output cube
        </brief>
        <description>
          The resultant cube containing the calibrated data.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>
    </group>
  </groups>

</application>
