<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<homePage>
  <div class="isisNavigationBar">
  <table>
    <tr>
      <td><img src="assets/banners/banner.jpg" width="600" height="106" alt="[USGS Banner]" border="0" usemap="#bannermap"/>
        <map name="bannermap" id="bannermap">
          <area shape="rect" target="_top" alt="Visit the USGS Home Page" coords="2,1,186,73" href="http://www.usgs.gov"
            title="Visit the USGS Home Page"/>
          <area shape="rect" target="_top" alt="Go to the Astrogeology Research Program Home Page" coords="2,75,249,102"
            href="http://astrogeology.usgs.gov"   title="Go to the Astrogeology Research Program Home Page"/>
          <area shape="default" alt="USGS" nohref="nohref"/>
        </map>
      </td>
    </tr>
  </table>
  </div>


  <h1>ISIS</h1>
  <h1 class="subtitle">Integrated Software for Imagers and Spectrometers</h1>
  <hr/>
  <table>
    <tr>
      <td valign="top">
        <h2><a name="WhatIsIsis">What is ISIS?</a></h2>
        <p>
          Integrated Software for Imagers and Spectrometers (ISIS) is free and
          open-source software (FOSS) developed by the USGS Astrogeology
          Science Center for NASA and the planetary community. ISIS is a
          fundamental tool for processing raw archival data into analysis ready
          products and includes standard image processing tools such as
          contrast, stretch, image algebra, filters, and statistical analysis.
          However, ISIS's key feature is the ability to place different types of
          data in the correct cartographic locations on extraterrestrial bodies.
          The cartographically located data can then be used to create archives,
          topographic or cartographic maps, digital elevation models, and other
          scientific products.
        </p>
        <h2><a name="SupportingPlanetarySpaceMissions">Supporting Planetary Space Missions</a></h2>
        <p>
          ISIS is a valuable resource for planetary missions that require
          systematic data processing, products for planning, and research and
          analysis of derived data products. Support for a mission is added to
          ISIS by creating sensor models, tools for ingesting mission-specific
          ancillary data, and optional tools for calibrating mission data. Once
          a mission is supported, data from that mission can be used with the
          full suite of processing and analysis tools in ISIS. ISIS supports
          data from NASA and International spacecraft missions including Lunar
          Orbiter, Apollo, Voyager, Mariner 10, Viking, Galileo, Magellan,
          Clementine, Mars Global Surveyor, Cassini, Mars Odyssey, Mars
          Reconnaissance Orbiter, MESSENGER, Lunar Reconnaissance Orbiter,
          Chandrayaan, Dawn, Kaguya, and New Horizons.
        </p>
      </td>
    </tr>
  </table>
</homePage>
