<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="ctxcal" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">

  <brief>
    Radiometrically calibrates a CTX image
  </brief>

  <description>
    <p>
    ctxcal performs radiometric corrections to images acquired by the Context
    Imager aboard the Mars Reconnaissance Orbiter spacecraft.  The CTX camera
    will make observations simulteously with the HiRise camera.
    </p>

    <p>
    The MRO CTX detector has a total of 5000 pixels, divided among an A
    channel and a B channel.  The pixels alternate between the two channels:
    ABABABAB, etc.  Images from CTX may or may not include all pixels in the
    acquired image.  There are special summing modes that are utilized
    on-board the spacecraft to average detector pixels to combine them into a
    single output pixel value.  The value of the ISIS label keyord,
    SpatialSumming, indicates the number of samples that were summed and
    averaged to result in the pixel values stored in the file.  Note that this
    will reduce the number of samples in the output image by a factor of at
    most the SpatialSumming mode value.
    </p>
    <p>
    The CTX camera has the ability to acquire images of differing sizes in
    both line and sample.  The starting hardware detector pixel for the
    acquired image is specified by the ISIS label keyword, SampleFirstPixel.
    The first pixel in the detector is indicated by a value of 0.
    </p>

    <p>
    Dark current pixels are taken for each line and are stored in the Isis
    cube as a table, named "Ctx Prefix Dark Pixels".  The number of dark
    current pixels in this table is dependent on the SpatialSumming and the
    SampleFirstPixel keywords from the labels.  The following table shows the
    association between these keywords and dark current pixels.
    </p>

    <table class="tableFormattedInformation">
      <caption>
        Association between keywords the number of dark current pixels
      </caption>
      <col class="number"/>
      <col class="number"/>
      <col class="number"/>
      <col class="text"/>
      <tr>
        <th>SpatialSumming</th>
        <th>SampleFirstPixel</th>
        <th colspan="2">Number of Dark current pixels in the table</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>1</td>
          <td>0</td>
          <td>24 </td>
          <td>(12 for each channel, stored as ABABABABABABABABABABABAB)</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>1</td>
          <td>&gt;0</td>
          <td>16 </td>
          <td>(8 for each channel, stored  as ABABABABABABABAB)</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>2</td>
          <td>0</td>
          <td>12 </td>
          <td>(The dc pixels for the A and B channel have been summed together)</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
          <td>2</td>
          <td>&gt;0</td>
          <td>8 </td>
          <td>(The dc pixels for the A and B channel have been summed together)</td>
      </tr>
    </table>

    <p>
    If SpatialSumming is 1 the dark current pixels are averaged together then
    this average is subtracted from all image pixels.  If SpatialSumming is 2,
    the dark current pixels for the A and B channel are averaged separately,
    then the A channel dark average is subtracted from the A channel image
    pixels and the B channel dark average is subtracted from the B channel
    image pixels.
    </p>

    <p>
    The equation ctxcal implements is as follows:

    <pre>
    r = ( dn - dc / (gain(i,j) * exp)
    </pre>

    where r is the average signal being generated at the focal plane (in
    DN/msec), dc is the dark current term (in DN/msec), gain(i,j) is the pixel
    dependent gain, and ex is the exposure time in milliseconds.
    </p>

    <p>
    If the IOF parameter is chosen, the output pixels are converted to
    relative reflectance (I/F) using the solar radiance, with an albedo 1
    target at normal incidence at Mars perihelion distance (2.07e+08 km) and
    a CTX response of 3660.5 DN/msec.
    </p>

  </description>

  <history>
    <change name="Tracie Sucharski" date="2006-11-02">
      Original version
    </change>
    <change name="Tracie Sucharski" date="2007-01-19">
        Moved the flat file into the mro calibration data area and changed the code to point to that area.
    </change>
    <change name="Tracie Sucharski" date="2007-03-16">
        Make sure input cube is a ctx image.
    </change>
    <change name="Deborah Lee Soltesz" date="2007-03-16" hidden="true">
        Reformatted table in documentation, converting illegal characters to HTML character entities.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2007-08-15">
        Added an application test
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2008-05-13">
      Removed references to CubeInfo 
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Koechle" date="2008-12-04">
      Removed hard coded flatfile, now searchs for highest version
    </change>
  </history>

  <category>
    <missionItem>Mars Reconnaissance Orbiter</missionItem>
  </category>

  <seeAlso>
    <applications>
      <item>ctxevenodd</item>
    </applications>
  </seeAlso>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Level 0 CTX image
        </brief>
        <description>
          An uncalibrated CTX image.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TO">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <pixelType>real</pixelType>
        <brief>
          Level 1 CTX image
        </brief>
        <description>
          The resultant radiometrically calibrated cube
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="FLATFILE">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <pixelType>real</pixelType>
        <brief>
          Flat Field file (pixel dependent gain)
        </brief>
        <internalDefault>Internal Default</internalDefault>
        <description>
          Flat Field file (pixel dependent gain).  If no file is entered, the
          default will be used.
        </description>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Calibration Parameters">
      <parameter name="IOF">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>True</item></default>
        <brief>
          Convert to I/F
        </brief>
        <description>
           The user has the option to request the output of ctxcal to be in
           either units of percent reflectance (IOF="YES") or in average signal
           level at the focal plane (IOF="NO") in DN/msec.  Ctxcal has a
           default I/F (percent reflectance) factor of 3660.5 DN/msecond response
           with an albedo 1 target a normal incidence at Mars perihelion distance
           (2.07 e+08).  Conversion to I/F takes place after calibration and
           pixel-to-pixel variation corrections.
        </description>
      </parameter>

    </group>
  </groups>
</application>
