<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<application name="grid" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">
  <brief>
    Add a graticule or rectangular grid to the input image
  </brief>

  <description>
    This program superimposes a user-defined grid on an input image. <br/><br/>
    <b>Two types of grids are available:</b>
    <blockquote>
    1.  A graticule based on <def link="Latitude">latitude</def> and 
        <def link="Longitude">longitude</def> coordinates where (MODE=GROUND).<br/>
    2.  A simple rectangular grid based on line and sample coordinates where (MODE=IMAGE).<br/>
    </blockquote>

    Defaults: 
    <ul>
    <li> MODE = GROUND </li>
    <li> BASELAT = 0.0 </li>
    <li> BASELON = 0.0 </li>
    <li> LATINC = 10 </li>
    <li> LONINC = 10 </li>
    </ul>
    
    Use the GROUND mode for images that have SPICE or map projection information.  
    Use the IMAGE mode for images that do not have SPICE or map projection information,
    or to draw grid lines based on sample and line information.
    <br/><br/>
    The grid pattern will intersect a specific origin of either (latitude,longitude) 
    or (sample,line) position.  Grid lines are drawn at intervals from the origin based 
    on the increment values defined by the user.  The graticule produced may not match 
    the image coordinates exactly, so the result will have outer grid cells that 
    might have different heights and widths than the interior grid cells.  In 
    addition, if the LATINC and LONINC are too large compared with your image 
    <def link="Scale">map scale</def>, the grid lines may miss your image. If the 
    increments are too small, the grid lines may be overly dense. <br/><br/>
    
    This application will draw grids on either ISIS <def link="Level0">level0</def>, 
    <def link="Level1">level1</def> (with successful <i>spiceinit</i>), and
    <def link="Level2">level2</def> <def link="Cube">cubes</def>, or mosaics.  
    The mapping information in the labels will be used to draw grid lines on mosaics 
    and Level2 images.  If the
    latitude and longitde information cannot be calculated or extracted using the image 
    label contents, then use the IMAGE mode.<br/><br/>
    
    <b>Example Parameter Settings for Grids:</b><br/> <br/>
    Example 1: Superimpose a basic latitude/longitude graticule with grid lines drawn
    every 10 degrees based on zero: <br/> 
    MODE=GROUND BASELAT=0 BASELON=0 LATINC=10 LONINC=10<br/><br/>

    Example 2: Superimpose a graticule on an input image that intersects at line 23 and
    sample 17, with vertical lines drawn every 30 pixels and horizontal lines every 
    40 pixels: <br/>
    MODE=IMAGE BASELINE=23 BASESAMPLE=17 SINC=30 LINC=40<br/>
    <b>Note:  MODE=GROUND cannot be used when sample and line coordinates are used.</b><br/><br/>

    Example 3: Superimpose a latitude/longitude graticule with a grid intersection at 
    -5.0 degree latitude and 140.0 degree longitude, with latitude lines drawn every 2.5 
    degrees and longitude lines drawn every 3 degrees:<br/>
    MODE=GROUND BASELAT=-5.0 BASELON=140 LATINC=2.5 LONINC=3 <br/><br/>
    
    Example 4:  Superimpose a latitude/longitude graticule within a subarea of an image
    (full latitude and longitude extent), with a grid line drawn every 2.5 degrees
    between latitudes -8 and -1 degrees and only between longitudes 140 and 145 degrees: <br/>
    MODE=GROUND BASELAT=0 BASELON=0 LATINC=2.5 LONINC=2.5 MINLAT=-8 MAXLAT=-1 MINLON=140 
    MAXLON=145 Bound=yes<br/><br/>
    
    For complex grids, the <i>grid</i> application can be run multiple times with different 
    parameter settings for each successive run that builds onto the previous output file.
    The TICKS option can be used to draw short ticks instead of grid lines.  The  
    OUTLINE option will draw grid lines along the outside edges of the first and last samples 
    and lines of the input file.  The BOUNDARY option will either draw grid lines around 
    the outside edges of the input file or around the bounding box specified by the user 
    with MINLAT, MAXLAT, MINLON, and MAXLON parameters.<br/><br/>
    
     
  </description>

  <category>
    <categoryItem>Utility</categoryItem>
    <categoryItem>Map Projection</categoryItem>
  </category>

 <seeAlso>
    <applications>
      <item>stats</item>
    </applications>
  </seeAlso>

  <history>
    <change name="Sean Crosby" date="2007-03-16">
      Original version 
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2007-07-27">
      Added category: Map Projection
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2008-04-22">
      Fixed problems with mapping outside of the projection space and with
      0lat/0lon boundaries.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2008-05-12">
      Removed references to CubeInfo 
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2008-06-12">
      Added outline option
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2009-01-06">
      Changed how mode=ground works
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2010-05-06">
      Added TICKS options
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2010-07-22">
      Added LINEWIDTH option
    </change>
    <change name="Mackenzie Boyd" date="2011-01-21">
      Added more line options, to change output to be HRS, LRS, NULL, or a DN.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2011-01-25">
      Bug fixes for projections that use PositiveWest or Planetographic
      coordinate systems. The BASELAT and BASELON parameters are now expected
      to be in the units of the projection (if your cube has a planetographic
      latitude system, and baselat=50, then there will be a line at the
      planetographic latitude of 50).
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2011-01-26">
      Added BOUNDARY, MINLAT, MAXLAT, MINLON and MAXLON options.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2011-12-08">
      Fixed a bug with the outline option. If the image had a larger number of
      samples than number of lines, all of the data at sample > number of lines
      would be considered a grid line. This could result in a large portion of
      the image losing legitimate DN values for the grid value. Fixes #607.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2012-01-04">
      Tested and documented for the January 2012 release. The documentation
      updates included were recommended by Chris Isbell.
    </change>
    <change name="Adam Licht" date="2012-12-26">
      Added functionality to choose the source of image background. Pixel Values
      for behind the grid can now be the image pixel value, HRS, LRS, NULL, or a DN.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2012-12-31">
      Incorporated Adam Licht's changes into Isis. This included re-formatting to match
      current Isis 3 coding standards, removal of error checking of conditions that
      cannot happen, fixes with running in batch mode/resetting of variable states
      between runs, some re-positioning of parameter locations, and creating
      tests. These changes shouldn't break any existing scripts that utilize grid. Fixes #917.
    </change>
    <change name="Moses Milazzo" date="2013-03-24">
      Added to documentation to alert the user to the fact that providing a poorly chosen 
      starting point or grid increment may result in unexpected behavior. Fixes #178.
    </change>
    <change name="Ella Mae Lee" date="2013-07-18">
      Updated the documentation and added examples. Fixes #178.
    </change>
    <change name="Janet Barrett" date="2014-06-23">
      Modified so that the output cube characteristics are obtained from the input cube
      and/or cube characteristics specified on the command line. Fixes #2063.
    </change>
  </history>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input cube 
        </brief>
        <description>
          Use this parameter to select the input file.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="TO">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Output cube
        </brief>
        <description>
          This file will contain the gridded image. 
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Grid Type">
      <parameter name="MODE">
        <type>string</type>
        <default><item>GROUND</item></default> 
        <brief>Grid options</brief>
        <description>
          This allows for selection of either IMAGE or GROUND coordinates when drawing the grid.
        </description>
        <list>
          <option value = "IMAGE">
            <brief>Add a rectangular grid in terms of lines and samples</brief>
            <description>
              A grid will be inserted into the image with spacing and position
              defined in line and sample coordinates.
            </description>
            <exclusions>
              <item>BASELAT</item>
              <item>BASELON</item>
              <item>LATINC</item>
              <item>LONINC</item>
              <item>MINLAT</item>
              <item>MAXLAT</item>
              <item>MINLON</item>
              <item>MAXLON</item>
              <item>BOUNDARY</item>
            </exclusions>
          </option>

          <option value="GROUND">
            <brief>Add a grid (graticule) in terms of lat/lon coordinates</brief>
            <description>
              A grid will be inserted into the image with spacing and position
              defined in <def link="Latitude">latitude</def> and <def link=
	      "Longitude">longitude</def> coordinates.
            </description>
            <exclusions>
              <item>LINC</item>
              <item>SINC</item>
              <item>BASELINE</item>
              <item>BASESAMPLE</item>
            </exclusions>
          </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TICKS">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>false</item></default>
        <brief>Draw ticks instead of lines</brief>
        <description>
          Draw ticks at grid line intersections (instead of drawing full lines).
        </description>
        <inclusions>
          <item>DIAGONALTICKS</item>
          <item>TICKSIZE</item>
        </inclusions>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="OUTLINE">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>false</item></default>
        <brief>Outline the image</brief>
        <description>
          This will draw grid lines at the very edges of the image.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="BOUNDARY">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>false</item></default>
        <brief>Include grid lines at the lat/lon extent of the image or as defined by the ground options</brief>
        <description>
          This will draw grid lines (or ticks) at the lat/lon extents of the
          image or those extents as provided by user input MINLAT, MAXLAT,
          MINLON, and MAXLON.
        </description>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Image Grid Parameters">
      <parameter name="BASELINE">
        <type>integer</type>
        <default><item>1</item></default>
        <brief>Starting line</brief>
        <description>
          Starting line of grid.  This, along with BASESAMPLE, defines the
          starting point (line) for drawing the grid.
        </description>
        <minimum inclusive="yes">1</minimum>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="BASESAMPLE">
        <type>integer</type>
        <default><item>1</item></default>
        <brief>Starting sample</brief>
        <description>
          Starting sample of grid.  This, along with BASELINE, defines the
          starting point (sample) for drawing the grid.
        </description>
        <minimum inclusive="yes">1</minimum>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="LINC">
        <type>integer</type>
        <default><item>100</item></default>
        <brief>Line increment</brief>
        <description>
          This defines the line increment when drawing the grid, starting at
          BASELINE. The line increment is the spacing between lines.
        </description>
        <minimum inclusive="yes">1</minimum>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="SINC">
        <type>integer</type>
        <default><item>100</item></default>
        <brief>Sample increment</brief>
        <description>
          This defines the sample increment when drawing the grid, starting at
          BASESAMPLE. The sample increment is the spacing between samples.
        </description>
        <minimum inclusive="yes">1</minimum>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Ground Grid Parameters">
      <parameter name="BASELAT">
        <type>double</type>
        <default><item>0.0</item></default>
        <brief>Starting latitude</brief>
        <description>
          This is the latitude on which LATINC is mathematically based. 
          This establishes a starting point for a global 'virtual' grid where
          latitude lines are drawn where the input image intersects the virtual
          grid. The application assumes user input reflects proper units (e.g.
          <def link="Planetographic Latitude">planetographic</def>, <def 
	  link="Planetocentric Latitude">planetocentric latitude</def>) as 
	  defined within the image.
        </description>
        <minimum inclusive="yes">-90.0</minimum>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="BASELON">
        <type>double</type>
        <default><item>0.0</item></default>
        <brief>Starting longitude</brief>
        <description>
          This is the longitude on which LONINC is mathematically based. 
          This establishes a starting point for a global 'virtual' grid
          where longitude lines are drawn where the input image intersects the
          virtual grid.
        </description>
        <minimum inclusive="yes">-360.0</minimum>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="LATINC">
        <type>double</type>
        <default><item>10.0</item></default>
        <brief>Latitude increment</brief>
        <description>
          This defines the latitude increment, based on BASELAT, on which grid
          lines are drawn. This establishes a global 'virtual' grid where
          latitude lines are drawn only where the input image intersects the
          virtual grid.
        </description>
        <minimum inclusive="yes">0.0</minimum>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="LONINC">
        <type>double</type>
        <default><item>10.0</item></default>
        <brief>Longitude increment</brief>
        <description>
          This defines the longitude increment, based on BASELON, on which grid
          lines are drawn. This establishes a global 'virtual' grid where
          longitude lines are drawn only where the input image intersects the
          virtual grid.
        </description>
        <minimum inclusive="yes">0.0</minimum>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Ground Grid Limits">
      <parameter name="MINLAT">
        <type>double</type>
        <internalDefault>Automatic</internalDefault>
        <brief>Lowest latitude value to extend grid lines</brief>
        <description>
          This defines the minimum latitude to which longitude grid lines will
          extend. If BOUNDARY is selected, a latitude line will be drawn at this
          latitude.
        </description>
        <minimum inclusive="yes">-90</minimum>
        <maximum inclusive="yes">90</maximum>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="MAXLAT">
        <type>double</type>
        <internalDefault>Automatic</internalDefault>
        <brief>Highest latitude value to extend grid lines</brief>
        <description>
          This defines the maximum latitude to which longitude grid lines will
          extend. If BOUNDARY is selected, a latitude line will be drawn at this
          latitude.
        </description>
        <minimum inclusive="yes">-90</minimum>
        <maximum inclusive="yes">90</maximum>
        <greaterThan><item>MINLAT</item></greaterThan>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="MINLON">
        <type>double</type>
        <internalDefault>Automatic</internalDefault>
        <brief>Lowest longitude value to extend grid lines</brief>
        <description>
          This defines the minimum longitude to which latitude grid lines will
          extend. If BOUNDARY is selected, a longitude line will be drawn at
          this longitude.
        </description>
        <minimum inclusive="yes">-360</minimum>
        <maximum inclusive="yes">360</maximum>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="MAXLON">
        <type>double</type>
        <internalDefault>Automatic</internalDefault>
        <brief>Highest longitude value to extend grid lines</brief>
        <description>
          This defines the maximum longitude to which latitude grid lines will
          extend. If BOUNDARY is selected, a longitude line will be drawn at
          this longitude.
        </description>
        <minimum inclusive="yes">-360</minimum>
        <maximum inclusive="yes">360</maximum>
        <greaterThan><item>MINLON</item></greaterThan>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Line Parameters">
      <parameter name="LINEWIDTH">
        <type>integer</type>
        <default><item>1</item></default>
        <brief>Thickness of lines (pixels)</brief>
        <description>
          This defines the thickness of grid lines in pixels.
        </description>
        <minimum inclusive="yes">1</minimum>
        <odd />
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="LINEVALUE">
        <type>string</type>
        <default><item>HRS</item></default>
        <brief>Select grid line value assignment option</brief>
        <description>
          With this option choose <def link="Digital Number">DN</def>, <def>LRS</def>, 
	  <def>HRS</def>, or <def>NULL</def> to define how to assign 
	  the grid line value.  Use DNVALUE parameter to assign a number if DN
	  option is chosen.
        </description>
        <list>
          <option value="HRS">
            <brief>Use HRS DN value</brief>
            <description>
              Use the special pixel value HRS (High Representation Saturation)
              as the grid line value. This may vary with bit type used.
            </description>
            <exclusions><item>DNVALUE</item></exclusions>
          </option>
          <option value="LRS">
            <brief>Use LRS DN value</brief>
            <description>
              Use the special pixel value LRS (Low Representation Saturation)
              as the grid line value. This may vary with bit type used.
            </description>
            <exclusions><item>DNVALUE</item></exclusions>
          </option>
          <option value="NULL">
            <brief>Use NULL DN value</brief>
            <description>
              Use the special pixel value NULL as the grid line value. This may
              vary with bit type used.
            </description>
            <exclusions><item>DNVALUE</item></exclusions>
          </option>

          <option value="DN">
            <brief>Use given DN value</brief>
            <description>
              Use the DN value specified in the DNVALUE parameter. It is
              recommended to run the <i>stats</i> application on the cube before 
	      selecting a DN value.
            </description>
          </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="DNVALUE">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief>DN value to be used</brief>
        <description>
          This is the DN value to be used as the value of the grid lines when
          LINEVALUE=DN. It is beneficial to first run the <i>stats</i> application
          to determine image minimum and maximum values.
        </description>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Background Type">
      <parameter name="BKGNDVALUE">
        <type>string</type>
        <default><item>IMAGE</item></default>
        <brief>Select background DN value assignment option</brief>
        <description>
          This option allows for any DN value, HRS, LRS, or NULL special pixel
          values to be chosen as the background value.
        </description>
        <list>
          <option value="IMAGE">
            <brief>Use the input cube value</brief>
            <description>
              Use the input cube pixel value as the background value. This will
              superimpose the grid on top of the input image.
            </description>
            <exclusions><item>BKGNDDNVALUE</item></exclusions>
          </option>
          <option value="HRS">
            <brief>Use HRS DN value</brief>
            <description>
              Use the special pixel value HRS (High Representation Saturation)
              as the background value. This may vary with bit type used.
            </description>
            <exclusions><item>BKGNDDNVALUE</item></exclusions>
          </option>
          <option value="LRS">
            <brief>Use LRS DN value</brief>
            <description>
              Use the special pixel value LRS (Low Representation Saturation)
              as the background value. This may vary with bit type used.
            </description>
            <exclusions><item>BKGNDDNVALUE</item></exclusions>
          </option>
          <option value="NULL">
            <brief>Use NULL DN value</brief>
            <description>
              Use the special pixel value NULL as the background value. This may
              vary with bit type used.
            </description>
            <exclusions><item>BKGNDDNVALUE</item></exclusions>
          </option>
          <option value="DN">
            <brief>Use given DN value</brief>
            <description>
              Use the DN value specified in the BKGNDDNVALUE parameter. It is 
              recommended to run the <i>stats</i> application on the cube before selecting a DN
              value.
            </description>
            <inclusions><item>BKGNDDNVALUE</item></inclusions>
          </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="BKGNDDNVALUE">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief>DN value to be used</brief>
        <description>
          This is the DN value to be used as the value of the background when
          BKGNDVALUE=DN. It may be beneficial to first run the <i>stats</i> application
          to determine image minimum and maximum values.
        </description>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Tick Parameters">
      <parameter name="DIAGONALTICKS">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>false</item></default>
        <brief>Draw tick marks diagonally ('x' instead of '+')</brief>
        <description>
          Draw tick marks diagonally (creating an 'x'), instead of default
          vertical/horizontal ('+')
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TICKSIZE">
        <type>integer</type>
        <default><item>5</item></default>
        <brief>Size (length) of tickmarks (pixels)</brief>
        <description>
          This defines the width and height (which are always equal) of the tick
          marks in pixels.
        </description>
        <minimum inclusive="yes">1</minimum>
        <odd />
      </parameter>
    </group>

  </groups>

  <examples>
    <example>
      <brief>Basic latitude/longitude graticule</brief>
      <description>
        In this example, the latitude and longitude grid lines are drawn every 10 
	degrees starting at 0.0 degree latitude and longitude.
      </description>
      <terminalInterface>
        <commandLine> 
          from=aeolis_reduced.cub to=grid_ex1.cub
        </commandLine>
        <description>
          Superimpose grid lines using default settings.
        </description>
      </terminalInterface>
      <guiInterfaces>
        <guiInterface>
          <image width="558" height="900" src="assets/images/grid_ex1_gui.png">
            <brief>Example GUI</brief>
            <description>Screenshot of GUI with default parameters. 
	    </description>
            <thumbnail width="139" height="225" caption="Grid GUI" src="assets/thumbs/grid_ex1_gui_thumb.png" />
          </image>
        </guiInterface>
      </guiInterfaces>
      <inputImages>
        <image src="assets/images/aeolis_reduced.png" width="895" height="622">
          <brief>Input file</brief>
          <description>This is the ungridded input image.
          </description>
          <thumbnail caption="Input image" src="assets/thumbs/aeolis_reduced_thumb.png" width="179" height="124"/>
          <parameterName>From</parameterName>
        </image>
      </inputImages>

      <outputImages>
        <image src="assets/images/grid_ex1.png" width="895" height="622">
          <brief> Gridded output file</brief>
          <description> 
	     This file is gridded every 10 degrees in latitude and longitude starting at 
	     0.0 degree latitude and longitude.
          </description>
          <thumbnail caption="Gridded output image" src="assets/thumbs/grid_ex1_thumb.png" width="179" height="124"/>
          <parameterName>TO</parameterName>
        </image>
      </outputImages>
    </example>

    <example>
      <brief>Simple rectangular grid</brief>
      <description>
        In this example, the grid lines are drawn based on the line and sample 
	coordinates entered by the user in IMAGE mode.
      </description>
      <terminalInterface>
        <commandLine> 
          from=aeolis_reduced.cub to=grid_ex2.cub mode=image baseline=23 basesamp=17 sinc=30 linc=40
        </commandLine>
        <description>
          Superimpose grid lines using line and sample coordinates.
        </description>
      </terminalInterface>
      <guiInterfaces>
        <guiInterface>
          <image width="558" height="900" src="assets/images/grid_ex2_gui.png">
            <brief>Example GUI</brief>
            <description>Screenshot of GUI with parameter settings defined by the user. 
	    </description>
            <thumbnail width="139" height="225" caption="Grid GUI" src="assets/thumbs/grid_ex2_gui_thumb.png" />
          </image>
        </guiInterface>
      </guiInterfaces>
      <inputImages>
        <image src="assets/images/aeolis_reduced.png" width="895" height="622">
          <brief>Input file</brief>
          <description>This is the ungridded input image.
          </description>
          <thumbnail caption="Input image" src="assets/thumbs/aeolis_reduced_thumb.png" width="179" height="124"/>
          <parameterName>From</parameterName>
        </image>
      </inputImages>

      <outputImages>
        <image src="assets/images/grid_ex2.png" width="895" height="622">
          <brief> Output file</brief>
          <description> 
	     The grid lines intersect at line 23 and sample 17, with vertical lines
	     drawn every 30 pixels and horizontal lines every 40 pixels outward from the origin.
          </description>
          <thumbnail caption="Gridded output image" src="assets/thumbs/grid_ex2_thumb.png" width="179" height="124"/>
          <parameterName>TO</parameterName>
        </image>
      </outputImages>
    </example>

    <example>
      <brief>Insert a graticule within the input image</brief>
      <description>
        In this example, the grid lines are drawn based on a set of user-defined
	values for the different latitude and longitude parameters.  The graticule 
	is drawn only within the minimum and maximum latitude and longitude extents 
	entered by the user.
      </description>
      <terminalInterface>
        <commandLine> 
          from=aeolis_reduced.cub to=grid_ex4.cub mode=ground baselat=0 baselon=0 latinc=2.5 
	  loninc=2.5 minlat=-8 maxlat=-1 minlon=140 maxlon=145 bound=yes
        </commandLine>
        <description>
          Superimpose grid lines using 2.5 degrees latitude and longitude increments from an 
	  origin (0,0) defined by the user.  The outer edges of the graticule bounding box will be
	  gridded (BOUND=YES).
        </description>
      </terminalInterface>
      <guiInterfaces>
        <guiInterface>
          <image width="558" height="900" src="assets/images/grid_ex3_gui.png">
            <brief>Example GUI</brief>
            <description>Screenshot of GUI with parameter settings defined by the user. 
	    </description>
            <thumbnail width="139" height="225" caption="Grid GUI" src="assets/thumbs/grid_ex3_gui_thumb.png" />
          </image>
        </guiInterface>
      </guiInterfaces>
      <inputImages>
        <image src="assets/images/aeolis_reduced.png" width="895" height="622">
          <brief>Input file</brief>
          <description>This is the ungridded input image.
          </description>
          <thumbnail caption="Input image" src="assets/thumbs/aeolis_reduced_thumb.png" width="179" height="124"/>
          <parameterName>From</parameterName>
        </image>
      </inputImages>

      <outputImages>
        <image src="assets/images/grid_ex4.png" width="895" height="622">
          <brief> Output file</brief>
          <description> 
	     The grid lines intersect at 0.0 degree latitude and longitude, and increments
	     every 2.5 degrees in latitude and longitude.  The outer edges of the
	     bounding box around the minimum and maximum extents are gridded (BOUND=YES).
          </description>
          <thumbnail caption="Gridded output image using BOUND=YES" src="assets/thumbs/grid_ex4_thumb.png" width="179" height="124"/>
          <parameterName>TO</parameterName>
        </image>
        <image src="assets/images/grid_ex4b.png" width="895" height="622">
          <brief> Second output file using BOUND=NO</brief>
          <description> 
	     The grid lines intersect at 0.0 degree latitude and longitude, and increments
	     every 2.5 degrees in latitude and longitude.  The outer edges of the
	     bounding box are not gridded (BOUND=NO). <br/><br/>
	     Command line:<br/>
	     grid from=aeolis_reduced.cub to=grid_ex4b.cub mode=ground baselat=0 baselon=0 latinc=2.5 
	     loninc=2.5 minlat=-8 maxlat=-1 minlon=140 maxlon=145 bound=no
          </description>
          <thumbnail caption="Gridded output image using BOUND=NO" src="assets/thumbs/grid_ex4b_thumb.png" width="179" height="124"/>
          <parameterName>TO</parameterName>
        </image>
      </outputImages>
    </example>


  </examples>

</application>
