<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="lorri2isis" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">
  
  <brief>
    Import New Horizons LORRI files into ISIS format
  </brief>
  <description>
    <p>
      This program will import FITS (Flexible Image Transport System) formatted files from the 
      New Horizons LORRI instument into the ISIS format. This include the main LORRI image,
      the Error image and the Quality image.
    </p>
    <p>
      The LORRI instrument has two summing modes, (1x1) and (4x4). The instrument team
      has assigned these modes separate NAIF IK codes, 98301 and 98302 respectively.
    </p>
  </description>
  
  <history>
    <change name="Stuart Sides" date="2013-10-08">
      Original version
    </change> 
    <change name="Stuart Sides" date="2014-06-08">
      Modified  to allow the FITS extension images to be imported
    </change> 
  </history>

  <seeAlso>
    <applications>
      <item>fits2isis</item>
    </applications>
  </seeAlso>

  <category>
    <missionItem>New Horizons</missionItem>
  </category>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          A New Horizons LORRI FITS file to be converted to an ISIS cube
        </brief>
        <description>
          Use this parameter to select the filename of a New Horizons
          LORRI file to be converted to a cube. This is expected to be a FITS formatted file. 
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.fit
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TO">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Output ISIS cube file for the main image
        </brief>
        <description>
          The output cube file that will containing the New Horizons LORRI image in ISIS format. The 
          main LORRI image must be the first image in the FITS file. 
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="ERROR">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <internalDefault>Optional</internalDefault>
        <brief>
          Output ISIS cube file for the Error image
        </brief>
        <description>
          The output cube file that will containing the New Horizons LORRI Error image in ISIS 
          format. The Error image must be in the first FITS extension (i.e., second image).
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="QUALITY">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <internalDefault>Optional</internalDefault>
        <brief>
          Output ISIS cube file for the Quality image
        </brief>
        <description>
          The output cube file that will containing the New Horizons LORRI Quality image in ISIS 
          format. The Quality image must be in the second FITS extension (i.e., third image).
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>

    </group>
  </groups>

</application>
