<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="cnetsplit" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">

  <brief>
    The application cnetsplit splits the input control network into user
    specified number of control networks.
  </brief>

  <description>
    The application cnetsplit splits the input control network into a user
    specified number of control networks with the user specified output name.
    A possible use of this application would be to allow extremely large
    control networks to be split, then further processing could be divided
    among multiple computers.  The application, "cnetmerge" can then be used
    to merge the individual control networks back into a single large
    network.  The application log will display statistics for the input
    ControlNet.
    <p>
      The input control network keyword values for Description, NetworkId, and
      Target Keywords will be copied to each output control network.  The
      DateTime and UserName keywords will be created new for the output control
      networks.  The output control networks are filled from smallest to
      largest output file name from the first points in the input control
      network to the last.
    </p>
    <p>
      We can denote the number of control points in the input file by
      <i><b>n</b></i> and the number of output files to be created is by
      <i><b>k</b></i>.  Then, denote the remainder of <i><b>n/k</b></i> by
      <i><b>R</b></i> .  If <i><b>R</b></i> is not zero, then, the first
      <i><b>R</b></i> files will have one more point than the last
      <i><b>k-R</b></i> files.
      Otherwise, if <i><b>R</b></i> = 0, i.e. if the number of output files
      evenly divides the number of points in the input control network, then
      each of the output files will have the same number of points.
    </p>
    <p>
      Errors thrown by cnetsplit will include the following:
      <ul>
        <li>No question marks in the ONET_PREFIX string.</li>
        <li>More than one set of question marks in the ONET_PREFIX string.</li>
        <li>Not enough question marks for the specified number of output
              files.</li>
        <li>Number of output files exceeds the number of control points in the
              intput control network.</li>
      </ul>
    </p>
  </description>

  <category>
    <categoryItem>Control Networks</categoryItem>
  </category>

  <history>
    <change name="Sharmila Prasad" date="2010-11-03">
      Original version
    </change>
    <change name="Sharmila Prasad" date="2010-12-21">
      Updated to make the app compatible for binary cnet
    </change>
    <change name="Sharmila Prasad" date="2011-07-29">
      changed ONET_FORMAT to ONET_PREFIX
    </change>
    <change name="Jeannie Backer" date="2011-10-03">
      Added appTests, improved error message, added documentation.
    </change>
    <change name="Jeannie Backer" date="2016-04-22">
      Modified to set the new control net's target and radii by using the input control net's
      values. References #3892
    </change>
    <change name="Jesse Mapel" date="2018-07-06">
      Removed calls to set control net target radii because they are no longer needed by
      the control network. Fixes #5457.
    </change>
  </history>

<groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="CNET">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input control network to be split.
        </brief>
        <description>
          The input control network whose control points will be
          divided among the output control networks.  This file is not modified
          by cnetsplit.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.net
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="ONET_PREFIX">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>
          The output file name pattern string containing question marks where
          the file number should be placed.
        </brief>
        <description>
          This string will be used to create unique output file names.  It
          should contain a set of question marks ("?") where the file number
          will be placed. The string should not have question marks
          anywhere else. For each output file, the question marks will be
          replaced with a number from one to the number of output files.
          For example, if the user sets the pattern to
          ONET_PREFIX="ControlNet????" and NUM_OUTPUT_FILES=999,
          then cnetsplit will create 999 files with file names
          "ControlNet0001.net" through "ControlNet0999.net".
          Note: If there are not enough "?"s for the number of output files to
          be created during this run, the user will be thrown an error .
        </description>
      </parameter>
    </group>
  <group name="Options">
    <parameter name="NUM_OUTPUT_FILES">
      <type>integer</type>
      <minimum inclusive="yes">2</minimum>
      <brief>
        The number of output files that will be created by cnetsplit
      </brief>
      <description>
        The control points from the input control network will be split among
        this number of output files.
      </description>
    </parameter>
  </group>
</groups>

  <examples>
    <example>

      <brief>
        Split a control network with 8 points into 3 control networks.
      </brief>

      <description>
        This example will show how a control network is split when the number
        of output networks does not evenly divide the number points in the
        input control network.
      </description>

      <terminalInterface>
        <commandLine>
          cnet=controlNet.net onet_prefix=outputNetSplit??? num_output_files=3
        </commandLine>
        <description>
          In this example, cnetsplit will split the file controlNet.net into 3
          output files with name pattern outputNetSplit???
        </description>
      </terminalInterface>

      <guiInterfaces>
        <guiInterface>
          <image width="571" height="550" src="assets/images/cnetsplitGuiExample.jpeg">
            <brief>
              Example GUI for cnetsplit.
            </brief>
            <description>
              Screen shot of GUI for cnetsplit.  This run of the program will
              split the file controlNet.net into 3 output files with name
              pattern outputNetSplit???
            </description>
            <thumbnail width="200" height="193" src="assets/thumbs/cnetsplitGuiThumb.jpeg" caption="Screenshot of GUI command."/>
          </image>
        </guiInterface>
      </guiInterfaces>

      <dataFiles>
        <dataFile path="assets/dataFiles/controlNet.pvl">
          <brief>
            PVL of the Input control network, (controlNet.net).
          </brief>
          <description>
            This is the input control network with 8 control points that will
            be divided among 3 output control networks.  This file is not
            changed by cnetsplit.
          </description>
          <parameterName>
            CNET
          </parameterName>
        </dataFile>

        <dataFile path="assets/dataFiles/outputNetSplit001.pvl">
          <brief>
            PVL of the first output control network, (outputNetSplit001.net).
          </brief>
          <description>
            This is the first of the output control networks created by
            cnetsplit.  It contains the 1st, 2nd, and 3rd control points from
            the input control network.
          </description>
          <parameterName>
            ONET_PREFIX
          </parameterName>
        </dataFile>

        <dataFile path="assets/dataFiles/outputNetSplit002.pvl">
          <brief>
            PVL of the second output control network, (outputNetSplit002.net).
          </brief>
          <description>
            This is the first of the output control networks created by
            cnetsplit.  It contains the 4th, 5th, and 6th control points from
            the input control network.
          </description>
          <parameterName>
            ONET_PREFIX
          </parameterName>
        </dataFile>

        <dataFile path="assets/dataFiles/outputNetSplit003.pvl">
          <brief>
            PVL of the third output control network, (outputNetSplit003.net).
          </brief>
          <description>
            This is the last of the output control networks created by
            cnetsplit.  It contains the 7th and 8th control points from the
            input control network.
          </description>
          <parameterName>
            ONET_PREFIX
          </parameterName>
        </dataFile>
      </dataFiles>

    </example>
  </examples>
</application>
