<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="higlob" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">
  <brief>
    Combines HiRISE image data with all pixel data in the blobs
  </brief>

  <description>
    <p>
      This program will create a new image with the calibration pixel data
      at the top, followed by the main image data. Both the calibration and main image
      will have the buffer pixels added to the left side and the dark pixels to the right
      side.
      </p>
    <img src='assets/higlob_diagram.png' alt='Diagram of output pixel groups' width='444' height='520' />
    <p>
       The pixel values are retrieved from either the Isis tables or the main image.
       The calibration buffer and dark pixels are pulled from the "HiRISE Ancillary" table. The main 
       calibration image pixels come from the "HiRISE Calibration Image" table. The image buffer
       and dark pixels come from the "HiRISE Ancillary" table. The observation pixels come from
       the main Isis cube.
     </p>
     <p>
       The calibration image and observation image pixels of a HiRISE image can be flipped from left to right
       using the "FLIP" parameter. See the "FLIP" parameter description for details.
     </p>
  </description>

  <category>
    <missionItem>Mars Reconnaissance Orbiter</missionItem>
  </category>

  <history>
    <change name="Stuart Sides" date="2004-10-06">
      Original version
    </change>
    <change name="Stuart Sides" date="2005-06-07">
      Fixed problem with special pixels in image ancillary, calibration and calibration ancillary
      areas. They are now converted to double precision special pixels before being inserted
      into the Buffer.
    </change>
    <change name="Stuart Sides" date="2005-07-21">
      Fixed another problem with special pixels in the image ancillary table. The
      16 bit integer special pixel values in table were not being converted to double
      special pixels when being dumped into the output buffer.
    </change>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2005-09-23">
        During our first observation in cruise, it was determined that channel 1 required
        flippping rather than channel 0.  This confusion due to assumptions of which channel,
        0 or 1, was on the left or right side of the CCD.  Channel 1 is on the left, channel 0 on the
        right.    Also changed the FLIP parameter to an integer to allow the user to choose
        either channel to flip (so we don't have to do this again!)
    </change>
    <change name="Stuart Sides" date="2006-09-19">
      Fixed a memory leak caused by not deleting a global pointer.
    </change>
    <change name="Brendan George" date="2006-09-28">
        Documentation fixes
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2008-05-13">
      Removed references to CubeInfo 
    </change>
  </history>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input HiRISE cube
        </brief>
        <description>
  	      The HiRISE cube containing the image and tables from the EDR product. This must 
          be an Isis cube (i.e., "hi2isis" must be run before "higlob").
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TO">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Combined output cube
        </brief>
        <description>
          The output cube containing the main image data, calibration data, buffer pixels
          and dark pixels.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Options">
      <parameter name="FLIP">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>Specify HiRISE channel (0 or 1) image &amp; calibration image to flip</brief>
        <default><item>1</item></default>
        <description>
          <p>
               This is typically  channel 1 (discovered after launch!) rather than 0, but this
               option allows you to choose the channel you want to flip.  The default (1) is
               the one designated as the channel to flip to best assist in calibration analysis.
          </p>
          <p>
              If FLIP matches the value of the ChannelNumber keyword in the Instrument
              group, then both the observation and calibration image data will be filpped left to
              right. This does not modify the byte order of the individual pixels, and does not
              flip any of the buffer or dark pixels.
          </p>
          <p>
              To ensure that you flip no channel, set FLIP to "None".
          </p>
        </description>
        <list>
           <option value="0">
                <brief>Channel 0</brief>
                <description>Flips HiRISE channel 0 images</description>
            </option>
            <option value="1">
                <brief>Channel 1</brief>
                <description>Flips HiRISE channel 1 images</description>
            </option>
           <option value="None">
                <brief>None</brief>
                <description>Do not flip any data in image</description>
            </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>
    </group>
  </groups>
</application>
