<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<application name="apinit" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">
  <brief>
    Initialize aerial photo with interior and exterior orientation information.
  </brief>

  <description>
    This program is used to initialize the interior and exterior orientation of film-based aerial photographs.  Interior orientation information such as the focal length, optical distortion, and fiducial
    locations are input by the user and recorded on the label of the cube in the Instrument group.   This information is typical found in a USGS Report of Calibration that is specific for the camera
    flown during the particular aerial survey.   Apriori exterior orientation information such as the position of the aircraft and it's attitude are
    computed from user input such as altitude and latitude/longitude at the center of the image.  The computed exterior orientation is stored as binary tables in the cube.  

    This program mimics the capabilities of the "spiceinit" program which is used for initalized interior/exterior orientation information for NASA space instruments observing other than Earth 
    targets.  Once the interior/exterior information is added to a cube, other ISIS cartography programs can be used such as cam2map (orthorectification), caminfo (image georeferencing information), 
    qmos (mosaicking tools), and jigsaw (bundle adjustments to the aircraft position/attitude for creating seamless mosaics).

    The results of this program should not be immediately used until the exterior orientation has been corrected.   That is, do not run cam2map and expect proper 
    georeferencing/orthorectification.   There will be an error in attitude because there is not enough user information to determine the twist/yaw of the aircraft.  Instead run 
    "findfeatures" to automatically generate a ground control network and then jigsaw to solve for the actual aircraft position and attitude.
  </description>
  <category>
    <categoryItem>Aerial Photos</categoryItem>
  </category>

  <history>
    <change name="Jeff Anderson" date="2013-11-15">
      Original Version
    </change>
    <change name="Kristin Berry" date="2015-07-22">
       Added NaifStatus::CheckErrors() to see if any NAIF errors were signaled. References #2248.
    </change>
    <change name="Ian Humphrey" date="2017-09-15">
      Made sure that the minusApposJ array has all its values initialized. Caused CentOS7 app test to fail. References #4809.
    </change>
  </history>

    <groups>
    <group name="Input File">
      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          The filename of the input cube to have the interior/exterior orientation added
        </brief>
        <description>
          The input file which will have new group labels that indicate information about the aerial photograph.  The information provided by the user should be sufficient enough to
          create a functioning camera model so that the interior/exterior orientation information can be solved for in jigsaw..
        </description>
        <filter>*.cub</filter>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Observation / Exterior Orientation Information">
      <parameter name="DATETIME">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>Date and time of the obseration</brief>
        <description>
          Date and time in format ?????.   Important to get this information correct if plan to compute phase incidence and emission angles.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="ALTITUDE">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief>Estimated altitude</brief>
        <description>
          Estimated mean altitude above terrian in meters???????
        </description>
        <minimum inclusive="no">0</minimum>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="CENTERLAT">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief>Estimated latitude at center of image</brief>
        <description>
          ???
        </description>
        <minimum inclusive="yes">-90</minimum>
        <maximum inclusive="yes">90</maximum>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="CENTERLON">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief>Estimated longitude at center of image</brief>
        <description>
          ???
        </description>
        <minimum inclusive="yes">-360</minimum>
        <maximum inclusive="yes">360</maximum>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="SHAPEMODEL">
        <type>cube</type>
        <brief>Shape model of earth</brief>
        <description>
          ???
        </description>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Interior Orientation Information">
      <parameter name="FOCALLENGTH">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief>Camera focal length</brief>
        <description>
          Focal length of the camera in millimeters.  This is often referred to as the calibrated focal length in the camera calibration report. 
        </description>
        <minimum inclusive="no">0</minimum>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="FIDUCIALX">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>X position of the eight fiducials in the focal plane</brief>
        <description>
          ???
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="FIDUCIALY">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>Y position of the eight fiducials in the focal plane</brief>
        <description>
          ???
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="FIDUCIALSAMPLE">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>Sample positions of the eight fiducials in the image</brief>
        <description>
          ???
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="FIDUCIALLINE">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>Line positions of the eight fiducials in the image</brief>
        <description>
          ???
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="FIDUCIALTEMPLATE">
        <type>cube</type>
        <brief>Template cube containing average example of the eight fiducials</brief>
        <description>
          ???
        </description>
        <default><item>None</item></default>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="KCOEFS">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>Five radial optical distortion coefficients (k0-k4)</brief>
        <description>
          ???
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="PCOEFS">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>Four decentering distortion coefficients (p1-p4)</brief>
        <description>
          ???
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="XP">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief>X coordinate for calibrated principal point</brief>
        <description>
          ???
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="YP">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief>Y coordinate for calibrated principal point</brief>
        <description>
          ???
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="XIPP">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief>X coordinate for indicated principal point</brief>
        <description>
          ???
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="YIPP">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief>Y coordinate for indicated principal point</brief>
        <description>
          ???
        </description>
      </parameter>


    </group>

    <group name="Archive Information">
      <parameter name="ROLLNUMBER">
        <type>string</type>
        <default><item>Unknown</item></default>
        <brief>Roll number containing the image</brief>
        <description>
          The film roll number that contained this image. This can typically be found on the image. 
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="FRAMENUMBER">
        <type>string</type>
        <default><item>Unknown</item></default>
        <brief>Frame number of the image</brief>
        <description>
          The frame number on the roll. This can typically be found on the image. 
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="CAMERASN">
        <type>string</type>
        <default><item>Unknown</item></default>
        <brief>Camera serial number</brief>
        <description>
          The serial number of the camera.  Often found in the calibration report.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="LENSESN">
        <type>string</type>
        <default><item>Unknown</item></default>
        <brief>Lense serial number</brief>
        <description>
          The serial number of the lense.  Often found in the calibration report.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="CALREPORT">
        <type>string</type>
        <default><item>Unknown</item></default>
        <brief>Calibration report</brief>
        <description>
          The USGS Report No. that contains the information used to define the interior orientation including focal length, optical distortion coefficients, and fiducial mark locations.
        </description>
      </parameter>
    </group>
  </groups>

</application>
