<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="leisa2isis" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">
  
  <brief>
    Import New Horizons LEISA files into ISIS format
  </brief>
  <description>
    <p>
      This program will import FITS (Flexible Image Transport System) formatted files from the 
      New Horizons LEISA instument into the ISIS format. 
    </p>
  </description>
  
  <history>
    <change name="Kristin Berry" date="2014-08-28">
       Adapted from lorri2isis.
    </change>
    <change name="Kristin Berry" date="2015-06-15">
       Updated to read quality and error extensions in Band-interleaved (BIL) format (like the primary image) to work 
       with new format files. 
    </change>
    <change name="Kristin Berry" date="2015-06-22">
       Updated to add the option to change pixels in the input image to Nulls when the corresponding pixel in the QUALITY fits extension is  equal to 1, 2, or 8.
    </change>
  </history>

  <seeAlso>
    <applications>
      <item>fits2isis</item>
    </applications>
  </seeAlso>

  <category>
    <missionItem>New Horizons</missionItem>
  </category>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          A New Horizons LEISA FITS file to be converted to an ISIS cube
        </brief>
        <description>
          Use this parameter to select the filename of a New Horizons
          LEISA file to be converted to a cube. This is expected to be a FITS formatted file. 
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.fit
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TO">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Output ISIS cube file for the main image
        </brief>
        <description>
          The output cube file that will contain the New Horizons LEISA image in ISIS format. 
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="ERRORMAP">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <internalDefault>Optional</internalDefault>
        <brief>
          Output ISIS cube file for the error image
        </brief>
        <description>
          The output cube file that will containing the New Horizons LEISA error extension data 
          as an cube in ISIS format. The error extension image must be in the fifth FITS
          extension (i.e., sixth image).
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="QUALITY">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <internalDefault>Optional</internalDefault>
        <brief>
          Output ISIS cube file for the quality image
        </brief>
        <description>
          The output cube file that will containing the New Horizons LEISA quality extension data 
          as an cube in ISIS format. The quality extension image must be in the sixth FITS
          extension (i.e., seventh image).
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      </group>

      <group name="Options">
        <parameter name="REPLACE">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>FALSE</item></default>
        <brief>
          Replace flagged  pixels in the Data Quality extension with Nulls. 
        </brief>
        <description>
          Replace pixels in the imported LEISA image with NULLS if they are set to 1 (for High Speed Header, Bond Joint, or Bad Pixels), 2 (for Cosmic Ray) , or 8 (for user-identified bad pixels) in the Data Quality fits extension. 
        </description>
        </parameter>
      </group>
  </groups>

</application>
