<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="tagcams2isis" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">

  <brief>
    Import OSIRIS-REx TAGCAMS images into ISIS format
  </brief>
  <description>
    <p>
      This program will import FITS (Flexible Image Transport System) formatted 
      files from the OSIRIS-REx TAGCAMS instrument suite, NavCam, NFTCam and
      StowCam, into the ISIS3 cube format.
    </p>
    <p>
       The instruments use an Aptina MT9P031 1/2.5 inch 5MP Digital Image
       Sensor where the pixel array consists of a 2752-column by 2004-row
       matrix of pixels. The manufacturer sets the physical origin of 0, 0
       in the upper right corner of the entire array. The active array
       region consists of 2592-columns and 1944-rows. The NAV team will 
       typicall acquire all pixels in the pixel array (i.e., 2752x2004)
       during operations. Reference [4] describes the pixel array and
       details on operations and image acquisition. Note that this
       application will result in the proper image orientation consistent
       with the Kinetx system in the output ISIS cube image. The pixel
       (1,1) at the upper left the ISIS cube is consistent with the
       Kinetx system.
    </p>
    <p>
      All three instrument files can be imported by tagcams2isis but the StowCam
      is not properly converted to 3-color band cube. All instrument data will
      typically contain boundary data around the borders of the image. These
      data are comprised of dark pixels and several rows/columns of active
      boundary pixels to minimize edge effects. These boundary pixels would
      be removed by calibration processes, but at this time, there is no
      plan to implement radiometric calibration. As such, the default behaviour
      is to remove all boundary pixel data. See the REMOVECALPIXELS parameter.
    </p>
    <br/>
    <h2>References</h2>
    <br/>
    <cite>
      1) Bos, Brent, et al. (2018). Touch And Go Camera System (TAGCAMS) for the OSIRIS-REx
      Asteroid Sample Return Mission. Space Science Reviews. 214. 10.1007/s11214-017-0465-2. 
    </cite>
    <br/>
    <br/>
    <cite>
      2) Crombie, K, et al. (2017) OSIRIS-REx Touch-and-Go Camera Suite (TAGCAMS) Data Product Software 
      Interface Specification, UA-SIS-9.4.4-322, Rev. 3.0 (03/09/2017)
    </cite>
    <br/>
    <br/>
    <cite>
      3) Caplinger, M., et al. (2016) TAGCAMS Users Guide MSSS-TAG-REQ-4401 Final,
      Malin Space Science Systems, Inc.
    </cite>
    <br/>
    <br/>
    <cite>
      4) Aptina Imaging Corporation. (2005) 1/2.5-Inch 5Mp CMOS Digital Image Sensor (MT9P031),
      https://www.mouser.com/pdfdocs/Leopard_Imaging_Aptina_931LI5M03.pdf
    </cite>
    <br/>
    <br/>
  </description>

  <history>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2018-03-07">
      Original version
    </change>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2019-01-11">
      Add new FITS keywords to propagate into labels from input FITS file.
      Add parameter to remove calibration pixels from input image if they
      are present in the input (raw L0) image. Compute inital camera head
      temperature for use in camera model. Add SourceProductId keyword.
    </change>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2019-01-25">
      Updated parameters for conversion of raw camera head temperature from
      DNs to degrees Celsius as provided by NAV team.
    </change>
  </history>

  <seeAlso>
    <applications>
      <item>fits2isis</item>
    </applications>
  </seeAlso>

  <category>
    <missionItem>OSIRIS-REx</missionItem>
  </category>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          An OSIRIS-REx TAGCAMS FITS file to be converted to an ISIS cube
        </brief>
        <description>
          Use this parameter to select the filename of an OSIRIS-REx TAGCAMS
          file to be converted to an ISIS cube. This is expected to be a
          FITS formatted file.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.fits
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TO">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Output ISIS cube file
        </brief>
        <description>
          The output cube file that will contain the OSIRIS-REx TAGCAMS
          image in ISIS format.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Parameters">
      <parameter name="REMOVECALPIXELS">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <brief>Remove image boundary calibration pixels</brief>
        <description>
          <p>
            This parameter allows users to remove the boundary calibration
            pixels from the input image. Raw TAGVCAMS frames will have
            2752 samples and 2004 lines. The active region of the image
            is 2592 samples and 1944 lines.
          </p>
          <p>
            The border region of TAGCAMS images has 50 dark and 4 boundary
            pixels (54 total) at the top of the image. The bottom has 2 dark
            and 4 boundary pixels (6 total). The left side of the image has
            134 dark and 10 bounary pixels (144 total). The right side of
            the imagehas 10 dark and 6 boundary pixels (16 total).
            All of these pixels will be removed if this parameter is set
            to TRUE/YES.
          </p>
          <p>
            The OSIRIS-REx mission provides the TAGCAMs images in raw
            form so these boundaries are generally present in these images.
            Due to the lack of a calibration application in ISIS3, it is
            recommended these pixels be removed on import so that they
            are conveniently excluded for subsequent processing. For this
            reason, the default is (TRUE) to remove these pixels.
          </p>
        </description>
        <default><item>True</item></default> 
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="TARGET">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>Provide observation target if not in EDR</brief>
        <description>
            This parameter may be necessary as some FITS labels do not adequately defined
            the TARGET keyword in the labels.  OSIRIS-REx takes a very long trip to 
            finally arrive at Bennu orbit in 2018.  During cruise, several flybys occur.  The
            proper specification of the TARGET is critical to valid instantiation of
            ISIS camera models.  
        </description>
        <internalDefault>Label Value</internalDefault> 
      </parameter>
    </group>
  </groups>

</application>
