<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="isisexport" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">
  <brief>
    Convert from ISIS cube to another format
  </brief>

  <description>
    <p>
      NOTE: This program and the associated template files are incomplete. The documentation
      describes what the eventual intended capabilities are. Many capabiliteis are not implemented
      at this time.
    </p>
    <p>
      Exports an ISIS cube file to an external, non-ISIS, format. The intended output formats
      include PDS4, PDS3, and FITS compatible label and image files. The contents of the label file are
      generated using a template file. The template file name is generated automatically from the ISIS
      cube label information. If the template can not be found, the user must specify its name using
      the TEMPLATE parameter.
    </p>
    <p>
      The image file is generated from the input ISIS cube specified by the FROM parameter.
      The output image file will be a copy of the input ISIS cube with the image data stored in
      Band Sequential format.
    </p>
    <p>
      This application uses the <a href="https://pantor.github.io/inja">Inja templating engine</a>
      to render the template file. The input data from the cube and extra data sources
      is converted to JSON and then it is accessed via the Inja templating syntax.
      See the <a href="https://pantor.github.io/inja">Inja documentation</a> for the full template
      syntax. The data from the label of the input cube is accessible under "MainLabel",
      the data from the originally ingested PVL or XML label stored on the input cube is accessible
      under "OriginalLabel",
      and the extra data is accessible under "ExtraPvl", "ExtraXml", and "ExtraJson".
    </p>
  </description>

  <category>
    <categoryItem>Import and Export</categoryItem>
  </category>

  <history>
    <change name="Stuart Sides" date="2021-01-03">
      Original version
    </change>
  </history>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input cube
        </brief>
        <description>
          This is the input cube that will be exported.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TEMPLATE">
        <type>filename</type>
        <internalDefault>None</internalDefault>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input template
        </brief>
        <description>
          The file name of the input template. This file contains "inja" compatible
          template syntax. The data used to replace the
          template elements comes from the ISIS cube label, the original label
          (PDS3, FITS, PDS4), and user specified input PVL, XML, or JSON files.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TO">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Output label file name
        </brief>
        <description>
          The output file name of the exported label. The output image name will be derived from this
          parameter by removing the last extension and adding an appropriate file extension.
        </description>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Data">
      <parameter name="DATA">
        <type>filename</type>
        <internalDefault>None</internalDefault>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Output JSON data
        </brief>
        <description>
          The output file name to store the template data source. This is a dump of the JSON data used
          by the template engine to fill in the template elements. It is a combination of the ISIS
          main cube lable, the original lable, and any other data sources supplied. The purpose of this
          parameter is for debugging the templates.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="EXTRAPVL">
        <type>filename</type>
        <internalDefault>None</internalDefault>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Extra PVL data
        </brief>
        <description>
          The PVL data contained in the file(s) specified by this parameter will
          be added to the template data source under ExtraPvl. If multiple PVL files
          are specified, then they will be merged together.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="EXTRAXML">
        <type>filename</type>
        <internalDefault>None</internalDefault>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Extra XML data
        </brief>
        <description>
          The XML data contained in the file(s) specified by this parameter will
          be added to the template data source under ExtraXml. If multiple XML files
          are specified, then they will be merged together.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="EXTRAJSON">
        <type>filename</type>
        <internalDefault>None</internalDefault>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Extra JSON data
        </brief>
        <description>
          The JSON data contained in the file(s) specified by this parameter will
          be added to the template data source under ExtraJson. If multiple JSON files
          are specified, then they will be merged together.
        </description>
      </parameter>
    </group>
  </groups>
</application>
