<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="pds2hideal" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">
  <brief>
      Reimport an exported hirise PDS product to an Isis Ideal camera.
  </brief>

  <description>
    <pre>
       The purpose oof this program is to re-import exported HiRISE Ideal camera cubes
       into Isis. The input label for this program should be a PDS label containing the
       location of the exported image and table files.

       This application requires the following files:
       <ul>
         <li>PDS label file</li>
         <li>PDS image file</li>
         <li>PDS binary table file containing the INSTRUMENT_POINTING_TABLE</li>
         <li>PDS binary table file containing the INSTRUMENT_POSITION_TABLE</li>
         <li>PDS binary table file containing the BODY_ROTATION_TABLE</li>
         <li>PDS binary table file containing the SUN_POSITION_TABLE</li>
       </ul>

      When imported, the Spice table data will be attached to the cube.
    </pre>
  </description>

  <category>
    <missionItem>Mars Reconnaissance Orbiter</missionItem>
  </category>

  <history>
    <change name="Jeannie Backer" date="2012-11-21">
      Original Version of application pds2hideal. Fixes #700.
    </change>
  </history>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input file containing the PDS label.
        </brief>
        <description>
          Name of the file containing the labels of the input PDS image.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.img *.lbl
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TO">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Name of the output file to contain the imported Isis cube.
        </brief>
        <description>
          The name of the output file.  This file will contain the imported
          Isis HiRISE Ideal cube and the related Spice Tables.
        </description>
        <pixelType>signedWord</pixelType>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="SHAPEMODELPATH">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>
          String containing the location of the ShapeModel file of the original
          Isis cube that was exported to PDS.
        </brief>
        <description>
          This parameter should contain the directory path of the ShapeModel
          file. This path will be added to the ShapeModel keyword in the
          Kernels Group of the output cube. It should be the same path as shown
          in the original Isis cube before it was exported to the PDS product.
        </description>
        <default>
          <item>
            $base/dems/
          </item>
        </default>
      </parameter>
      </group>
  </groups>

</application>
