<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="socetlinescankeywords" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">
  <brief>
    Create the Line Scanner Sensor section of a SOCET Set Line Scanner support file
  </brief>

  <description>
    This is an ISIS to SOCET Set (trademark BAE Systems) translation program for Line Scanner
    images.  It calculates keyword values specific to SOCET Set's USGSAstro Line Scanner sensor
    model and generates the USGSAstro Line Scanner section of a SOCET Set Support file for input
    to the USGSAstro SOCET Set program 'import_pushbroom.' <br/>
    <br/>
    <i>With the exception of HiRISE jitter corrected images, the input cube must be a "level 1"
    image <b>with SPICE data attached to the label</b> (see spiceinit).</i>  HiRISE jitter
    corrected images (see hijitter) do not have Spacecraft Position Kernel (SPK) data attached
    to the label, so these are handled as a special case in the program.<br/>
    <br/>
    The following are supported instruments and derived products:
    <pre>
       MRO-HiRISE
       MRO-HiRISE IDEAL (i.e., noproj'ed images)
       MRO-HiRISE IDEAL Jitter Corrected (i.e., hijitter'ed images)
       MRO-CTX
       LRO-NACL
       LRO-NACR
<!--
       MEX-HRSC
       MGS-MOC
-->
    </pre>
  </description>

  <category>
    <categoryItem>SOCET Set Translation</categoryItem>
  </category>

    <seeAlso>
    <applications>
      <item>spiceinit</item>
      <item>hijitter</item>
    </applications>
  </seeAlso>

  <history>
    <change name="E. Howington-Kraus" date="2008-10-23">
      Original version
    </change>
    <change name="K. Edmundson" date="2011-05-13">
      Added NADIR_CENTER_TIME parameter
    </change>
    <change name="E. Howington-Kraus" date="2011-08-04">
      Changed default NADIR_CENTER_TIME from None to 0.0
    </change>
    <change name="E. Howington-Kraus" date="2012-04-26">
      Added MOUNT_ANG_TBL option
    </change>
    <change name="O. Thomas" date="2012-08-23">
      Renamed program from calc_pushbroom_keywords to socetlinescankeywords, added quaternions, made
      changes from SOCET Set Generic Pushbroom sensor model to the USGSAsro Line Scanner sensor
      model, and removed the MOUNT_ANG_TBL option.  Started modifications to meet ISIS coding
      standards.
    </change>
    <change name="E. Howington-Kraus" date="2013-02-20">
      Completed modifications to meet ISIS coding standards for formal installation into ISIS.
      Added support for HiRISE jitter-corrected images created at U of A.  Added check for needed
      SPICE data (blobs) attached to the cube label. Renamed parameter PUSHKEY to TO.  Temporarily
      removed support for MEX-HSRC and MGS-MOC sensors until they are tested and working under the
      SOCET Set USGSAstro Line Scanner sensor model.  References #1490.
    </change>
    <change name="E. Howington-Kraus" date="2013-06-21">
      Modified to (1) generate ephemeris points and quaternions at a closer time interval if the
      spacing of the attached SPICE data are too sparse for the SOCET Set USGSAstro Line Scanner
      sensor model; (2) increase the precision of the output SOCET Set keyword values; (3) redefine
      the pixel-location of the input image's center ephemeris time, and (4) compute spacecraft
      velocity values instead of using SPICE velocity data blobs.  Fixes #1672.
    </change>
    <change name="Jesse Mapel" date="2018-03-23">
      Added SEMI_MAJOR_AXIS and ECCENTRICITY to the output. Fixes #5362.
    </change>
  </history>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Filename of a cube
        </brief>
        <description>
          Level 1 Input Line Scanner cube with SPICE data attached. Supported instruments and
          derived products are MRO-HiRISE, MRO-HiRISE IDEAL, MRO-HiRISE IDEAL Jitter Corrected,
          MRO-CTX, LRO-NACL, and LRO-NACR.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TO">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <brief>SOCET Set Support file keywords</brief>
        <internalDefault>None</internalDefault>
        <description>
          Output text file of the SOCET Set USGSAstro Line Scaner section of a SOCET Set support
          file. This output file is one of the input files to USGSAstro SOCET Set program
          'import_pushbroom.'
        </description>
      </parameter>

<!--
Commented this parameter out until HRSC is supported in SS
      <parameter name="HRSC_NADIRCENTERTIME">
        <brief>Ephemeris time at center of HRSC nadir image
        </brief>
        <description>
          Ephemeris time at center of HRSC nadir image.  This is
          used so that the SOCET Set keyword T0_CENTER value references
          the same absolute ephemeris time in an HRSC image set.
        </description>
        <type>double</type>
        <default><item>0.0</item></default>
      </parameter>
-->
    </group>
  </groups>
</application>
