<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="kaguyami2isis" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">

  <brief>Import PDS formatted Kaguya Multiband Imager (MI) image into Isis format</brief>

  <description>
    <p>
      This program will import a PDS formatted Kaguya MI VIS and NIR level 1 (EDR) or level 2B2
      image into an Isis cube.
    </p>
    <p>
      The user is given the option to specify incoming <def link="Special Pixels">special pixel</def>
      values in the PDS file so that they can be assigned equivalent values for special pixels
      in ISIS. The order of precedence for special pixels in ISIS from highest to
      lowest priority is the following:
      <blockquote>
      <ol>
        <li><def>NULL</def></li>
        <li><def>HRS</def></li>
        <li><def>LRS</def></li>
        <li><def>HIS</def></li>
        <li><def>LIS</def></li>
      </ol>
      </blockquote>
      If any incoming <def link="Digital Number">pixel value</def> falls within
      two different special pixel types, the <def link="Special Pixel">special
      pixel</def> with the higher priority is assigned.  The user may also
      specify a range of pixel values to be assigned to the different special pixels.
      If the range of pixel values defined by the user for the different special
      pixels overlap, the special pixel with the highest priority is assigned.  For
      example, if NULLMIN=0.0, NULLMAX=3.0, LISMIN=3.0, and LISMAX=5.0, the actual
      raw value 3.0 can be assigned as a NULL or LIS, but is translated to NULL because
      NULL has a higher priority than LIS.  The conversion of images from ISIS2 to
      ISIS follows the same rules as PDS images, except that the label information
      is propagated to the output file.
    </p>
    <p>
      The user should note that the Kaguya MI data files will most likely contain
      a SCALING_FACTOR that is not equal to 1.0. The SCALING_FACTOR is used to scale
      the pixel values in the PDS file before they are imported to the ISIS file.
      Before the scaling is done on the pixel values, the special pixel conversions
      will be applied first. After the special pixel conversions are done, then the
      scaling factor is applied to those pixels that don't have special pixel values.
      As a result, you may get results that you weren't expecting.
    </p>
  </description>

  <history>
    <change name="Janet Barrett" date="2011-05-09">
      Original version
    </change>
    <change name="Janet Barrett" date="2012-05-02">
      At this time, there is no camera model for the Kaguya MI data. In order to
      be able to perform photometry on the Kaguya MI data, the SubSolarLongitude
      and SubSolarLatitude information needed to be calculated. These calculations
      are done by using the aaplus library developed by P J Naughter at
      http://www.naughter.com. This library can only be distributed in binary form,
      so it has to stay in the local directory of ISIS where it will not be
      distributed. The formulae used to do the calculations were taken from Meeus
      "Astronomical Algorithms" (1st Ed). This code can be removed as soon as a camera
      model is available for the Kaguya MI camera. The start and stop times for these
      images are very close, so the start time is used to calculate the SubSolar lat/lon
      information.
    </change>
    <change name="Lynn Weller" date="2012-01-23">
      Application category name changed from Import and Export to Kaguya.  Fixes mantis ticket #951.
    </change>
    <change name="Janet Barrett" date="2013-06-13">
      Fixed code so that it sets the NaifFrameCode appropriately according to the base band specified
      in the labels.  Fixes mantis tickets #1167 and #1680.
    </change>
    <change name="Janet Barrett" date="2014-02-10">
      Added parameters (SETNULLRANGE, SETHRSRANGE, SETHISRANGE, ETLRSRANGE, SETLISRANGE)
      to allow the user to specify special pixel values. Fixes #2033.
    </change>
    <change name="Adam Paqeutte" date="2016-08-04">
      Added a new error message informing the user that the file they are using is not compatible with
      kaguyami2isis. Fixes #2358.
    </change>
    <change name="Kaitlyn Lee" date="2020-03-31">
      Updated documentation to include level 2B2 support.
    </change>
  </history>

  <category>
    <missionItem>Kaguya</missionItem>
  </category>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input PDS formatted Kaguya MI VIS or NIR file
        </brief>
        <description>
          Use this parameter to select the Kaguya MI VIS or
	        NIR level 1 or level 2B2 filename. This file must contain the PDS labels.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.img *.IMG *.lbl *.LBL
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TO">
         <type>cube</type>
         <fileMode>output</fileMode>
         <brief>
           Output Isis cube
         </brief>
         <description>
           Use this parameter to select the output filename
         </description>
         <filter>
           *.cub
         </filter>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Special Pixels">
      <parameter name="SETNULLRANGE">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default>
          <item>NO</item>
        </default>
        <brief>Option to convert pixel values to NULL</brief>
        <description>
          If this option is set to "yes" or "true", a range of input raw pixels
          defined by the NULLMIN and NULLMAX parameters are converted to <def>NULL</def>
          pixels.  All other valid pixels that do not fall within the ranges
          specified for LIS, LRS, HIS, and HRS pixels are transferred to the output file
          unchanged.  If the <def link="Bit Type">bit type</def> of the input
          file is changed, the NULL and HRS <def link="Special Pixels">special
          pixels</def> may be incorrectly set to valid pixel values.  For example,
          if a raw 8-bit file is output to 16 or 32-bit, the pixel values "0"
          and "255" may be converted to actual values instead of retaining the
          special pixel property.  If the output file remains as 8-bit, then "0"
          stays as NULL and "255" stays as HRS.
        </description>
        <inclusions>
          <item>NULLMIN</item>
          <item>NULLMAX</item>
        </inclusions>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="NULLMIN">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief> Minimum value for NULL</brief>
        <description>
          Minimum pixel value to set to <def>NULL</def>.  All values greater than or equal to
          NULLMIN and less than or equal to NULLMAX are converted to NULL.
        </description>
        <inclusions>
          <item>SETNULLRANGE</item>
        </inclusions>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="NULLMAX">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief> Maximum value for NULL </brief>
        <description>
          Maximum pixel value to set to <def>NULL</def>.  All values greater than or equal to
          NULLMIN and less than or equal to NULLMAX are converted to NULL.
        </description>
        <inclusions>
          <item>SETNULLRANGE</item>
        </inclusions>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="SETHRSRANGE">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default>
          <item>NO</item>
        </default>
        <brief>Option to convert pixel values to HRS</brief>
        <description>
          If this option is set to "yes" or "true", a range of input raw pixels
          defined by the HRSMIN and HRSMAX parameters are converted to HRS
          pixels.  All other valid pixels that do not fall within the ranges
          specified for LIS, LRS, HIS, and NULL pixels are transferred to the output file
          unchanged.  If the <def link="Bit Type">bit type</def> of the input
          file is changed, the NULL and HRS <def link="Special Pixels">special
          pixels</def> may be incorrectly set to valid pixel values.  For example,
          if a raw 8-bit file is output to 16 or 32-bit, the pixel values "0"
          and "255" may be converted to actual values instead of retaining the
          special pixel property.  If the output file remains as 8-bit, then "0"
          stays as NULL and "255" stays as HRS.
        </description>
        <inclusions>
          <item>HRSMIN</item>
          <item>HRSMAX</item>
        </inclusions>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="HRSMIN">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief> Minimum value for HRS</brief>
        <description>
          Minimum pixel value to set to <def>HRS</def>.  All values greater than or equal to
          HRSMIN and less than or equal to HRSMAX are converted to HRS.
        </description>
        <inclusions>
          <item>SETHRSRANGE</item>
        </inclusions>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="HRSMAX">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief> Maximum value for HRS</brief>
        <description>
          Maximum pixel value to set to <def>HRS</def>.  All values greater than or equal to
          HRSMIN and less than or equal to HRSMAX are converted to HRS.
        </description>
        <inclusions>
          <item>SETHRSRANGE</item>
        </inclusions>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="SETHISRANGE">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default>
          <item>NO</item>
        </default>
        <brief>Option to convert pixel values to HIS</brief>
        <description>
          If this option is set to "yes" or "true", a range of input raw pixels
          defined by the HISMIN and HISMAX parameters are converted to HIS
          pixels.  All other valid pixels that do not fall within the ranges
          specified for LIS, LRS, HRS, and NULL pixels are transferred to the
          output file unchanged.
        </description>
        <inclusions>
          <item>HISMIN</item>
          <item>HISMAX</item>
        </inclusions>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="HISMIN">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief> Minimum value for HIS</brief>
        <description>
          Minimum pixel value to set to <def>HIS</def>.  All values greater than or equal to
          HISMIN and less than or equal to HISMAX are converted to HIS.
        </description>
        <inclusions>
          <item>SETHISRANGE</item>
        </inclusions>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="HISMAX">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief> Maximum value for HIS</brief>
        <description>
          Maximum pixel value to set to <def>HIS</def>.  All values greater than or equal to
          HISMIN and less than or equal to HISMAX are converted to HIS.
        </description>
        <inclusions>
          <item>SETHISRANGE</item>
        </inclusions>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="SETLRSRANGE">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default>
          <item>NO</item>
        </default>
        <brief>Option to convert pixel values to LRS</brief>
        <description>
          If this option is set to "yes" or "true", a range of input raw pixels
          defined by the LRSMIN and LRSMAX parameters are converted to LRS
          pixels.  All other valid pixels that do not fall within the ranges
          specified for LIS, HIS, HRS, and NULL pixels are transferred to the
          output file unchanged.
        </description>
        <inclusions>
          <item>LRSMIN</item>
          <item>LRSMAX</item>
        </inclusions>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="LRSMIN">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief> Minimum value for LRS</brief>
        <description>
          Minimum pixel value to set to <def>LRS</def>.  All values greater than or equal to
          LRSMIN and less than or equal to LRSMAX are converted to LRS.
        </description>
        <inclusions>
          <item>SETLRSRANGE</item>
        </inclusions>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="LRSMAX">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief> Maximum value for LRS </brief>
        <description>
          Maximum pixel value to set to <def>LRS</def>.  All values greater than or equal to
          LRSMIN and less than or equal to LRSMAX are converted to LRS.
        </description>
        <inclusions>
          <item>SETLRSRANGE</item>
        </inclusions>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="SETLISRANGE">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default>
          <item>NO</item>
        </default>
        <brief>Option to convert pixel values to LIS</brief>
        <description>
          If this option is set to "yes" or "true", a range of input raw pixels
          defined by the LISMIN and LISMAX parameters are converted to LIS
          pixels.  All other valid pixels that do not fall within the ranges
          specified for LRS, HIS, HRS, and NULL pixels are transferred to the
          output file unchanged.
        </description>
        <inclusions>
          <item>LISMIN</item>
          <item>LISMAX</item>
        </inclusions>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="LISMIN">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief> Minimum value for LIS </brief>
        <description>
          Minimum pixel value to set to <def>LIS</def>.  All values greater than or equal to
          LISMIN and less than or equal to LISMAX are converted to LIS.
        </description>
        <inclusions>
          <item>SETLISRANGE</item>
        </inclusions>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="LISMAX">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief> Maximum value for LIS </brief>
        <description>
          Maximum pixel value to set to <def>LIS</def>.  All values greater than or equal to
          LISMIN and less than or equal to LISMAX are converted to LIS.
        </description>
        <inclusions>
          <item>SETLISRANGE</item>
        </inclusions>
      </parameter>
    </group>
  </groups>
</application>
