<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="lromakeflat" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">

  <brief>
    Create a flat-field image for line-scan, push-frame, and framing instruments
  </brief>

  <description>
    <p>
      This program creates flat-field images for line scan, push frame, and framing instruments.
      All input cubes should have the same number of samples; any images in the list that do not
      have the same number of samples as the first image will not be used.  The names of the cube
      files used to create the flat-field image must be entered using an ASCII file (FROMLIST) with
      one filename per line (any line beginning with a '#' or '//' is treated as a comment).  The
      specific equation for each camera type is below.
    </p>
    <ul>
      <li>Line Scan</li>
        <p>
          A frame is a NUMLINES line section of data. The equation for the final single line, single
          band, flat field file is:
         <br />
          Mean Calculation:
         <br />
         Sum( Sum(FrameColumn) / Average(Frame) * ValidPixels(FrameColumn) ) /
         TotalColumnValidPixels
         <br />
          Median Calculation:
         <br />
          Median(PixelColumn(ValidPixel / Average(Frame)))
        </p>

      <li>Push Frame</li>
        <p>
          Mean Calculation:
          <br />
          The equation for the final single framelet, single band flat field file is:<br /> Average(
          PixelInFramelet1, PixelInFramelet2, PixelInFramelet3, ... )
          <br />
          Median Calculation:
          <br />
          Median(PixelColumn(ValidPixel / Average(Frame)))
        </p>
      <li>Framing</li>
        <p>
          Mean Calculation:
          <br />
          The equation for the final single framelet, single band flat field file is:<br /> Average(
          PixelInCube1, PixelInCube2, PixelInCube3, ... )
          <br />
          Median Calculation:
          <br />
          Median(PixelColumn(ValidPixel / Average(Frame)))
        </p>
    </ul>
    <p>
      <b>Warning: This program creates potentially large temporary files</b>
    </p>
  </description>

  <history>
    <change name="Victor Silva" date="2016-09-12">
      Original version, Adapted from Isis version of makeflat.
    </change>
  </history>

  <category>
    <categoryItem>Math and Statistics</categoryItem>
    <categoryItem>Radiometric and Photometric Correction</categoryItem>
  </category>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROMLIST">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          List of input cubes
        </brief>
        <description>
          Use this parameter to select the file which contains a list of
          cube filenames to be used to create the flat file.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.lis
        </filter>
     </parameter>

      <parameter name="TO">
        <type>cube</type>
        <pixelType>real</pixelType>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Output name prepended to flat field output cubes
        </brief>
        <description>
         Output prefix of the flat field cube's name
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="EXCLUDE">
        <type>filename</type>
        <internalDefault>None</internalDefault>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Output PVL-formatted file of all excluded files and sections of data
        </brief>
        <description>
         Output PVL-formatted file of all excluded files and sections of data.
        </description>
      </parameter>
    </group>
    <group name="Camera Options">
      <parameter name="IMAGETYPE">
        <type>string</type>
        <default><item>LINESCAN</item></default>
        <brief>
          This is the type of camera which took the image.
        </brief>
        <description>
          The type of camera that captured the input image.
        </description>
        <list>
          <option value="LINESCAN">
            <brief>Line scan camera</brief>
            <description>
              Line scan cameras collect an image a single line of data at a time. This option makes
              the flat field a single line of data.
            </description>
            <inclusions>
              <item>NUMLINES</item>
            </inclusions>
            <exclusions>
              <item>FRAMELETHEIGHT</item>
              <item>HEIGHT_LINES</item>
            </exclusions>
          </option>
          <option value="PUSHFRAME">
            <brief>Push frame camera</brief>
            <description>
              Push frame cameras collect multiple lines, one framelet, of data at once. This
              option makes the flat field a single framelet of data.
            </description>
            <inclusions>
              <item>FRAMELETHEIGHT</item>
            </inclusions>
            <exclusions>
              <item>NUMLINES</item>
              <item>HEIGHT_LINES</item>
            </exclusions>
          </option>
          <option value="FRAMING" >
            <brief>Framing camera</brief>
            <description>
              Framing cameras collect an entire cube of data at once. This option makes the
              flat field the size of one of the input images.
            </description>
            <exclusions>
              <item>NUMLINES</item>
              <item>FRAMELETHEIGHT</item>
            </exclusions>
          </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="NUMLINES">
        <type>integer</type>
        <brief>
          This is the number of lines to consider when doing statistics
        </brief>
        <description>
          A single line often does not have enough data in it to perform good tolerance
          calculations. The tolerance calculations will be performed on this many lines as
          a time, and if found to be invalid, this many lines will be excluded from the output
          flat file calculations at a time.
        </description>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="FRAMELETHEIGHT">
        <type>integer</type>
        <brief>
          This is the height of each framelet in the image.
        </brief>
        <description>
          Push frame images consist of framelets. The framelet size needs to be
          known in order to make a flat field file for a push frame camera.
        </description>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Processing Options">
      <parameter name="NORMALIZATION">
        <type>string</type>
        <default><item>NO</item></default>
        <brief>
          Include Normalization Step
        </brief>
        <description>
          If this pre-processing step was not done prior, Makeflat will normalize each pixel by the frame's mean in
          order to normalize to 1. You can select image dimensions (height and width in pixels) to use when calculating frame mean.
        </description>
        <list>
          <option value="YES">
            <brief>
              The normalization process will be applied.
            </brief>
            <description>
              The normalization process will be applied to each pixel location
              prior to stacking.
            </description>
            <inclusions>
              <item>WIDTH_PIXELS</item>
              <item>HEIGHT_LINES</item>
            </inclusions>
          </option>
          <option value="NO">
            <brief>
              The normalization process will not be applied.
            </brief>
            <description>
              Each pixel location will not be normalized prior to stacking.
            </description>
            <exclusions>
              <item>WIDTH_PIXELS</item>
              <item>HEIGHT_LINES</item>
            </exclusions>
          </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="STDEVTOL">
        <type>double</type>
        <default><item>2</item></default>
        <brief>
          This is the number of standard deviations to use as outlier boundary.
        </brief>
        <description>
          Any pixel column averages beyond this boundary will be excluded. The default value is
          +- 1 standard deviation. Any pixel column average within this range will be included.
        </description>
      </parameter>
    </group>
    <group name="Normalization Options">
      <parameter name="WIDTH_PIXELS">
        <type>integer</type>
        <default><item>0</item></default>
        <brief>
          Width in Pixels from center of image to use for normalization
        </brief>
        <description>
          If value is left at zero, pixels will be normalized using entire width frame of image.
        </description>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="HEIGHT_LINES">
        <type>integer</type>
        <default><item>0</item></default>
        <brief>
          Height in Lines from center of image to use for normalization
        </brief>
        <description>
          If LINESCAN, height will always equal 1. If value is left at zero and is not LINESCAN,
          pixels will be normalized using entire frame height of image.
        </description>
      </parameter>
    </group>
  </groups>
</application>
