<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="hyb1pds4gen" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">

  <brief>
    Convert Hayabusa1 image from from ISIS cube to PDS4 format
  </brief>

  <description>
   This programs exports an ISIS Haybusa cube to a PDS4 product.
   If available, Instrument and  Mapping information will be written to the detached
   output PDS4 formatted xml label file.
    <p>
       Note that not all require keyword values in the generated PDS4 labels can be determined automatically
       by ISIS. Some must be updated by the user (by opening up the xml label output by this
       application and editing it with a text editor) for the generated label to be PDS4 compliant.
       The values UNK (unknown) and TBD (to be determined) are used as placeholders in
       the generated label.
       TBD are PDS4 required values and must be replaced by the user for the output label to be PDS4 compliant.
       Some of these TBDs can only be replaced with one of several specific enumerated values to meet compliancy.
       These possible values can be found in the
       <a href="https://pds.jpl.nasa.gov/pds4/doc/im/current/index_1900.html">PDS4 Information Model Specification</a>
       in the Value/Class column of the table for the associated tag or in the index at the end of the document.
       Searching this page for the name of the field you need to determine a value for is recommended.
    </p>

    <p>
      For example: For a cube with map-projected data, ISIS will populate planar_coordinate
      encoding_method with a value on its own, but if it did not and instead had "TBD", we would find at
      <a href="https://pds.jpl.nasa.gov/pds4/doc/im/current/index_1900.html#attribute_cart_planar_coordinate_information_cart_planar_coordinate_encoding_method">planar_coordinate_coding_method</a>
      that there are 3 possible values: 'Coordinate Pair', 'Distance and Bearing', 'Row and Column'.
    </p>

    <p>
      Not everything is in the
      <a href="https://pds.jpl.nasa.gov/pds4/doc/im/current/index_1900.html">PDS4 Information Model Specification</a>
       at this time, so if the information about a tag is not in there, it may be necessary to find
        the options in the appropriate schematron file (.sch) available at:
        <a href="https://pds.jpl.nasa.gov/pds4/schema/released/">PDS4 Released Schema</a>.
        For the previous example, the same information can be found in the
        <a href="https://pds.jpl.nasa.gov/pds4/cart/v1/PDS4_CART_1700.sch">PDS4 Cartography schematron file </a>.
    </p>

    <p>
      UNK  is used as a placeholder if any value can be used and still be a valid PDS4-formatted
      xml header. UNKs can, but are not required to be, replaced by the user with
      better information.
    </p>

  </description>

  <category>
    <categoryItem>Import and Export</categoryItem>
  </category>


  <history>
    <change name="Jeannie Backer" date="2018-05-20">
      Original version
    </change>
  </history>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input cube to be converted
        </brief>
        <description>
          The cube to be converted to pds format.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TO">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Output pds image
        </brief>
        <description>
          The resulting pds file. For PDS4, a detached label of the same name with the file extension .xml
          will be created in the same directory.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.img
        </filter>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Keywords">
      <parameter name="PDS4LOGICALIDENTIFIER">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>
          String value for the PDS4 logical_identifier keyword.
        </brief>
        <description>
          This value is used to set the required PDS4 value, logical_identifier. It should be a
          6-part colon separated string of the form
          <b>urn:space_agency:archiving_agency:pds_approved_bundle_id:pds_approved_collection_id:product_id</b>.
          Note that space_agency is generally "nasa" and archiving_agency is generally "pds".
        </description>
      </parameter>
    </group>

  </groups>

</application>
