<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="lrolola2isis" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
   xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">

  <brief>
    Imports LIDAR data from LRO LOLA instrument.
  </brief>

  <description>
    <p>
      Imports LIDAR data from LRO LOLA instrument.
    </p>

  </description>

  <history>
    <change name="Makayla Shepherd and Tyler Wilson" date="2017-01-29">
      Original version
    </change>
    <change name="Debbie Cook" date="2018-03-19">
      Added items that will be needed to bundle adjust:  new point keyword
      simultaneousImages that is an array of serial numbers of the measures
      on images taken simultaneously with the Lidar data, a threshold to
      screen measures that are off the image, and both point (lat/lon/radius)
      and range constraints.  Also added point type and set it to Constrained.
    </change>
    <change name="Debbie Cook" date="2018-04-16">
      Fixed the case where a Lidar point has no simultaneous measures on
      any images in the input list.  In this case do not write out the
      point because it has no constraints.  In the future, the
      functionality may change to include points without simultaneous
      measures in the bundle adjustment.  References #5343.
    </change>
    <change name="Ken Edmundson" date="2018-06-20">
      Changed call to Camera::SetGround to use the SurfacePoint with the input
      lidar point coordinates. Ensures use of lidar point radius instead of the
      local radius.
    </change>
    <change name="Ken Edmundson" date="2018-06-25">
      Changed internal default for lidar coordinate a priori uncertainties to "none", allowing FREE
      lidar points.
      </change>
    <change name="Debbie A Cook" date="2019-02-23">
      Added new file OUTPUTTYPE=TEST, to be used strictly for testing.
      This option does a SLOW sort on the output data. The resulting output file
      is sorted by pointID, which allows testing software to compare
      output with truth data.  References #5343.
      </change>
    <change name="Debbie A Cook" date="2019-03-11">
      Added new input parameter FROMLIST to allow entering multiple input
      Lidar CSV files.  All input points are written out into a single Lidar data 
      file.  References #5343.
      </change>
  </history>

  <category>
    <missionItem>Lunar Reconnaissance Orbiter</missionItem>
  </category>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input LOLA Lidar RDR data in CSV format
        </brief>
        <description>
          This file is downloaded from Washington University at
          
          "https://ode.rsl.wustl.edu/moon/indextools.aspx?displaypage=lolardr"
          
          It contains altimetry readings organized along the spacecraft orbit track.
          
        </description>
        <exclusions>
           <item>FROMLIST</item>
        </exclusions>
        <filter>
          *.csv
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="FROMLIST">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <internalDefault>None</internalDefault>
        <brief>
          Input LOLA Lidar CSV file list from which to generate the Lidar control point file
        </brief>
        <description>
          This file contains a list of CSV files of LOLA Lidar RDR  that will be used to generate 
          an Isis Lidar control point file.  Each file in FROMLIST is expected to be a CSV with
          LOLA Lidar RDR data. See FROM for more information on the data.
        </description>
        <exclusions>
           <item>FROM</item>
        </exclusions>
        <filter>
          *.lis
        </filter>
      </parameter>
      
      <parameter name="CUBES">
         <type>filename</type>
         <fileMode>input</fileMode>
         <brief>
           List with cubes to add as measures to the lidar points.
         </brief>
         <filter>
           *.lis
         </filter>
       </parameter>
       <parameter name="TO">
          <type>filename</type>
          <fileMode>output</fileMode>
          <brief>
            Output lidar point data 
          </brief>
        </parameter>
        <parameter name="OUTPUTTYPE">
          <type>string</type>
          <description>
            The output type, either binary or json.
          </description>
          <default><item>BINARY</item></default>
          <list>
            <option value="BINARY">
              <brief> Binary output file (.dat)</brief>
            </option>
            <option value="JSON">
              <brief> JSON output file (.json)</brief>
            </option>
            <option value="TEST">
              <brief> DO NOT USE (only for tests) ordered JSON output file (.json) </brief>
            </option>
          </list>
        </parameter>
    </group>
    <group name="Processing Parameters">
        <parameter name="POINTID">
          <type>string</type>
          <brief>
            The pattern to be used to create point ids.
          </brief>
          <description>
            <p>
              This string will be used to create unique IDs for each control
              point created by this program. The string must contain a
              single series
              of question marks ("?"). For example: "VallesMarineris????"
            </p>
            <p>
              The question marks will be replaced
              with a number beginning with zero and incremented by one each time
              a new control point is created. The example above would cause the
              first control point to have an ID of "VallesMarineris0000", the
              second ID would be "VallesMarineris0001" and so on.
              The maximum number of new control points for this example would be
              10000 with the final ID being "VallesMarineris9999".
            </p>
            <p>
              Note: Make sure there are enough "?"s for all the control
              points that might be created during this run. If all the possible
              point IDs are exhausted the program will exit with an error, and 
              will not produce an output control network file. 
            </p>
            <p>
              Examples of POINTID:
            </p>
            <ul>
              <li>POINTID="JohnDoe?????"</li>
              <li>POINTID="Quad1_????></li>
              <li>POINTID="JD_???_test1"</li>
            </ul>
          </description>
        </parameter>
        <parameter name="THRESHOLD">
        <type>double</type>
        <minimum inclusive="yes">0</minimum>
        <default>
          <item>0.0</item>
        </default>
          <brief>
            The threshold allowed for points to be off the image in pixels..
          </brief>
          <description>
            <p>
              This value is used to screen measures during back projection.
              If a Lidar point maps into an image with coordinates outside
              of the valid pixel range extended by the threshold value, it
              will be rejected as a measure for that point.
            </p>
          </description>
        </parameter>            
    </group>
    <group name="Point Uncertainties">
        <parameter name="POINT_RANGE_SIGMA">
          <brief> Range uncertainty for all points (meters)</brief>
          <description>
            This value will be used as the range uncertainty
            for all points.  Units are meters.
          </description>
          <type>double</type>
          <internalDefault>none</internalDefault>
          <minimum inclusive="yes">0</minimum>
        </parameter>

        <parameter name="POINT_LATITUDE_SIGMA">
         <brief> Latitude uncertainty for all points (meters)</brief>
         <description>
           This value will be used as the latitude uncertainty
           for all points.  Units are meters.
         </description>
         <type>double</type>
         <internalDefault>none</internalDefault>
         <minimum inclusive="yes">0</minimum>
        </parameter>
  
        <parameter name="POINT_LONGITUDE_SIGMA">
         <brief> Longitude uncertainty for all points (meters)</brief>
         <description>
           This optional value will be used as the longitude
           uncertainty for all points. Units are meters.
         </description>
         <type>double</type>
         <internalDefault>none</internalDefault>
         <minimum inclusive="yes">0</minimum>
        </parameter>

        <parameter name="POINT_RADIUS_SIGMA">
          <brief> Radius uncertainty for all points (meters)
          </brief>
          <description> 
            This value will be used as the radius uncertainty for 
            all points.  Units are meters.
          </description>
          <type>double</type>
          <internalDefault>none</internalDefault>
          <minimum inclusive="yes">0</minimum>
        </parameter>
    </group>
  </groups>
</application>
