<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="isis2std" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">

  <brief>
    Exports a cube to a PNG, BMP, GIF, TIFF, JPEG, or JPEG 2000
  </brief>

  <description>
    <p>
      This program will export an ISIS cube to one of several popular standard
      formats.  The current supported formats are BMP,  GIF, JPEG, JP2, PNG, and TIFF.  
    </p>
    <p>
      This program depends on TrollTech's version of the Qt Library to export BMP, 
      GIF and JPEG formated output images. For these format types, due to limitations of Qt, the
      input file size must not exceed 2 gigabytes and the only valid output bit type is 8BIT. 
    </p>
    <p>
      The JPEG2000 (JP2) and TIFF formats do not depend on the Qt library.  These formats do not 
      have the 2 GB limitation for input files and the output bit type may be 8BIT, U16BIT or S16BIT.
      For these formats, the writing routines output are streamed lines from the cube, and little
      of the image is held in memory at any one time, therefore increasing the processing speed to
      convert the file.  It is recommended that large images are exported to JP2  or TIFF format. 
      For some output image types, users may specify a value for the level of compression 
      represented as a percentage using the QUALITY parameter. The default is no compression 
      (i.e. QUALITY = 100%).
    </p>
    <p>
      Each of the input cube parameters (FROM, ALPHA, RED, GREEN, and BLUE) requires a single band 
      from an ISIS cube. If a cube contains multiple bands, the user must specify a single band of 
      the input image. To do this, the user must append a plus sign and the band number to be used 
      to the input file name. For example, inputFile.cub+4 indicates that the 4th band in the cube 
      will be used. No band needs to be specified if the cube only has a single band.
    </p>
    <p>
      In addition, if the cube has Mapping labels, the program will produce a world file for use 
      in Arc and/or other GIS packages.  The file will have an extension that uses the first and 
      last letters for the image extenstion and a "w". For example, tif produces a world file 
      extension of tfw.
    </p>
    <p>
      To ensure acceptable contrast in the output file, the user may select from three stretch
      options: linear, piecewise-linear, or manual.  
    </p>
    <p>
      Special pixels such as Low Saturation values and Nulls are set to black and High Saturation 
      values are set to white. See the BITTYPE parameter documentation for more information about 
      which output pixel values are assigned for particular input DNs of the various bit types.
    </p>
  </description>

  <history>
    <change name="Jeff Anderson" date="2005-06-15">
      Original version
    </change>
    <change name="Drew Davidson" date="2005-06-27">
      Added application test
    </change>
    <change name="Jacob Danton" date="2006-02-06">
      Added two new modes (rgb and argb) and updated the appTest.
    </change>
    <change name="Elizabeth Miller" date="2006-05-08">
      Added MIN and MAX percent options
    </change>
    <change name="Jacob Danton" date="2006-05-22">
      Added seperate MINIMUM and MAXIMUM parameters for all channels.
    </change>
    <change name="Brendan George" date="2007-05-03">
      Modified to use Filename class, and added appropriate appTest
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2007-07-10">
      Modified to give an error if write fails. Memory leak fixed.
    </change>
    <change name="Jeff Anderson" date="2007-08-20">
      Modified so that ISIS Null pixels are written as zeros in the output cube
      and low data in the input is written as a one
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Koechle" date="2007-08-22">
      Added a check to see that raw image data will be less than 4GB.  
      Throw exception if it is too big.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2008-05-12">
      Removed references to CubeInfo 
    </change>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2008-10-17">
      Added QUALITY parameter to set compression levels
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2008-11-04">
      Fixed checkDataSize() since Qimage has a maximum size of 2 GB, not 4GB.
      Added some QT error catching.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Koechle" date="2009-02-20">
      Documentation Change
    </change>
    <change name="Janet Barrett" date="2010-01-27">
      Added support for JPEG2000 files.
    </change>
    <change name="Stuart Sides and Steven Lambright" date="2012-04-03">
      Added minimum and maximum input stretch values and output file 
      name to the output log. fixes #761
    </change>
    <change name="Travis Addair" date="2012-04-03">
      Added support for exporting cubes greater than 2GB to TIFFs.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2012-08-28">
      Fixed some problems with the big tiff exports that caused
      corrupt outputs. The 2GB limitation should be removed
      completely now. References #579.
    </change>
    <change name="Jeannie Backer" date="2013-06-05">
      Fixed bug where alpha channel was not being utilized for ARGB option. Fixed bug that mapped 
      Nulls as the min value for TIFF and JP2 formats. Changed ImageExporter calls to new method 
      names, where needed. Added test for ARGB parameter. Added xml example. Added appTests to 
      improve coverage for isis2std program and the ImageExporter and its derived classes. 
      Fixes #1380.
    </change>
  </history>
  <category>
    <categoryItem>Import and Export</categoryItem>
  </category>

  <seeAlso>
    <applications>
      <item>isis2raw</item>
      <item>isis2fits</item>
    </applications>
  </seeAlso>

  <oldName>
    <item>dform</item>
    <item>isis2tif</item>
    <item>isis2jpg</item>
    <item>isis2gisworld</item>
  </oldName>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input cube to export
        </brief>
        <description>
          Use this parameter to select the filename and band to export. For
          example, file.cub+5 will select band 5
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="ALPHA">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input cube to export as the alpha channel
        </brief>
        <description>
          Use this parameter to select the filename and band to export. For
          example, file.cub+5 will select band 5
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="RED">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input cube to export as the red channel
        </brief>
        <description>
          Use this parameter to select the filename and band to export. For
          example, file.cub+5 will select band 5
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="GREEN">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input cube to export as the green channel
        </brief>
        <description>
          Use this parameter to select the filename and band to export. For
          example, file.cub+5 will select band 5
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="BLUE">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input cube to export as the blue channel
        </brief>
        <description>
          Use this parameter to select the filename and band to export. For
          example, file.cub+5 will select band 5
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TO">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Output file 
        </brief>
        <description>
          Use this parameter to specify the name of the output file.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="MODE">
        <type>string</type>
        <default><item>GRAYSCALE</item></default>
        <brief>Image mode</brief>
        <description>
          This parameter specifies the image mode. If GRAYSCALE, a single one-band cube is used.  
          If RGB, three one-band cubes are used. If ARGB, four one-band cubes are used.
        </description>
        <list>
          <option value="GRAYSCALE">
            <brief>
              Output has one channel (gray scaled).
            </brief>
            <description>
              If this option is chosen, the output image will have a single channel and the user 
              will be required to specify the parameter FROM.  
            </description>
            <exclusions>
              <item>ALPHA</item>
              <item>RED</item>
              <item>GREEN</item>
              <item>BLUE</item>
              <item>AMIN</item>
              <item>AMAX</item>
              <item>RMIN</item>
              <item>RMAX</item>
              <item>GMIN</item>
              <item>GMAX</item>
              <item>BMIN</item>
              <item>BMAX</item>
            </exclusions>
          </option>
          <option value="RGB">
            <brief>
              Output has three channels (red, green, and blue).
            </brief>
            <description>
              If this option is chosen, the output image will have three channels and the user will
              be required to specify the parameters RED, GREEN, and BLUE. 
            </description>
            <exclusions>
              <item>FROM</item>
              <item>ALPHA</item>
              <item>MINIMUM</item>
              <item>MAXIMUM</item>
              <item>AMIN</item>
              <item>AMAX</item>
            </exclusions>
          </option>
          <option value="ARGB">
            <brief>
              Output has four channels (alpha, red, green, and blue).
              </brief>
            <description>
              If this option is chosen, the output image will have four channels and the user will 
              be required to specify the parameters ALPHA, RED, GREEN, and BLUE. 
            </description>
            <exclusions>
              <item>FROM</item>
              <item>MINIMUM</item>
              <item>MAXIMUM</item>
            </exclusions>
          </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Output Settings">
      <parameter name="FORMAT">
        <type>string</type>
        <default>
          <item>PNG</item>
        </default>
        <brief>Format of output image</brief>
        <description>
          This parameter is used to select the output format.  It can be one of
          PNG, BMP, JPEG, TIF, GIF, or JP2.  Note that not all formats may be
          available.  It will depend on your installation of the Qt libraries.
        </description>

        <list>
          <option value="PNG">
            <brief>Output image will be PNG</brief>
            <description>
              The output image is in PNG (Portable Network Graphics) format. The default extension 
              for this format is "png."
            </description>
            <exclusions>
              <item>BITTYPE</item>
            </exclusions>
          </option>
          <option value="BMP">
            <brief>Output image will be BMP</brief>
            <description>
              The output image is in BMP (Bit Mapped Graphics) format. The default extension for 
              this format is "bmp."
            </description>
            <exclusions>
              <item>BITTYPE</item>
            </exclusions>
          </option>
          <option value="GIF">
            <brief>Output image will be GIF</brief>
            <description>
              The output image is in GIF (Graphics Interchange Format) format. The default 
              extension for this format is "gif."
            </description>
            <exclusions>
              <item>BITTYPE</item>
            </exclusions>
          </option>
          <option value="TIFF">
            <brief>Output image will be TIFF</brief>
            <description>
              The output image is in TIFF (Tagged Image Files Format) format. The default extension
              for this format is "tif."
            </description>
          </option>
          <option value="JPEG">
            <brief>Output image will be JPEG</brief>
            <description>
              The output image is in JPEG (Joint Photographic Experts Group) format. The default 
              extension for this format is "jpg."
            </description>
            <exclusions>
              <item>BITTYPE</item>
            </exclusions>
          </option>
          <option value="JP2">
            <brief>Output image will be JPEG2000</brief>
            <description>
              The output image is in JPEG2000 (Joint Photographic Experts Group 2000) format. The 
              default extension for this format is "jp2."
            </description>
            <exclusions>
              <item>QUALITY</item>
            </exclusions>
          </option>
        </list>
      </parameter> 
      <parameter name="QUALITY">
        <type>integer</type>
        <brief>Specify output image quality</brief>
        <default><item>100</item></default>
        <description>
          This parameter allows the user to specify level of quality
          (compression) for the output image.  Some output image types may not
          utilize this parameter.  The range is from 100 (no compression and
          highest quality) to 0 (highest compression and reduced quality).  A
          value of -1 can be given to use the default settings.
        </description>
        <minimum inclusive="yes">-1</minimum>
        <maximum inclusive="yes">100</maximum>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="BITTYPE">
        <type>string</type>
        <default>
          <item>8BIT</item>
        </default>
        <brief>Bit type of output file</brief>
        <description>
          This parameter allows the user to set the bit type of the output image.
          Some FORMAT values will only allow 8BIT outputs.
          16 bit signed (-32767=black, 32768=white)
        </description>
        <list>
          <option value="8BIT">
            <brief>Output is 8 bit unsigned integer data</brief>
            <description>
              Pixels values are within 8-bit unsigned integer data range from 0 to 255.
            </description>
          </option>
          <option value="U16BIT">
            <brief> Output is 16 bit unsigned integer data </brief>
            <description>
              Pixel values are within the 16-bit unsigned integer data range from 0 to 65535. This 
              option is not available for some output formats.
            </description>
          </option>
          <option value="S16BIT">
            <brief> Output is 16 bit signed integer data </brief>
            <description>
              Pixel values are in 16-bit signed integer data range -32768 to 32767. This option is 
              not available for some output formats.
            </description>
          </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Stretch Options">
      <parameter name="STRETCH">
        <type>string</type>
        <default>
          <item>LINEAR</item>
        </default>
        <brief>Type of stretch</brief>
        <description>
          This parameter is used to select one of three ways to stretch (or map)
          output pixels.  The are LINEAR, PIECEWISE, or MANUAL.
        </description>

        <list>
          <option value="LINEAR">
            <brief> Linear stretch </brief>
            <description>
              A minimum and maximum are automatically computed based on the
              statistics of the selected band.  A histogram of the band is used
              to pick the minimum at 0.5% of the data and the maximum at 99.5%
              of the data.  Input pixels less than or equal to the minimum are
              stretched to black while pixels greater than or equal to the
              maximum are stretched to white.  A linear mapping occurs between
              the minimum and maximum.
            </description>
            <exclusions>
              <item>MINIMUM</item>
              <item>MAXIMUM</item>
              <item>AMIN</item>
              <item>AMAX</item>
              <item>RMIN</item>
              <item>RMAX</item>
              <item>GMIN</item>
              <item>GMAX</item>
              <item>BMIN</item>
              <item>BMAX</item>
            </exclusions>
          </option>
          <option value="PIECEWISE">
            <brief> Piecewise-linear stretch </brief>
            <description>
              This option is similar to the LINEAR option.  A minimum and
              maximum are automatically computed.  Additionally, the median is
              computed and it is mapped to the middle gray value (halfway
              between white and black). Therefore, it is a piecewise-linear
              stretch with input pixels mapped linearly between either 1) the
              minimum/median or 2) the median/maximum.  This option is useful
              for contrast stretching cubes with skewed histograms to ensure a
              balanced contrast.
            </description>
            <exclusions>
              <item>MINIMUM</item>
              <item>MAXIMUM</item>
              <item>AMIN</item>
              <item>AMAX</item>
              <item>RMIN</item>
              <item>RMAX</item>
              <item>GMIN</item>
              <item>GMAX</item>
              <item>BMIN</item>
              <item>BMAX</item>
            </exclusions>
          </option>
          <option value="MANUAL">
            <brief> Manual stretch </brief>
            <description>
              This option allows you to pick your own stretch.  You must
              enter a value for MINIMUM and MAXIMUM
            </description>
            <exclusions>
              <item>MINPERCENT</item>
              <item>MAXPERCENT</item>
            </exclusions>
          </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="MINIMUM">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief>Minimum pixel value</brief>
        <description>
          The minimum input pixel value which will be mapped to black.
        </description>
        <lessThan>
          <item>MAXIMUM</item>
        </lessThan>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="MAXIMUM">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief>Maximum pixel value</brief>
        <description>
          The maximum input pixel value which will be mapped to white.
        </description>
        <greaterThan>
          <item>MINIMUM</item>
        </greaterThan>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="AMIN">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief>Minimum pixel value for the alpha channel</brief>
        <description>
          The minimum input pixel value which will be mapped to black.
        </description>
        <lessThan>
          <item>AMAX</item>
        </lessThan>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="AMAX">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief>Maximum pixel value for the alpha channel</brief>
        <description>
          The maximum input pixel value which will be mapped to white.
        </description>
        <greaterThan>
          <item>AMIN</item>
        </greaterThan>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="RMIN">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief>Minimum pixel value for the red channel</brief>
        <description>
          The minimum input pixel value which will be mapped to black.
        </description>
        <lessThan>
          <item>RMAX</item>
        </lessThan>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="RMAX">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief>Maximum pixel value for the red channel</brief>
        <description>
          The maximum input pixel value which will be mapped to white.
        </description>
        <greaterThan>
          <item>RMIN</item>
        </greaterThan>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="GMIN">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief>Minimum pixel value for the green channel</brief>
        <description>
          The minimum input pixel value which will be mapped to black.
        </description>
        <lessThan>
          <item>GMAX</item>
        </lessThan>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="GMAX">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief>Maximum pixel value for the green channel</brief>
        <description>
          The maximum input pixel value which will be mapped to white.
        </description>
        <greaterThan>
          <item>GMIN</item>
        </greaterThan>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="BMIN">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief>Minimum pixel value for the blue channel</brief>
        <description>
          The minimum input pixel value which will be mapped to black.
        </description>
        <lessThan>
          <item>BMAX</item>
        </lessThan>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="BMAX">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief>Maximum pixel value for the blue channel</brief>
        <description>
          The maximum input pixel value which will be mapped to white.
        </description>
        <greaterThan>
          <item>BMIN</item>
        </greaterThan>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="MINPERCENT">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief>Minimum Percent</brief>
        <description>
          The percentage of data in the histogram used to compute the minimum
          pixel value in the stretch.
        </description>
        <default><item>0.5</item></default>
        <lessThan>
          <item>MAXPERCENT</item>
        </lessThan>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="MAXPERCENT">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief>Maximum Percent</brief>
        <description>
          The percentage of data in the histogram used to compute the maximum
          pixel value in the stretch.
        </description>
        <default><item>99.5</item></default>
        <greaterThan>
          <item>MINPERCENT</item>
        </greaterThan>
      </parameter>
    </group>
  </groups>
  <examples>
    <example>
      <brief>
        Example of red/green/blue output of isis2std program. 
      </brief>
      <description>
        This example creates an output TIFF format file from 3 bands of an ISIS cube, designated 
        red, green, and blue using a linear stretch and 8 bit output type. A histogram is created 
        from the input values.  Using this histogram, we determine the minimum value to be any DN 
        in the bottom 0.2% of the data. These DNs will be set to black in the output. Similarly, 
        the maximum value is any DN in the top 99.8% of the data and these DNs will be set to white.
      </description>
      <terminalInterface>
        <commandLine>
          red=rgb.cub+1 green=rgb.cub+2 blue=rgb.cub+3 to=rgb.tif mode=rgb format=tiff bittype=8bit stretch=linear minpercent=0.2 maxpercent=99.8
        </commandLine>
        <description>
          Command line for this example.
        </description>
      </terminalInterface>
      <guiInterfaces>
        <guiInterface>
          <image height="550" width="391" src="assets/images/isis2stdGUI.jpg">
            <brief>
              GUI for this example.
            </brief>
            <description>
              This image show the graphical user interface for this program.
            </description>
            <thumbnail height="200" width="142" src="assets/thumbs/isis2stdGUI.jpg" caption="isis2std with RGB input and 8BIT output"/>
          </image>
        </guiInterface>
      </guiInterfaces>
      <dataFiles>
        <dataFile path="assets/dataFiles/rgb.tfw">
          <brief>
            Output world text file.
          </brief>
          <description>
            The output text world file for this image.
          </description>
          <parameterName>TO</parameterName>
        </dataFile>
      </dataFiles>
      <inputImages>
        <image height="550" width="670" src="assets/images/redBand.jpg">
          <brief>
            Red band.
          </brief>
          <description>
            The input cube band to be exported as the red channel in the output image.
          </description>
          <thumbnail height="164" width="200" src="assets/thumbs/redBand.jpg" caption="The first band of the input cube, shown in red."/>
          <parameterName>RED</parameterName>
        </image>
        <image height="550" width="670" src="assets/images/greenBand.jpg">
          <brief>
            Green band.
          </brief>
          <description>
            The input cube band to be exported as the green channel in the output image.
          </description>
          <thumbnail height="164" width="200" src="assets/thumbs/greenBand.jpg" caption="The first band of the input cube, shown in green."/>
          <parameterName>GREEN</parameterName>
        </image>
        <image height="550" width="670" src="assets/images/blueBand.jpg">
          <brief>
            Blue band.
          </brief>
          <description>
            The input cube band to be exported as the blue channel in the output image.
          </description>
          <thumbnail height="164" width="200" src="assets/thumbs/blueBand.jpg" caption="The first band of the input cube, shown in blue"/>
          <parameterName>BLUE</parameterName>
        </image>
      </inputImages>
      <outputImages>
        <image height="550" width="733" src="assets/images/rgbTIFFoutput.jpg">
          <brief>
            Output image.
          </brief>
          <description>
            The 8 bit output image, in TIFF format, created using the input red, green, and blue channels.
          </description>
          <thumbnail height="150" width="200" src="assets/thumbs/rgbTIFFoutput.jpg" caption="The color output image."/>
          <parameterName>TO</parameterName>
        </image>
      </outputImages>
    </example>
  </examples>
</application>
