<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="isis2gml" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">

  <brief>
    output a GML polygon from an ISIS cube
  </brief>

  <description>
    This program calculates a footprint polygon, in (longitude, lattitude) space, for a cube and
    outputs a graphical markup language (GML) file containing the polygon. The input cube  
    can be in either camera space (level1) or map projected space (level2). An ID tag can be added
    to the GML header, see the LABEL parameter.
  </description>

  <history>
    <change name="Robert Sucharski" date="2007-01-22">
      Original version
    </change>
    <change name="Stuart Sides" date="2013-06-29">
      Added ability to output either a 0 to 360 longitude domain or -180 to 180 longitude
      domain polygon. If the cube is map projected (level2) the default will be to match
      the projection. Also modified the gml output to be more standards compliant including
      a matching XSD file.
    </change>
  </history>

  <category>
    <categoryItem>Import and Export</categoryItem>
  </category>

  <groups>

    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input cube
        </brief>
        <description>
          Input cube to use for polygon generation 
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub *.CUB
        </filter>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="TO">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <brief>
          GML formatted file containing the footprint polygon
        </brief>
        <internalDefault>Same as input Cube</internalDefault>
        <description>
          Use this parameter to specify the name of the output GML file. The output file
          will be a geographic markup language (GML) file containing a (longitude, lattitude)
          polygon. If no file name is entered the input cube file name will be used with an
          extension of "gml". A second output file will be created with the same base name as 
          the "gml" file, but with the extension of "xsl." The "xsl" file is a standard part
          of the GML output.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.gml *.GML
        </filter>
      </parameter>
      </group>

      <group name="GML options">
        <parameter name="LABEL">
          <type>string</type>
          <internalDefault>none</internalDefault>
          <brief>
            Adds an ID tag to the GML header 
          </brief>
          <description>
            This value is placed in the GML header within the ID tag. The information within
            the ID tag can be used by GIS packages to display a label on the footprint. If no 
            value is entered no ID tag will be generated for the GML file.
          </description>
        </parameter>

        <parameter name="LONGITUDEDOMAIN">
          <type>string</type>
          <default><item>DEFAULT</item></default>
          <brief>
            Domain of the polygon longitudes
          </brief>
          <description>
            This value controls the longitude domain of the output GML polygons.
          </description>
          <list>
            <option value="DEFAULT">
              <brief>Use the cube projection domain or 0/360 if not projected</brief>
              <description>
                Longitudes in the GML polygon will be in the same domain as the input cube projection
                if the cube is projected. If the input cube is not projected longitudes will be in 
                the 0 to 360 domain.
              </description>
            </option>
            <option value="180">
              <brief>Create -180 to 180 longitues</brief>
              <description>
                Longitudes within the polygon will be in the 180 to -180 domain
              </description>
            </option>
            <option value="360">
              <brief>Create 0 to 360 longitues</brief>
              <description>
                Longitudes within the polygon will be in the 0 to 360 domain
              </description>
            </option>
          </list>
        </parameter>
      </group>

    </groups>
</application>

