<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="phohillier" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">

  <brief>
    Apply Hillier photometric correction to multiband cubes
  </brief>

  <description>
    <p>
      <b>phohillier</b> implements a photometric correction based upon a paper 
      titled "Multispectral Photometry of the Moon and Absolute Calibration of 
      Clementine UV/Vis Camera" by Hillier, Burratti and Hill, published in Icarus 
      141, 205-225 (1999).  The equation for I/F photometric correction from 
      this source is:
    </p>
    <PRE>
      I/F = (mu0/(mu+mu0)*F(phase)

              where:
                  mu0 = cos(incidence)
                  mu   = cos(emission)
                  F(phase) = b0*e(-b1*phase) + a0 + a1*phase + a2*phase^2 + 
                                      a3*phase^3 + a4*phase^4
    </PRE>
    <p>
      The equation described there utilizes the Lommel-Seeliger function to 
      account for scattering dependance on incidence and emission angles.  Lunar 
      Reflectance approximately follows this function and this is the dependence 
      expected for signly scattered light.  Thus is should be a good 
      approximation for dark objects such as the Moon where singly scattered 
      light dominates reflectance.   The phase function is a fourth order 
      polynomial with an exponential term to better account for opposition 
      surge. 
    </p>
    <p>
      This application provides features that allow multiband cubes to be 
      photometrically corrected with a properly formatted PVL input file much 
      like that of ISIS program <b>photomet</b>.   This application restricts 
      much of the options available to the more sophiscated photomet 
      application.  Below is an example input parameter file for this 
      application:
    </p>
  <pre>
Object = NormalizationModel 
  Group = Algorithm 
    Name = Albedo 
    PhotoModel = Hillier
    Incref=30.0
    Emaref=0.0
    Pharef=30.0
  EndGroup 
EndObject 

Object = PhotometricModel 
  HillierUnits = Degrees
  Group = Algorithm
    Name = Hillier
    FilterName = "Filter1"
    BandBinCenter = 100.1
    B0 = 0.0432753
    B1 = 0.0644091
    A0 = -0.0207532
    A1 = 0.00165219
    A2 = -3.94007e-05
    A3  = 4.19325e-07
    A4 = -1.69163e-09
  EndGroup

  Group = Algorithm
    Name = Hillier
    FilterName = "Filter2"
    BandBinCenter = 112.5
    B0 = 0.0332283
    B1 = 0.00667452
    A0 = -0.0258405
    A1 = -9.04379e-05
    A2 = 7.59709e-06
    A3 = -1.06395e-07
    A4 = 5.18268e-10
  EndGroup

  Group = Algorithm
    Name = Hillier
    FilterName = "Filter8"
    BandBinCenter = 545.3
    BandBinCenterTolerance = 1.0E-2
    B0 = 0.0347020
    B1 = 0.0211712
    A0 = -0.0244440
    A1 = 0.000388924
    A2 = 4.72860e-07
    A3 = -5.00731e-08
    A4 = 3.07309e-10
  EndGroup
EndObject
  </pre>
    <p>
      The NormalizationModel object will (currently) always apply an Albedo 
      normalization.  The value of the Name parameter is ignored here.  Also 
      ignored is the value if PhotoModel as it is always "Hillier".  The Incref, 
      Emaref and Pharef are the incidence, emission and phase angles to be  used 
      as the photometric standard.  It will be used to normalize the photometric 
      correction parameter to these angles.    The equation used to create the 
      photometrically corrected I/F dn is:
    </p>
      <pre>
          odn = idn * (phostd  / ph)
         
              where phostd is the Hillier photometry at the given Incref, 
                                     Emaref and Pharef angles
                         ph        is the photometric correction for the 
                                     incidence, emission and phase at each pixel
      </pre>
  <p>
      In the above example, parameters B0-B1 and A0-A4 are the parameters for 
      the Hillier equation.  Additional parameters area needed in order to apply 
      a specific set of parameters in an Algorithm group to selected bands. The
      set of parameters, B0-B1, A0-A4, within an Algorithm group are applied to
      a band if (ABS(Center-BandBinCenter) &lt;= ABS(BandBinCenterTolerance)).  
      The "Center" parameter in the above equality comes from the Center keyword 
      in the BandBin group of the input cube file specified in the FROM 
      parameter.  This keyword must exist in the input cube or an error is 
      generated and the program aborts.   BandBinCenter and 
      BandBinCenterTolerance are contained in each Algorithm group.  Only 
      BandBinCenter is required.  If BandBinCenterTolerance is not present in an 
      Algorithm group a value of 1.0E-6 is used.  All input bands in the FROM 
      file must be matched to at least one of the Algorithm parameters otherwise 
      an error is generated and the application is aborted.
    </p>
    <p>
      The parameter HillierUnits is provided to specify if the phase angle is in 
      units of degrees or radians.  It does not have to exist in any group or 
      even in the top Object section.  If it does not exist, "Radians" is the 
      default.
    </p>
    <p>
      An additional feature of the PVL structure is that any keyword that exists 
      in the Object section of the PhotometricModel Object is propagated to each 
      Algorithm group when it  is read in unless the keyword already exists in 
      the Algorithm group.  If a keyword exists in both the PhotometricModel 
      object and an Algorithm group, the keyword in the Algorithm group has 
      precedence.
    </p>
    <p>
      Below is an example of a small PVL file that will process all bands that 
      have a center wavelength of 100.0 to 900.0 (units do not matter as long as
      the PVL ALgorithm groups contain the same units as the BandBin Center 
      keyword in the input cube file).  The units of phase is provided in 
      Radians for this particular example and is overridden from the keyword in 
      the PhotometricModel object:
    </p>
    <PRE>
Object = NormalizationModel 
  Group = Algorithm 
    Name = Albedo 
    PhotoModel = Hillier
    Incref=30.0
    Emaref=0.0
    Pharef=30.0
  EndGroup 
EndObject 
      
Object = PhotometricModel 
  HillierUnits = Degrees
  Group = Algorithm
    Name = Hillier
    FilterName = "AllFilters"
    BandBinCenter = 500.0
    BandBinCenterTolerance = 400.0
    HillierUnits = Radians
    B0 = 0.0347020
    B1 = 0.0211712
    A0 = -0.0244440
    A1 = 0.000388924
    A2 = 4.72860e-07
    A3 = -5.00731e-08
    A4 = 3.07309e-10
  EndGroup
EndObject      
    </PRE>
    <p>
      Additional consequences of the photometric correction processing is any 
      incidence angle greater than i90 degrees is set to the ISIS special Null 
      pixel value.  And, of course, any ISIS special pixel encountered on input 
      is propagated to the output TO file without modification.
    </p>
  </description>

  <history>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2010-02-21">
      Original version.
    </change>
  </history>

  <category>
    <categoryItem>Radiometric and Photometric Correction</categoryItem>
    <categoryItem>Cameras</categoryItem>
  </category>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input cube
        </brief>
        <description>
          Use this parameter to select the input filename.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TO">
        <type>cube</type>
        <pixelType>real</pixelType>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Output cube
        </brief>
        <description>
          This file will contain the photometrically corrected image data after 
          being corrected by with Hillier algorithm.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="PHOPAR">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Pvl file
        </brief>
        <description>
          This file will contain the parameters B0-B1, A0-A4 to use when 
          applying the Hellier photometric correction.  See the main program 
          documentation for a full description.
        </description>
	       <filter>*.pvl</filter>
      </parameter>
    </group>
  </groups>
</application>
