<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Id: sumspice.xml 6565 2016-02-11 00:15:35Z kbecker@GS.DOI.NET $ -->
<application name="sumspice" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">

  <brief>
    Update ISIS start times, pointing and spacecraft position with Gaskell SPC
  SUMFILEs
  </brief>

  <description>
   <h3>Overview</h3>
    <p>
      This program allows the user to update a cube's labels, spaceraft attitude
      (pointing) and position with the information found in a corresponding
      Gaskell SUMFILE. SUMFILEs are a product of  Gaskell's stereo
      photoclinometry (SPC) digital elevation model (DEM) generation process.
      SUMFILEs are generated for each file included in the processing to
      generate the DEM.
    </p>
    <p>
       Part of the SPC DEM processing flow is to control all the images. The
       SUMFILE is a direct product from the SPIC control process that
       (typically) corresponds to a single file. The SUMFILE contains updates to
       pointing attitude and spacecraft position, among other things. The
       contents of the SUMFILE and their purpose are described below.
    </p>
    <p>
       The objective of this program is to (optionally) apply timing changes (as
       seen in Hayabusa 1 images), pointing and spacecraft updates directly to
       ISIS cubes. This provides ISIS users the ability to apply consistent
       control to ISIS images that have corresponding SUMFILEs and use the DEM
       generated from the SPC process for orthorectiifed cartographic
       mapping processes in ISIS. This includes creating CK and SPK kernels from
       the result of this application for more widely distributed use of SPC
       results.
    </p>
    <p>
      Here is an example of the contents of a Gaskell SPC SUMFILE (<b>NOTE: </b>
      Line numbers are not part of the SUMFILE but are annotated here for
      documentation purposes which follows):
      <pre>
  1   W46908480918
  2   2014 NOV 12 17:20:03.128
  3     2048  2048   500 65535                                       NPX, NLN, THRSH
  4       0.1356800000D+03    0.1044000000D+04    0.9380000000D+03   MMFL, CTR
  5      -0.9665063720D+01    0.1326644487D+02   -0.6673084308D+01   SCOBJ
  6      -0.6442479111D+00   -0.1829032409D-01    0.7645979944D+00   CX
  7       0.5935707119D+00    0.6184779444D+00    0.5149357652D+00   CY
  8      -0.4823053379D+00    0.7855892670D+00   -0.3875965231D+00   CZ
  9       0.7254908676D+00   -0.3292717307D+00    0.6043534796D+00   SZ
 10     74.07410   0.00000   0.00000   0.00000  74.07410   0.00000   K-MATRIX
 11     0.00000D+00    0.00000D+00    0.00000D+00    0.00000D+00   DISTORTION
 12     0.1007758363D-02    0.1482813397D-02    0.8902614968D-03   SIGMA_VSO
 13     0.3071768580D-04    0.3093941486D-04    0.1565302183D-04   SIGMA_PTG
 14 LANDMARKS
 15 AO0001   2049.39    668.15
 16 AO0002   2020.70    644.81
 17 AO0003   2035.17    708.66
 18 BD0009   1902.39    884.05
 19 BD0010   1891.13    909.86
 20    ...
 21 EK0022    675.73   1371.97
 22 EQ0088    721.76    738.13
 23 FI0002    727.77    220.40
 24 LIMB FITS
 25 END FILE
    </pre>
      The lines of a Gaskell SUMFILEs are described as:
      <ul>
        <li>
          Line 1: An ID for the SUMFILE (occasionally, but not always, the image
          name).
        </li>
        <li>
          Line 2: The potentially corrected start, center or stop time in UTC
          for the image.
        </li>
        <li>
          Line 3: The number of pixels, the number of lines, the lower DN
          threshold, and the upper DN threshold.
        </li>
        <li>
          Line 4: The focal length (in mm), followed by the pixel center and the
          line center (i.e. boresight/optical axis).
        </li>
        <li>
          Line 5: The vector from the spacecraft to the object center (i.e. the
        spacecraft position in body fixed coordinates).
        </li>
        <li>
          Line 6: The pixel (x) unit vector, in body fixed coordinates.
        </li>
        <li>
          Line 7: The line (y) unit vector, in body fixed coordinates.
        </li>
        <li>
          Line 8: The boresight (z) unit vector, in body fixed coordinates.
        </li>
        <li>
          Line 9: The sun direction unit vector, in body fixed coordinates.
        </li>
        <li>
          Line 10: The k matrix
        </li>
        <li>
          Line 11: Used to contain distortion information, but it is always zero now.
        </li>
        <li>
          Line 12: The formal spacecraft position uncertainty , ie. the sigma VSO.
        </li>
        <li>
          Line 13: The formal spacecraft orientation uncertainty , ie. the sigma PTG.
        </li>
        <li>
          Line 14-23: A list of landmarks containing the ID, pixel sample
          center, and pixel line center.
        </li>
        <li>
          Line 24+: A list of limb fits containing the landmark-on-limb centers.
        </li>
        <li>
          Line 25: Last line of a Gaskell SUMFILE ends with the END FILE
          statement.
        </li>
      </ul>
    </p>
   <h3>Usage</h3>
    <p>
      <i>sumspice</i> has been used to apply Gaskell SPC control to Hayabusa
      Itokawa AMICA images. There is up to 12 seconds of uncertainty in the
      start times of these images. The Hayabusa team improved the start time
      with brute force comparisons of the position of Itokawa in the AMICA field
      of view. The SUMFILEs contained the correction of the start time.
      Unfortunately, the PDS archive of the AMICA data has not been updated with
      the new start times. This was the motivation behind adding support for the
      start time adjustment.
    </p>
    <p>
      The basic processing options are to update the start times (UPDATE=TIMES)
      and pointing (CK) (UPDATE=POINTING) and spacecraft position (SPK)
      (UPDATE=POSITION) data in the ISIS label/file with that contained in the
      SUMFILE. Both the pointing and spacecraft position can be updated in the
      same run (UPDATE=SPICE). And, finally, it may be useful to start over by
      resetting the times to their original values - UPDATE=RESET provides this
      option (and removes the SumTimeHistory and disables SPICE requiring a
      rerun of
               <i>spiceinit</i>.
    </p>
    <p>
      To apply the complete functionality of <i>sumspice</i>, the start time
      must be updated first if required. Note that it is rather uncommon the
      start time will need to be updated. If it needed/desired,
      the UPDATE=TIMES option will recompute the SpacecraftClockStartTime, which
      is used primarily by most camera models for best accuracy of image
      acquisition times. This option will force a rerun of <i>spiceinit</i>
      after observation times are updated mainly to reestablish the body
      orientation and solar illumination angles for the new start time. This
      option will reassign computed values, relative to the SUMFILE reference
      time (see SUMTIMES) to  SpacecraftClockStartCount,
      SpacecraftClockStopCount, StartTime and StopTime label keywords. Most
      camera models use at least one of these values to establish observation
      times. These times are used to associate the correct ephemeris data from
      SPICE kernels.
    </p>
    <p>
      The update of pointing attitude and spacecraft position requires
      <i>spiceinit</i> to be applied to the image. This operation will update
      the InstrumentPointing and InstrumentPosition Tables in the label of the
      ISIS cube with the contents of the Gaskell SUMFILE. Note that SUMFILEs
      contain vectors in body-fixed format, so you must ensure the proper PCK is
      used with the image. NAIF routines are used to apply any required
      transformations to retain the integrity of the data. Once the fidelity of
      the updates are confirmed, new CK and SPK kernels can be created using the
      ISIS <i>ckwriter</i> and <i>spkwriter</i> applications, respectively.
    </p>
    <h3>Activity Tracking</h3>
    <p>
      <i>sumspice</i> does supply some aid in tracking its activity in the ISIS
      label. When timing is updated, there is a group called
      <i>SumTimeHistory</i> that is created upon the first operation pertaining
      to  changes that were made to the timing keywords (typically) in the
      <i>Instrument</i> group in the ISIS label. Four keywords are affected by
      timing operations in <i>sumspice</i>. These are SpacecraftClockStartCount,
      SpacecraftClockStopCount, StartTime, and StopTime. The first two keywords,
      SpacecraftClockStartCount and pacecraftClockStopCount, are in the form of
      spacecraft clock, or SCLK, format. Manipulation of these two keywords
      requires the existance of an ISIS camera model to determine the
      appropriate SCLK NAIF id for conversion from UTC (as stored in the
      SUMFILE, line 2) to SCLK. The later two keywords, StartTime, and StopTime,
      are conversions of the times to UTC. These keywords are only updated if
      they exist in the <i>Instrument</i> group in the ISIS label.
    </p>
    <p>
      When any of these keywords are updated in the ISIS label, previous values
      are recorded in the <i>SumTimeHistory</i> group created upon the first run
      of <i>sumspice</i> that modifies these keywords. Any subsequent run of
      <i>sumspice</i> that modifies times have previous values appended to the
      corresponding keywords, thus creating an running history of timing
      operations and enabling the UPDATE=RESET option to retain original timing
      values if needed. Using the reset option removes the
      <i>SumTimeHistory</i> group. Here is an example of the
      <i>SumTimeHistory</i> group after an update.
    </p>
    <PRE>
  Group = SumTimeHistory
    # SUMFILE(s) used to update the SCLK timing in the instrument group (SPC).
    SUMFILE                   = N2395699394
    SpacecraftClockStartCount = 2395694888 &lt;1/32sec&gt;
    SpacecraftClockStopCount  = 2395695365 &lt;1/32sec&gt;
    StartTime                 = 2005-09-21T10:44:07
    StopTime                  = 2005-09-21T10:44:07
  End_Group
    </PRE>
    <p>
      Note that the TOLOG file, if specified, will also contain a record of the
      activities that were applied, including the timing values resulting from
      these operations.
    </p>
    <p>
       When updating pointing or spacecraft position, a keyword named SUMFILE is
      added to the <i> InstrumentPointing</i> and <i>InstrumentPosition</i>
      tables, respectively that records the name of the SUMFILE used to update
      the ephemeris data in those objects. When <i>spiceinit</i> is run, this
      table is replaced, thus removing the keyword, indicating original SPICE
      data is contained in those objects.
    </p>
    <h3>SUMTIME Considerations</h3>
    <p>
       Regarding the SUMFILE reference time, the SUMTIME parameter is provided
       for the user to specify that the UTC time in the SUMFILE represents the
       start, mid or end time of the image exposure time. The following table
       provides known reference times contained in SUMFILEs for
       spacecraft/instruments. Knowing the correct reference contained in the
       SUMFILE is critical to determine the correct SUMFILE for a given ISIS
       cube and updating the ISIS labels with the time and ephemeris data
       contained therein.
    </p>
    <TABLE border = "1">
        <CAPTION><h4>SUMFILE SUMTIME References</h4></CAPTION>
        <TR>
          <TH>Spacecraft</TH>
          <TH>Instrument</TH>
          <TH>Reference</TH>
        </TR>
        <TR>
          <TD>Hayabusa 1</TD>
          <TD>AMICA</TD>
          <TD>Start</TD>
        </TR>
        <TR>
          <TD>Dawn</TD>
          <TD>FC</TD>
          <TD>Center (Note: Dawn FC has a 193 ms delay from start time)</TD>
        </TR>
       <TR>
         <TD>OSIRIS-REx</TD>
          <TD>OCAMS (MapCam, SamCam, PolyCam)</TD>
          <TD>Center</TD>
        </TR>
        <TR>
          <TD>MESSENGER</TD>
          <TD>MDIS</TD>
          <TD>Center</TD>
        </TR>
    </TABLE>
   <h3>Processing Sequences</h3>
    <p>
       Here is an example that shows the commonly used command sequence for the
       Hayabusa AMICA instrument. This process will update times and ephemeris
       data, which includes pointing and spacecraft position.
      <PRE>
# First transfer the SUMFILE timing to the ISIS cube labels
sumspice from=st_2395699394_v.lev0.cub sumfile=N2395699394.SUM  update=times sumtime=start  tolog=haya_amica.log

# Now rerun spiceinit as a timing update forces this
spiceinit   from=st_2395699394_v.lev0.cub shape=user model='$hayabusa/kernels/dsk/hay_a_amica_5_itokawashape_v1_0_512q.bds'

# Finally, apply the pointing and spacecraft position update in a single run
sumspice from=st_2395699394_v.lev0.cub sumfile=N2395699394.SUM  update=spice sumtime=start  tolog=haya_amica.log
      </PRE>
    </p>
  </description>

  <history>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2015-02-25">
      Original Version
    </change>
    <change name="Jeannie Backer" date="2015-12-07">
      Generalized to program work with Dawn and Hayabusa data. Clock times are
      now updated in the instrument group and the original times are saved in
      the Archive group of the cube labels.
    </change>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2016-02-09">
      Added implementation to support NAIF META kernel files. Updated
      documentation.
    </change>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2016-09-19">
      Refactored code to: 1) accomdate for different time references in
      SUMFILEs (start, center, stop - see SUMTIME parameter), 2) modified
      update options to be more flexible (see UPDATE parameter), 3) added more
      robust determination of observation times, 4) added start time delay
      options, particularly for Dawn FC, which has a 193 ms start time delay,
      5) added a log option that reports operations and timing operations for
      confirmation and analysis, 6) improved logging of timing activities to
      labels, 7) timing updates are no longer required before applying SPICE
      update options (not required for all instruments), 8) modified how
      SPICE/camera model is disabled (in Kernels group) after a timing update,
      9) added SUMTIME, UPDATE, TOLOG parameters and removed the MODE
      parameter, 10) changed the default for TIMEDIFF to INFINITY from 0 so
      success is guaranteed, and 11) added UPDATE=RESET option to restore
      original times. Some of these changes breaks backwards compatibility.
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Combs" date="2017-05-19">
      Changed pvl.DIFF of input for hayabusa app test to ignore file names. Allows test to pass when
      not using default data area. Fixes #4738.
    </change>
    <change name="Kaitlyn Lee" date="2018-04-08">
      Updated the pvl.DIFF's of the input for the dawn test to ignore the 
      InstrumentPointing keyword. Fixes #5379.
    </change>
    <change name="Kaitlyn Lee" date="2018-04-12">
      Added a call to writeHistory() of the SumFinder class that will add a sumspice
      entry to each input cube's History blob after a successful run. Fixes #4972.
    </change>
    <change name="Jacob Cain" date="2022-11-22">
        Changed FROM type to cube. Fixes #4780.
    </change>
  </history>

  <category>
    <categoryItem>Utility</categoryItem>
  </category>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">

      <parameter name= "FROM">
        <type>cube</type>
        <filter>*.cub</filter>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          A single cube to process.
        </brief>
        <description>
          The name of a single input cube whose labels will be updated using a
          Gaskell SUMFILE.  <b>Note: </b>Use the FROMLIST parameter instead of
          this one if there are multiple cubes to process.
        </description>
        <default><item>None</item></default>
        <exclusions>
          <item>FROMLIST</item>
        </exclusions>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name= "FROMLIST">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          A list of cubes to process.
        </brief>
        <description>
          A text file containing a list of input cubes whose labels will be
          updated using Gaskell SUMFILEs. <b>Note: </b>Use the FROM parameter
          instead of this one if there is only one cube to process.
        </description>
        <default><item>None</item></default>
        <exclusions>
          <item>FROM</item>
        </exclusions>
      </parameter>


      <parameter name="SUMFILE">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          The name of the SUMFILE to be used to update the input cube(s).
        </brief>
        <description>
          The name of a single Gaskell SUMFILE containing time and SPICE
          information. <b>Note: </b>Use the SUMFILELIST parameter instead of
          this one if the exact SUMFILE that should be used to update the
          cube(s) is unknown or if there are more than one.
        </description>
        <filter>*.SUM</filter>
        <default><item>None</item></default>
        <exclusions>
          <item>SUMFILELIST</item>
        </exclusions>
      </parameter>

     <parameter name="SUMFILELIST">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          A list of SUMFILEs to search for the best match to update the given
        cube(s).
        </brief>
        <description>
          A text file containing a list of Gaskell SUMFILEs that each contain
          time and SPICE information.  <b>Note: </b>Use the SUMFILE parameter
          instead of this one if the desired SUMFILE is known for the given
          cube(s).
        </description>
        <filter>*.lis</filter>
        <default><item>None</item></default>
        <exclusions>
          <item>SUMFILE</item>
        </exclusions>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TOLOG">
         <type>filename</type> <fileMode>output</fileMode>
         <brief>
           Optional output log file of results
         </brief>
         <description>
           If a name is provided, the results of each cube
           file is written to the specified file.
         </description>
         <filter>*.log</filter>
         <default><item>None</item></default>
       </parameter>

      <parameter name="SUMTIME">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>
          Specify what the time in the SUMFILE represents: start, center or
          end time
        </brief>
        <description>
          <p>
            This parameter is provided to explicity specify what the time in the
            SUMFILE represents. Typically, this is the start time (default) but
            not always. The user must make this determination.
          </p>
          <p>
            This may be important when searching for the SUMFILE associated with
            the ISIS cube when using the times from each source. <i>sumspice</i>
            will make adjustments based upon this value and the exposure
            duration as found in the ISIS cube file label.
          </p>
        </description>
        <list>

          <option value="START">
            <brief>
              Time contained in SUMFILE refers to start time
            </brief>
            <description>
               The UTC time stored in the SUMFILE refers to the start time of
               the observation.
            </description>
          </option>

          <option value="CENTER">
            <brief>
              Time contained in SUMFILE refers to center of the exposure time
            </brief>
            <description>
               The UTC time stored in the SUMFILE refers to the center of the
               exposure time of the observation.
            </description>
          </option>

          <option value="STOP">
            <brief>
              Time contained in SUMFILE refers to end of the exposure time
            </brief>
            <description>
               The UTC time stored in the SUMFILE refers to the stop time of
               the observation. This option is not common but may be used so is
               added for completeness.
            </description>
          </option>
        </list>
        <default><item>CENTER</item></default>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="UPDATE">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>
          Determines update operation to apply to ISIS file from SUMFILE data
        </brief>
        <description>
          Determines which elements of the ISIS cube to update with the
          appropriate SUMFILE contents. Note that there are input
          requirements for each option. if a SUMFILELIST was provided, the
          program will search for the file in the given list whose time is
          within the specified TIMEDIFF tolerance and is the closest to the
          SpacecraftClockStartCount in the cube. If multiple files in the
          SUMFILELIST have the same time, this program will choose to use the
          first one in the list with the closest time. If no SUMFILE is found
          within this tolerance, a warning will be printed to the output log and
          the program will exit without updating the input cube.
        </description>
        <list>

          <option value="NONE">
            <brief>
              Essentailly a NOOP, but does determine cube/SUMFILE pairings
            </brief>
            <description>
              <p>
                If the NONE option is selected, the program will only determine
                which SUMFILE applies to each cube. This option is useful as a
                dryrun to ensure the pairings are good. You can also get a
                useful output log in TOLOG that will provide timing information.
              </p>
            </description>
          </option>

          <option value="TIMES">
            <brief>
              Update the start and end times in the ISIS cube label.
            </brief>
            <description>
              <p>
                If the TIMES option is selected, the program will update the
                UTC StartTime/EndTIme and
                SpacecraftClockStartCount/SpacecraftClockStopCount ISIS cube
                Instrument group. The UTC on the second line of the SUMFILE
                will replace the StartTime value in the cube's Instrument
                group. The ExposureDuration in the label is then used to find
                the new StopTime. These new start/stop time values are used to
                determine the new SpacecraftClockStartCount and the new
                SpacecraftClockStopCount. The original values of these
                keywords and the SUMFILE used to update the keywords will be
                saved in the cube's Archive group.
              </p>
              <p>
                Note that this option will effectively require
                <i>spiceinit</i> to be ran after it completes. <i>sumspice</i>
                 forces this by disabling existing geometry (by removing the
                NaifKeywords object and some keywords in the Kernels group).
                Changing start times will change positions of the spacecraft and
                target body. A rerun of spiceinit will update these relative
                positions. This step should be applied prior to using any other
                option of this application.
              </p>
            </description>
          </option>

          <option value="SPICE">
            <brief>
              Update the InstrumentPosition and InstrumentPointing tables in the
            cube file
            </brief>
            <description>
              If the SPICE option is selected, the program will search for the
              SumFile keyword in the cube's Archive group. If no such keyword
              exists or if the SumFile saved to the labels is not found in the
              given SUMFILELIST, a warning will be printed to the output log
              and the program will exit without updating the SPICE tables.
              Otherwise, the spacecraft position and pointing information will
              be updated using the information provided in the matching
              SUMFILE. This option is equivalent to running both the POINTING
              and POSITION option.
            </description>
          </option>

          <option value="POINTING">
            <brief>
              Update the InstrumentPointing tables in the cube file.
            </brief>
            <description>
              If the POINTING option is selected, the program will update only
              the spacecraft pointing SPICE information with the data contained
              in the SUMFILE. The file must have be ran through spiceint
              previous and the SPICE data must be attached as a Table in the
              ISIS cube (i.e., spiceint must have ATTACH=TRUE)
            </description>
          </option>

          <option value="POSITION">
            <brief>
              Update the InstrumentPosition tables in the cube file
            </brief>
            <description>
              If the POSITION option is selected, the program will update only
              the spacecraft position SPICE information with the data contained
              in the SUMFILE. The file must have be ran through spiceint
              previous and the SPICE data must be attached as a Table in the
              ISIS cube (i.e., spiceint must have ATTACH=TRUE)
            </description>
          </option>

          <option value="RESET">
            <brief>
              Resets the timing to original times
            </brief>
            <description>
              This option has been added to essentially reset the timing
              adjustments that were made back to the original values. This is to
              prevent one having to start over completely with a new version of
              the file. This will preserve any processing that has taken place.
              This option will use the keywords  in the SumtimeHistory group
              that record all timing <i>sumspice</i> operations that have taken
              place on the file to reset all existing keywords in the Instrument
              group related to observation timing. The final act of this option
              will also remove the SumtimeHistory group and disable SPICE
              operations until a run of
                             <i>spiceinit</i> is made.
            </description>
          </option>

        </list>
        <default><item>SPICE</item></default>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TIMEDIFF">
          <type>double</type>
        <brief>
          The maximum allowed time difference between the cube
          time and the time found in the SUMFILE.
        </brief>
        <description>
          <p>
            This value is always considered to specify the time differential when
            looking for matching SUMFILES. This tolerance is used when both the
            SUMFILE and  SUMFILELIST are given to constrain the difference in
            observation times contained in the cube label and the SUMFILE. If no
            value is provided, then the default behavior is to choose the SUMFILE
            that has the closest time as specified in  SUMTIME to the
            corresponding time contained in cube label, assertained in conjunction
            with the camera model.
          </p>
          <p>
              Note that it is critical to provided a tolerance value here if
              known (e.g., ~12 seconds for Hayabusa/AMICA) so that the correct
              SUMFILE is determined.
          </p>
        </description>
        <internalDefault>INFINITY</internalDefault>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="METAKERNEL">
          <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>List of SPICE kernels to support conversions</brief>
        <description>
            In some cases, additional kernels may be required in order to
            compute some of the data acquired from the NAIF toolkit. If
            the ISIS labels do not contain sufficient kernels, this
            parameter can specify a NAIF meta kernel, or a single kernel
            of any supported NAIF type that will be loaded prior to any
            computations. These kernels remain loaded for all files and
            for the entirety of the runtime of this application. See <a
            href="https://naif.jpl.nasa.gov/pub/naif/toolkit_docs/C/req/kernel.html">
            SPICE Kernel Required Reading for additional</a> information
            about NAIF meta kernels.
        </description>
        <filter>*.meta *.tm</filter>
        <default><item>None</item></default>
      </parameter>

      </group>
  </groups>
</application>
