<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Id: sumspice.xml 6565 2016-02-11 00:15:35Z kbecker@GS.DOI.NET $ -->
<application name="sumspice" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">

  <brief>
    Update ISIS start times, pointing and spacecraft position with Gaskell 
  SUMFILEs 
  </brief>

  <description>
   <h3>Overview</h3>
    <p>
      This program allows the user to update a cube's labels, spaceraft attitude 
      (pointing) and position with more accurate information found in the 
      appropriate Gaskell SUMFILE. There are multiple options for the how the 
      labels should be updated. See the MODE parameter documentation for a 
      description of these options.
    </p>
    <p>
      The Gaskell SUMFILEs provided are expected to have a format
      described below:
      <ul>
        <li>
          Line 1: An ID for the SUMFILE (usually the image name).
        </li>
        <li>
          Line 2: The correct start UTC for the image.
        </li>
        <li>
          Line 3: The number of pixels, the number of lines, the lower DN 
          threshold, and the upper DN threshold.
        </li>
        <li>
          Line 4: The focal length (in mm), followed by the pixel center and the 
          line center (i.e. boresight/optical axis).
        </li>
        <li>
          Line 5: The vector from the spacecraft to the object center (i.e. the 
        spacecraft position in body fixed coordinates). 
        </li>
        <li>
          Line 6: The pixel (x) unit vector, in body fixed coordinates.
        </li>
        <li>
          Line 7: The line (y) unit vector, in body fixed coordinates.
        </li>
        <li>
          Line 8: The boresight (z) unit vector, in body fixed coordinates.
        </li>
        <li>
          Line 9: The sun direction unit vector, in body fixed coordinates.
        </li>
        <li>
          Line 10: The k matrix
        </li>
        <li>
          Line 11: Used to contain distortion information, but it is always zero now.
        </li>
        <li>
          Line 12: The formal spacecraft position uncertainty , ie. the sigma VSO.
        </li>
        <li>
          Line 13: The formal spacecraft orientation uncertainty , ie. the sigma PTG.
        </li>
        <li>
          A list of landmarks containing the ID, pixel center, and line center.
        </li>
        <li>
          A list of limb fits containing the landmark-on-limb centers.
        </li>
      </ul>

      Here is an example:
      <pre>
  W46908480918
  2014 NOV 12 17:20:03.128
    2048  2048   500 65535                                       NPX, NLN, THRSH
      0.1356800000D+03    0.1044000000D+04    0.9380000000D+03   MMFL, CTR
     -0.9665063720D+01    0.1326644487D+02   -0.6673084308D+01   SCOBJ    
     -0.6442479111D+00   -0.1829032409D-01    0.7645979944D+00   CX       
      0.5935707119D+00    0.6184779444D+00    0.5149357652D+00   CY       
     -0.4823053379D+00    0.7855892670D+00   -0.3875965231D+00   CZ       
      0.7254908676D+00   -0.3292717307D+00    0.6043534796D+00   SZ       
    74.07410   0.00000   0.00000   0.00000  74.07410   0.00000   K-MATRIX 
    0.00000D+00    0.00000D+00    0.00000D+00    0.00000D+00   DISTORTION 
    0.1007758363D-02    0.1482813397D-02    0.8902614968D-03   SIGMA_VSO  
    0.3071768580D-04    0.3093941486D-04    0.1565302183D-04   SIGMA_PTG  
LANDMARKS                                                                       
AO0001   2049.39    668.15                                                      
AO0002   2020.70    644.81                                                      
AO0003   2035.17    708.66
BD0009   1902.39    884.05                                                      
BD0010   1891.13    909.86                                                      
   ...
EK0022    675.73   1371.97                                                      
EQ0088    721.76    738.13                                                      
FI0002    727.77    220.40                                                      
LIMB FITS
END FILE                                                                        
    </pre>
    </p>
   <h3>Usage</h3>
    <p>
      <i>sumspice</i> has been used to apply Gaskell control to Hayabusa Itokawa 
      AMICA images. There is up to 12 seconds of uncertainty in the start times 
      of these images. The Hayabusa team improved the start time with brute 
      force comparisons of the position of Itokawa in the AMICA field of view. 
      The SUMFILEs contained the correction of the start time. This was the 
      motivation behind adding support for the start time adjustment.
    </p>
    <p>
      To apply the complete functionality of <i>sumspice</i>, the start time 
      must be updated first if required. Note that it is rather uncommon the 
      start time will need to be updated. If it is, this option will recompute 
      the SpacecraftClockStartTIme which is used primarily by most camera models 
      for best accuracy of image acquisition times. This mode will require a 
      rerun of  <i>spiceinit</i> mainly to reestablish the body orientation for 
      the new start time. 
    </p>
    <p>
      The update of pointing attitude and spacecraft position requires 
      <i>spiceinit</i> to be applied to the image. This operation will update 
      the InstrumentPointing and InstrumentPosition Tables in the label of the 
      ISIS cube with the contents of the Gaskell SUMFILE. Note that SUMFILEs 
      contain vectors in body-fixed format, so you must ensure the proper PCK is 
      used with the image. NAIF routines are used to apply any required 
      transformations to retain the integrity of the data. Once the fidelity of 
      the updates are confirmed, new CK and SPK kernels can be created using the 
      ISIS <i>ckwriter</i> and <i>spkwriter</i> applications, respectively.
    </p>
  </description>

  <history>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2015-02-25">
      Original Version
    </change>
    <change name="Jeannie Backer" date="2015-12-07">
      Generalized to program work with Dawn and Hayabusa data. Clock times are 
      now updated in the instrument group and the original times are saved in 
      the Archive group of the cube labels.
    </change>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2016-02-09">
      Added implementation to support NAIF META kernel files. Updated 
      documentation. 
    </change>
  </history>

  <category>
    <categoryItem>Utility</categoryItem>
  </category>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">

      <parameter name= "FROM">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          A single cube to process.
        </brief> 
        <description>
          The name of a single input cube whose labels will be updated using a 
          Gaskell SUMFILE.  <b>Note: </b>Use the FROMLIST parameter instead of 
          this one if there are multiple cubes to process.
        </description>
        <default><item>None</item></default>
        <exclusions>
          <item>FROMLIST</item>
        </exclusions>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name= "FROMLIST">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          A list of cubes to process.
        </brief> 
        <description>
          A text file containing a list of input cubes whose labels will be 
          updated using Gaskell SUMFILEs. <b>Note: </b>Use the FROM parameter 
          instead of this one if there is only one cube to process.
        </description>
        <default><item>None</item></default>
        <exclusions>
          <item>FROM</item>
        </exclusions>
      </parameter>


      <parameter name="SUMFILE">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          The name of the SUMFILE to be used to update the input cube(s).
        </brief>
        <description>
          The name of a single Gaskell SUMFILE containing an updated start time 
          and SPICE information. <b>Note: </b>Use the SUMFILELIST parameter 
          instead of this one if the exact SUMFILE that should be used 
          to update the cube(s) is unknown or if there are more than one.
        </description>
        <filter>*.SUM</filter>
        <default><item>None</item></default>
        <exclusions>
          <item>SUMFILELIST</item>
          <item>TIMEDIFF</item>
        </exclusions>
      </parameter>

     <parameter name="SUMFILELIST">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          A list of SUMFILEs to search for the best match to update the given 
        cube(s). 
        </brief>
        <description>
          A text file containing a list of Gaskell SUMFILEs that each contain an 
          updated start time and SPICE information.  <b>Note: </b>Use the 
          SUMFILE parameter instead of this one if the exact SUMFILE is known 
          for the given cube(s). 
        </description>
        <filter>*.lis</filter>
        <default><item>None</item></default>
        <exclusions>
          <item>SUMFILE</item>
        </exclusions>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="MODE">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>
          Determines how the program will use the appropriate SUMFILE to update 
          the labels. 
        </brief>
        <description>
          Determines how the program will use the appropriate SUMFILE to update 
          the labels. Note that there are input requirements for each option.
        </description>
        <list>
          <option value="UPDATETIMES">
            <brief>
              Update the start and end times in the cube's label.
            </brief>
            <description>
              If the UPDATETIMES option is selected, the program update the time 
              and clock values in the cube's Instrument group. If a single 
              SUMFILE is given, the program will use this file. If a SUMFILELIST 
              was provided, the program will search for the file in the given 
              list whose time is within the specified TIMEDIFF tolerance and is 
              the closest to the SpacecraftClockStartCount in the cube. If 
              multiple files in the SUMFILELIST have the same time, this program 
              will choose to use the first one in the list with the closest 
              time. If no SUMFILE is found within this tolerance, a warning will 
              be printed to the output log and the program will exit without 
              updating the input cube's labels. Otherwise, the UTC on the second 
              line of the SUMFILE will replace the StartTime value in the cube's 
              Instrument group. The ExposureDuration in the label is then used 
              to find the new StopTime. These new start/stop time values are 
              used to determine the new SpacecraftClockStartCount and the new 
              SpacecraftClockStopCount. The original values of these keywords 
              and the SUMFILE used to update the keywords will be saved in the 
              cube's Archive group.
            </description>
          </option>
          <option value="UPDATESPICETABLES">
            <brief>
              Update the InstrumentPosition and InstrumentPointing tables in the cube's label.
            </brief>
            <description>
              If the UPDATESPICETABLES option is selected, the program will 
              search for the SumFile keyword in the cube's Archive group. If 
              no such keyword exists or if the SumFile saved to the labels is 
              not found in the given SUMFILELIST, a warning will be printed to 
              the output log and the program will exit without updating the 
              SPICE tables. Otherwise, the spacecraft position and pointing 
              information will be updated using the information provided in the 
              matching SUMFILE. Requirements: to run sumspice using the 
              UPDATESPICETABLES option, the input cube must have already been 
              run through sumspice with the UPDATETIMES option and then run 
              through spiceinit.
            </description>
            <exclusions>
              <item>TIMEDIFF</item>
            </exclusions>
          </option>
        </list>
        <default><item>UPDATETIMES</item></default>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TIMEDIFF">
          <type>double</type>
        <brief>
          The maximum allowed time difference between the cube's current start 
          time and the time found in the SUMFILE.
        </brief>
        <description>
          This value is used when the UPDATETIME option is selected and a 
          SUMFILELIST is provided. The file in the SUMFILELIST with the time 
          that is closest to the cube's start clock must be within this 
          tolerance for the cube to be updated.
        </description>
        <default><item>0.0</item></default>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="METAKERNEL">
          <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>List of SPICE kernels to support conversions</brief>
        <description>
            In some cases, additional kernels may be required in order to 
            compute some of the data acquired from the NAIF toolkit. If the ISIS 
            labels do not contain sufficient kernels, this parameter can specify 
            a NAIF meta kernel, or a single kernel of any supported NAIF type 
            that will be loaded prior to any computations. These kernels remain 
            loaded for all files and for the entirety of the runtime of this 
            application. See <a href="https://naif.jpl.nasa.gov/pub/naif/toolkit_docs/C/req/kernel.html">
            SPICE Kernel Required Reading for additional</a> information about 
            NAIF meta kernels.
        </description>
        <filter>*.meta *.tm</filter>
        <default><item>None</item></default>
      </parameter>

      </group>
  </groups>
</application>
