<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="hiequal" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">

  <brief>
      Tonematches a set of HiRISE cubes prior to mosaicking
  </brief>

  <description>
      <p>
        This program can be used to tonematch or equalize the brightness and 
        contrast of the input HiRISE cubes prior to mosaicking. The set of N
        cubes inputed must be all Red, all Blue-Green, or all Infared, where N 
        is an integer 2-10 for RED sets and exactly 2 both for IR and BG sets. 
        The order the cube names are provided in does not matter, but the cubes 
        must all follow a linear sequence without skipping cubes all the same 
        (i.e., the user cannot run this application on cubes RED1-RED3 and RED5 
        without also providing the program RED4).  Statistics are gathered by 
        line, taking into account the bin number of the cube (automatically 
        derived from the number of samples in the line).  The statistics are 
        used in an IntersectionStatistics object's least squares solution to 
        determine multiplicative and additive corrections to each image.  The 
        user has the option to stop the processing after the statistics and 
        corrective factors have been computed for examination. Alternatively, 
        the processing can continue and the corrective factors will be applied 
        to each image (by making sure the APPLY checkbox is ticked).  The actual
        equation to be used for each cube is:
        <pre>
            newdn(s,l)   =   (olddn(s,l) - avg()) * MULT() + avg() + BASE()
        </pre> where
        <pre>
            s = sample index
            l = line index 
          </pre>
      </p>

      <p>
          The BASE and MULT values are computed independently for each image, therefore we have two
          least squares computations with M unknowns, where M is the number of 
          cubes to be equalized. The intersections, O, between all the cubes are 
          computed and O &lt; M should hold in all cases.  In order for the
          least squares equation to be solved, there must be at least as many
          knowns as unknowns.  Therefore, you must hold one or more cubes to 
          alleviate this problem.  Holding a cube forces MULT and BASE to 1.0 
          and 0.0 respectively.
      </p>

      <p>
         If the APPLY option is selected, the equalized cubes will be named the same as the input cubes
         with the addition of a '.equ' prior to the '.cub' extension.
      </p>
  </description>

  <category>
    <missionItem>Mars Reconnaissance Orbiter</missionItem>
  </category>

<seeAlso>
    <applications>
      <item>equalizer</item>
    </applications>
  </seeAlso>

  <history>
    <change name="Travis Addair" date="2009-05-07">
      Original version
    </change>
    <change name="Travis Addair" date="2009-06-08">
      Fixed test data for compatibility across all systems and improved 
      documentation for clarity 
    </change>
    <change name="Travis Addair" date="2009-08-06">
      Changed parameter TO to OUTSTATS and added parameter TOLIST allowing the 
      user to specify the location of output files.  Output files are now placed 
      into the directory of the input cube when TOLIST is on the default 
      setting.  Statistic gathering results are now placed in the print file.
    </change>
  </history>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
        <parameter name="FROMLIST">
          <type>filename</type>
          <fileMode>input</fileMode>
          <brief>
              List of cubes to equalize
          </brief>
          <description>
              A list of HiRISE cubes to equalize.  The types (i.e., RED, BG, IR) 
              must match in order to do the equalization. 
          </description>

        </parameter>
        <parameter name="HOLDLIST">
            <type>filename</type>
            <fileMode>input</fileMode>
            <brief>
                List of filenames to hold 
            </brief>
            <description>
                List of cubes that are to be held in the equalization.  
                An additive and a multiplicative factor of 0 and 1 will be applied 
                to all cubes that were held.  All cubes listed in this file must 
                also be contained in FROMLIST.
            </description>
            <internalDefault>None</internalDefault>
            <filter>
              *.txt *.lis *.lst
            </filter>
        </parameter>  

        <parameter name="TOLIST">
            <type>filename</type>
            <fileMode>input</fileMode>
            <brief>
                The list of the equalized cubes to be created
            </brief>
            <description>
                This list of output files should contain a file to correspond to each 
                input file.  The output files will be written to the exact location 
                with the exact name specified unless it happens to be identical to 
                that of its corresponding input file, in which case an error will be 
                thrown.  If this file is not specified, but the APPLY option is 
                still selected, the output cubes will be placed in the directory of
                its input file, and named the same with the exception of ".equ" 
                extension (e.g. "foobar.cub" becomes foobar.equ.cub").
            </description>
            <internalDefault>Automatic</internalDefault>
            <filter>
              *.txt *.lis *.lst
            </filter>
        </parameter>  

        <parameter name="OUTSTATS">
          <type>filename</type>
          <fileMode>output</fileMode>
          <brief>
               Text file containing thorough equalization related statistics
          </brief>
          <description>
               This file will contain the statistics of all of the intersecting 
               areas along with the computed equalizing factors 
               (BASE and MULT).  Specifying this output file is optional.  
          </description>
          <internalDefault>None</internalDefault>
          <filter>
            *.txt *.pvl *.lis *.lst
          </filter>
        </parameter>

        <parameter name="APPLY">
            <type>boolean</type>
            <brief>
                Apply correction to the cubes
            </brief>
            <description>
                This option allows the user to decide whether they want to do the 
                equalization calculations only, or do the calculations and apply the 
                correction to the images.  If the APPLY option is not selected, you must
                specify a TO file.  If it is selected you can still optionally specify a TO file and
                the MULT/BASE values will be applied to each input cube.  The output cubes
                will be named the same with the exception of ".equ" extension (e.g. "foobar.cub"
                becomes "foobar.equ.cub").
            </description>
              <inclusions>
                <item>TOLIST</item>
              </inclusions>
             <default><item>TRUE</item></default>
        </parameter>
    </group>
  </groups>

    <examples>
    <example>
      <brief> RED Images Equalized </brief>
      <description>
        This example shows the use of the hiequal application with default 
        settings (i.e., no TO file with APPLY set true).  For demonstrative 
        purposes, the first image (RED0) has had its pixel values multiplied by 
        .8 with the "fx" application, and the two images have been mosaicked 
        together with "hiccdstitch".
      </description>
      <terminalInterface>
        <commandLine> fromlist= ../RedList.lst holdlist= ../RedHoldList.lst
        </commandLine>
        <description>
          Specify a list of 2 adjacent RED images to equalize along with a 
          holding list of one of the images (RED1) that enables the necessary 
          calculations to be performed.  All other options are at default 
          values.
        </description>
      </terminalInterface>

      <inputImages>
        <image src="assets/images/before.jpg" width="512" height="512">
          <brief> Mosaic of the input images for hiequal</brief>
          <description>
              This is a small section of the two input images for this example 
              mosaicked together, showing part of the intersection line prior to 
              tonematching.
          </description>
          <thumbnail caption=" Mosaic of unequalized adjacent images." src="assets/thumbs/before.jpg" width="200" height="200"/>
          <parameterName>FROMLIST</parameterName>
        </image>
      </inputImages>

      <outputImages>
        <image src="assets/images/after.jpg" width="512" height="512">
          <brief> Mosaic of the output images for hiequal</brief>
          <description> 
              The same section of the equalized output images mosaicked 
              together after the tonematching has been applied.
          </description>
          <thumbnail caption="Output image of mosaic showing results of the hiequal application." src="assets/thumbs/after.jpg" width="200" height="200"/>
        </image>
      </outputImages>

    </example>
  </examples>
</application>
