<?xml version="1.0"?>
<application name="cnetwinnow" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">
  <brief>
    Sets problem measures to ignored based on an examination of the residual histogram.
  </brief>

  <description>
    <p>
      After <b>jigsaw</b> has done a bundle adjustment on a group of overlapping Isis, level 
      1, <def>cube</def>s every image measure in the network will have associated residuals.
      A historgram of the residuals is constructed in order to determine the magnitude at which
      the noise (bad data) starts to dominate the solution.  The points are segregated into three
      categories in assending order of residual magnitude: inocent, suspect, and guilty.  The
      progam then attempts to ingore all the suspect and guilty measures based on the criteria
      for measure rejection provided.  If guilty measures cannot be ingored a report is generated
      documenting why.  No additional action is taken if suspect measure cannot be elliminated.
    </p>

    <h4>Known Issues</h4>
      <blockquote>
      Not spliting a network into <b>islands</b> is one of the primary considerations for whether
      or not a measure can be ingorned.  However, having even a single measure conecting mass of
      images A to mass of image B is currently considered sufficient for 'connecting' them together
      as a network.  Obviously this is a necissary, though grossly insufficient requirment.
      </blockquote>
  </description>

  <category>
    <categoryItem>Control Networks</categoryItem>
  </category>

  <seeAlso>
    <applications>
      <item>jigsaw</item>
      <item>deltack</item>
      <item>qnet</item>
    </applications>
  </seeAlso>

  <history>
    <change name="Orrin Thomas" date="2012-04-13">
      Original version
    </change>
  </history>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROMLIST">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          cube list
        </brief>
        <description>
          This file contains a list of all <def>cube</def>s in the <def>control network</def>
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.txt *.lis
        </filter>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="CNET">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input control network
        </brief>
        <description>
          This file is a <def>control network</def> generated from programs such as
          <b>autoseed</b> or <b>qnet</b>.  It contains the <def>control point</def>s
          and associated measures.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.net
        </filter>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="ONET">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Output control network
        </brief>
        <description>
          This output file contains the updated <def>control network</def> with
          the problem measures set to ignor.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.net
        </filter>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="FILE_PREFIX">
            <type>string</type>
            <internalDefault>none</internalDefault>
            <brief>output file prefix</brief>
            <description>
              2 Reports will be generated:
              1. FILE_PREFIXGuilty.csv, a report of apparently bad points that could not be set to ignored,
              2. FILE_PREFIXIgnored.csv, a report of all the measures that were set to ignor.
            </description>
        </parameter>
    </group>


    <group name="Histogram Analysis Parameters--The user is advised to use caution if changing the defualts">
      <parameter name="BIN_WIDTH">
        <brief>The width of the histogram bins in unweighted pixels.</brief>
        <description>
            The program will build and analyze a histogram of the R^2 residual lengths.
            This prameter tells the software how wide to make each bin.  Unless the user
            has studied the behaviour of residuals (particularly with regard to their
            networks), we do not advise changing the default.
        </description>
        <type>double</type>
        <default>
          <item>0.1</item>
        </default>
          <minimum inclusive="no">0</minimum>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="SUSPECT_BUMP_PERCENT">
        <brief> The percent that that a local histogram maximum must be greater than a local minimum to be considered suspect.</brief>
        <description>
            If all of the measurements in network belong to Gaussian distribution (one of the typical assumptions in
            least squares analysis) then the residual histogram should be strictly decreasing in the tail.  There should
            be only one local maxima near the median (a results of using equal distance bins instead of equal area).  All
            other local maxima are 'bumps' and reveal where the assumption of Gaussian noise is breaking down.  The
            SUSPECT_BUMP_PERCENT is the minimum bump height (in percentage of the preceding local minima) for a bump to be
            considered suspect.  And barring user override will be the boundary between inocent and suspect points.
            Changing the default is not typically recomended.
        </description>
        <type>double</type>
        <default>
          <item>5</item>
        </default>
        <minimum inclusive="yes">0</minimum>
        <maximum inclusive="yes">100</maximum>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="GUILTY_BUMP_PERCENT">
        <brief> The percent that that a local histogram maximum must be greater than a local minimum to be considered guilty.</brief>
        <description>
            If all of the measurements in network belong to Gaussian distribution (one of the typical assumptions in
            least squares analysis) then the residual histogram should be strictly decreasing in the tail.  There should
            be only one local maxima near the median (a results of using equal distance bins instead of equal area).  All
            other local maxima are 'bumps' and reveal where the assumption of Gaussian noise is breaking down.  The
            GUILTY_BUMP_PERCENT is the minimum bump height (in percentage of the preceding local minima) for a bump to be
            considered guilty.  And barring user override will be the boundary between suspect and guilty points.
            Changing the default is not typically recomended.
        </description>
        <type>double</type>
        <default>
          <item>10</item>
        </default>
        <minimum inclusive="yes">0</minimum>
        <maximum inclusive="yes">100</maximum>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="SUSPECT_FLOOR">
        <brief>There will be no attempt to set residuals smaller than this user defined limit to ignored.</brief>
        <description>
            SUSPECT_FLOOR is the lowest that the boundary between inocent and suspect residual magnitudes will slip.
            Histogram analysis may however result in a higher magnitude boundary.
        </description>
        <type>double</type>
        <default>
          <item>1.0</item>
        </default>
        <minimum inclusive="yes">0.0</minimum>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="GUILTY_FLOOR">
        <brief>Every residual greater than user defined GUILTY_FLOOR is guilty</brief>
        <description>
            GUILTY_FLOOR is the highest that the boundary between suspect and guilty residual magnitudes will slip.
            Histogram analysis may however result in a lower magnitude boundary--strickly greater than the inocent-suspect boundary.
        </description>
        <type>double</type>
        <default>
          <item>2.5</item>
        </default>
        <minimum inclusive="yes">0.0</minimum>
      </parameter>
   </group>

   <group name="Measure Rejection Criteria">
      <parameter name="HULL_REDUCTION_PERCENT">
        <brief>Maximum precent reduction to the area of the convex hull of the measures in an image.</brief>
        <description>
          Maximum precent reduction to the area of the convex hull of the measures in an image.
        </description>
        <type>double</type>
        <default>
          <item>15</item>
        </default>
        <minimum inclusive="yes">0</minimum>
        <maximum inclusive="yes">100</maximum>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="MEASURE_REDUCTION_PERCENT">
        <brief>Maximum precent reduction of the measures in an image.</brief>
        <description>
          Maximum precent reduction of the measures in an image.
        </description>
        <type>double</type>
        <default>
          <item>30</item>
        </default>
        <minimum inclusive="yes">0</minimum>
        <maximum inclusive="yes">100</maximum>
      </parameter>
   </group>
 </groups>
</application>
