<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="kaguyasp2isis" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">

  <brief>
    Imports a Kaguya SP (Spectral Profiler) file
  </brief>

  <description>
  <p>
    This program will import a Kaguya SP (Spectral Profiler) file to a tab delimited text file.
    The text file will contain one record for each wavelength in the SP file. There are 296
    wavelengths available in an SP file. Each record in the output file will contain all the
    observations for a specific wavelength. The user can limit the number of observations that
    are listed by using the MINOBS and MAXOBS parameters.
  </p>
  <p>
    The documents in the kaguyasp2isis/assets directory provide information about the Kaguya
    Spectral Profiler data. The directory also contains a cheat sheet to determine what the 
    different Quality Assessment values mean.
  </p>
  <p>
    Please note that there is no attempt by this program to remove redundant or erroneous
    data at the instrument joins (e.g., VIS, NIR1, NIR2). Also, the data currently available
    do not extend to the NIR2 wavelengths in calibrated form.
  </p>
  </description>

  <history>
    <change name="Janet Barrett" date="2014-02-19">
      Original version. This program imports binary data
      from a Kaguya Spectral Profiler file and puts the 
      data into a tab delimited table.
    </change>
    <change name="Tyler Wilson" date="2015-08-19">
      Changed the line:  <categoryItem>Utility</categoryItem>
      to <missionItem>Kaguya</missionItem> so that this
      app does not appear under a list of Core ISIS programs,
      but instead appears with kaguyami2isis and kaguyac2isis
      under Mission Specific programs in the documentation.	
    </change>	
  </history>

  <category>
    <missionItem>Kaguya</missionItem>
  </category>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input Kaguya SP file
        </brief>
        <description>
          This is the input Kaguya SP file
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.spc
        </filter>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="TO">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Output Kaguya text file
        </brief>
        <description>
          The output file will be formatted as a tab delimited
          file and will contain all requested observations for
          a single wavelength in each record of the file. Each
          observation will include the raw, radiance, reflectance,
          and QA information.
        </description>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Limit Parameters">
      <parameter name="MINOBS">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>Minimum observation</brief>
        <description>
          This is the minimum observation of the observation range
          for which information will be obtained from the input
          file. If no value is specified, then the minimum will be
          set to 1.
        </description>
        <default><item>None</item></default>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="MAXOBS">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>Maximum observation</brief>
        <description>
          This is the maximum observation of the observation range
          for which information will be obtained from the input 
          file. If no value is specified, then the maximum will be
          set to the maximum observation in the input file.
        </description>
        <default><item>None</item></default>
      </parameter>
    </group>
  </groups>
</application>
