<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="eis2isis" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">

  <brief>
    Import Clipper EIS NAC files into ISIS format
  </brief>
  <description>
    <p>
      This program will import PDS4 formatted files from the Europa Clipper Europa Imaging System (EIS) instrument into the ISIS
      Cube format. This includes three required components: the main EIS data image, the associated image label, and the associated
      main image readout times table (CSV). Two additional (optional) files are the checkline image (and associated xml label) 
      and the checkline image readout times table (CSV).
    </p>
  </description>

  <history>
    <change name="Makayla Shepherd, Stuart Sides, Ian Humphrey" date="2017-12-19">
      Original version.
    </change>
    <change name="Tyler Wilson" date="2018-04-03">
      Added normalizeTimeTable which outputs check tables (and check line tables) with time values
      normalized in the interval [-1,1].  Added checktable/check line readout table, and normalized
      readout table to the output cubes (the main image and the checkline image).
    </change>
     <change name="Tyler Wilson" date="2018-04-04">
        Added PvlGroup jitter with PvlKeyword Coefficients to output cube labels, and initialized 
        the Coefficients array to (0.0,0.0,0.0)
    </change>
    <change name="Tyler Wilson" date="2018-04-12">
       Added the ability to write the checkline cube as a Blob to the Pvl label of the main
       EIS cube.
   </change>
   <change name="Summer Stapleton-Greig" date="2019-06-13">
      Updated application to be able to handle both the nacRs and the wacFc
      image ingestion. This change should cover the basics of the other two
      camera models as well. Also updated logic for the nacRs to handle cases
      differently: a main image may now be ingested without the associated
      checkline image, a main image may not be ingested without the associated
      times text file, and a checkline image may not be ingested without it's
      associated line times text file. Test have been updated to reflect these
      changes.
  </change>
  <change name="Stuart Sides and Summer Stapleton-Greig" date="2019-06-17">
     Updated application to ingest PDS4 rather than PDS3 files as the mission
     will be using the PDS4 standards for their label .xml files.
 </change>
  <change name="Kristin Berry" date="2020-01-08">
     Updates to documentation to add detail and bring it up to date with the current version of the software, prior to checkin to dev. 
     Move NAC-only keywords into a NAC-only group.
 </change>
  </history>

  <seeAlso>
    <applications>
      <item>pds2isis</item>
    </applications>
  </seeAlso>

  <category>
    <missionItem>Clipper</missionItem>
  </category>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          An EIS main image file to be converted to an ISIS cube
        </brief>
        <description>
          Use this parameter to select the filename of the xml label for a a Clipper EIS <em>main image</em>
          file to be converted to a cube. This is expected to be a PDS4 formatted file. The associated image must 
	  have the same name as the label and end in ".dat." 
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.xml
        </filter>
      </parameter>

    <parameter name="TO">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Output ISIS cube file for the main image
        </brief>
        <description>
          The output cube file that will contain the EIS NAC <em>main image</em> in ISIS format.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>

    </group>

    <group name="NAC Only"> 

	<parameter name="FROM2">
	  <type>filename</type>
	  <fileMode>input</fileMode>
	  <internalDefault>None</internalDefault>
	  <brief>
	    An EIS NAC checkline image file to be converted to an ISIS cube
	  </brief>
	  <description>
	    Use this parameter to select the filename of the xml label for a Clipper EIS NAC <em>checkline image</em>
	    file to be converted to a cube. This is expceted to be a PDS4 formatted file.  The associated image must 
	    have the same name as the label and end in ".dat." 
	  </description>
	  <filter>
	    *.xml
	  </filter>
	</parameter>

      <parameter name="MAINREADOUT">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <internalDefault>None</internalDefault>
        <brief>
          Input CSV file containing the main image readout times
        </brief>
        <description>
          Use this parameter to select the filename of the main image readout times CSV file. This
          file contains the line numbers and associated readout times for each line.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.csv
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="CHECKLINEREADOUT">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <internalDefault>None</internalDefault>
        <brief>
          Input CSV file containing the checkline readout times
        </brief>
        <description>
          Use this parameter to select the filename of the checkline image readout times CSV file.
          This file contains the <em>checkline</em> numbers and associated readout times for each
          <em>checkline</em>.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.csv
        </filter>
      </parameter>


      <parameter name="TO2">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <internalDefault>None</internalDefault>
        <brief>
          Output ISIS cube file for the checkline image 
        </brief>
        <description>
          The output cube file that will contain the EIS NAC <em>checkline image</em> ISIS format.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>
    </group>
   </groups>

</application>
