<?xml version="1.0"?>
<application name="deltack" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd"> 


  <brief>
    Update camera pointing for a single image
  </brief>

  <description>
    <p>
      <b>deltack</b> can be used to correct most instances of problems with 
      camera attitude.  It adjusts camera orientation in the labels of a single 
      Isis 3 cube (resection). In order for <b>deltack</b> to work properly, the 
      input cube must have been initialized with <b>spiceinit</b> using 
      ATTACH="YES". 
    </p>
    <h3>BUNDLE Method</h3>
    <p>
      Like <b>jigsaw</b>, <b>deltack</b> works on both framing cameras and line 
      scanners using the BUNDLE method.  The user must supply a 
      latitude/longitude for at least one sample/line coordinate in the image. 
      Angles 1 and 2 of the camera orientation stored in the cube labels will be 
      adjusted to align the coordinate with the entered latitude/longitude.  To 
      solve for all three camera angles, select the TWIST option.  A second 
      coordinate point and desired latitude/longitude must be entered if the 
      <b>TWIST</b> option is used. <b>deltack</b> will adjust the camera 
      orientation to align both points with their corresponding 
      latitudes/longitudes with minimal residuals in sample and line.
    </p>
    <p>
      The camera pointing is updated using an iterative least-squares bundle 
      adjustment.  The number of iterations (<b>MAXIT</b>)and tolerance 
      (<b>SIGMA0</b>) for  convergence are input parameters to <b>deltack</b>.  
      Solving for two angles only is similar to a translation of the image in 
      sample and line. Solving for the twist as well will result in both a 
      translation and a rotation.
    </p>

    <p>
      <b>deltack</b> creates a set of two output files for analyzing the 
      results. <b>BUNDLEOUT.TXT</b> provides an overall summary of the 
      resection.  It lists the user input parameters selected and tables of 
      statistics for both the image and the point(s). <b>RESIDUALS.CSV</b> 
      provides a table of the measured image coordinates and the final sample, 
      line, and overall residuals in both millimeters and pixels.
    </p>
   <h3>DIRECT Method</h3>
     <p>
       The DIRECT method can be applied to cameras/instruments that are not 
       supported by <b>jigsaw</b> or the viewing geometry conditions are not 
       supported in BUNDLE. The DIRECT method is particularly useful for the 
       Cassini VIMS (and other (spot) spectrometer type instruments) and for 
       cases where the geometry is partially or completely off the target body. 
       The DIRECT method primarily differs from the BUNDLE method in that it 
       computes a rotation matrix directly from the SAMP1/LINE1 to the LAT1/LON1 
       surface intercept vectors from the spacecraft position reference in the 
       J2000 coordinate system. Essentially, these are the look direction 
       vectors from those camera coordinates in J2000 which eliminates any 
       peculiarities within the camera coordinate system. And, most importantly, 
       it does not require all sample/line coordinates to map to valid geometric 
       coordinates. It does not, however, support the TWIST option or the 
       two-point scenario as does the BUNDLE method.
     </p>
     <p>
       This approach works in variable acquistion time instrument systems, such 
       as line scan, pushbroom, pushframe and (spot) spectrometers (as well as 
       framing camera instruments) because the rotation matrix is determined 
       independent of spacecraft position. It also works for situations where 
       the geometry is off the target body because the look vector is always 
       properly set in the ISIS camera model even if it does not intersect the 
       surface. Note, however, in the later case, the LAT1/LON1 position must 
       intersect the target body to obtain a valid sample/line coordinate. 
     </p>
     <p>
       The DIRECT method was designed to correct the pointing for the Cassini 
       VIMS spectrometer but it is designed to be generally applicable to all 
       cameras supported in the ISIS system. The BUNDLE method does not work on 
       the VIMS instrument and likely many other complex camera systems with 
       peculiar geometric configurations, such as (spot) spectrometers. The 
       recommended procedure to determine an update to VIMS pointing is to first 
       determine the geometric coordinate of a commmon feature in a reference 
       image, such as a Cassini ISS observation for example, where the same 
       latitude/longitude coordinate maps to a line/sample in the VIMS image. 
       The VIMS geometric coordinate is expected not match the feature in the 
       ISS image but <b>qview</b> and/or <b>campt</b> must report a valid 
       line/sample coordinate from the latitude/longitude coordinate. The next 
       step is to choose the best sample/line coordinate in the VIMS image that 
       best matches the feature in the ISS image. To correctly update the 
       pointing in the VIMS image, provide the latitude/longitude coordinate 
       from the ISS image in the LAT1/LON1 parameters and the line/sample 
       coordinate of the feature in the VIMS image in the SAMP1/LINE1 parameters 
       to <b>deltack</b>. You may make a copy of the original image prior to 
       running <b>deltack</b> if desired.
     </p> 
     <p>
       A similar procedure to the one described for VIMS will also work to 
       update the pointing of an image where the SPICE ephemeris data does not 
       provide a valid latitude/longitude on the target body. The distinction is 
       that the SAMP1/LINE1 coordinate need not intersect the body. Indeed, this 
       is a common problem encountered typically with older data sets and 
       generally with flyby images where the target is partially or fully in the 
       field of view of the camera. There is an alternative technique for flyby 
       images of this type that does not require a second reference image. The 
       case where this technique is most effective is typically used for framing 
       cameras where the center of the target body is in view and there is at 
       least 1 pixel in the image that maps to the surface where geometric data 
       can be computed. Using <b>campt</b>, provide the sample/line coordinate 
       of any valid geometric point in the image - it does not have to visibly 
       intersect the target body - any sample/line coordinate will suffice. 
       <b>campt</b> reports the sub-spacecraft latitude/longitude coordinate for 
       every valid geometric coordinate - it will always be the same coordinate 
       for framing cameras. If the full disk of the target body is viewable and 
       the image is relative free of noise/artifacts, the <b>center</b> program 
       computes the centroid sample/line coordinate of the target body. If this 
       condition is not met, use <b>qview</b> to manually approximate the center 
       pixel coordinate of the body. Provide the centroid sample/line in the 
       SAMP1/LINE1 coordinate and the 
       SubSpacecraftLatitude/SubSpacecraftLongitude values computed by 
       <b>campt</b> in the LAT1/LON1 parameter to <b>deltack</b>. 
     </p>
   </description>

  <category>
    <categoryItem>Control Networks</categoryItem>
  </category>

  <seeAlso>
    <applications>
      <item>jigsaw</item>
    </applications>
  </seeAlso>

  <history>
    <change name="Jeff Anderson" date="2006-09-06">
      Original version
    </change>
    <change name="Tracie Sucharski" date="2007-05-02">
      Added inclusion of TWIST to SAMP2,LINE2,LAT2,LON2,RAD2.  
      Without this inclusion, the AML was requiring these parameters
      even if TWIST was false.
    </change>
    <change name="Debbie A. Cook" date="2007-07-12">
      Added pvl status report for a successful update.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Koechle" date="2007-10-05">
      Added check to see if cube has existing polygon, if so delete it.
    </change>
    <change name="Debbie A. Cook" date="2011-06-06">
      Updated to current version of BundleAdjust class.
    </change>
    <change name="Debbie A. Cook" date="2011-06-07">
      Changed point type "Ground" to "Fixed".
    </change>
    <change name="Debbie A. Cook" date="2011-09-28">
      Updated documentation in response to Mantis issue #187.
    </change>
    <change name="Brent A. Archinal" date="2011-09-30">
      Updated documentation, mostly to indicate units.
    </change>
    <change name="Debbie A. Cook" date="2011-10-04">
      Added documentation for output files and removed creation of 
      output csv tables because the tables are not useful for
      only one or two points.  The information is already listed
      in bundleout.txt.
    </change>
    <change name="Kimberly Oyama" date="2014-03-28">
      Added check for history group in input cube. If it's there, add a new 
      entry. If not, add a new history group. Added an app test. Fixes #1350. 
    </change>
    <change name="Jeannie Backer" date="2014-07-23">
      Modified to create a bundle settings object for the bundle adjustment.
    </change>
    <change name="Ian Humphrey and Makayla Shepherd" date="2015-09-01">
      Changed code to accommodate changes in Sensor and Camera relationships.
    </change>
    <change name="Jeannie Backer" date="2016-04-22">
      Modified to use the FROM cube labels to set output control net's 'target' 
      instead of the TargetName. Removed check for TargetName since this happens 
      when the ControlNet target is set. References #3892 
    </change>
    <change name="Jeannie Backer" date="2016-08-18">
      Removed deprecated parameter from call to BundleSettings::setSolveOptions. 
      References #4162. 
    </change>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2017-08-01">
      Added new DIRECT method to update the pointing for instrument with special 
      conditions. The DIRECT method is intended for use with instrument camera 
      models that do not work in jigsaw (more specifically, BundleAdjust) such 
      as Cassini VIMS. Added the METHOD parameter to allow user to select which 
      method to apply. The default is METHOD=BUNDLE which chooses pre-existing 
      behavor. Updated documentation to reflect these new changes. Fixes #4868. 
    </change>
    <change name="Ken Edmundson" date="2018-05-23">
      Modifed call to bundleAdjustment->solveCholeskyBR() to return a raw pointer to a
      BundleSolutionInfo object. Am also deleting this pointer because jigsaw.cpp takes
      ownership from BundleAdjust.
    </change>    
  </history>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input camera cube
        </brief>
        <description>
  	       The file specification for the input cube. The cube will have its 
           camera pointing updated. 
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Options">
      <parameter name="METHOD">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>Specify the method to use to compute the pointing adjustment</brief>
        <description>
          <p>
            There are two types of methods that can be used to compute the
            pointing update: BUNDLE and DIRECT.
          </p>
        </description>
        <default><item>BUNDLE</item></default>
        <list>
            <option value="BUNDLE">
                <brief>
                  Use jigsaw bundle adjustment method
                </brief>
                <description>
                    The BUNDLE method uses jigsaw photogrammetric techniques to 
                    adjust the pointing differences from a point to a 
                    latitude/longitude coordinate. BUNDLE is also more flexible 
                    in that it can also correct for TWIST by providing a second 
                    set of SAMP2/LINE2 and LAT2/LON2 parameters.
                </description>
            </option>
           <option value="DIRECT">
                <brief>
                    Use direct adjustment method 
                </brief>
                <description>
                   The DIRECT method computes the pointing differences in look 
                   directions of the SAMP1/LINE1 point and LAT1/LON1 coordinate. 
                   All entries in the InstrumentPointing table object are 
                   adjusted by a constant linear rotation. This method does not 
                   currently support the TWIST option.
                </description>
                <exclusions>
                  <item>SIGMA0</item>
                  <item>MAXITS</item>
                  <item>TWIST</item>
                  <item>LINE2</item>
                  <item>SAMP2</item>
                  <item>LAT2</item>
                  <item>LON2</item>
                  <item>RAD2</item>
                </exclusions>
            </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>
    </group>


    <group name="Bundle Adjustment Options">
      <parameter name="SIGMA0">
        <brief>Standard deviation of unit weight</brief>
        <description>
           Convergence is reached when the solution parameters change by less 
           than Sigma0. Units:  unitless.
        </description>
        <type>double</type>
        <default><item>1.0e-10</item></default>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="MAXITS">
        <brief>Iterations</brief>
        <description>Maximum number of iterations</description>
        <type>integer</type>
        <default><item>10</item></default>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="TWIST">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <brief>Solve for camera twist</brief>
        <default><item>False</item></default>
        <description>
          In addition to angle1 and angle2, if this parameter is set the program 
          will solve for the camera twist.  This requires input of a second 
          fixed coordinate (SAMP2,LINE2) and (LAT2,LON2)
        </description>
        <inclusions>
          <item>LINE2</item>
          <item>SAMP2</item>
          <item>LAT2</item>
          <item>LON2</item>
          <item>RAD2</item>
        </inclusions>
      </parameter>
   </group>

   <group name="Fixed Points">
     <parameter name="SAMP1">
       <type>double</type>
       <brief>Sample coordinate, point #1</brief>
       <description>
          The sample coordinate for fixed point #1 (LAT1,LON1).  Units:: pixels
       </description>
     </parameter>

     <parameter name="LINE1">
       <type>double</type>
       <brief>Line coordinate, point #1</brief>
       <description>
          The line coordinate for fixed point #1 (LAT1,LON1).    Units:: pixels
       </description>
     </parameter>

     <parameter name="LAT1">
       <type>double</type>
       <brief>Latitude, point #1</brief>
       <description>
          Desired planetocentric latitude at the image coordinate (SAMP1,LINE1).
          Units:  degrees.
       </description>
       <minimum inclusive="yes">-90.0</minimum>
       <maximum inclusive="yes">90.0</maximum>
     </parameter>

     <parameter name="LON1">
       <type>double</type>
       <brief>Longitude, point #1</brief>
       <description>
          Desired east longitude at the image coordinate (SAMP1,LINE1).
          Units:  degrees
       </description>
       <minimum inclusive="yes">0.0</minimum>
       <maximum inclusive="yes">360.0</maximum>
     </parameter>

     <parameter name="RAD1">
       <type>double</type>
       <brief>Radius, point #1</brief>
       <internalDefault>Computed</internalDefault>
       <description>
          Desired radius at the image coordinate (SAMP1,LINE1).  It 
          will be automatically computed using the shape model that was
          entered in the "spiceinit" application.  Units:  meters.
       </description>
       <minimum inclusive="no">0.0</minimum>
     </parameter>

     <parameter name="SAMP2">
       <type>double</type>
       <brief>Sample coordinate, point #2</brief>
       <description>
          The sample coordinate for fixed point #2 (LAT2,LON2).  Units:  pixels.
       </description>
       <inclusions>
           <item>TWIST</item>
       </inclusions>
     </parameter>

     <parameter name="LINE2">
       <type>double</type>
       <brief>Line coordinate, point #2</brief>
       <description>
          The line coordinate for fixed point #2 (LAT2,LON2).  Units:  pixels.
       </description>
       <inclusions>
           <item>TWIST</item>
       </inclusions>
     </parameter>

     <parameter name="LAT2">
       <type>double</type>
       <brief>Latitude, point #2</brief>
       <description>
          Planetocentric latitude at the image coordinate (SAMP2,LINE2).
          Units:  degrees.
       </description>
       <minimum inclusive="yes">-90.0</minimum>
       <maximum inclusive="yes">90.0</maximum>
       <inclusions>
          <item>TWIST</item>
       </inclusions>
     </parameter>

     <parameter name="LON2">
       <type>double</type>
       <brief>Longitude, point #2</brief>
       <description>Desired east longitude at the image coordinate (SAMP2,LINE2).
                    Units:  degrees.
       </description>
       <minimum inclusive="yes">0.0</minimum>
       <maximum inclusive="yes">360.0</maximum>
       <inclusions>
           <item>TWIST</item>
       </inclusions>
     </parameter>

     <parameter name="RAD2">
       <type>double</type>
       <brief>Radius, point #2</brief>
       <internalDefault>Computed</internalDefault>
       <description>
         Radius at the image coordinate (SAMP2,LINE2). It will be automatically 
         computed using the shape model that was initialized in the "spiceinit" 
         application.  Units:  meters.
       </description>
       <minimum inclusive="no">0.0</minimum>
       <inclusions>
          <item>TWIST</item>
       </inclusions>
     </parameter>
   </group>
  </groups>

</application>
