<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="cnetmerge" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">

  <brief>
    Merges multiple Control Networks into one
  </brief>

  <description>
    <p>
      This program attempts to merge a set of (two or more)
      <def link="Control Network">Control Networks</def> into a single network.
      The merging process starts with a "base" network into which each
      successive "add" network is added.  When conflicts arise between the base
      network and the network being added, a set of user-selected options are
      used to determine how the conflicts are resolved.
    </p>

    <p>
      When more than two Control Networks are merged, note that the "base"
      network is updated iteratively when each successive network is added.
      So the definition of the "base" network is dynamic in this case.
    </p>

    <p>
      For any point or measure that is edit locked in the base network, that
      point or measure will never be modified regardless of the OVERWRITE
      options set.  When a point is edit locked, the reference measure is locked
      implicitly.  So, for example, if OVERWRITEREFERENCE is selected, and a
      control point is edit locked, that point's reference will not be
      overwritten.
    </p>

    <p>
      Note: Each network must share the same target.
    </p>
  </description>

  <history>
    <change name="Christpher Austin" date="2008-04-04">
      Original version
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2008-06-24">
      Clarified error messages and added documentation.  (Removed netmerge from
      the system, because it did the same thing, just not quite as clean)
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2008-08-05">
      Fix xml app name error
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2008-11-13">
      Rebuilt for more Control Point Id control, including a REPLACE option.
      Only FORCE prefixes the original Control Network Id to the new Control
      Point Ids, then logs the number of duplicate Control Points.  NORMAL and
      REPLACE leave the Control Point Ids alone.
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2009-01-09">
      Added the FROMLIST input option.
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2009-01-13">
      Changed MERGETYPE param name and options to be more clear. Changed MODE
      to INPUTTYPE. Added the REPORT param which reveals any Control Points
      that have been renamed or replaced durring the merge.
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2009-01-15">
      Added Filename expansion to the listed nets and a few other minor
      readability changes.
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2009-11-19">
      Multiple changes based on user request, including removal of RENAME,
      replacing REPLACE with MERGE while merging at the Control Measure level.
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2010-03-15">
      Changed an outdated error message.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2010-10-19">
      Updated to work with recent control network changes
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2011-01-19">
      Altered to compile with the new Control redesign.
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2011-02-25">
      Fixed a simple pointer ownership issue.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2011-04-11">
      Updated parameter names
    </change>
    <change name="Travis Addair" date="2011-05-26">
      Separated reference resolution control out of OVERWRITEMEASURES and into
      new parameter OVERWRITEREFERENCE.
    </change>
    <change name="Travis Addair" date="2011-05-27">
      Overhauled documentation to better explain the distinction between the
      base Control Network and the networks being added into it.
    </change>
    <change name="Debbie A. Cook and Tracie Sucharski" date="2011-06-07">
      Change point type "Ground" to "Fixed"
    </change>
    <change name="Travis Addair" date="2011-05-27">
      Overhauled the application to reflect functional changes to the program,
      and fix inconsistencies between the documentation and the code.  The
      program now operates without regard for point type, and properly honors
      all OVERWRITE options in all situations, which fixes #230.  A fourth
      option has been added, OVERWRITEMISSING, which will remove measures that
      do not appear in newer networks being added to the base, which fixes #228.
      The log file has been revamped to print out a PVL report for each network,
      and each conflicting point or measure.  Every conflict will be reported
      along with a reason (based on user parameter options) for the ultimate
      resolution.  This is in reference to issue #229, but more logging will
      need to be done in order to warn the user of potential pitfalls in their
      selected options.
    </change>
    <change name="Jai Rideout" date="2011-08-04">
      Made a small modification to the code in mergeNetworks(...) that created a
      new control network for each file in the file list. FileList's overloaded
      '[]' operator that was used inside of the call to Filename's constructor
      confused the compiler on Ubuntu10.04 systems.
    </change>
    <change name="Travis Addair, Janet Richie, Elpitha Howington-Kraus" date="2011-10-07">
      Rewrote large sections of the documentation to make more clear,
      accessible, and user-friendly.
    </change>
    <change name="Travis Addair" date="2012-04-17">
      Moved duplicate point check for DUPLICATEPOINTS=ERROR to occur before
      merging is attempted.  In this way, errors can be caught before expensive
      merging begins.  Also enabled logging of duplicate points.  If the user
      specifies a LOG file with DUPLICATEPOINTS=ERROR, all duplicate points will
      be reported to that file before the program terminates.
    </change>
    <change name="Travis Addair" date="2011-04-18">
      Removed the REVERSE option and changed the CNET parameter to BASE.  When
      INPUTTYPE=CNETS, BASE will act exactly as CNET did.  However, when
      INPUTTYPE=LIST, the BASE parameter can now be provided in order to set an
      explicit base network, effectively adding it to the front of the input
      list.  If the explicit base network also appears in the input list, it
      will be ignored there to avoid adding it twice.  If not value is provided
      for BASE, the first element in the list is considered the base network.
    </change>
  </history> 

  <category>
    <categoryItem>Control Networks</categoryItem>
  </category>

  <groups>
    <group name="Input">
      <parameter name = "INPUTTYPE">
        <type>string</type>
        <default><item>LIST</item></default>
        <brief>How the program should retrieve its input</brief>
        <description>
          This parameter specifies whether the program should take its input
          from a list of Control Networks to be merged (LIST) or directly from
          a pair of parameters specifying a base and add network (CNETS).
        </description>
        <list>
          <option value = "LIST">
            <brief>Merge a list of networks</brief>
            <description>
              <p>
                This option will have the program retrieve its input from a list
                of Control Networks (one per line), and merge them one by one.
                The first network in the list acts as the initial "base" network
                into which each successive network is "added".  The last network
                in the file is the last network to be added to the network, and
                thus will have either highest or lowest priority in certain
                conflict resolutions depending on the option(s) specified in the
                "Conflict Resolution" parameter group.
              </p>
              <p>
                If a value is provided for the BASE parameter, then that network
                will become the new, explicit base.  This will effectively place
                the explicit base at the front of the input list.  If the
                explicit base appears elsewhere in the list, it will be ignored
                there to avoid adding it to the output twice.
              </p>
            </description>
            <exclusions>
              <item>CNET2</item>
            </exclusions>
          </option>
          <option value = "CNETS">
            <brief>Merge a pair of networks</brief>
            <description>
              Selecting this option is like providing a list of networks to be
              merged with only two networks.  The first network (BASE) will
              act as the base network, and the second network (CNET2) will act
              as the network being "added".
            </description>
            <inclusions>
              <item>BASE</item>
            </inclusions>
            <exclusions>
              <item>CLIST</item>
            </exclusions>
          </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name = "CLIST">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          List of Control Networks to be merged
        </brief>
        <description>
          <p>
            Starting from the first network in the list as the "base", the
            program will "add" each following network in the order specified by
            this list to produce the output.  When conflicts arise, they are
            resolved in accordance with the options in the "Conflict Resolution"
            group.
          </p>
          <p>
            If a value is provided for the BASE parameter, then that network
            will effectively be added to the front of this list, becoming the
            new base network into which all the networks in this list are added.
            If the BASE filename also appears elsewhere in this list, it will be
            ignored in the list to avoid adding it twice.
          </p>
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.txt *.lis *.list *.lst
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="BASE">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <internalDefault>Automatic</internalDefault>
        <brief>
          "Base" Control Network
        </brief>
        <description>
          <p>
            The "base" Control Network into which all other control networks
            will be "added".  When no overwrite option(s) from the "Conflict
            Resolution" group are selected, any conflicts will be resolved by
            retaining the values from this network.
          </p>
          <p>
            This parameter is required for the INPUTTYPE of CNETS, and is
            optional for LIST.  When INPUTTYPE=LIST and an explicit BASE is
            provided, the value of this parameter will act as the first network
            in the list, making it the base network into which all other
            networks are added.  If a network with the same filename appears in
            the input list, it will be ignored in the list to avoid adding it
            twice.
          </p>
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.ctl *.pvl *.net
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="CNET2">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Control Network to be "added"
        </brief>
        <description>
          The Control Network to be "added" into the base network.  When an
          overwrite option(s) in the "Conflict Resolution" group is selected, 
          the conflicting value from this network will replace the existing
          value in the base network.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.ctl *.pvl *.net
        </filter>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Output">
      <parameter name="ONET">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Merged Control Network
        </brief>
        <description>
          The output Control Network, which is the merged result of the input
          networks.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.ctl *.pvl *.net
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="NETWORKID">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>The NetworkId keyword value for the merged ControlNet</brief>
        <description>
          The NetworkId keyword for the newly merged ControlNet will be set to
          this given value. The Networkid is a single word identifier or name
          assigned to a Control Network.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="DESCRIPTION">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>The Description keyword value for the merged ControlNet</brief>
        <description>
          The Description keyword for the newly merged ControlNet will be set
          to this given value.  This should be a brief description of the
          purpose of the merged control network.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="LOG">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <internalDefault>None</internalDefault>
        <brief>
          Reports Control Points that conflicted
        </brief>
        <description>
          This file will contain a report that reveals all Control Points that
          were conflicted during the merging process. If no Control Points
          conflicted, then this file will be empty.
        </description>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Conflict Resolution">
      <parameter name="DUPLICATEPOINTS">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>
          How to handle Control Points appearing in both base and add networks
        </brief>
        <default><item>ERROR</item></default>
        <description>
          This parameter specifies how conflicting Control Points between two
          networks are handled when merging.  The current options are to report
          an error and abort the program when a Control Point appears in both
          the base and add networks (ERROR), or to attempt to merge the
          conflicts in the duplicated point (MERGE).
        </description>
        <list>
          <option value="ERROR">
            <brief>Disallow merging networks with duplicate points</brief>
            <description>
              This option will check for conflicting Control Points in the
              Control Networks and report an error and abort the program when
              a conflict occurs.  If no conflict occurs, all Control Points
              will be added without changing any existing points in the base
              network.  For the purposes of this option, a conflict can be as
              simple as two Control Points sharing the same ID.  In such a
              case, an error will be reported and the program aborted, even
              if nothing else is different between them.
            </description>
            <exclusions>
              <item>OVERWRITEPOINTS</item>
              <item>OVERWRITEMEASURES</item>
              <item>OVERWRITEREFERENCE</item>
              <item>OVERWRITEMISSING</item>
            </exclusions>
          </option>
          <option value="MERGE">
            <brief>Merge duplicate points and resolve their conflicts</brief>
            <description>
              This option will attempt to merge duplicate points between the
              base network and the successive networks being added to it.
              When conflicts arise, they will be resolved in accordance with
              the various overwrite options.  By default (i.e., when no
              overwrite option is selected), values in the base network will
              take priority over those in the networks added to it, but this
              can be changed when selecting an overwrite option(s).  For
              example, if OVERWRITEMEASURES is selected, then Line/Sample
              measurements in the last network added will take precedence over
              all the Line/Sample measurements for conflicting measures in the
              base network and the networks that were added prior.
            </description>
          </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="OVERWRITEPOINTS">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>False</item></default>
        <brief>Replace conflicting Control Points as networks are added</brief>
        <description>
        <p>
          When this option is SELECTED, whenever a Control Point conflicts
          between the base network and the network being added, the
          Control Point values in the base network will be replaced with the
          values from the added network.  When this option is NOT SELECTED,
          the conflict will be noted in the LOG file (if provided), but the
          values from the base network will be retained in the output network.
        </p>

        <p>
          Note that Control Point values being retained or overwritten
          include the point type (fixed, constrained or free), ignore status,
          editlock status, apriori and/or adjusted ground coordinates,
          apriori and/or adjusted ground coordinate sigma values, 
          constrained coordinate flags.
        </p>

        <p>
          It should also be noted that even when this options is NOT SELECTED,
          measures can still be added and, depending on the OVERWRITE options
          selected, modified and deleted from points.  This options therefore
          applies only to control point data values, not items contained within
          control points.
        </p>
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="OVERWRITEMEASURES">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>False</item></default>
        <brief>
          Replace conflicting Control Measures as networks are added
        </brief>
        <description>
          When this option is SELECTED, whenever a Control Measure conflicts
          between the base network and the network being added, the Control
          Measure in the base network will be replaced with that from the
          added network.  When this options is NOT SELECTED, the conflict will
          be noted in the LOG file (if provided), but the Control Measure
          from the base network will be retained in the output network.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="OVERWRITEREFERENCE">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>False</item></default>
        <brief>
          Replace Reference Measures in conflicting Control Points
        </brief>
        <description>
          <p>
            If a Control Point in the current "base" network and the current
            network being added to it have different Reference Measures, there
            is ambiguity about which Control Measure should be defined as the
            one and only Reference Measure in the output Control Network.  When
            this option is SELECTED, the Reference Measure in the network being
            added will overwrite the existing reference status of the Reference
            Measure in the base network.  If this option is NOT SELECTED, the
            base Reference Measure will be retained.  In both cases, both
            Control Measures make it into the merged network, but only one will
            be listed as the Reference Measure for that Control Point.
          </p>

          <p>
            Regardless of the other OVERWRITE options selected, a reference
            measure will NEVER be modified unless this option is SELECTED.  So,
            for example, if OVERWRITEMEASURES is selected, and the reference
            measure exists in the new network with a different line/sample, the
            base's line/sample will be retained if OVERWRITEREFERENCE is not
            selected.  If this options is selected, however, the reference is
            subject to modification or removal like any other measure.
          </p>
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="OVERWRITEMISSING">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>False</item></default>
        <brief>
          Omit Control Measures missing in network(s) added to the base network
        </brief>
        <description>
          When this option is SELECTED, if a Control Measure exists in a
          conflicting Control Point in the base network, but not the network
          being added to it, then the missing Control Measure will not be
          included in the output merged Control Network for that Control Point.
          If this option is NOT SELECTED (the default), and a Control Measure
          exists in either the base or the "add" network, it will be included
          in the ouput network.
        </description>
      </parameter>
    </group>
  </groups>
</application>
