<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<application name="amica2isis" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">
<!-- $Id: amica2isis.xml 6226 2015-06-09 20:46:13Z jwbacker@GS.DOI.NET $ -->

  <brief>Import PDS/FITS formatted Hayabusa image into ISIS cube</brief>

  <description>
    <p>
       This application will import and convert a Hayabusa Asteroid Multiband
       Imaging Camera (AMICA) PDS image to an ISIS cube. The application reads
       and translates eight AMICA filters.  See chart in <i>AMICA Filters</i>
       below for details on the different filters.
    </p>
    <br/>
    <h3>Requirements</h3>
    <ul>
      <li>
        Detached header file (.lbl) (<em>FROM</em>)
      </li>
      <li>
        Raw image data (.fit) (specified in <em>FROM</em> label)
      </li>
      <li>
        Output ISIS file name (.cub) (<em>TO</em>)
      </li>
      <li>
        Users may need to override the target name (<em>TARGET</em>)
      </li>
    </ul>
    <p>
       The input PDS formatted detached header file (.lbl) for the Hayabusa
       AMICA image must be used in the FROM parameter.  This header contains a
       reference to a FITS formatted file ending in a .fit extension containing
       the image data.  Both files must reside in the same directory or errors
       will occur.
    </p>
    <h3>When TARGET Parameter Should Be Specified</h3>
    <ul>
      <li>
        When Hayabusa AMICA EDR labels contain an incorrect value for the
      TARGET_NAME keyword
      </li>
      <li>
         Define TARGET = "SKY" to later project the data with
        <em>skymap</em>.
      </li>
    </ul>
    <br/>
    <h2>Mission Overview</h2>
    <p>
       The Hayabusa spacecraft was launched on 9 May 2003.  The AMICA
       instrument acquired more than 1,400 multispectral and high resolution
       images of the asteroid 25143 Itokawa beginning 12 September 2005 for
       three months.  The primary goal of the mission was to land on the
       asteroid and return samples to Earth.  The spacecraft safely landed on
       Itokawa in November 2005 and returned the samples to Earth in June 2010.
       Further information can be found in Ishiguro et al. (2010)
    </p>
    <p>
        During the rendezvous phase with Itokawa, Hayabusa was designed to find
        its position relative to the asteroid autonomously using optical
        navigation cameras (ONC) and range data based on light-detection and
        ranging (LIDAR) technology. The ONC-T, a refractive telescope camera head,
        is referred to as the AMICA when used for scientific observations. Prior
        to "touch-and-go sampling", Itokawa was mapped by AMICA to select
        sampling sites free of serious obstacles such as meter-sized boulders
        and craters.
    </p>
    <h2>Instrument Overview</h2>
    <p>
       The AMICA instrument is a refracting telescope consisting of five lenses,
       each of which is cosmic-radiation-resistant and anti-reflection coated.
       A quartz optical parallel window is placed in front of the first lens for
       radiation protection.  The SITe charge-coupled device (CCD) chip,
       developed and built by NEC TOSHIBA Space Systems, Ltd., is of the
       back-illuminated MPP (Multi-Pinned Phase) type. The CCD is kept below -10
       degrees C in ordinary in-flight condition.  The CCD dimensions are 1024 x
       1000 visible pixels (full dimensions are 1024 x 1024) and the camera
       field of view is 5.83 x 5.69 degrees.  The 12 columns on either side of
       the 1024 x 1000 pixel array are dark due to an obscuring mask. DNs in
       these areas were found to be dependent on both incident flux and
       wavelength, suggesting that the masks are not perfectly impermeable to
       light.  Therefore, these pixels cannot be used for dark current
       correction.  The remaining unobscured region has the dimensions 1000 x
       1000.
    </p>
    <p>
       AMICA is one of the ONCs comprised of  three units: three CCD camera
       heads (ONC-T, ONC-W1, and ONC-W2), an analog signal processing unit
       (ONC-AE), and a digital signal processing unit (ONC-E). AMICA (ONC-T) and
       two wide-angle navigation cameras (ONC-W1 and ONC-W2) are controlled
       through ONC-E and ONC-AE, and the signals obtained are converted from
       analog to digital in ONC-AE. The digitized images are numerically
       processed by the ONC-E. The design of the AMICA camera head flight model
       is essentially the same as that of its prototype model. It is a CCD
       camera with a refractor telescope consisting of cosmic
       radiation-resistant and antireflection-coated lenses. The CCD device was
       configured in a frame-transfer architecture with an image area and a
       frame storage area. The depth of field (the distance between the camera
       and objects that are observed in focus) was designed to be 75 m to
       infinity.
    </p>
    <p>
       AMICA has an eight position filter wheel, of which seven filters are nearly
       equivalent to the ECAS bands (Tedesco et al. 1982). Below is a table of
       the filters and their specifications:
    </p>
    <br/>
    <h2>AMICA Filters</h2>
    <p>
       The following table provides the specifications for each of the eight
       AMICA filters.
    </p>
      <TABLE BORDER="1">
            <CAPTION>
                AMICA Filter Specifications
              </CAPTION>
          <TR>
            <TH>Name</TH>
            <TH>Wavelength (nm)</TH>
            <TH>FWHM (nm)</TH>
          </TR>
          <TR>
              <TD>ul</TD>
              <TD>381</TD>
              <TD>45</TD>
          </TR>
          <TR>
              <TD>b</TD>
              <TD>429</TD>
              <TD>108</TD>
          </TR>
          <TR>
              <TD>v</TD>
              <TD>553</TD>
              <TD>72</TD>
          </TR>
          <TR>
              <TD>w</TD>
              <TD>700</TD>
              <TD>70</TD>
          </TR>
          <TR>
              <TD>x</TD>
              <TD>861</TD>
              <TD>81</TD>
          </TR>
          <TR>
              <TD>p</TD>
              <TD>960</TD>
              <TD>75</TD>
          </TR>
          <TR>
              <TD>zs</TD>
              <TD>1008</TD>
              <TD>66</TD>
          </TR>
          <TR>
              <TD>WIDE</TD>
              <TD>650</TD>
              <TD>300</TD>
          </TR>
      </TABLE>

    <br/>
    <h2>Data Archive</h2>
    <p>
       The Hayabusa AMICA data archive is located at  several locations.  The
       Japanese provide the data from the
      <a href="http://darts.isas.jaxa.jp/pub/planet/pds3/hay-a-amica-3-hayamica-v1.0/">Japanese Hayabusa AMICA archive website</a>.
      The data are also available from the
      <a href="http://sbn.psi.edu/pds/resource/hayamica.html">NASA PDS Small
      Bodies Node</a> and is the recommended source.
    </p>
    <p>
       The file naming convention for ONC images is
       {T}{C}{nnnnnnnnnn}_{filter}.fits, where: {T} indicates the type of data
       ("S" for scientific data or "N" for navigation data), {C}
       identifies the name of the instrument (T, W1, and W2 for ONC-T (i.e.
       AMICA), ONC-W1, and ONC-W2, respectively); {nnnnnnnnnn} is the mission
       elapsed time when the images is generated in ONC-E; {filter} is the name
       of the filter (ul, b, v, w, x, p, and zs, respectively).
    </p>
    <br/>
    <h2>References</h2>
    <cite>
       Ishiguro, Masateru, et al. "The Hayabusa Spacecraft Asteroid Multi-band
       Imaging Camera (AMICA)". Icarus 207.2 (2010): 714-731.
    </cite>
    <br/>
    <cite>
      Tedesco, E.F., D.J. Tholen, and B. Zellner.  The eight-color asteroid
      survey:  Standard stars.  Astron. J. 87, 1587-1592, 1982.
    </cite>

  </description>

  <history>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2013-11-27">
      Original version
    </change>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2014-04-03">
      Added support for subimage areas.  This was done by using the AlphaCube
      (or crop) feature which provides necessary elements for the AMICA camera
      model to work properly.  Fixes #2056.
    </change>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2015-02-26">
      Removed AlphaCube usage to favor more flexible implementation in the
      AMICA camera model. Output of the image data is now in real format.
      Fixes #2180 and #2193.
    </change>
  </history>

  <category>
    <missionItem>Hayabusa</missionItem>
  </category>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input PDS formatted detached header file for AMICA image
        </brief>
        <description>
           This file is the PDS label (ending in .lbl) to the image data.  The
           image data are stored in  FITS format with the detached .lbl file
           describing generic access to the data.  The program,
           <em>amica2isis</em>, will also read the FITS file and extract
           the header contained therein.  Some FITS label values are transferred
           to the output ISIS files as well for completeness.
        </description>
        <filter>*.lbl *.LBL</filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TO">
         <type>cube</type>
         <pixelType>real</pixelType>
         <fileMode>output</fileMode>
         <brief>Output ISIS cube filename</brief>
         <description>
           Use this parameter to select the output filename of the ISIS cube
           generated by this application.
         </description>
         <filter>*.cub</filter>
       </parameter>

    </group>
    <group name="Parameters">
        <parameter name="TARGET">
            <type>string</type>
            <brief>Provide target name if absent or incorrect in input (FROM)
              label
            </brief>
            <description>
              <p>
                 This parameter may be necessary as some AMICA EDR labels may
                 not contain correct values for the TARGET_NAME keyword. This
                 parameter can be used to provide the correct name of the target.
                 It may also be used to specify SKY as the target to support
                 projecting data to the celestial sphere.
              </p>
            </description>
            <internalDefault>Label Value</internalDefault>
        </parameter>
    </group>
  </groups>
</application>
