<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="camstats" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">

  <brief>
    Generates and outputs camera statistics for a cube in raw camera geometry
  </brief>

  <description>
    <p>
    This program generates camera statistics from a user-supplied
    <def>Level0</def> or <def>Level1</def> cube.  The output of camstats can be
     directed to a <def>PVL</def> file or a comma-delimited text file (flat file).
    For each output group, the program will calculate the minimum, maximum,
    average, and standard  deviation values.  The output groups are listed below:
    <blockquote>
    <ul>
      <li><def>Latitude</def></li>
      <li><def>Longitude</def></li>
      <li><def>Sample Resolution</def></li>
      <li><def>Line Resolution</def></li>
      <li><def link="Pixel Resolution">Resolution</def></li>
      <li><def>Aspect Ratio</def></li>
      <li><def>Phase Angle</def></li>
      <li><def>Emission Angle</def></li>
      <li><def>Incidence Angle</def></li>
      <li><def>Local Solar Time</def></li>
      <li><def>North Azimuth</def></li>
    </ul>
    </blockquote>
    </p>
    <p>
    The output values are calculated using the entire image area.  However, 
    the number of data collection points for the statistics can be controlled 
    by using the line increment (LINC) and sample increment (SINC) parameters.  
    The default value for LINC and SINC are 1.  If the default value is used,
    then every line and sample of the image is used in the calculation of the 
    output values.  The increment value can be increased to reduce program
    execution time. If a value other than 1, for example the number 10, is 
    assigned to LINC and SINC, then every tenth line and tenth sample of the
    image are used in the calculation of the output values.  The edges of the 
    image are always sampled even if the increment does not fall on the edge.
    Keep in mind that sparse increments assigned to LINC and SINC are 
    susceptible to an adverse effect on the accuracy of the statistics.
    </p>
  </description>

  <history>
    <change name="Robert Sucharski" date="2007-01-22">
      Original version.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2007-08-14">
      Added an application test.
    </change>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2008-02-27"> 
        Check for special pixel values and write them as NULL values in keywords 
        and the flat text file.
    </change>
     <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2008-05-12">
          Removed references to CubeInfo .
     </change>
     <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2008-06-11">
       Added the ATTACH option.
     </change>
    <change name="Steven Koechle" date="2008-11-12">
       Camstats now outputs history to the cube when it finishes execution.
     </change>
    <change name="Tammy Becker" date="2012-01-19">
       Modified documentation and added Glossary links.
     </change>
    <change name="Janet Richie, Ella Mae Lee" date="2012-11-20">
       Modified documentation, fixes #1174.
    </change>
    <change name="Lynn Weller" date="2013-02-25">
      Removed links to applications imbedded in text and replaced with
      italicized application name.  Added application links to the
      "Related Objects and Documents" section of the documentation.
       Fixes mantis ticket #1525.
    </change>
    <change name="Jeffrey Covington" date="2015-02-19">
      Updated FORMAT and APPEND documentation to be more clear. Made general
      edits for clarity.
    </change>
      
  </history>

  <category>
    <categoryItem>Cameras</categoryItem>
  </category>

  <seeAlso>
    <applications>
      <item>spiceinit</item>
      <item>qmos</item>
      <item>getkey</item>
    </applications>
  </seeAlso>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input cube filename
        </brief>
        <description>
          Input cube with appropriate camera labels (refer to <i>spiceinit</i>).
          The input must be a <def>Level0</def> or <def>Level1</def> cube.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub *.CUB
        </filter>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="ATTACH">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <brief>
          Attach results to the cube's label
        </brief>
        <description>
          If this option is selected, the output camera statistics will be
          attached to the input cube's label under the group "CameraStatistics."
          <p>
          Applications such as <i>qmos</i> reference the attached label for 
          geometric information of the cube.
          </p>
        </description>
        <default><item>FALSE</item></default>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TO">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Ouput text filename
        </brief>
        <internalDefault>None</internalDefault>
        <description>
          A text file in label format (<def>PVL</def>), which will contain the 
	  results of <i>camstats</i>.  This output file, for example, can be used 
	  with the <i>getkey</i> application to pass the results to other programs
          when developing scripts.  
          <p>
             Alternatively, the output can be written to a text file format, 
	     see the "FORMAT" parameter for more information.
          </p>
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.txt *.TXT
        </filter>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="FORMAT">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>
          Output file format (PVL or FLAT)
        </brief>
        <description>
          This is the format type for the output file. <def>PVL</def> format is the 
	  default. The format is ignored unless the TO parameter is specified.
        </description>  
        <default><item>PVL</item></default>
        <list>
          <option value="PVL">
            <brief>
              Format the output file specified by TO as PVL. This format
              can be read using the <i>getkey</i> program.
            </brief>
            <description>
              Output the results to a PVL formatted file specified by TO.
            </description>
          </option>
          <option value="FLAT">
            <brief>
              Format the output file specified by TO as a comma delimited text file.
            </brief>
            <description>
              Output the results to a comma delimited text file specified by TO. 
              This file format can easily be imported into spreadsheet applications
              like Excel.
            </description>
          </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>
 
      <parameter name="APPEND">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <brief>
          Append results to output file specified by TO.
        </brief>
        <description>
          <p>
            If this option is not selected, the output from the <i>camstats</i> 
	    application is appended to the output file. If this option is
	    set to "NO" or "FALSE," any information in the TO file is 
	    overwritten.
          </p>
          <p>
            Note: This will append the formatted results to the end of the TO 
            file without regard to the formatting of the current contents.
          </p>
        </description>
        <default><item>FALSE</item></default>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Option">
      <parameter name="LINC">
        <type>integer</type>
        <brief>
          Line Increment
        </brief>
        <description>
          LINC will control the number of lines where statistical data are collected.  
	  If a LINC of 10 is entered, every tenth <def link="Line">line</def> will be 
	  used in the data collection. This parameter as well as the SINC parameter
          are primarily used to reduce runtime for very large images by collecting
          data from a smaller statistical sample rather than the entire image.  
          <p>
            Note: Keep in mind that if the LINC increment is set too sparsely, this 
	    could adversely influence the accuracy of the statistics.
          </p> 
        </description>
        <default><item>1</item></default>
      </parameter>

     <parameter name="SINC">
        <type>integer</type>
        <brief>
          Sample Increment
        </brief>
        <description>
          SINC will control the number of samples where statistical data are 
	  collected.  If a SINC of 10 is entered, every tenth <def 
	  link="Sample">sample</def> will be used in the data collection.
          This parameter as well as the LINC parameter are primarily used to reduce
          runtime for very large images by collecting data from a smaller
          statistical sample rather than the entire image.
          <p>
            Keep in mind that if the SINC increment is set too sparsely, 
	    this could adversely influence the accuracy of the statistics.
          </p>
        </description>
        <default><item>1</item></default>
      </parameter>
    </group>
   </groups>
</application>

