<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="camstats" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">

  <brief>
    Generates and outputs camera statistics for a cube in raw camera geometry
  </brief>

  <description>
    <p>
    Camstats generates camera statistics from a user-supplied <def>Level0</def> 
    or <def>Level1</def> cube.  The output of camstats can be directed to a 
    <def>PVL</def> file or a comma-delimited text file (flat file).  For each 
    output group, the program will calculate the minimum, maximum, average, and 
    standard  deviation values.  The output groups are listed below:
    <blockquote>
    <ul>
      <li><def>Latitude</def></li>
      <li><def>Longitude</def></li>
      <li><def>Sample Resolution</def></li>
      <li><def>Line Resolution</def></li>
      <li><def link="Pixel Resolution">Resolution</def></li>
      <li><def>Aspect Ratio</def></li>
      <li><def>Phase Angle</def></li>
      <li><def>Emission Angle</def></li>
      <li><def>Incidence Angle</def></li>
      <li><def>Local Solar Time</def></li>
      <li><def>North Azimuth</def></li>
    </ul>
    </blockquote>
    </p>
    <p>
    The output values are calculated using the entire image area.  However, 
    the number of data collection points for the statistics can be controlled 
    by using the line increment (LINC) and sample increment (SINC) parameters.  
    The default value for LINC and SINC are 1.  If the default value is used,
    then every line and sample of the image are used in the calculation of the 
    output values.  The increment value can be increased to reduce program
    execution time. If a value other than 1, for example the number 10, is 
    assigned to LINC and SINC, then every tenth line and tenth sample of the
    image are used in the calculation of the output values.  The edges of the 
    image are always sampled even if the increment does not fall on the edge.
    Keep in mind that sparse increments assigned to LINC and SINC are 
    susceptible to an adverse effect on the accuracy of the statistics.
    </p>
  </description>

  <history>
    <change name="Robert Sucharski" date="2007-01-22">
      Original version.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2007-08-14">
      Added an application test.
    </change>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2008-02-27"> 
        Check for special pixel values and write them as NULL values in keywords 
        and the flat text file.
    </change>
     <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2008-05-12">
          Removed references to CubeInfo .
     </change>
     <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2008-06-11">
       Added the ATTACH option.
     </change>
    <change name="Steven Koechle" date="2008-11-12">
       Camstats now outputs history to the cube when it finishes execution.
     </change>
    <change name="Tammy Becker" date="2012-01-19">
       Modified documentation and added Glossary links.
     </change>
    <change name="Janet Richie, Ella Mae Lee" date="2012-11-20">
       Modified documentation, fixes #1174.
     </change>
  </history>

  <category>
    <categoryItem>Cameras</categoryItem>
  </category>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input cube filename
        </brief>
        <description>
          Input cube with appropriate camera labels (Refer to <a href=
      "http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Application/presentation/Tabbed/spiceinit/spiceinit.html"
      ><i>Spiceinit</i></a>).
          The input must be a <def>Level0</def> or <def>Level1</def> cube.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub *.CUB
        </filter>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="ATTACH">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <brief>
          Attach results to the cube's label
        </brief>
        <description>
          If this option is selected, the output camera statistics will be
          attached to the input cube's label under group called "CameraStatistics."
          <p>
          Applications such as <a href=
          "http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Application/presentation/Tabbed/qmos/qmos.html"
          ><i>Qmos</i></a> reference the attached label for geometric information of the cube.
          </p>
        </description>
        <default><item>FALSE</item></default>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TO">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Ouput text filename
        </brief>
        <internalDefault>None</internalDefault>
        <description>
          A text file in label format (<def>PVL</def>), which will contain the 
	  results of <i>camstats</i>.  This output file can be used in conjunction 
	  with the <a href=
          "http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Application/presentation/Tabbed/getkey/getkey.html"
          ><i>getkey</i></a> application in order to pass the results to another 
	  program when developing scripts.  
          <p>
             Alternatively, the output can be written to a text file format, 
	     see the "FORMAT" parameter for more information.
          </p>
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.txt *.TXT
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="FORMAT">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>
          Output format (PVL or FLAT)
        </brief>
        <description>
          Format type for output file.  <def>PVL</def> format is the default.
        </description>
        <default><item>PVL</item></default>
        <list>
          <option value="PVL">
            <brief>
              PVL Format
            </brief>
            <description>
              Output file will be in PVL format
            </description>
          </option>
          <option value="FLAT">
            <brief>
              Flat File Format
            </brief>
          <description>
            The output file will be a comma-delimited flat file.  This format 
	    can easily be imported into spreadsheet applications such as <i>Excel</i>.
          </description>
          </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="APPEND">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <brief>
          Option to append results to output file
        </brief>
        <description>
          If this option is selected, the <i>camstats</i> output will be appended 
	  to an existing file specified as the "TO" file.  If "append" is not 
	  selected, the output information defaults and overwrites the existing
	  "TO" file.
        </description>
        <default><item>FALSE</item></default>
      </parameter>
    </group>


    <group name="Option">
      <parameter name="LINC">
        <type>integer</type>
        <brief>
          Line Increment
        </brief>
        <description>
          LINC will control the number of lines where statistical data are collected.  
	  If a LINC of 10 is entered, every tenth <def link="Line">line</def> will be 
	  used in the data collection.  
          <p>
          This option is useful for very large images (long images with a large 
	  number of lines) where every 10th or 100th line (LINC=10 or LINC=100) 
	  collects enough geometric data of the input for statistics while 
          causing the application to execute much faster. 
            <p>
              Keep in mind that if the LINC increment is set too sparsely, this 
	      could adversely influence the accuracy of the statistics.
            </p> 
          </p>
        </description>
        <default><item>1</item></default>
      </parameter>

     <parameter name="SINC">
        <type>integer</type>
        <brief>
          Sample Increment
        </brief>
        <description>
          SINC will control the number of samples where statistical data are 
	  collected.  If a SINC of 10 is entered, every tenth <def 
	  link="Sample">sample</def> will be used in the data collection.
          <p>
          This option is useful for very large images (wide images with a 
	  large number of samples) where every 10th or 100th sample (SINC=10 
	  or SINC=100) collects enough geometric data of the input for 
	  statistics while causing the application to execute much faster. 
            <p>
              Keep in mind that if the SINC increment is set too sparsely, 
	      this could adversely influence the accuracy of the statistics.
            </p> 
          </p>
        </description>
        <default><item>1</item></default>
      </parameter>
    </group>
   </groups>
</application>

