<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="camstats" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">

  <brief>
    Outputs camera statistics for a  cube in raw camera geometry
  </brief>

  <description>
    This program will generate camera statistics from a user supplied "level 1" cube.  The output of camstats can be directed 
    to a PVL file or flat text file.  For each output group, the program will calculate the minimum, maximum, average, and standard 
    deviation.  The output groups are:
    <pre>
      Latitude
      Longitude
      Sample Resolution
      Line Resolution
      Resolution
      Aspect Ratio
      Phase Angle
      Emission Angle
      Incidence Angle
      Local Solar Time
      North Azimuth
    </pre>
    The output values are calculated using the full image area.  However, the number of data collection
     points  for the statistics can be controlled by using the line increment (linc) and  sample increment (sinc)
     parameters.  If the default linc and sinc of one are used then every line and sample of the image is 
     used in the calculation of the output values.  If the user enters a linc or sinc, then the number of data 
     collection points will be reduced.  However, the edges of the image area always used  even if they an 
     incrament does not fall on the edge.

  </description>

  <history>
    <change name="Robert Sucharski" date="2007-01-22">
      Original version
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2007-08-14">
      Added an application test
    </change>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2008-02-27"> 
        Check for special pixel values and write them as NULL values in keywords 
        and the flat text file.
    </change>
     <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2008-05-12">
          Removed references to CubeInfo 
     </change>
     <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2008-06-11">
       Added the ATTACH option
     </change>
    <change name="Steven Koechle" date="2008-11-12">
       Camstats now outputs history to the cube when it finishes execution
     </change>
  </history>

  <category>
    <categoryItem>Cameras</categoryItem>
  </category>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input  file
        </brief>
        <description>
          Input cube with appropriate camera labels (instrument and kernel groups)
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub *.CUB
        </filter>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="ATTACH">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <brief>
          Attach result to the cube in the Table "CameraStatistics"
        </brief>
        <description>
          If this option is selected, the output camera statistics will be
          attached as the Table "CameraStatistics" in the FROM cube's labels.
          Note: This does alter the input cube.
        </description>
        <default><item>FALSE</item></default>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TO">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Text file output
        </brief>
        <internalDefault>None</internalDefault>
        <description>
          A text file in label format which will contain the results of this program.  this file can be used
          in conjunction with the "getkey" program in order to pass the results to another program 
          when developing scripts.  The output can also be a flat text file, see the "FORMAT" parameter.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.txt *.TXT
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="FORMAT">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>
          Output Format
        </brief>
        <description>
          Format type for output file.  PVL format is the default.
        </description>
        <default><item>PVL</item></default>
        <list>
          <option value="PVL">
            <brief>
              PVL Format
            </brief>
            <description>
              Output file will be in PVL format
            </description>
          </option>
          <option value="FLAT">
            <brief>
              FlatFile Format
            </brief>
          <description>
            Output file will be a comma deliminated flatfile.  This form can easily be imported into spreadsheet applications.
          </description>
          </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="APPEND">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <brief>
          Append Output to File
        </brief>
        <description>
          If this option is selected, the output from the application will be appended to the "TO" file.  if it is not 
          selected, and information in the "TO" file will be overwritten.
        </description>
        <default><item>FALSE</item></default>
      </parameter>
    </group>


    <group name="Option">
      <parameter name="LINC">
        <type>integer</type>
        <brief>
          Line increment
        </brief>
        <description>
          Will contol the number of lines where statistical data is collected.  if a LINC of 10 is entered, every tenth line
          will be used in the data collection.
        </description>
        <default><item>1</item></default>
      </parameter>

     <parameter name="SINC">
        <type>integer</type>
        <brief>
          Sample increment
        </brief>
        <description>
          Will contol the number of samples where statistical data is collected.  if a SINC of 10 is entered, every tenth sample
          will be used in the data collection.
        </description>
        <default><item>1</item></default>
      </parameter>
    </group>
   </groups>
</application>

