<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="hi2isis" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">

  <brief>
    Import HiRISE EDR images into Isis cube format
  </brief>

  <description>
    <p>
      Converts a single channel HiRISE EDR into an Isis Cube file.
      The observation image data from the EDR is transfered into the Isis Cube data.
      The observation line prefix and suffix data will be combined into a single Isis table
      named "HiRISE Ancillary". The calibration image data will be placed into an Isis
      table named "HiRISE Calibration Image", and the calibration line prefix and suffix
      data will be combined into a single Isis table named "HiRISE Calibration Ancillary".
    </p>
    <p>
      8 bit EDR pixels are checked for invalid values in the following order: 
      gaps (255 = 0xFF), high instrument saturation (254 = 0xFE), and low
      instrument saturation (0 = 0x00). See the following table for what these 
      values are converted to. Once the special pixels have been delt with the 
      8 bit data is processed in one of two ways depending on the UNLUT 
      parameter. If UNLUT is false then the 8 bit values are simply moved into 
      a signed 16 bit integer without modifying their magnitude. If UNLUT is
      true, the 8 bit values are converted to their 14 bit value by applying 
      the lookup table and stored in a signed 16 bit integer. The lookup table
      from the EDR labels contaings 256 pairs of 14 bit values. The first pair
      is the range of 14 bit pixels that were compressed to 8 bit pixel value 
      zero (0). The second pair is the range compressed to pixel value one (1),
      and so on. 8 bit pixels are mapped to the corresponding average of the 
      14 bit lookup table range.
    </p>
    <table class="tableFormattedInformation">
      <caption>8 bit EDR pixel mapping and stats</caption>
      <tr>
        <th>Input DN</th>
        <th>Output DN</th>
        <th>Counter</th>
        <th>Explanation</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>255 (0xFF)</td>
        <td>NULL</td>
        <td>Gap</td>
        <td>Downlink data gaps are filled with 255s</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>254 (0xFE)</td>
        <td>HIS</td>
        <td>HIS</td>
        <td>Sensor saturated on the high end</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>0 (0x00)</td>
        <td>LIS</td>
        <td>LIS</td>
        <td>Sensor saturated on the low end</td>
      </tr>
    </table>

    <p>
      16 bit EDR pixels are checked for invalid values in the following order: 
      gaps (-1 = 0xFFFF), low order byte appears to be the beginning of a gap
      (0x??FF), outside of unsigned 14 bit range (0 to 16383), high instrument saturation
      (16383 = 0x3FFF), and low instrument saturation (0 = 0x0000).
      Since the byte order of all HiRISE
      EDR products is most significant byte first all integer values within the EDR
      will be converted to the native byte order of the machine running "hi2isis"
      unless the cube attribute specifies otherwise.
    </p>
    <table class="tableFormattedInformation">
      <caption>16 bit EDR pixel mapping and stats</caption>
      <tr>
        <th>Input DN</th>
        <th>Output DN</th>
        <th>Counter</th>
        <th>Explanation</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>-1 (65535) (0xFFFF)</td>
        <td>NULL</td>
        <td>Gap</td>
        <td>Downlink data gaps are filled with 255s (0xFF)</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>(0x??FF) followed by (0xFFFF)</td>
        <td>NULL (possibly)</td>
        <td>Suspected</td>
        <td>Beginning of a gap (see LSBGAP parameter)</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>0 &lt; pixel &gt; 16383</td>
        <td>NULL</td>
        <td>Invalid</td>
        <td>The pixel is not in the unsigned 14 bit legal range</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>16383 (0x3FFF)</td>
        <td>HIS</td>
        <td>HIS</td>
        <td>Sensor saturated on the high end</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>0 (0x00)</td>
        <td>LIS</td>
        <td>LIS</td>
        <td>Sensor saturated on the low end</td>
      </tr>
    </table>

    <p>
      The line prefix and suffix data for the calibration and observation image are converted
      and stored into their respective tables in the same manner as the image pixels.
      The Isis tables which hold 
      prefix and suffix data have four, four byte integer fields. These are "Gap Flag", 
      "LineNumber", "BufferPixels", and "DarkPixels". The BufferPixel field contains twelve
      integers and the DarkPixel field contains sixteen integers. Other information from the
      EDR prefix tables such as the synchronization pattern are not transfered to the Isis file.
    </p>
    <p>
      The "GapFlag" is taken directly from byte zero of the EDR line prefix data and is stored
      in the least significant byte of the four byte field integer. The upper three bytes are set to all
      zeros. The byte from the EDR has two possible values, all zeros and all ones. This means
      the Isis GapFlag value as an integer has two possible values, 255 and zero (0).
    </p>
      The "LineNumber" is taken from bytes three, four and five of the EDR line prefix data and
      is stored into a single four byte integer with the most significant byte set to zero.
    <p>
    </p>
      The twelve values for "BufferPixels" are taken from the EDR line prefix buffer pixels.
      8-bit buffer pixels are converted to 16 bit values in exactly the same way as image pixels.
      All buffer pixels are stored in the 
      corresponding Isis "BufferPixels" array. All pixel values will be
      stored in the low order two bytes and will be swapped if the native byte order is least 
      significant byte first.
    <p>
      The sixteen values for "DarkPixels" are taken from the EDR line suffix dark pixels, and are
      handled in the same manner as the buffer pixels.
    </p>
    <img src='assets/hi2isis_diagram.png' alt='Diagram of output Isis cube' width='499' height='520' />

  </description>

  <history>
    <change name="Stuart Sides" date="2004-04-26">
        Original version
    </change>
    <change name="Stuart Sides" date="2004-06-15">
        Updated according to new SIS. Added Calibration, Ancillary calibration
        and Ancillary Image BLOBs.
    </change>
    <change name="Stuart Sides" date="2004-10-18">
        Added documentation specific to the Isis tables that are created.
    </change>
    <change name="Stuart Sides" date="2004-10-22">
      Fixed a bug with the allocation of the TableField "image". It now works for 
      HiRISE EDRs that have a binning mode other than one (1).
    </change>
    <change name="Stuart Sides" date="2005-02-28">
      Added gap and lookup table handling. Both 8 and 16 bit inputs are now
      converted to 16 bit output. The lookup table for 8 bit is applied. The output
      DN for an 8 bit input is the average of the lookup table range values. Added
      new option (LSBGAP) to handle 16 bit pixels with a low order byte of 0xff immediately
      before a gap. By default, this new option will convert these pixels to a gap. With
      the option turned off, these pixels will be left unaltered.
    </change>
    <change name="Stuart Sides" date="2005-06-27">
      Added the parameter UNLUT to give the ability to apply the 8 to 14 bit
      look up table or not. Also fixed problem with gaps, LIS and HIS being reported
      correctly but not converted correctly to double precision values before 
      being inserted into the BUFFER.
    </change>
    <change name="Stuart Sides" date="2005-07-21">
      Added new keywords to the results group. For each of the six sections, the
      program now outputs the number gaps, LIS, HIS, PossibleGaps, and Invalid
      pixels.
    </change>
    <change name="Stuart Sides" date="2006-04-07">
      Fixed a bug with signedword data where gaps were being reported as LIS
      instead of gap. Added more progress information.
    </change>
    <change name="Brendan George" date="2006-06-14">
        Removed call to OriginalLabel, ProcessImportPds now handles this
    </change>
    <change name="Brendan George" date="2006-09-26">
        Documentation fixes
    </change>
    <change name="Brendan George" date="2007-01-17">
        Added blob testing to default appTest
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2008-03-18">
      Checks if input file is rdr.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2008-05-13">
      Removed references to CubeInfo 
    </change>
  </history>

  <category>
    <missionItem>Mars Reconnaissance Orbiter</missionItem>
  </category>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input PDS formatted HiRISE EDR image file.
        </brief>
        <description>
          Use this parameter to select the HiRISE EDR image filename. This must
          be a single channel original HiRISE EDR file.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.img *.IMG
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TO">
         <type>cube</type>
         <fileMode>output</fileMode>
         <brief>
           Output Isis cube
         </brief>
         <description>
           Use this parameter to select the output filename. The output file will
           contain the observation, buffer, and dark pixels from both the main
           image and the calibration areas.
         </description>
         <filter>
           *.cub
         </filter>
       </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Options">
      <parameter name="LSBGAP">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default>
          <item>true</item>
        </default>
        <brief>
           Ignore least significant byte of 0xFF before a gap.
        </brief>
        <description>
          Ignore legal 16 bit pixels with a low order byte of 0xff immediately
          preceding a gap. Pixels like this are normally treated as a gap
          and converted to NULL.
          Set this parameter to FALSE if you want these pixels treated as
          if they were valid data. Set this parameter to TRUE if you want
          these pixels treated as if they were gaps.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="UNLUT">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default>
          <item>true</item>
        </default>
        <brief>
          Convert 8-bit values back to 14-bit values
        </brief>
        <description>
          <p>
            If the input data is stored in 8-bit values, and this parameters is
            set to true then the lookup table will be used to convert all valid
            image, buffer and dark pixels back to 14-bit values. This includes
            both the main image and calibration areas. If this parameter is false
            then the valid pixels will be left at their 8 bit lutted values.
          </p>
          <p>
            The label keyword "Unlutted" in the "Instrument" object is used to
            indicate if the valid pixels are in their 8 bit lutted (Unlutted = FALSE),
            or their 14 bit unlutted (Unlutted = TRUE) representation. Note: Invalid
            pixels (i.e., Gaps, NULL, HRS, HIS, LRS, and LIS) are always represented
            as 16 bit special pixel values.
          </p>
        </description>
      </parameter>
    </group>
  </groups>
</application>
