<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="ddd2isis" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">

  <brief>
    Import msss ddd file into Isis format
  </brief>

  <description>
    This program will import a ddd image into an Isis cube. The ddd format files
    are created by Malin Space Science Systems.
  </description>

  <history>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2009-01-06">
      Original version
    </change>
    <change name="Janet Barrett" date="2013-04-29">
      The program was not working on some newly released MSL ddd files because
      the number of bytes in the header has increased. The program was modified
      to read in the image offset from the file header. This image offset is a
      4 byte integer that starts at byte 20 in the file header. If the offset is
      set to 0, then this means the label is 1024 bytes long. The offset must be
      a multiple of 1024. Fixes #1594.
    </change>
    <change name="Janet Barrett" date="2013-07-11">
      Modified code to write out number of lines, number of samples, number of
      bands, bit type, and label bytes to assist in determining how the file
      should be read in. If the input file is a standard ddd file, then this
      program will be able to import it. If the data is interleaved, then it
      will need to be read in using a combination of the raw2isis and crop
      programs. Fixes #1713.
    </change>
    <change name="Kaitlyn Lee" date="2018-03-01">
      We were given a python program that reads in data from a ddd file
      to use as an example. In the python program, the formula they used to
      calculate the number of bands is different from the one we previously used.
      The old formula did the number of total band bits / 8; the formula is now
      (the number of total band bits / 8) / the number of bytes of the data type
      of the file's bit type. Added the ability to process files with multiple
      bands. Removed the internal default of the output parameter set to None so
      that an output file is now requried. Fixes #703.
    </change>
    <change name="Adam Paquette" date="2020-02-28">
      Updated the dataTypes QMap with a new mapping (32, 4) to handle ingesting
      the updated uvflat files from malin. Fixes #3715.
    </change>
  </history>

  <category>
    <categoryItem>Import and Export</categoryItem>
  </category>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input ddd file
        </brief>
        <description>
          Use this parameter to select the ddd filename.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.ddd
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TO">
         <type>cube</type>
         <fileMode>output</fileMode>
         <brief>
           Output Isis cube
         </brief>
         <description>
           Use this parameter to select the output filename
         </description>
         <filter>
           *.cub
         </filter>
       </parameter>
    </group>
  </groups>
</application>
