<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="vims2map" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">
  <brief>
    Convert vims image to a map projection
  </brief>

  <description>
    This program converts a cube  in camera coordinates to a map projection.    The input cube requires SPICE data and therefore
    the program "spiceinit" should be run on it  prior to "vims2map".   The map
    projection is defined using a PVL file specificied through the MAP 
    parameter.  The system default is to use the Sinusoidal projection 
    ($ISIS3DATA/base/templates/maps/sinusoidal.map).

    <p>If you need to generate your own map file you can use the "maptemplate" program or alternatively, hand create a file using your favorite editor.
    The map file need only specify the ProjectionName as defaults will be computed for the remaining map file parameters.  The following table
    indicates how the defaults are established:
    </p>

    <table border="1">
      <tr>
        <td>PARAMETER</td>
        <td>DEFAULT</td>
      </tr>

      <tr>
        <td>TargetName</td>
        <td>Read from Instrument group in the input cube labels</td>
      </tr>

      <tr>
        <td>EquatorialRadius<br />PolarRadius</td>
        <td>Read from SPICE pck file set during spiceinit.  The pck file is defined in the Kernels group via the TargetAttitudeShape keyword</td>
      </tr>

      <tr>
        <td>LatitudeType</td>
        <td>Planetocentric</td>
      </tr>

      <tr>
        <td>LongitudeDirection</td>
        <td>PositiveEast</td>
      </tr>

      <tr>
        <td>LongitudeDomain</td>
        <td>Normally, 360.  However, if the cube crosses the longitude boundary the value will change to 180</td>
      </tr>

      <tr>
        <td>MinimumLatitude<br />MaximumLatitude<br />MinimumLongitude<br />MaximumLongitude</td>
        <td>Computed from the input cube or read from the map file.   However, any combination of the four values can then be overridden by the user</td>
      </tr>

      <tr>
        <td>PixelResolution<br />Scale</td>
        <td>Computed from the input cube or read from the map file.  The value can be overridden by the user.</td>
      </tr>

    </table>

    <p>
      If you only entered the input cube (FROM) and output cube (TO)  and changed no other parameters the following is the default Mapping group:
    </p>
    <pre>
  Group = Mapping
    TargetName             = Obtained from the Instrument group
    EquatorialRadius       = Obtained from TargetAttitudeShape kernel
    PolarRadius            = Obtained from TargetAttitudeShape kernel

    LatitudeType           = Planetocentric
    LongitudeDirection     = PositiveEast
    LongitudeDomain        = 360 (Could be automatically adjusted to 180 by LONSEAM)

    MinimumLatitude        = Computed from the input camera cube
    MaximumLatitude        = Computed from the input camera cube
    MinimumLongitude       = Computed from the input camera cube
    MaximumLongitude       = Computed from the input camera cube

    ProjectionName         = Sinusodial
    CenterLongitude        = Average of MinimumLongitude and MaximumLongitude
    PixelResolution        = Computed from the input camera cube
  EndGroup
    </pre>

   Note that an important concept here is the map file can come from an existing map projected cube.
   Because the cube has PVL labels and contains the Mapping group, you can essentially force
   the input camera cube to have the same mapping parameters and/or selectively use some of the components of the cube's mapping group.

   <p>If you are attempting to construct a mosaic, it is important that the PixelResolution, EquatorialRadius, PolarRadius, LatitudeType,
   LongitudeDirection, LongitudeDomain, ProjectionName, and projection specific parameters (e.g., CenterLongitude, CenterLatitude) are the same for all cubes.  That is, you should
    create one map file  and use it as input for all the cubes in your mosaic.
   However, the ground range (MinimumLatitude, MaximumLatitude, MinimumLongitude, MaximumLongitude) should not be entered or you will create projected images
   with large amounts of NULL pixels.  The following Mapping group could be used for mosaicking:
   </p>
   <pre>
 Group = Mapping
   ProjectionName         = Sinusodial
   CenterLongitude        = 0
   PixelResolution        = 100 &lt;meters&gt;
 EndGroup
   </pre>

   <p>
     Finally, depending on the projection, problems can occur with cubes that fall on the projection longitude seam.  For example, if you are making a mosaic with LongitudeDomain = 360 and
     your cube crosses 0/360 seam, this program would compute the default longitude range of the cube to MinimumLongitude = 0 and MaximumLongitude = 360.  A very large output image
     could be created depending on the pixel resolution.  The LONSEAM parameter allows you to selectively handle this case.  If you are making mosaics near the seam you will need to
     understand and alter the default for this parameter.
   </p>
  </description>

  <category>
    <missionItem>Cassini</missionItem>
  </category>

  <history>
    <change name="Stacy Alley" date="2008-02-13"> 
      Original version
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2008-05-13">
      Removed references to CubeInfo 
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2008-01-27">
      Fixed parameter names
    </change>
  </history>

  <oldName>
    <item>lev1tolev2</item>
    <item>plansinu</item>
    <item>planorth</item>
  </oldName>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROMLIST">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          List of cubes to map
        </brief>
        <description>
          A list of map projected cubes to 
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.txt *.lis *.lst
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="MAP">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          File containing mapping parameters
        </brief>
        <defaultPath>$base/templates/maps</defaultPath>
        <default><item>$base/templates/maps/sinusoidal.map</item></default>
        <description>
          A file containing the desired output mapping parameters in PVL form.  This
          file can be a simple hand produced label file.  It can also be an existing cube label
          which contains a Mapping group.  You can produce map file using the "maptemplate" program.
        </description>
        <helpers>
          <helper name="H1">
            <function>PrintMap</function>
            <brief>View MapFile</brief>
            <description>
              This helper button will cat out the mapping group of the given mapfile to the session log
               of the application
             </description>
            <icon>$ISIS3DATA/base/icons/labels.png</icon>
          </helper>
        </helpers>
        <filter>
          *.map *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TO">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
          <pixelType>real</pixelType>
        <brief>
          Newly mapped cube
        </brief>
        <description>
          This file will contain the map projected image.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Output Map Resolution">
      <parameter name="PIXRES">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>Defines how the pixel resolution in the output map file is obtained</brief>
        <default><item>CAMERA</item></default>
        <description>
          This parameter is used to specify how the pixel resolution is obtained for the output map
          projected cube.
        </description>
        <list>
           <option value="CAMERA">
              <brief>Compute resolution from input cube</brief>
              <description>
                This option will automatically determine the resolution from the input  cube specified using the FROM parameter.
              </description>
              <exclusions>
                <item>RESOLUTION</item>
              </exclusions>
            </option>

           <option value="MAP">
              <brief>Read resolution from input map file</brief>
              <description>
                This option will use either the PixelResolution (meters/pixel) or Scale (pixels/degree) in the map file.
              </description>
              <exclusions>
                <item>RESOLUTION</item>
              </exclusions>
            </option>

           <option value="MPP">
              <brief> Get resolution from user in meters per pixel</brief>
              <description>
                This option allows the user to specify the resolution in meters per pixel using the RESOLUTION parameter
              </description>
              <inclusions>
                <item>RESOLUTION</item>
              </inclusions>
            </option>

           <option value="PPD">
              <brief> Get resolution from user in pixels per degree</brief>
              <description>
                This option allows the user to specify the resolution in pixels per degree using the RESOLUTION parameter
              </description>
              <inclusions>
                <item>RESOLUTION</item>
              </inclusions>
            </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="RESOLUTION">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief>Pixel resolution</brief>
        <description>
          Specifies the resolution in either meters per pixel or pixels per degree
        </description>
        <minimum inclusive="no">0.0</minimum>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Output Map Ground Range">
      <parameter name="DEFAULTRANGE">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>Defines how the default ground range is determined</brief>
        <default><item>MINIMIZE</item></default>
        <description>
          This parameter is used to specify how the default latitude/longitude ground range for the output map projected image
          is obtained.  The ground range can be obtained from the camera or map file.  Note the user can overide the default using the MINLAT, MAXLAT, MINLON, MAXLON parameters.
          The purpose of the ground range is to define the coverage of the map projected image.  Essentially, the ground range and
          pixel resolution are used to compute the size (samples and line) of the output image.
        </description>

        <list>
          <option value="MINIMIZE">
             <brief>Minimize output image size</brief>
             <description>
               This option will use the camera and projection in combination to ensure the output image size (samples, lines) is minimized.  Using a ground range can cause NULL padding for
               projections with curved merdians and/or parallels and hence large output images.  The amount of padding can be quite large for extremely high resolution maps.
             </description>
             <inclusions><item>LONSEAM</item></inclusions>
             <exclusions>
               <item>MINLAT</item>
               <item>MAXLAT</item>
               <item>MINLON</item>
               <item>MAXLON</item>
               <item>TRIM</item>
             </exclusions>
           </option>

           <option value="CAMERA">
              <brief> Compute default range from input cube</brief>
              <description>
                This option will automatically determine the mininum/maximum latitude/longitude from the input camera model cube specified
                using the FROM parameter.
              </description>
              <inclusions><item>LONSEAM</item></inclusions>
            </option>

           <option value="MAP">
              <brief> Read default range from map file</brief>
              <description>
                This option will read the mininum/maximum latitude/longitude from the input map file.  All four values are expected to be defined.
              </description>
              <exclusions><item>LONSEAM</item></exclusions>
            </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="MINLAT">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief>Starting latitude</brief>
        <internalDefault>Use default range</internalDefault>
        <description>
          The minimum latitude of the ground range.   If this is entered by the user it will override the default camera or map value.  By default,
          planetocentric latitudes are assumed unless the MAP file specifies otherwise.
        </description>

        <minimum inclusive="yes">-90.0</minimum>
        <maximum inclusive="yes">90.0</maximum>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="MAXLAT">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief>Ending latitude</brief>
        <internalDefault>Use default range</internalDefault>
        <description>
          The maximum latitude of the ground range.   If this is entered by the user it will override the default camera or map value.
          By default, planetocentric latitudes are assumed unless the MAP file specifies otherwise.
        </description>
        <minimum inclusive="yes">-90.0</minimum>
        <maximum inclusive="yes">90.0</maximum>
        <greaterThan><item>MINLAT</item></greaterThan>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="MINLON">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief>Starting longitude</brief>
        <internalDefault>Use default range</internalDefault>
        <description>
          The minimum longitude of the ground range.   If this is entered by the user it will override the default camera or map value.
           By default, positive east longitudes in the range of 0 to 360 are assumed unless the MAP file specifies otherwise.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="MAXLON">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief>Ending longitude</brief>
        <internalDefault>Use default range</internalDefault>
        <description>
          The maximum longitude of the ground range.   If this is entered by the user it will override the default camera or map value.
           By default, positive east longitudes in the range of 0 to 360 are assumed unless the MAP file specifies otherwise.
        </description>
        <greaterThan><item>MINLON</item></greaterThan>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TRIM">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>FALSE</item></default>
        <brief>
          Trim pixels outside ground range
        </brief>
        <description>
          If this option is selected, pixels outside the latitude/longtiude
          range will be trimmed or set to null.
          This is useful for certain projections whose lines of latitude and
          longitude are not parallel to image lines and sample columns.
        </description>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Longitude Seam Options">
      <parameter name="LONSEAM">
        <type>string</type>
        <default><item>AUTO</item></default>
        <brief>
          How should images at the longitude seam be handled
        </brief>
        <description>
          With this option you can turn on/off the automatic longitude domain switching that occurs
          when a file crosses the boundary of the longitude domain (0-360 or -180 to 180).  If the switching is turn off then
          you have the choice of making the program continue or exit when the cube does cross the bounday.
        </description>

        <list>
           <option value="AUTO">
              <brief>Automatically correct Longitude Domain</brief>
              <description>
                If the cube crosses the longitude seam automatically compute the LongitudeDomain   When the cube
                is near 0 or 360 degrees the program will assume 180 LongitudeDomain.  When the cube is near 180 or -180 degrees
                it will assume 360 LongitudeDomain.
              </description>
            </option>

           <option value="ERROR">
              <brief>Abort program if cube crosses seam</brief>
              <description>
                If the cube crosses the longitude seam the program will exit with an error message
              </description>
            </option>

            <option value="CONTINUE">
               <brief>Continue program if cube crosses seam</brief>
               <description>
                 If the cube crosses the longitude seam the program will continue.  The LongitudeDomain in the MAP file will be used.  If the MAP file does not
                 have a LongitudeDomain, 0-360 will be used. Note that this could create an extremely large image.
               </description>
             </option>
        </list>

      </parameter>
    </group>
  </groups>
</application>
