<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="hicolormos" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">
  <brief>
    Create a color mosaic of a HiRISE cubes from an observation and update labels required by hirdrgen.
  </brief>

  <description>
    <p>
  ** The output from this program is required by hirdrgen ** <br/>
  If the final product wil not be an RDR, mapmos or automos can be used to produce a mosaic.  
  This program produces a mosaic and adds keywords to the label group "Mosaic" that are required 
  by hirdrgen. <br/>

  The  input cubes  to this program must be from the same observation,  stacked by hicubeit, and 
  map projected.<br/>

  the CCDs of the HiRISE instrument are arranged in a way that color products can only be produced in two 
  positions of the CCD array.  The CCDs that overlap for a color product are RED4, IR10, and
  BG12 or RED5, IR11, and BG13.  The program hicubeit is used to stack the individual CCDs into 
  a multi band cube.  The output from hicubeit is the required input for hicolormos.  The from1 and 
  from2 parameters allow these two CCD stacks to be input.  The program hicolormos can also be run 
  with only the from1 parameter.<br/>  

   A new label group, that is required by hirdrgen, called "Mosaic"  is added to the image labels of 
   the output cube.  The original label blob is also propagated from the from1 input file.
   </p>

<p>
  <b> processing sequence for color products that will become RDRs </b><br/>
         <b>Slither</b> -  match the blue-green and/or the infer-red to the red CCD.<br/>
         <b>hicubeit</b> - stack the matching CCDs to make a three band cube.<br/>
         <b>cam2map</b> - project the cube.  hicolormos requiers a map projected cube.<br/>
         <b>hicolormos</b> - mosaic files and add keywords to the mosaic group.<br/>
         <b>hirdrgen</b> - produce a RDR product.<br/>
</p>
  </description>

  <category>
    <missionItem>Mars Reconnaissance Orbiter</missionItem>
  </category>

  <history>
    <change name="Robert Sucharski" date="2006-07-19">
      Original version,
    </change>
    <change name="Elizabeth Miller" date="2007-02-20">
      Changed OriginalLabel name to IsisCube
    </change>
    <change name="Robert Sucharski" date="2007-04-12">
      Added keywords SubSolarAzimuth, NorthAzimuth, and SpecialProcessingFlag to mosaic group in output labels.
    </change>
    <change name="Robert Sucharski" date="2007-06-26">
      Fixed a bug, needed to add traverse when looking for PVL group archive.
    </change>
    <change name="Rovert Sucharski" date="2007-10-18">
      Added code to get the avg line and sample for gathering camera infomation if using the avg latitude and longitude fails.
      We contine to use the latitude and logitude so that we are backwards compatible.  We added this new code because 
      the camera could not find an itersect for some images (polar) if we used projection latitude and longitude to "setGround".
     </change>
  </history>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROM1">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          First input file
        </brief>
        <description>
          The first file that will be added to a color mosaic.  This file is also used to propagate
          the Original label blob.     This file must be the output file from hicubeit and map projected.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="FROM2">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <internalDefault>None</internalDefault>
        <brief>
          Second input file. this file is not required.
        </brief>
        <description>
          This is the second cube that will be added to a color masaic.  This file should be the output
          from hicubeit and map projected.  This input file is not required.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TO">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <brief>
          The name of the output cube
        </brief>
        <description>
          This is the name that will be given to the output cube.  this cube is a mosaic of the two
           from files and has the new group "mosaic' added.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="PRIORITY">
        <type>string</type>
        <default>
          <item>ONTOP</item>
        </default>
        <brief>The priority of pixel placement</brief>
        <description>
          This parameter is used to select one of two ways to masaic the
          pixels in areas of overlap.
        </description>

        <list>
          <option value="ONTOP">
            <brief>Input cube will be placed on top of the mosaic </brief>
            <description>
              When the input pixel is not Null, the input pixel
              value will be written to the output cube.
            </description>
          </option>
          <option value="BENEATH">
            <brief>Input cube will be placed beneath the mosaic</brief>
            <description>
              When the mosaic pixel is not Null it will be left unchanged.
            </description>
          </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>
    </group>
  </groups>
</application>
