<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="qtie" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">
  <brief>
    Create and edit control networks
  </brief>

  <description>
    <p>
   This program will update the camera pointing of a level 1 image matching to a 
   base map.   The camera pointing is updated using an iterative least-squares bundle
   adjustment.  This is the interactive version of the program, deltack.
    </p>
    <p>
    To run qtie, you will enter a base map (projected) and a match cube 
    (unprojected).  There are 2 core windows used in this application.
    </p>
    <h3>qtie window</h3> 
    The main qtie window is similar to the qview application. You will see many
    of the same tools, such as "Band Selection", "Zoom", "Pan", "Stretch" and 
    "Find" along the right border. The "Tie" tool is the last button along the
    right toolbar. It will be the default tool selected when qtie is launched.
    <p>
    In this window, select the "Open images" button or the Open action (from 
    File menu).  You will be prompted to enter the base map cube first followed 
    by the level 1 (unprojected) cube to be tied to the base map.
    </p>
      When the "Tie" tool is activated, the mouse buttons have the following 
      function in the cube viewports of the main qtie window:
    <pre>
      <strong>Left Button:</strong>  Modify the closest control point

      <strong>Middle Button:</strong>  Delete the closest control point 

      <strong>Right Button:</strong>  Create new control point
    </pre>
    <h3>Qtie Tool window</h3>
      This is the point editor window of qtie for modifying or creating a point.
      The window will display the cube that is the base map on the left and 
      the level 1 cube on the right.  Both measures (base map and level 1) may be 
      moved.  The measure can be adjusted by:
    <pre>
      move to the cursor position under the crosshair by clicking the left mouse button

      move 1 pixel at a time by using arrow keys on the keyboard 

      move 1 pixel at a time by using arrow buttons above the right view
    </pre>
    Other point editor functions / options include the following:
    <pre>
      <i>In the File menu:</i>    
        <strong>Save Control Network As</strong> Save the ground points
        in a control network.

        <strong>Close</strong> Close the Tie Point Tool.

      <i>In the Options menu:</i>
        <strong>Registration</strong> Set or view and save registration 
        templates.

      <i>Along the top of the window:</i>
        <strong>Twist</strong> Turning off twist will solve for right ascension and
        declination only which is a translation of the image.  Solving for twist 
        includes both translation and rotation.

        <strong>Maximum Iterations</strong> Maximum number of iterations to try
        for convergence to tolerance before stopping.

        <strong>Tolerance</strong> Tolerance in pixels.  When the bundle adjustment
        drops below this value, the solution has converged.

      <i>Along the right border of the window:</i>
        <strong>Geom</strong>  Geom the right view to match the left view 

        <strong>Rotate</strong>  Rotate the right view

      <i>Below the left view:</i>
        <strong>Blink controls</strong>  Blink the left and right view in the
        left view window using the "Blink Start" button (with play icon) and 
        "Blink Stop" button (with stop icon).  The arrow keys above the right view 
        may be used to move the right view in order to update the blinking in real 
        time.

        <strong>Find</strong>   Center the right view so that the same latitude / 
        longitude is under the crosshair as the left view. 

      <i>Below the right view:</i>
        <strong>Register</strong>  Sub-pixel register the the right view to
        the left view.

        <strong>Save Point</strong>  Save both left and right measures in a
        control point.

        <strong>Solve</strong> Attempt the bundle solution using the points picked with
        the given input parameters such as Twist, Maximum Iterations and Tolerance.
        If the solution converges, you will be asked whether you want to update
        the camera pointing.
    </pre>

  </description>

  <category>
    <categoryItem>Display</categoryItem>
  </category>

  <history>
    <change name="Tracie Sucharski" date="2008-12-03">
      Original version
    </change>
    <change name="Tracie Sucharski" date="2008-12-30">
      Add option to save ground points to a ControlNet.
    </change>
    <change name="Tracie Sucharski" date="2008-01-20">
      Correct user documentation in qtie.xml.
    </change>
    <change name="Tracie Sucharski" date="2009-06-10">
      Added error checking when opening files and allow new files to be opened.
    </change>
    <change name="Eric Hyer" date="2010-03-22">
      Discontinued forcing of gui style to windows
    </change>
  </history>
</application>
