<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="cisscal" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">

  <brief>
    Radiometric correction of  Cassini ISS camera images. 
  </brief>

  <description>
    <p>
      This program performs radiometric corrections on images acquired by the 
      Cassisi Imaging Science Subsystem (ISS) camera.  It performs bitweight 
      correction, bias subtraction, dark subtraction, non-linearity correction, 
      flat field correction, DN to flux conversion, and correction factor 
      division.  The user may choose between intensity units and I/F for the DN 
      to flux conversion.  This application is derived from the IDL CISSCAL 
      application developed by the Cassini Imaging Central Laboratory for 
      Operations (CICLPOS) using the following set of steps:
    </p>
    <p>
      <strong>
        Step 1: Correct Bitweight
      </strong>
       This step is performed on images that do not have a data  conversion 
       type  of "Table" or compression type of "Lossy" due to loss of  
       information in  these processses.  This step is also skipped if the image
       has a zero gain state due to the lack of data for this case.  Bitweight 
       correction requires no user defined parameters.  It uses a bitweight file 
       found in the Cassini calibration bitweight directory.
    </p>
    <p>
      <strong>
        Step 2: Subtract Bias 
      </strong> 
      This step defaults to a method that uses a line dependent bias. That 
      method derives the bias by performing a linear fit to an array of
      overclocked pixels taken out of the binary prefix data and saved off by 
      the <strong>ciss2isis</strong> application. This method cannot be 
      performed if the image has a compression type of "Lossy".  In that case, 
      the BiasStripMean value found in the Instrument Group of the cube's labels 
      is subtracted from every pixel. This alternative method cannot be 
      implemented if the instrument used was CAS-ISS3  or earlier since, 
      according to the SIS, the BiasStripMean keyword contains invalid data for 
      these images.  Bias subtraction requires no user defined parameters.
    </p>
    <p>
      <strong>
        Step 3: Subtract Dark
      </strong> 
      This step uses a spline interpolation to construct a  dark image by
      calculating, for each pixel, a duration to be used with the coefficients
      found in the dark parmeter file.  Dark current removal requires no user
      defined parameters and should be performed on all images. It uses a dark
      parameter file and if a narrow angle camera was used, a bias distortion
      table. These are found in the Cassini calibration darkcurrent directory.
    </p>
    <p>
      <strong>
        Step 4: Linearize
      </strong> 
      This step corrects for non-linearity.  It requires no user defined
      parameters and should be performed on all images.   It uses a linearity
      correction table found in the Cassini calibration linearize directory.
    </p>
    <p>
      <strong>
        Step 5: Correct Flat field 
      </strong> 
      This step consists of two parts: dust ring removal  and division by flat
      field.  <strong>Dust ring removal</strong>  only applies to images from
      narrow angle cameras.  This process masks a dust ring found on images and,
      if the image has SummingMode equal to 1 (i.e. it is a full, 1024x1024
      image) and is recent (after 286th day of 2003), divides out a mottle map.
      <strong> Flat field correction </strong> is applied to all images. During
      this process, each pixel is divided by the average of the center of the 
      image.  For SummingMode 2 or 4, the results from this method diverge from 
      the IDL results due to differences in the bilinear method used to expand 
      the flat file image.  Flat field correction requires no user defined 
      parameters. If narrow angle, it uses a dust ring file found in the Cassini 
      calibration dustring directory.  If narrow and full, it also uses a mottle 
      file and an effective wavelength file found in dustring and efficiency 
      directories. And, for any image a slope database and a flat file are used, 
      found in slope and slope/slope2flat directories.  
    </p>
    <p>
      <strong>
        Step 6: Convert DN to Flux
      </strong> 
      This step consists of 4 processes and the user must enter a value of 
      "intensity" or "I/F" for the parameter "fluxunits".  In the first process, 
      DNs are <strong>converted to electrons</strong> by multiplying by the true
      gain.  Second, the image is <strong>divided by the exposure time</strong>, 
      correcting for shutter offset effect. Third, the image is                                                          
      <strong>divided by the optics area</strong> and, if intensity units are 
      chosen, <strong>divided by the solid angle</strong>.  In the last process,           
      each pixel is <strong>divided by an efficiency factor</strong>. This value 
      is dependent on the flux units chosen by the user: intensity units 
      (photons/cm<sup>2</sup>/s/nm/ster) or I/F (irradiance over solar flux).  
      If "I/F" is chosen, the input cube must have been run through the Isis3 
      application <strong>spiceinit</strong> to be able to calculate Solar 
      Distance.  The results from this method diverge from the IDL results due 
      to differences in the way they calculate solar distance. However, the DN 
      results are still within 0.2% after we divide by the efficiency factor. DN 
      to Flux conversion should be performed on all images. Converting DN to 
      flux units requires a shutter offset file, a spectral file (if I/F is 
      chosen), a transmission file, and a quantum efficiency correction file 
      found in the Cassini calibration offset, efficiency, efficiency/systrans 
      and correction directories.
    </p>
    <p>
      <strong>
        Step 7: Divide by Correction Factor
      </strong> 
      This step is implemented in order to force theory and observation to match.
      It consists of 2 processes.  First, if polarized, (i.e. a filter value of 
      IRP0, IRP90, P0, P60, or P120) the image is divided by a polarization
      factor.  Next, the image is divided by its correction factor.  This step 
      requires no user defined parameters. It uses a polarization factor file 
      and a correction factor file found in the Cassini calibration correction 
      directory.
    </p> 
    <p>
    <strong>
      Omitted IDL Steps: 
    </strong> 
      In the original IDL program, there were 2 steps that were omitted in this 
      application since they act as noise removal that can be filtered using
      other applications after calibration is complete. 
      
      The first omitted step is <strong>2-Hz noise removal</strong>.  This is meant to
      remove horizontal banding patterns introduced during image readout of
      Cassini ISS images and has two peaks in the power spectrum near 2Hz. There
      are two methods to this correction. The first method invovles the
      smoothing and filtering of the overclocked pixel array, thus removing high
      frequency random noise, slow-varying, and DC-offset components. The second
      method requires large regions of dark sky pixels present for all lines and
      uses an image mean to construct a 2-Hz signal.
      
      The second omited step is <strong>A-B pixel pairs correction</strong> 
      (also referred to as anti-blooming correction or bright/dark pixel pair 
      removal). In the IDL program, this correction is only performed if the 
      labels of the image indicate that the AntiBloomingStateFlag is "On" and 
      the InstrumentModeId is "Full" (i.e., SummingMode is 1). In this 
      correction, bright/dark pixel pairs are identified and replaced with a 
      boxcar average of their horizontal neighbors. 
    </p>

  </description>

  <history>
    <change name="Jeannie Walldren" date="2008-11-05">
      Original version
    </change>
    <change name="Jeannie Walldren" date="2008-11-12">
      Fixed documentation.
    </change>
    <change name="Jeannie Walldren" date="2008-12-22">
      Fixed bug in bitweight correction.  Updated documentation.
    </change>
    <change name="Jeannie Walldren" date="2009-01-09">
      Updated user documentation "Related Objects and Documents" section 
      document web links.
    </change>
    <change name="Jeannie Walldren" date="2009-01-12">
      Fixed documentation.
    </change>
    <change name="Jeannie Walldren" date="2009-01-26">
      Fixed bug that caused errors on other compilers.
    </change>
    <change name="Jeannie Walldren" date="2009-02-12">
      Modified the "I/F" option to make 2 attempts to locate the the target 
      before throwing an exception.  First, the Isis::Camera class is used to 
      look for the target at the center point of the cube.  If this fails, the 
      subspacecraft point is used to find the target.  Only if both fail will 
      the application throw an error.
    </change>
    <change name="Jeannie Walldren" date="2009-05-27">
      Modified cisscal and its DarkCurrent class to reflect updates to the new 
      idl cisscal program version, 3.6.  Updated documentation and app test to 
      reflect these changes.
    </change>
  </history>

  <category>
    <missionItem>Cassini</missionItem>
  </category>

  <seeAlso>
    <applications>
      <item>
        ciss2isis
      </item>
      <item>
        spiceinit
      </item>
    </applications>
    <documents>
      <document>
        <title>
            Cassini ISS Software Interface Specification (SIS)
        </title>
        <source>
          <filename>edrsis.pdf</filename>
          <path>http://pds-imaging.jpl.nasa.gov/data/cassini/cassini_orbiter/coiss_0011_v2/document/</path>
        </source>
        <author>Charles Avis and Carolyn Porco</author>
        <publisher>Cassini Electronic Library</publisher>
      </document>
      <document>
        <title>
            CISSCAL User Guide
        </title>
        <source>
          <filename>cisscal_manual.pdf</filename>
          <path>http://pds-imaging.jpl.nasa.gov/data/cassini/cassini_orbiter/coiss_0011_v2/document/</path>
        </source>
        <publisher>Planetary Data System Rings Node</publisher>
      </document>
      <document>
        <title>
            Cassini ISS Image Calibration: Theoretical Basis
        </title>
        <source>
          <filename>theoretical_basis.pdf</filename>
          <path>http://pds-imaging.jpl.nasa.gov/data/cassini/cassini_orbiter/coiss_0011_v2/document/</path>
        </source>
        <author>R. West</author>
        <publisher>Planetary Data System Rings Node</publisher>
      </document>
      <document>
        <title>
            Cassini ISS Calibration Report
        </title>
        <source>
          <filename></filename>
          <path>http://pds-imaging.jpl.nasa.gov/data/cassini/cassini_orbiter/coiss_0011_v2/document/report/</path>
        </source>
        <author>Cassini ISS Development Team</author>
        <publisher>Planetary Data System Rings Node</publisher>
      </document>
      <document>
        <title>
          Cassini ISS Calibration Report: 7.0 Radiometric Calibration Steps 
        </title>
        <source>
          <filename> </filename>
          <path>http://pds-imaging.jpl.nasa.gov/data/cassini/cassini_orbiter/coiss_0011_v2/document/report/iss/7.0/7.0.html</path>
        </source>
        <author>Alfred McEwen and James Winburn</author>
        <publisher>Planetary Data System Rings Node</publisher>
      </document>
    </documents>
  </seeAlso>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input Isis cube
        </brief>
        <description>
          Use this parameter to choose an Isis cube to be calibrated.  To ensure 
          that it contains all needed keywords in its label, input cube should 
          have been imported using <strong>ciss2isis</strong> and, if "I/F" is chosen, input cube 
          must have been run through <strong>spiceinit</strong> application.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TO">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <pixelType>real</pixelType>
        <brief>
           Output Isis cube
        </brief>
        <description>
           Use this parameter to select the output filename of the calibrated 
           Isis cube.
        </description>
        <filter>
           *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>
    </group>
    <group name = "Input Values">
      <parameter name = "FLUXUNITS">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>Options for converted flux units</brief>
        <description>
          A list of the types of units to which user may choose to convert from
          DNs. 
        </description>
        <default><item>INTENSITY</item></default>
        <list>
          <option value="INTENSITY">
            <brief>Intensity units </brief>
            <description> 
              This option indicates that the user prefers to convert DNs to 
              standard intensity units (photons/cm^2/s/nm/ster).
            </description>
          </option>
          <option value="I/F">
            <brief>Irradiance/SolarFlux </brief>
            <description> 
              This option indicates that the user prefers to normalize intensity
              in terms of solar flux (I/F).  Input cube must have been run 
              through <strong>spiceinit</strong> application.
            </description>
          </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>
    </group>
  </groups>
  <examples>
    <example>
      <brief>Cube calibrated using intensity units.</brief>
      <description>
        This example shows how to calibrate a Cassini ISS cube, converting to 
        intensity units.
      </description>
      <terminalInterface>
        <commandLine> 
          from=../IN/inputCube.cub to=../OUT/outputCube.cub 
        </commandLine>
        <description> 
          Run the <strong>cisscal</strong> application to calibrate the cube.
        </description>
      </terminalInterface>
      <guiInterfaces>
        <guiInterface>
          <image width="496" height="550" src="assets/images/cisscalGuiEx1.jpg">
            <brief>Example Gui</brief>
            <description>
              Screenshot of GUI with parameters filled in to perform the <strong>cisscal</strong>
              application.  Input and output cubes are always required. The
              radio button INTENSITY is chosen as default.
            </description>
            <thumbnail width="180" height="200" caption="Cisscal Gui using intensity" src="assets/thumbs/cisscalGuiThumbEx1.jpg" />
          </image>
        </guiInterface>
      </guiInterfaces>
      <dataFiles>
        <dataFile path="assets/dataFiles/cisscalStatsEx1.pvl">
          <brief>
            Stats on output cube
          </brief>
          <description>
            This pvl file contains the results of the <strong> stats</strong> application run on 
            the example 1 output cube.  This may be compared with the pvl file 
            of the same application run on the example 2 output cube.
          </description>
          <parameterName>
            FLUXUNITS
          </parameterName>
        </dataFile>
      </dataFiles>
      <inputImages>
        <image width="479" height="550" src="assets/images/cisscalInput.jpg">
          <brief>
            Input image
          </brief>
          <description>
            This is a Titan narrow-angle image that was imported into Isis cube 
            format using <strong>ciss2isis</strong>.
          </description>
          <thumbnail width="174" height="200" src="assets/thumbs/cisscalInputThumb.jpg" caption="Input cube"/>
          <parameterName>
            FROM
          </parameterName>
        </image>
      </inputImages>
      <outputImages>
        <image width="479" height="550" src="assets/images/cisscalOutputEx1.jpg">
          <brief>
            Output image
        </brief>
        <description>
          This is the Titan narrow-angle image calibrated and converted to 
          intensity units.
        </description>
        <thumbnail width="174" height="200" src="assets/thumbs/cisscalOutputThumbEx1.jpg" caption="Output cube calibrated with intensity units"/>
        <parameterName>
          TO
        </parameterName>
        </image>
      </outputImages>
    </example>
    <example>
      <brief>Cube calibrated using I/F.</brief>
      <description>
        This example shows how to calibrate a Cassini ISS cube, converting to 
        I/F.
      </description>
      <terminalInterface>
        <commandLine> 
          from=../IN/inputCube.cub to=../OUT/outputCube.cub fluxunits="I/F"
        </commandLine>
        <description> 
          Run the <strong>cisscal</strong> application to calibrate the cube.
        </description>
      </terminalInterface>
      <guiInterfaces>
        <guiInterface>
          <image width="496" height="550" src="assets/images/cisscalGuiEx2.jpg">
            <brief>Example Gui</brief>
            <description>
              Screenshot of GUI with parameters filled in to perform the <strong>cisscal</strong>
              application.  Input and output cubes are always required. The
              radio button I/F is chosen.
            </description>
            <thumbnail width="180" height="200" caption="Cisscal Gui using I/F" src="assets/thumbs/cisscalGuiThumbEx2.jpg" />
          </image>
        </guiInterface>
      </guiInterfaces>
      <dataFiles>
        <dataFile path="assets/dataFiles/cisscalStatsEx2.pvl">
          <brief>
            Stats on output cube
          </brief>
          <description>
            This pvl file contains the results of the <strong> stats</strong> application run on 
            the example 2 output cube.  This may be compared with the pvl file 
            of the same application run on the example 1 output cube.
          </description>
          <parameterName>
            FLUXUNITS
          </parameterName>
        </dataFile>
      </dataFiles>
      <inputImages>
        <image width="479" height="550" src="assets/images/cisscalInput.jpg">
          <brief>
            Input image
          </brief>
          <description>
            This is a Titan narrow-angle image that was imported into Isis cube 
            format using <strong>ciss2isis</strong> and run through <strong>spiceinit</strong>.
          </description>
          <thumbnail width="174" height="200" src="assets/thumbs/cisscalInputThumb.jpg" caption="Input cube"/>
          <parameterName>
            FROM
          </parameterName>
        </image>
      </inputImages>
      <outputImages>
        <image width="479" height="550" src="assets/images/cisscalOutputEx2.jpg">
          <brief>
            Output image
          </brief>
          <description>
            This is the Titan narrow-angle image calibrated and converted to 
            I/F.
          </description>
          <thumbnail width="174" height="200" src="assets/thumbs/cisscalOutputThumbEx2.jpg" caption="Output cube calibrated with I/F"/>
          <parameterName>
            TO
          </parameterName>
        </image>
      </outputImages>
    </example>
  </examples>
</application>
