<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="fplanemap" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">

  <brief>
       Produce focal plane coordinates from control net file
  </brief>

  <description>
      <p>
          <b>fplanemap</b> produces a comma separated value (CSV) file 
          containing focal plane coordinates from a control network file.  The 
          file is assumed to originate from a <b>coreg</b> run comparing two 
          files either in  camera or projected space.  
      </p>
      <p>
          Typical processing strategies would include identifying a trusted 
          source image (truth or MATCH file used in <b>coreg</b> ) that has no 
          distortion and comparable resolution.  The registration of the truth 
          image to the image requiring analysis (FROM) should produce strong 
          correlations for the best results. Areas of least variation in 
          topography will also contribute to better results. 
      </p>
      <p>
          This application was developed primarily to analyze image distortion, 
          which is very sensitive to correlation imperfections.  The content of 
          the CSV output TO file contains all the information necessary to apply 
          linear or least square fits to equations.   The following describes 
          the output CSV file format.
      </p>
      <p>
          The output TO CSV file contains 11 columns.   Note that a camera model 
          for the FROM file is required since it is used to get the actual 
          focal plane coordinates.  The sample and line coordinates recorded in 
          the output file will be the same as in the control net file. The 
          sample/line coordinate provided there is used to determine the 
          latitude and longitude of the coordinate.   Below is a small portion 
          of an output TO CSV file:
          <pre>
OldSample,OldLine,NewSample,NewLine,X,Y,XC,YC,GoodnessOfFit,Latitude,Longitude
51,3,46.5738,6.52725,-0.125346,3.18205,-0.152566,3.58934,0.514252,32.2544,82.1228
17,37,22.0716,36.9117,-0.0278861,3.11492,-0.030747,3.51921,0.44952,32.2264,82.0898
51,37,54.8234,41.0111,-0.025531,3.18319,-0.0403855,3.6141,0.543963,32.2264,82.1228
84,37,86.1196,39.766,-0.0232456,3.24823,-0.0344203,3.70423,0.225104,32.2264,82.1548
51,43,49.5502,46.0587,-0.0410861,3.18351,-0.055586,3.59933,0.255932,32.2215,82.1228
51,49,51.7797,45.6973,-0.0566404,3.18382,-0.0543615,3.60573,0.347588,32.2165,82.1228
84,49,90.1357,49.14,-0.0541637,3.24884,-0.0616203,3.71664,0.446062,32.2165,82.1548
17,55,15.761,61.5159,-0.0748423,3.11587,-0.103437,3.5031,0.204652,32.2116,82.0898
51,55,48.6316,58.2457,-0.0721934,3.18412,-0.0914211,3.59775,0.383612,32.2116,82.1228
84,55,89.9976,55.097,-0.0696208,3.24915,-0.0791061,3.71678,0.338814,32.2116,82.1548
17,60,11.4821,61.6077,-0.0878837,3.11609,-0.10402,3.49073,0.436698,32.2074,82.0898
51,60,48.1177,61.9931,-0.0851532,3.18435,-0.102458,3.59659,0.266318,32.2074,82.1228
84,60,89.7459,59.6435,-0.0825007,3.24938,-0.0924634,3.71647,0.326716,32.2074,82.1548
17,66,14.9112,70.9194,-0.103532,3.11635,-0.13111,3.50144,0.365906,32.2025,82.0898
          </pre>
      </p>
      <p>
              Analysis of the data may result in adjustments to the boresight 
              and/or the distortion model.  The plot below is derived from the data 
              from the above file. 
        </p>
          <p>
               <img src='assets/output.png' alt='Plot of Y Component in mm' width='675' height='452' />
          </p> 
      <p>
             This data as plotted can be used to derive distortion model parameters 
              by fitting a line through the data.
      </p>
      <p>
          The following table describes each column: 
      </p>
                <br><h1 align="center">CSV Output Columns</h1></br>
                <TABLE BORDER="1">
                      <CAPTION>
                        Data generated from the <b>fplanemap</b> application
                        </CAPTION>
                    <TR>
                      <TH>Column</TH>
                      <TH>Description</TH>
                    </TR>
                    <TR>
                       <TD>OldSample</TD>
                       <TD>
                         The original sample coordinate of the point at the 
                         center of the registration pixel location.  This 
                         coordinate comes from the MATCH file in <b>coreg</b>.
                       </TD>
                    </TR>
                    <TR>
                        <TD>OldLine</TD>
                        <TD>
                            The original line coordinate of the point at the 
                            center of the registration pixel location.   This 
                         coordinate comes from the MATCH file in <b>coreg</b>.
                        </TD>
                    </TR>
                    <TR>
                        <TD>NewSample</TD>
                        <TD>
                            The registered sample coordinate from the FROM file 
                            in  <b>coreg</b> and <b>fplanemap</b> . 
                        </TD>
                    </TR>
                    <TR>
                        <TD>NewLine</TD>
                        <TD>
                            The registered line coordinate from the FROM file 
                            in  <b>coreg</b> and <b>fplanemap</b>.
                        </TD>
                    </TR>
                    <TR>
                        <TD>X</TD>
                        <TD>
                            The  distorted focal plane X coordinate (xd) that 
                            maps from the old distorted pixel location 
                            (OldSample, OldLine).  The units are typically in 
                            millimeters.
                        </TD>
                    </TR>
                    <TR>
                        <TD>Y</TD>
                        <TD>
                            The distorted focal plane Y coordinate (yd) that 
                            maps from the old distorted pixel location 
                            (OldSample, OldLine).  The units are typically in 
                            millimeters.
                        </TD>
                    </TR>
                    <TR>
                        <TD>XC</TD>
                        <TD>
                            The undistorted focal plane X coordinate (xc) that 
                            maps from the new distorted pixel location 
                            (NewSample, NewLine). The units are typically in 
                            millimeters.
                        </TD>
                    </TR>
                    <TR>
                        <TD>YC</TD>
                        <TD>
                            The undistorted focal plane Y coordinate (yc) that 
                            maps from the new distorted pixel location 
                            (NewSample,NewLine).  The units are typically in 
                            millimeters.
                        </TD>
                    </TR>
                    <TR>
                        <TD>GoodnessOfFit</TD>
                        <TD>
                            The coorelation coefficient as found in the control 
                            net file that indicates the quality of the 
                            registration for the point
                        </TD>
                    </TR>
                    <TR>
                        <TD>Latitude</TD>
                        <TD>
                            The latitude of the OldSamp/OldLine coordinate
                        </TD>
                    </TR>
                    <TR>
                        <TD>Longitude</TD>
                        <TD>
                            The longitude of the OldSample/OldLine coordinate
                        </TD>
                    </TR>
                </TABLE>
  </description>

  <category>
    <categoryItem>Registration and Pattern Matching</categoryItem>
  </category>  

  <history>
     <change name="Kris Becker" date="2010-09-24">
         Original Version
     </change>
  </history>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input file to provide focal plane data
        </brief>
        <description>
          This is the same file provided in the FROM parameter for the 
          coregistration program, such as <b>coreg</b>.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>

       <parameter name="CNETFILE">
          <type>filename</type>
          <fileMode>output</fileMode>
          <brief>
               Pvl file of ControlNet
          </brief>
          <description>
              <p>
                   This file will contain the ControlNet created from the run of a 
                   co-registration application such as <b>coreg</b>.  There are 
                   checks made to ensure that it satisfies expected conditions of a 
                   output control net from one of these types of applications.
              </p>
              <p>
                  There must be only two measures to a control point.  One must 
                  be designated the reference.  Points that have the Ignore 
                  property set to true are not considered in this application.
              </p>
          </description>
          <filter>
            *.net *.pbnet
          </filter>
        </parameter>

        <parameter name="TO">
          <type>filename</type>
          <fileMode>output</fileMode>
          <brief>
              Output file containing focal plane information
          </brief>
          <description>
              This file will contain the 11 parameters in comma separated values 
              (CSV) format that provides information about the orginal and 
              registered points, focal plane coordinates and latitude and 
              longitude data.
          </description>
          <internalDefault>None</internalDefault>
          <filter>
            *.csv
          </filter>
        </parameter>
      </group>
    
      <group name="Options">
        <parameter name="TOLERANCE">
            <type>double</type>
            <brief>
                Detector pixel tolerance
            </brief>
            <description>
                Places a limit on the maximum distance in the detector plane 
                the offset is expected to differ.  This value unit is in pixels 
                which is converted internally to the detector pixel unit, which 
                is typically millimeters.   Pixel size of the detector is 
                sometimes referred to as <i>pixel pitch</i>.
            </description>
            <default><item>5.0</item></default>
        </parameter>

        <parameter name="CHECKDN">
                <type>boolean</type>
                <default><item>False</item></default>
                <brief>
                  Check the DN in the file at the pixel location for validity
                </brief>
                <description>
                  A check will be performed at the pixel location of the original 
                  line and sample to ensure the pixel is valid.  The pixel must only 
                  have a pixel value that is not one of the ISIS special pixels
                </description>
          </parameter>
          </group>
  </groups>
</application>
