<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- $Id: mdis2isis.xml,v 1.13 2009/12/29 21:45:54 slambright Exp $ -->

<application name="mdis2isis" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">
  <brief>
    Import MESSENGER/MIDS EDR/RDR products into ISIS cubes
  </brief>

  <description>
    <p>
       mdis2isis converts PDS labelled MESSENGER/MDIS EDRs to ISIS labels.
      MDIS has a narrow angle camera (MDIS-NAC) and a wide angel camera (MDIS-WAC)
      with twelve filters.  This application will convert all these observations to ISIS format.
      The resulting ISIS cubes are ready for SPICE initialization and projection.
    </p>
    <p>
      Some of the images are compressed onboard the spacecraft.  When this is 
      detected, they are unlutted and each DN is converted to its precompressed 
      12-bit DN value.  All output files are created in floating point DN 
      format.
    </p>
    <p>
      There are DN limits that are imposed on the output pixel.  For the NAC 
      instrument, the valid range is 0 &lt; DN &lt; 3400.  The limit for the WAC 
      is 0 &lt; DN &lt; 3600.  For both instruments, 0 values are mapped to the 
      NULL special pixel value.  And values that exceed the maximum are set to 
      the HIS (high instrument saturation) special pixel value.
    </p>
  </description>

  <category>
    <missionItem>Messenger</missionItem>
  </category>

  <history>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2005-07-25">
      Original version
    </change>
    <change name="Elizabeth Miller" date="2005-11-15">
        Added appTest
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2007-12-10">
        Added lookup table capabilities
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2007-12-11">
        Fixed problem where labels went outside the IsisCube object
    </change>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2008-01-19">
        Added validation of filter number here.  The number in the label is 
        unreliable and requires validation as filter identification is critical 
        in calibration and camera model (at a minimum).    If it cannot be 
        determined, the number is set to "Unknown" which renders the file 
        unusable for calibration and geometric operations.
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2008-03-18">
      Checks if input file is rdr.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2008-05-13">
      Removed references to CubeInfo 
    </change>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2008-09-03">
       Reworked the lut inversion implementation to use a different dn table 
       source.  This altered the resulting DNs a bit.  Also instituted DN limits 
       for low (0) and high saturation levels for WAC (3600) and NAC (3400).  DN 
       values that exceed these maximums are set to NULL and HIS (High 
       Instrument Saturation), respectively.  Started the SOURCE_PRODUCT_ID 
       pedigree  chain.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2009-12-29">
      Now looking for mdisCalibration????.trn in $messenger/calibration instead of
      $messenger/translations
    </change>
  </history>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input cube file name
        </brief>
        <description>
          The input MDIS EDR/RDR file
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.IMG *.IMA
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TO">
        <type>cube</type>
        <pixelType>real</pixelType>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Output cube
        </brief>
        <description>
          Output file converted from PDS EDR format to ISIS.  This ISIS file will have all the
          information transferred from the PDS EDR file that is necessary to 
          initialize for geometric processing (see spiceinit, cam2map, etc...).
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Parameters">
        <parameter name="TARGET">
            <type>string</type>
            <brief>Provide observation target if not in EDR</brief>
            <description>
                This parameter may be necessary as some EDR labels do not adequately defined
                the TARGET_NAME keyword in the labels.  Messenger takes a very long trip to 
                finally arrive at Mercury orbit in 2011.  During cruise, many flybys occur.  The
                proper specification of the TARGET_NAME is critical to valid instantiation of
                ISIS camera models.  

                At the time of the original writing of this application, NULL was a frequently
                occuring value of the TARGET_NAME keyword even for flyby encounters.
                This keyword allows one to specify the observed body explicitiy for these cases.

                The default is to honor the value in the EDR label as it is anticipated this will be
                corrected in subsequent EDR generation.
            </description>
            <internalDefault>Label Value</internalDefault> 
        </parameter>
      <parameter name="UNLUT">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <brief>
          Convert 8-bit values to 12-bit values
        </brief>
        <description>
          If this is set to true, and the input cube is lutted, a lookup table 
          will be used to convert the original DN values to their original 
          12-bit values. This must be set to true for calibration.
        </description>
        <default>
          <item>
            true
          </item>
        </default>
      </parameter>
    </group>
  </groups>

</application>
