<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="tgocassisstitch" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">

  <brief>
    Stitch together multiple TGO CaSSIS framelets into full frame images.
  </brief>

  <description>
    Stitch together multiple TGO CaSSIS framelets into full frame images. The
    labels from the first framelet in each frame are used as a starting point
    for the frame labels. If spiceinit has been run on the first framelet, then
    that information will be propagated to the frame. Information that is
    unique to each framelet, along with the location of each framelet will be
    output in the "Stitch" group on the frame cubes' label.
  </description>

  <history>
    <change name="Jesse Mapel" date="2017-09-09">
      Original version
    </change>
    <change name="Jesse Mapel" date="2017-09-15">
      Changed name from tgostitch to stitch. Still only works with TGO CaSSIS images. References #5156.
    </change>
    <change name="Kristin Berry" date="2017-11-14">
      Backward Compatibility Issue: Changed name from stitch to tgocassisstitch and
      changed output parameter name "TO" to "OUTPUTPREFIX."
    </change>
    <change name="Adam Goins" date="2018-02-15">
      Modified stitchFrame to store the Archive group for ingested framelets. Fixes #5333.
    </change>
    <change name="Anton Hibl" date="2023-02-24">
      Modified stitchFrame to have logic for suffix or prefix in the output
      filename. Fixes #5125.
    </change>
  </history>

  <category>
    <missionItem>ExoMars Trace Gas Orbiter</missionItem>
  </category>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROMLIST">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          A list of TGO CaSSIS framelet images to stitch into full frames.
        </brief>
        <description>
          A list of TGO CaSSIS framelet images to stitch. The images will be
          sorted into frames based on their serial number the same way that
          observation mode works in the jigsaw application. So, the list of
          images can contain framelets from multiple different frames.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.lis
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="CUBENAME">
        <type>cube</type>
        <default><item>nil</item></default>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          An optional name for the output cube.
        </brief>
        <description>
          An optional name for the output cube instead of the default timestamp
          style naming.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="OUTPUTPREFIX">
        <type>cube</type>
        <default><item>nil</item></default>
         <fileMode>output</fileMode>
         <brief>
           Output ISIS cube basename prefix.
         </brief>
         <description>
           The stitched cubes will be output as this basename plus the last
           component of the serial number. Usually this will be the start time
           for the frame.
         </description>
         <filter>
           *.cub
         </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="OUTPUTSUFFIX">
         <type>cube</type>
         <default><item>nil</item></default>
         <fileMode>output</fileMode>
         <brief>
           output ISIS cube basename suffix.
         </brief>
         <description>
           The stitched cubes will be output as the last component of the serial
           number plus this basename. Usually this will be the start time for
           the frame.
         </description>
         <filter>
           *.cub
         </filter>
       </parameter>
    </group>
  </groups>
</application>
