<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="kaguyasp2ascii" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">

  <brief>
    Converts Kaguya SP (Spectral Profiler) file to a tab delimited text file 
  </brief>

  <description>
  <p>
    This program will read a binary SELENE Kaguya SP (Spectral Profiler) data file 
    (downloaded as a .spc file from <a href="http://l2db.selene.darts.isas.jaxa.jp/">the archive site</a>) and create a 
    user-specified, tab-delimited text file.

    The multi-column ASCII text file will contain one record for each of the 296 wavelengths (bands or channels) in the SP file. 
    The bands are derived from 3 separate sensors, with wavelengths as follows: UVVIS wavelength = 512.6 -1010.7 nm; NIR1 
    wavelength = 883.5 - 1676.0 nm; NIR2 wavelength = 702.1-2587.9 nm.  Each record in the output file will contain ancillary data 
    and all of the observations for a specific wavelength. You can limit the number of observations that
    are listed by using the MINOBS and MAXOBS parameters. The ancillary data include a quality assessment (QA) parameter, 
    raw DN, radiance, and ref_1 and ref_2 (reflectance  values that have been photometrically corrected using values for
    highlands and mare, respectively) for each wavelength and each observation. SP binary data files can have less than 10 observations
    or more than 50. This program works on both Level 2B and Level 2C products from Kaguya, with two caveats:
    the NIR portions of the Level 2B products are not calibrated or photometrically corrected, but the L2C products have been fully
    calibrated and photometrically corrected. </p>

  <p>
    The documents in the kaguyasp2ascii/assets directory provide information about the Kaguya Spectral 
    Profiler data. The directory also contains a summary of what the different Quality Assessment values 
    mean (from p. 82 of the <a href="http://l2db.selene.darts.isas.jaxa.jp/help/en/LISM_SPICE_Fromat_en_V01-03.pdf">LISM SPICE documentation</a>).
  </p>
  <p>
    Note that this program does not process the SP data in any way once the binary data is converted to ASCII.
    For example, you likely would not want to work with SP data that have oblique viewing angles or are poorly illuminated 
    (these must be filtered from the archive site), or you may want to remove redundant or erroneous data at the instrument joins 
    (e.g., spikes in DN values at the ends of the VIS, NIR1, NIR2). For the latter, the QA values will help you to identify these.
    QA values with any of the three left-most bits set to 1 can be removed from each spectrum. 
  </p>
  <p>
    References: 
    <br /> 
     Yamamoto, S. et al. (2011) Preflight and in-flight calibration of the spectral profiler onboard the SELENE (Kaguya). IEEE Trans. Geosci. Remote Sens. 49 (11), p. 4660-4676.
     <br />
     Yamamoto, S. et al. (2014) Calibration of NIR2 of Spectral Profiler onboard Kaguya/SELENE, IEEE Trans. Geosci. Remote Sens. 52 (11), p. 6882-6898.
     <br /> 
     Yokota, Y., et al. (2011) Lunar photometric properties at wavelengths 0.5-1.6mm acquired by SELENE Spectral Profiler and their dependency on local albedo and latitudinal zones. Icarus, 215, 639-660, <a href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.icarus.2011.07.028">http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.icarus.2011.07.028</a>.
  </p>
  </description>

  <history>
    <change name="Janet Barrett" date="2014-02-19">
      Original version. This program imports binary data
      from a Kaguya Spectral Profiler file and puts the 
      data into a tab delimited table.
    </change>
    <change name="Kristin Berry" date="2015-08-24">
      Updated to deal with format change for newer files . Now will output both reflectances  
      and calibrated NIR2 data if available. Also, updated to put actual QA information in 
      the output file, which was not happening correctly before, and updated online
      documentation to match Lisa Gaddis's rewrite.
      Additionally, headers are now tab-separated, rather than comma-separated.
      Fixes #2218
    </change>
    <change name="Kristin Berry" date="2015-09-18">
      Backward Compatibility Issue: The application name was changed from kaguyasp2isis to 
      kaguyasp2ascii since this application does not output an ISIS Cube, which could
      impact processing scripts/pipelines which use the old application name. 
    </change>
  </history>

  <category>
    <missionItem>Kaguya</missionItem>
  </category>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input Kaguya SP file
        </brief>
        <description>
          This is the input Kaguya SP file.  For an attached label, use the .spc file, or for a detached label, use the .lbl file.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.lbl *.spc
        </filter>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="TO">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Output Kaguya text file
        </brief>
        <description>
          The output file will be formatted as a tab delimited
          file and will contain all requested observations for
          a single wavelength in each record of the file. Each
          observation will include the raw, radiance, reflectance,
          and QA information. If two reflectances are available,
          as in newer-format files, both will be included in the output file.
        </description>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Limit Parameters">
      <parameter name="MINOBS">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>Minimum observation</brief>
        <description>
          This is the minimum observation of the observation range
          for which information will be obtained from the input
          file. If no value is specified, then the minimum will be
          set to 1.
        </description>
        <default><item>None</item></default>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="MAXOBS">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>Maximum observation</brief>
        <description>
          This is the maximum observation of the observation range
          for which information will be obtained from the input 
          file. If no value is specified, then the maximum will be
          set to the maximum observation in the input file.
        </description>
        <default><item>None</item></default>
      </parameter>
    </group>
  </groups>
</application>
