<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<application name="msi2isis"
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">

  <brief>
    Import NEAR MSI files into ISIS format
  </brief>
  <description>
    This program will import raw images, acquired from the Near Earth Asteroid
    Rendezvous - Shoemaker (NEAR Shoemaker) mission's Multispectral Imager
    (MSI) instrument, to ISIS data file format.

    The raw image must be in FITS (Flexible Image Transport) format and
    have a PDS label file that points to the location of the FITS image. You
    must input either the label file or the FITS file for the "TO" input
    parameter.  Projected images are not supported.  Please note if the FITS
    file is given, the label file must exist in the same directory or the
    program will throw an error.

    This program will verify that the input files are valid by checking the
    following label keyword values.  An error will be  thrown if any of these
    criteria are not met.
    <ul>
      <li>INSTRUMENT_ID = MSI</li>
      <li>LINE_SAMPLES = 537</li>
      <li>LINES = 244</li>
      <li>SAMPLE_DISPLAY_DIRECTION = RIGHT</li>
      <li>LINE_DISPLAY_DIRECTION = UP</li>
    </ul>

    The output cube- successfully imported into ISIS goes through the following
    processes:
    <ul>
      <li>Convert the raw FITS image data to an ISIS cube.</li>
      <li> Save the labels from the input PDS label file to the output
           ISIS cube. Note that FITS labels are not transferred. </li>
      <li>Enlarge the image from 537 samples x 244 lines to 537 x 412 using the
          user-specified interpolation algorithm. Defaults to cubic
          convolution.</li>
      <li>Flip the image vertically, i.e. across the horizontal axis.</li>
      <li>Trim 33 pixels from the top, bottom, left and right sides. These
            pixels along the borders will be set to nulls.</li>
    </ul>

    <h3>Image Trimming</h3>
    <p>
        Shortly after orbit insertion around Eros, the NEAR spacecraft
        experienced a failed burn that contaminated the MSI instrument with
        hydrazine. The NEAR/MSI team developed a preliminary remediation [1] of
        the blur effect of the contamination using FFTs to correct the point
        spread function (PSF). A residual side effect of this correction was
        degradation of ~33 pixels on all edges of the images.  As a result, by
        default, NEAR/MSI images are trimmed 33 pixels around all edges after
        import. MSI images requiring trmming of these data are of the form
        m0132069107f4_2p_iof_dbl.img.
    </p>
    <p>
        Additional remediation work of the PSF function used to correct MSI
        images was performed by Golish [2] that resulted in an enhanced PDF
        correction that did not introduce edge-artifacts as was seen in [1].
        The TRIM parameter was added to optionally retain the 33 pixels around
        the image edges when the dataset from [2] is used. File names that do
        not require trimming are of the form m0132069107f4_2p_iof_gbl.img (note
        the <e>gbl</e>).
    </p>
    <p>
        Note the images produced by Golish [2] have already been expanded. So
        msi2isis was altered to check for the expanded size (in lines only) to
        allow for the full frame to be ingested. In this case, the intermediate
        step to interpolate in the line dimension to expand the the number of
        lines from 244 to 412 is not needed and excluded from ingestion
        processing. All other (label) checks were left to complete the
        validation of the input files.
    </p>
    <br/>
    <h2>References</h2>
    <br/>
    <cite>
      1. Li, H., et al. (2002) Preliminary Remediation of Scattered Light in
      NEAR MSI Images. Icarus 155, 244-252. <a
      href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0019103501967454">
      https://doi.org/10.1006/icar.2001.6745</a>
    </cite>
    <br/>
    <br/>
    <cite>
      2. Golish, D.R., et al. (2021) Improved Remediation of NEAR MSI Images of
      Asteroid (433) Eros. LPSC LII, Abstract
      <a href="https://www.hou.usra.edu/meetings/lpsc2021/pdf/1682.pdf">
      #1682</a>.
    </cite>
    <br/>
    <br/>
  </description>

  <history>
    <change name="Jeannie Backer" date="2013-03-27">
      Original version of msi2isis. References #1248.
    </change>
     <change name="Kristin Berry" date="2014-05-19">
         Updated to add labels from the input PDS label file to the output ISIS
         cube. References #2088.
    </change>
     <change name="Kris Becker" date="2019-08-15">
         Correct SpacecraftClockStartCount/SpacecraftClockStopCount values to be
         compatible with NAIF SCLK kernels that enables use in the camera model.
         Save original values in new keywords prepended with "Original".
    </change>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2021-02-19">
         Added the TRIM parameter to optionally trim data around the edges of
         some MSI images due to degradation resulting from remediation of the
         PSF.
    </change>
  </history>

  <seeAlso>
    <applications>
      <item>fits2isis</item>
      <item>enlarge</item>
      <item>flip</item>
      <item>trim</item>
    </applications>
  </seeAlso>

  <category>
    <missionItem>Near Earth Asteroid Rendezvous</missionItem>
  </category>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input NEAR MSI file to be converted to an ISIS cube
        </brief>
        <description>
          Name of the input NEAR MSI image file to be imported into ISIS
          format. You may enter the label or the image file. If the image
          file is given, the program will search in the same directory for a
          label file with the same base name as the image file base name.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.lbl *.fit *.fits
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TO">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Output ISIS cube filename
        </brief>
        <description>
          Name of the ISIS output cube file that has been imported, enlarged,
          flipped, and trimmed.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Scaling Parameters">
      <parameter name="INTERP">
        <type>string</type>
        <default>
          <item>CUBICCONVOLUTION</item>
        </default>
        <brief>Type of interpolation for enlarge process</brief>
        <description>
          This is the type of interpolation to be performed on the input when
          the image is enlarged from 537 samples x 244 lines to
          537 samples x 412 lines.
        </description>
        <list>
          <option value="CUBICCONVOLUTION">
            <brief>Cubic Convolution interpolation</brief>
            <description>
              Each output pixel is set to the value calculated by
              a cubic convolution interpolation of the calculated input pixel.
            </description>
          </option>
          <option value="NEARESTNEIGHBOR">
            <brief>Nearest Neighbor</brief>
            <description>
              Each output pixel is set to the pixel nearest the
              calculated input pixel.
            </description>
          </option>
          <option value="BILINEAR">
            <brief>Bi-Linear interpolation</brief>
            <description>
              Each output pixel is set to the value calculated by
              a bi-linear interpolation of the calculated input pixel.
            </description>
          </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Trimming Parameters">
      <parameter name="TRIM">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <brief>Trim all image border edges</brief>
        <description>
           This parameter is provided to turn off trimming 33 pixels from the
           edge of images. When TRIM=TRUE, 33 pixels on all sides of the
           expanded image are set to NULL but not removed. The source of this
           degradation is image edge-effects created from the remediation of
           hydrazine contamination of the MSI filters. If TRIM=FALSE, no pixels
           around the edge of the images are NULLed. This is useful to retain
           image edges that originate from several alternative archive sources
           [2].
        </description>
        <default><item>true</item></default>
      </parameter>
    </group>
  </groups>

  <examples>
    <example>
      <brief>
        Usage of this import application
      </brief>
      <description>
        This example shows how to import an MSI fits file to the ISIS
        cube format using the label file.
      </description>
      <terminalInterface>
        <commandLine>
          from=msi_raw_file.lbl to=imported.cub
        </commandLine>
        <description>
          The command line arguments to import a file to cube format.
        </description>
      </terminalInterface>
      <guiInterfaces>
        <guiInterface>
          <image width="550" height="494" src="assets/images/msi2isisGUI.jpg">
            <brief>
              The application's GUI
            </brief>
            <description>
              Example with parameters set to import MSI raw image to a cube.
            </description>
            <thumbnail width="200" height="180" caption="GUI Example" src="assets/thumbs/msi2isisGUI.jpg"/>
          </image>
        </guiInterface>
      </guiInterfaces>
      <inputImages>
        <image src="assets/images/fits2isis.cub.jpg" width="550" height="601">
          <brief>
            Original image
          </brief>
          <description>
            Example of raw NEAR MSI image without the enlarge, flip, and trim processes performed by msi2isis.
          </description>
          <thumbnail width="183" height="200" caption="Raw image" src="assets/thumbs/fits2isis.cub.jpg" />
          <parameterName>FROM</parameterName>
        </image>
      </inputImages>
      <outputImages>
        <image src="assets/images/imported.cub.jpg" width="550" height="603">
          <brief>
            Imported NEAR MSI cube
          </brief>
          <description>
            Example of imported NEAR MSI image with the enlarge, flip, and trim processes applied.
          </description>
          <thumbnail width="182" height="200" caption="Imported cube" src="assets/thumbs/imported.cub.jpg" />
          <parameterName>TO</parameterName>
        </image>
      </outputImages>
    </example>
  </examples>
</application>
