<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="msi2isis" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"  xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">

  <brief>
    Import NEAR MSI files into ISIS format
  </brief>
  <description>
    This program will import raw images, acquired from the Near Earth Asteroid
    Rendezvous - Shoemaker (NEAR Shoemaker) mission's Multispectral Imager
    (MSI) instrument, to ISIS data file format.

    The raw image must be in FITS (Flexible Image Transport) format and
    have a PDS label file that points to the location of the FITS image. You must input either the label file or the FITS file for the "TO" input
    parameter.  Projected images are not supported.  Please note if the FITS file is given, the label file must
    exist in the same directory or the program will throw an error.

    This program will verify that the input files are valid by checking the
    following label keyword values.  An error will be  thrown if any of these
    criteria are not met.
    <ul>
      <li>INSTRUMENT_ID = MSI</li>
      <li>LINE_SAMPLES = 537</li>
      <li>LINES = 244</li>
      <li>SAMPLE_DISPLAY_DIRECTION = RIGHT</li>
      <li>LINE_DISPLAY_DIRECTION = UP</li>
    </ul>

    The output cube- successfully imported into ISIS goes through the following processes:
    <ul>
      <li>Convert the raw FITS image data to an ISIS cube.</li>
      <li> Save the labels from the input PDS label file to the output ISIS cube. Note that FITS labels are not transferred. </li>
      <li>Enlarge the image from 537 samples x 244 lines to 537 x 412 using the user-specified interpolation algorithm. Defaults to cubic convolution.</li>
      <li>Flip the image vertically, i.e. across the horizontal axis.</li>
      <li>Trim 33 pixels from the top, bottom, left and right sides. These
            pixels along the borders will be set to nulls.</li>
    </ul>

  </description>

  <history>
    <change name="Jeannie Backer" date="2013-03-27">
      Original version of msi2isis. References #1248.
    </change>
     <change name="Kristin Berry" date="2014-05-19">
         Updated to add labels from the input PDS label file to the output ISIS cube. References #2088.
    </change>
  </history>

  <seeAlso>
    <applications>
      <item>fits2isis</item>
      <item>enlarge</item>
      <item>flip</item>
      <item>trim</item>
    </applications>
  </seeAlso>

  <category>
    <missionItem>Near Earth Asteroid Rendezvous</missionItem>
  </category>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input NEAR MSI file to be converted to an ISIS cube
        </brief>
        <description>
          Name of the input NEAR MSI image file to be imported into ISIS
          format. You may enter the label or the image file. If the image
          file is given, the program will search in the same directory for a
          label file with the same base name as the image file base name.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.lbl *.fit *.fits
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TO">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Output ISIS cube filename
        </brief>
        <description>
          Name of the ISIS output cube file that has been imported, enlarged,
          flipped, and trimmed.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Scaling Parameters">
      <parameter name="INTERP">
        <type>string</type>
        <default>
          <item>CUBICCONVOLUTION</item>
        </default>
        <brief>Type of interpolation for enlarge process</brief>
        <description>
          This is the type of interpolation to be performed on the input when
          the image is enlarged from 537 samples x 244 lines to
          537 samples x 412 lines.
        </description>
        <list>
          <option value="CUBICCONVOLUTION">
            <brief>Cubic Convolution interpolation</brief>
            <description>
              Each output pixel is set to the value calculated by
              a cubic convolution interpolation of the calculated input pixel.
            </description>
          </option>
          <option value="NEARESTNEIGHBOR">
            <brief>Nearest Neighbor</brief>
            <description>
              Each output pixel is set to the pixel nearest the
              calculated input pixel.
            </description>
          </option>
          <option value="BILINEAR">
            <brief>Bi-Linear interpolation</brief>
            <description>
              Each output pixel is set to the value calculated by
              a bi-linear interpolation of the calculated input pixel.
            </description>
          </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>
    </group>
  </groups>

  <examples>
    <example>
      <brief>
        Usage of this import application
      </brief>
      <description>
        This example shows how to import an MSI fits file to the ISIS cube format using the label file.
      </description>
      <terminalInterface>
        <commandLine>
          from=msi_raw_file.lbl to=imported.cub
        </commandLine>
        <description>
          The command line arguments to import a file to cube format.
        </description>
      </terminalInterface>
      <guiInterfaces>
        <guiInterface>
          <image width="550" height="494" src="assets/images/msi2isisGUI.jpg">
            <brief>
              The application's GUI
            </brief>
            <description>
              Example with parameters set to import MSI raw image to a cube.
            </description>
            <thumbnail width="200" height="180" caption="GUI Example" src="assets/thumbs/msi2isisGUI.jpg"/>
          </image>
        </guiInterface>
      </guiInterfaces>
      <inputImages>
        <image src="assets/images/fits2isis.cub.jpg" width="550" height="601">
          <brief>
            Original image
          </brief>
          <description>
            Example of raw NEAR MSI image without the enlarge, flip, and trim processes performed by msi2isis.
          </description>
          <thumbnail width="183" height="200" caption="Raw image" src="assets/thumbs/fits2isis.cub.jpg" />
          <parameterName>FROM</parameterName>
        </image>
      </inputImages>
      <outputImages>
        <image src="assets/images/imported.cub.jpg" width="550" height="603">
          <brief>
            Imported NEAR MSI cube
          </brief>
          <description>
            Example of imported NEAR MSI image with the enlarge, flip, and trim processes applied.
          </description>
          <thumbnail width="182" height="200" caption="Imported cube" src="assets/thumbs/imported.cub.jpg" />
          <parameterName>TO</parameterName>
        </image>
      </outputImages>
    </example>
  </examples>
</application>
