<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="hiccdstitch" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">
  <brief>
    Stitch together multiple HiRISE CCD images
  </brief>

  <description>
      <p>
    This program combines images from multiple HiRISE CCDs into a single
    output image file.  The output file can be considered to be a special
    type of mosaic in which the different CCD images are placed next to
    each other in positions that correspond to detector numbers.  The input
    files must each contain both channels of a single detector, which are
    the files produced by the "histitch" program.  CCD images with lower
    CCD numbers are placed into the output file to the left of CCD images
    with higher CCD numbers.  By default the CCD images are placed into the 
    output file from left to right, i.e., in order of increasing CCD number.  This
    order can be changed with the MosaicOrder keyword in the "shiftdef"
    file.
      </p>
      <p>
    Images are inserted at locations
    corresponding to the relative offsets of the detectors.  In most cases,
    pixel replication is used when processing an input image so that it
    matches the scale of the image with the lowest summing mode.  However,
    if any of the input images were observed with a summing mode of 3, then
    pixel replication is used for all images to match the scale that would
    have been obtained with a summing mode of 1.  No resampling of input
    pixel values is done.
      </p> 
      <p>
     In many cases, adjacent images do not line up vertically due to observing
     conditions and other factors.  The SHIFTDEF parameter allows the user to
     apply arbitrary offsets in lines to any or all the input images so they align
     properly.
      </p>
      <p>
     It has been determined that summing modes add an additional delay to
     imaging due to pre-cycling of the detector electronics.  Typically, images
     have an additional <b>180 * (summing mode  - 1)</b> lines delay
     in the actual imaging
     of the target.  These lines are unbinned, not subject to the summing mode
     applied during imaging.  This is not an issue if all images being stitched by
     this application are the same summing mode.  If images with different
     summing modes are acquired in the same observation, then this offset
     is automatically applied to the images with differing summing modes.  This
     will result in adding
     lines of offset to some images and increasing the number of lines in the
     resulting output image.
      </p>
      <p>
          The input files may contain multiple bands but all input files must contain
          the same number of bands.   This is useful for creating color products
          where the input files are compatable with the constraints of this application.
      </p>
  </description>

  <category>
    <missionItem>Mars Reconnaissance Orbiter</missionItem>
  </category>

  <history>
    <change name="Jim Torson" date="2005-06-24">
       Original version 
    </change>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2006-03-02">
        Eliminated the requirement that all CCDs be adjacent.  As a side
        effect,  24 pixels on the left edge of the adjacent CCDs are no
        longer clipped but are layed on top of the last 24 pixels on the
        right side of preceding CCDs.
    </change> 
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2006-03-31">
        Added the SHIFTDEF parameter that allows for offsets to be provided
        for any CCD.  Also added the PLACEMENT parameter that writes the
        line and sample coordinate of each CCD in the output TO file.
    </change>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2006-09-27">
        Added recently discovered time delay as a function of summing modes.
        This adds lines of offset to images with higher summing modes.  These
        lines are unbinned but are subject to the smallest occuring summing
        mode in that the offsets are reduced by the number of offsets divided by
        the minimum summing mode.
     </change>  
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2006-11-27">
        Modified to allow a single CCD image file as input to hiccdstitch.
        Previously, two or more CCDs image files were required.  With this
        change only one need be provided (to expedite pipeline processing).
     </change>
     <change name="Tracie Sucharski" date="2007-03-13">
         Modified to allow user to determine the order the ccd's are laid down
         through the use of the MosaicOrder keyword in the shiftdef file.
         Also added option to replicate pixels by nearestNeighbor, Bilinear
         or cubicConvolution.  Also deleted ChannelNumber and CpmmNumber
         keywords so that output image cannot be projected.
     </change>
     <change name="Kris Becker" date="2007-07-31">
         Modified to allow for stitching of multiband cubes.  This will allow
         users to create color products as long all files have the same
         number of bands. 
      </change>
      <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2008-05-13">
        Removed references to CubeInfo 
      </change>
   </history>

  <groups>
    <group name="Input Files">
      <parameter name="FROMLIST">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          List of cubes to stitch together
        </brief>
        <description>
          The name of a file containing a list of HiRISE image files to be
          stitched together.  Each file should be listed on a separate
          line.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="SHIFTDEF">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <helpers>
          <helper name="H1">
            <function>helperButtonLog</function>
            <brief>View file in log area</brief>
            <description>This helper button will display the shiftdef file in the log area</description>
            <icon>$ISIS3DATA/base/icons/view_text.png</icon>
          </helper>
        </helpers>
        <filter>
          *.def
        </filter>
        <defaultPath>$mro/calibration</defaultPath>
        <default><item>$mro/calibration/HiccdstitchOffsets.def</item></default>
        <brief>
          Pvl file containing mosaic order for ccd's  and the absolute shifts for CCD
          lines and samples.
        </brief>
        <description>
            <p>
                This file contains objects for each CCD and for each combo
                of binning/tdi that requires a 
                modification to its placement in the mapping of the HiRISE
                focal plane.  The name of each object is the CCD name for
                which the shift in line or sample is needed.  For example, the
                leftmost CCD, CCD 0 is named "RED0", the next "RED1" and
                so on.  The binning/tdi groups are named by combining the
                binning and tdi mode.  For example, summing=1 and tdi=64 the
                group would be "1/64".   Hiccdstitch searches for names of objects that match
                the stitched input cube files ccd then for the proper combo of summing and tdi.
                If the group for summing/tdi isn't found, values from the ccd object will be
                used.   These offsets will be applied to the
                default sample and line location of where the CCD is mapped to
                in the focal plane.
            </p>
            <p>
                Offsets for both line and sample can be supplied.  None, one or
                both can be provided for any CCD.  Negative values shift the 
                image left if a sample offset is given or up if a line offset is given.
                Positive values in sample and line shift the image right and down,
                respectively.
            </p>
            <p>
                These shifts are absolute shifts and only apply to
                the specified CCD and are not propagated to subsequent CCDs
                left to right in the focal plane layout.  (HiRISE CCD arrangement
                is always left to right as far as hiccdstitch is concerned, unless
                overiridden by the MosaicOrder keyword.)  For
                example, if stitching all 10 RED CCDs in an image you find that
                RED5 must be shifted left 20 pixels but all other CCDs line up file
                to the right, meaning RED6 through RED9, then you are required
                to privide groups for RED6, RED7, RED8 and RED9 with the same
                SampleOffset provided for RED5.  This is the only way proper
                sample alignment is retained.
            </p>
            <p>
                Below is an example of the format of the input file for the
                SHIFTDEF file:
            </p>
            <pre>
            Object = Hiccdstitch

            # Defaults for Red0 images
              Object = RED0
                SampleOffset     = -10
                LineOffset       = 5

                # Summing=1, Tdi=64 values.  Any of the three keywords (MosaicOrder, SampleOffset, LineOffset) 
                #  can exist in the summing/tdi groups that will override the defaults in the RED0 object.
                Group = 1/64
                  SampleOffset = 0
                  LineOffset = 0
                End_Group

                # Summing=1, Tdi=128
                Group = 1/128
                  SampleOffset = 20
                End_Group

                # If a summing/tdi group does not exist, the ccd defaults are used
              End_Object

              Object = RED3
                SampleOffset     = 13
                LineOffset       = -5
              End_Object

              Object = RED5
                LineOffset       = 22
              End_Object

              Object = RED9
                # MosaicOrder of -1, indicates the ccd is placed in mosaic first.
                 MosaicOrder = -1
               End_Object

               Object = IR11
                SampleOffset     = -4
                LineOffset       = 2
              End_Object

              Object = BG12
                SampleOffset     = 12
              End_Object
            End_Object
            End
            </pre>
            <p>
                The only keywords that hiccdstitch reads from this file
                are <b>SampleOffset</b> , <b>LineOffset</b> and 
                <b>MosaicOrder</b>.  All other keywords are ignored.
                All CCD objects must be contained within the
                <b>Hiccdstitch</b> object.
            </p>
            <p>
                Note that this file is an optional parameter.  If it is not
                provided, then all CCD files provided are mapped to
                focal plane positions as specified in the HiRISE
                Instrument Operations Handbook.  Note that the size
                of a HiRISE pixel is 0.012 millimeters and the measurements
                in the handbook are also in millimeters.
            </p>
        </description>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Output Files">
      <parameter name="TO">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Output stitched cube
        </brief>
        <description>
          The output cube into which the input cubes will be placed.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="PLACEMENT">
        <type>filename</type>
        <internalDefault>None</internalDefault>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Output file providing the placement of CCDs in the TO cube
        </brief>
        <description>
            If provided, the actual line and sample locations of each CCD as
            they map to the TO cube are recorded here.  This format is the
            the same as the format provided in the STITCHDEF file.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.def
        </filter>
      </parameter>
    </group>
    <group name="Interpolation">
      <parameter name="INTERP">
        <type>string</type>
        <default>
          <item>NEARESTNEIGHBOR</item>
        </default>
        <brief>Type of interpolation</brief>
        <description>
          This is the type of interpolation to be performed on the input when 
          ccds of different summing modes are combined.
        </description>
        <list>
          <option value="NEARESTNEIGHBOR">
            <brief>Nearest Neighbor</brief>
            <description>
              Each output pixel will be set to the pixel nearest the
              calculated input pixel.
            </description>
          </option>
          <option value="BILINEAR">
            <brief>Bi-Linear interpolation</brief>
            <description>
              Each output pixel will be set to the value calculated by
              a bi-linear interpolation of the calculated input pixel.
            </description>
          </option>
          <option value="CUBICCONVOLUTION">
            <brief>Cubic Convolutioin interpolation</brief>
            <description>
              Each output pixel will be set to the value calculated by
              a cubic convolution interpolation of the calculated input pixel.
            </description>
          </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>
    </group>
  </groups>
</application>
