<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="cnetmerge" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">

  <brief>
    Merges 2 ControlNets into one.
  </brief>

  <description>
    <p>
    Merges 2 Control Nets into a single Control Net.  Each Control Net must
    share the same  target, and be of the same type (i .e. Singleton,
    ImageToImage, ImageToGround ).
    </p>
  </description>

  <history>
    <change name="Christpher Austin" date="2008-04-04">
      Original version
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2008-06-24">
      Clarified error messages and added documentation.  (Removed netmerge from
      the system, because it did the same thing, just not quite as clean)
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2008-08-05">
      Fix xml app name error
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2008-11-13">
      Rebuilt for more Control Point Id control, including a REPLACE option.
      Only FORCE prefixes the original Control Network Id to the new Control
      Point Ids, then logs the number of duplicate Control Points.  NORMAL and
      REPLACE leave the Control Point Ids alone.
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2009-01-09">
      Added the FROMLIST input option.
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2009-01-13">
      Changed MERGETYPE param name and options to be more clear. Changed MODE
      to INPUTTYPE. Added the REPORT param which reveals any Control Points
      that have been renamed or replaced durring the merge.
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2009-01-15">
      Added Filename expansion to the listed nets and a few other minor
      readability changes.
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2009-11-19">
      Multiple changes based on user request, including removal of RENAME,
      replacing REPLACE with MERGE while merging at the Control Measure level.
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2010-03-15">
      Changed an outdated error message.
    </change>
  </history> 
  
  <category>
    <categoryItem>Control Networks</categoryItem>
  </category>

  <groups>
    
    <group name="Input">

      <parameter name = "INPUTTYPE">
        <type>string</type>
        <default><item>LIST</item></default>
        <brief>File I/O options</brief>
        <description>
          There is a choice to simply specify input cubes directly, use a list of input cubes in a text file, or to create output data only.
        </description>
        <list>
          <option value = "LIST">
            <brief>Select input Control Net list</brief>
            <description>
              Select a list of Control Nets, all to be merged.
            </description>
            <exclusions>
              <item>FROM1</item>
              <item>FROM2</item>
            </exclusions>
          </option>
          <option value = "CNETS">
            <brief>Select input Control Nets directly</brief>
            <description>
              Select the 2 Control Nets to be merged directly.
            </description>
            <exclusions>
              <item>FROMLIST</item>
            </exclusions>
          </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name = "FROMLIST">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input list file 
        </brief>
        <description>
          This file contains a list of all the Control Nets to be merged
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.txt *.lis *.list *.lst
        </filter>
      </parameter>
      
      <parameter name="FROM1">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input ControlNet
        </brief>
        <description>
          The first ControlNet to be merged.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.ctl *.pvl *.net
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="FROM2">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input ControlNet
        </brief>
        <description>
          The second ControlNet to be merged.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.ctl *.pvl *.net
        </filter>
      </parameter>

    </group>

    <group name="Output">

      <parameter name="TO">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Merged ControlNet
        </brief>
        <description>
          The output ControlNet, which is the merged result of the two input 
          ControlNets.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.ctl *.pvl *.net
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="REPORT">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <internalDefault>No Report Output</internalDefault>
        <brief>
          Reports Control Points that were renamed or replaced
        </brief>
        <description>
          This file will contain a report that reveals all Control Points that
          were renamed or replaced. If no Control Points were renamed or
          replaced, than this file will be empty.
        </description>
      </parameter>

    </group>

    <group name="Output Control">

      <parameter name="ID">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>The NetworkId for the merged ControlNet</brief>
        <description>
          The NetworkId keyword for the new merged ControlNet will be set to the 
          given value.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="DESCRIPTION">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>The Description for the merged ControlNet</brief>
        <description>
          The Descrition keyword for the new merged ControlNet will be set to the 
          given value.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="DUPLICATEPOINTS">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>Defines how duplicate Control Points are handled</brief>
        <default><item>ERROR</item></default>
        <description>
          This parameter is used to specify how duplicate Control Points of the
          given Control Networks are handled when merging.
        </description>
        <list>
           <option value="ERROR">
              <brief>Does not merge duplicate Control Points</brief>
              <description>
                This option will check for duplicate Control Points in the
                Control Nets and throw an error when a duplication occurs.
                If no duplication occurs, all Control Points will be transfered
                to the new Control Net as is.
              </description>
              <exclusions>
                <item>REPORT</item>
              </exclusions>
            </option>
            <option value="MERGE">
              <brief>Merges duplicate Control Points</brief>
              <description>
                This option will merge all duplicate Control Points in the
                following Control Net over the first Control Net.  When
                INPUTTYPE=CNETS, the FROM2 Control Net will override the
                duplicate Control Points in FROM1. When INPUTTYPE=LIST, a
                listed Control Net will override any and all duplicate Control
                Points from any and all previously listed Control Nets.
              </description>
            </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>
      
      <parameter name="OVERWRITEPOINTS">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>False</item></default>
        <brief>Merge conficting Control Points</brief>
        <description>
          Whenever a latitude or a longitude value has been changed on a held
          or ground Control Point, then the changed values will be merged when
          this parameter is TRUE. If this parameter is FALSE and a change is
          found, the change will be noted in the REPORT file, but will not be
          merged in the final output.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="OVERWRITEMEASURES">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>False</item></default>
        <brief>Merge conficting Control Measures</brief>
        <description>
          Whenever a the reference measure has been changed in a held or
          ground Control Measure, then the change will be merged when this
          parameter is TRUE. If this parameter is FALSE and a reference measure
          change is found, the change will be noted in the REPORT file, but
          will not be merged in the final output.
        </description>
      </parameter>

    </group>

  </groups>

</application>
