<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="dsk2isis" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">

  <brief>
    Converts NAIF DSK plate model to ISIS format
  </brief>

  <description>
      This application will convert a NAIF DSK plate model to an ISIS cube.  
      Users must  provide a valid map file to use for allocation of the ISIS 
      cube.  The scale and type of projection determine the size of the output 
      cube.
  </description>

  <history>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2014-02-19">
        Original Version
    </change>
    <change name="Jeannie Backer" date="2015-03-08">
        Wrote tests. Added application to ISIS trunk. References #2035
    </change>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2015-03-11">
        Process data tiles instead of a pixel at a time; Test for
        valid output map coordinate at every map pixel. References #2035
    </change>
</history>

  <category>
    <categoryItem>Map Projection</categoryItem>
  </category>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>Name of NAIF DSK DEM file</brief>
        <description>
          This parameter provides the name of the NAIF DSK file to convert to 
          ISIS format.  It is assumed to be in body fixed coordinates from which 
          intersections for each output map grid point will be computed using 
          NAIF's DSK toolkit.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.bds
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="MAP">
          <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>Name of file containing map description</brief>
        <description>
            This paramter provides the name of a file containing a valid map 
            projection defintion. One can use the ISIS maptemplate application 
            to create a map template.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.map
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TO">
        <type>cube</type>
       <pixelType>real</pixelType>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Output cube
        </brief>
        <description>
          Name of the output ISIS file created by this application containing 
          the rendering of the DSK DEM into and ISIS compatible DEM for use in 
          the ISIS system.
        </description>
      </parameter>

        <parameter name="METHOD">
            <type>string</type>
            <brief>
                DEM intersection method used
            </brief>
            <description>
              <p>
                This parameter provides two different methods to compute the 
                output radius value for a given latitude, longitude map grid 
                point.
              </p>
            </description>
            <default><item>RAY</item></default>
            <list>
                <option value="RAY">
                    <brief>
                        Ray intersection from image pixel location to DEM 
                    </brief>
                    <description>
                        Calculates an intercept location on the (irregularly                     
                        shaped) body from the observer point (i.e., image pixel 
                        location) and look (or ray) direction 
                    </description>
                </option>
                <option value="GRID">
                    <brief>
                        Calculate using surface point latitude, longitude grid 
                        point  
                    </brief>
                    <description>
                         The radius value of the DEM is determined at the 
                         intercept point of the triaxial ellipsoid from the 
                         center of the body. This method extends the surface (x, 
                         y, z) body fixed coordinate of the ellisoid by 
                         extending the vector by a factor of 1.5.  This creates 
                         the obsever point.  The direction vector is then the 
                         negation of the observer point.  From this, a DEM 
                         surface intercept point is determined.
                    </description>
                </option>
            </list>
        </parameter>
    </group>
  </groups>
</application>
