<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="hrsc2isis" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">

  <brief>Import HRSC image</brief>

  <description> 
    <p>
      This program imports Mars Express HRSC files. This includes both the HRSC 
      Stereo and the SRC instruments.
      The program populates all label keywords necessary to create the corresponding camera
      models.
    </p>
    <p>
      For the stereo instrument there is always prefix data. The
      prefix data is collected and used to look for "gaps" aka missing lines. The 
      line prefix data for HRSC
      files contain time and exposure duration for each line. We look for occurrences  
      where the time + exposure duration is not equal to the next line's time to find missing
      lines. This program uses two passes, the first reads the PDS file into a cube, the
      second inserts lines where gaps were identified.
    </p>
    <p>
      For the SRC instrument, this program reads the PDS file and converts it to an ISIS cube. The
      PDS file for the SRC instrument is much simpler than the stereo instrument files and requires
      no special processing. 
    </p>
  </description>

  <history>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2008-01-16">
      Original version
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2008-03-18">
      Checks if input file is rdr based on whether or not the input file has 
      prefix data.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2008-05-13">
      Removed references to CubeInfo 
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2008-07-28">
      Updated to support the HRSC camera model. The Kernels group now has the IK code
      properly added, the summing keyword is propagated, the times table is now compressed
      into only having entries on time changes, and the times no longer have a 'Z' at the end
      of them once imported.
    </change>
    <change name="Adam Paquette" date="2016-10-05">
      Updated the error messages thrown when hrsc2isis trys to ingest an image that is not an HRSC
      image, and when hrsc2isis trys to ingest a map projected image. Fixes #4259.
    </change>
    <change name="Stuart Sides" date="2020-03-31">
      Added ability to read HRSC SRC images
    </change>
  </history>

  <oldName>
    <item>mex2isis.pl</item>
    <item>readpfx</item>
  </oldName>

  <category>
    <missionItem>Mars Express</missionItem>
  </category>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input HRSC Stereo or SRC Image
        </brief>
        <description>
          Use this parameter to select the PDS filename.  This file
          must contain the PDS labels, however the image data can
          be detached and will be automatically obtained from the
          PDS image pointer keyword.  If the pointer is incorrect then
          use the IMAGE parameter to specify the file containing the
          binary image data.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.lbl *.LBL *.img *.IMG
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TO">
         <type>cube</type>
         <fileMode>output</fileMode>
         <brief>
           Output Isis cube
         </brief>
         <description>
           Use this parameter to select the output filename
         </description>
         <filter>
           *.cub
         </filter>
       </parameter>
    </group>
  </groups>

  <examples>
    <example>
      <brief>Import an HRSC stereo instrument image with gaps</brief>
      <description>
        This example covers importing an HRSC stereo instrument image and shows 
        what happens when gaps are found.
      </description>
      <terminalInterface>
        <commandLine> from=h0279_0000_re2.img to=h0279_0000_re2.cub</commandLine>
        <description>Run this program on "h0279_0000_re2.img"</description>
      </terminalInterface>

      <inputImages>
        <image src="assets/images/h0279_0000_re2.jpg" width="89" height="550">
          <brief>This is the raw input image, not imported with this program</brief>
          <description>
            This image was imported with pds2isis and then exported with isis2std, in order to get a 
            good idea of what the raw input image looks like.
          </description>
          <thumbnail caption=" Input HRSC Image " src="assets/thumbs/h0279_0000_re2.jpg" width="32" height="200" />
        </image>

        <image src="assets/images/h0279_0000_re2.in_zoomed.jpg" width="550" height="550">
          <brief> Input discontinuity from this example </brief>
          <description>
            This is a zoomed in region of what will become a gap from this example. Notice the 
            features aren't aligned in the middle of the image, as if there are missing lines.
          </description>
          <thumbnail caption=" Output HRSC Gap " src="assets/thumbs/h0279_0000_re2.in_zoomed.jpg" width="200" height="200" />
        </image>
      </inputImages>

      <outputImages>
        <image src="assets/images/h0279_0000_re2.out.jpg" width="76" height="550">
          <brief> Output image from this example </brief>
          <description>
            This is the output from this example. The large "black" areas are NULL lines where data 
            was missing, according to the prefix data on the raw input image.
          </description>
          <thumbnail caption=" Output HRSC Image " src="assets/thumbs/h0279_0000_re2.out.jpg" width="28" height="200" />
        </image>

        <image src="assets/images/h0279_0000_re2.out_zoomed.jpg" width="550" height="550">
          <brief> A gap from this example </brief>
          <description>
            This is a zoomed in region of a gap from this example. Notice the features on the top 
            and bottom would not normally line up  if the gap did not exist.
          </description>
          <thumbnail caption=" Output HRSC Gap " src="assets/thumbs/h0279_0000_re2.out_zoomed.jpg" width="200" height="200" />
        </image>
      </outputImages>
    </example>
  </examples>
</application>
