<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="hrsc2isis" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">

  <brief>Import HRSC image</brief>

  <description> 
    This program imports Mars Express HRSC files. This works by first
    determining whether or not the input file has prefix data. If there is
    prefix data, the prefix data is collected and used to look for "gaps" - HRSC
    files can give us a time and exposure duration  for each line, we look for 
    where the time + exposure duration =/= next line's time.   We populate a 
    table (LineScanTimes) with the prefix data and lineInFile with whether or 
    not a gap should be inserted. For all files, we now process the  data and if 
    there were gaps, they will be put in their proper places. This is a two-pass
    system for files with prefix data, one-pass for files without.  The Isis2
    equivalent to this program is mex2isis.pl. It is worth noting that
    regardless of the  input file's byte order, the prefix data byte order is 
    always LSB.
  </description>

  <history>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2008-01-16">
      Original version
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2008-03-18">
      Checks if input file is rdr based on whether or not the input file has 
      prefix data.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2008-05-13">
      Removed references to CubeInfo 
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2008-07-28">
      Updated to support the HRSC camera model. The Kernels group now has the IK code
        properly added, the summing keyword is propagated, the times table is now compressed
        into only having entries on time changes, and the times no longer have a 'Z' at the end
        of them once imported.
    </change>
  </history>

  <oldName>
    <item>mex2isis.pl</item>
    <item>readpfx</item>
  </oldName>

  <category>
    <missionItem>Mars Express</missionItem>
  </category>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input HRSC Image
        </brief>
        <description>
          Use this parameter to select the PDS filename.  This file
          must contain the PDS labels, however the image data can
          be detached and will be automatically obtained from the
          PDS image pointer keyword.  If the pointer is incorrect then
          use the IMAGE parameter to specify the file containing the
          binary image data.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.lbl *.img
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TO">
         <type>cube</type>
         <fileMode>output</fileMode>
         <brief>
           Output Isis cube
         </brief>
         <description>
           Use this parameter to select the output filename
         </description>
         <filter>
           *.cub
         </filter>
       </parameter>
    </group>
  </groups>

  <examples>
    <example>
      <brief>Import an HRSC image with gaps</brief>
      <description>
        This example covers importing an HRSC image and shows what happens when 
        gaps are found.
      </description>
      <terminalInterface>
        <commandLine> from=h0279_0000_re2.img to=h0279_0000_re2.cub</commandLine>
        <description>Run this program on "h0279_0000_re2.img"</description>
      </terminalInterface>

      <inputImages>
        <image src="assets/images/h0279_0000_re2.jpg" width="89" height="550">
          <brief>This is the raw input image, not imported with this program</brief>
          <description>
            This image was imported with pds2isis and then exported with isis2std, in order to get a 
            good idea of what the raw input image looks like.
          </description>
          <thumbnail caption=" Input HRSC Image " src="assets/thumbs/h0279_0000_re2.jpg" width="32" height="200" />
        </image>

        <image src="assets/images/h0279_0000_re2.in_zoomed.jpg" width="550" height="550">
          <brief> Input discontinuity from this example </brief>
          <description>
            This is a zoomed in region of what will become a gap from this example. Notice the 
            features aren't aligned in the middle of the image, as if there are missing lines.
          </description>
          <thumbnail caption=" Output HRSC Gap " src="assets/thumbs/h0279_0000_re2.in_zoomed.jpg" width="200" height="200" />
        </image>
      </inputImages>

      <outputImages>
        <image src="assets/images/h0279_0000_re2.out.jpg" width="76" height="550">
          <brief> Output image from this example </brief>
          <description>
            This is the output from this example. The large "black" areas are NULL lines where data 
            was missing, according to the prefix data on the raw input image.
          </description>
          <thumbnail caption=" Output HRSC Image " src="assets/thumbs/h0279_0000_re2.out.jpg" width="28" height="200" />
        </image>

        <image src="assets/images/h0279_0000_re2.out_zoomed.jpg" width="550" height="550">
          <brief> A gap from this example </brief>
          <description>
            This is a zoomed in region of a gap from this example. Notice the features on the top 
            and bottom would not normally line up  if the gap did not exist.
          </description>
          <thumbnail caption=" Output HRSC Gap " src="assets/thumbs/h0279_0000_re2.out_zoomed.jpg" width="200" height="200" />
        </image>
      </outputImages>
    </example>
  </examples>
</application>
