<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<application name="hyb2onc2isis" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">
<!-- $Id: hyb2onc2isis.xml 6226 2017-07-05 20:46:13Z kewilliams@usgs.gov $ -->

  <brief>Import PDS/FITS formatted Hayabusa2 image into ISIS cube</brief>

  <description>
    <p>
       This application will import and convert a Hayabusa2 Optical Navigation Camera (ONC) FITS image to an ISIS cube.

    </p>
    <br/>
    <h3>Requirements</h3>
    <ul>
      <li>
        Raw image data file (.fit) (specified in <em>FROM</em> label)
      </li>
      <li>
        Output ISIS file name (.cub) (specified in <em>TO</em> label)
      </li>
      <li>
        Target name if target must be overridden (specified in <em>TARGET</em>).
      </li>
    </ul>
    <p>
       The input FITS formatted header file for the Hayabusa2
       image must be used in the FROM parameter.
    </p>
    <h3>When TARGET Parameter Should Be Specified</h3>
    <ul>
      <li>
        When Hayabusa2 EDR labels contain an incorrect value for the
      TARGET_NAME keyword
      </li>
      <li>
         To define TARGET = "SKY" to later project the data with
        <em>skymap</em>.
      </li>
    </ul>
    <br/>
    <h2>Mission Overview</h2>
    <p>
       The Hayabusa2 spacecraft was launched on 3 Dec 2014.  The Optical Navigation Camera (ONC)
       package is positioned on the nadir-facing panel.
    </p>
    <p>
       The mission purpose is to rendezvous with (and provide a sample return from)
       the Apollo asteroid 162173 Ryugu, a Cg-type asteroid.
    </p>
    <h2>Instrument Overview</h2>
    <p>
       The ONC package consists of three cameras: the telescopic (ONC-T) camera and two wide-angle
       cameras (ONC-W1,ONC-W2).
    </p>
    <p>
       The wide-angle cameras each have a square 65.24 x 65.24 deg. field of view (FOV). The wide-angle
       camera ONC-W1 and ONC-W2 have focal lengths of
       10.35 mm and 10.44 mm, respectively. The telescope camera
       has a 6.35 x 6.35 deg. FOV. The telescopic camera ONC-T has a focal length of 121.1 mm.
    </p>
    <p>
       The ONC package has a set of eight bandpass filters. Below is a table of
       the filters and their specifications:
    </p>
    <br/>
    <h2>ONC Filters</h2>
    <p>
       The following table provides the specifications for each of the six
       ONC-T bandpass filters.
    </p>
      <TABLE BORDER="1">
            <CAPTION>
                ONC Filter Specifications
              </CAPTION>
          <TR>
            <TH>Filter Number</TH>
            <TH>Band center (nm)</TH>
            <TH>FWHP Bandwidth (nm)</TH>
          </TR>
          <TR>
              <TD>ul</TD>
              <TD>390</TD>
              <TD>40</TD>
          </TR>
          <TR>
              <TD>Wide</TD>
              <TD>775</TD>
              <TD>850</TD>
          </TR>
          <TR>
              <TD>v</TD>
              <TD>550</TD>
              <TD>30</TD>
          </TR>
          <TR>
              <TD>w</TD>
              <TD>700</TD>
              <TD>30</TD>
          </TR>
          <TR>
              <TD>x</TD>
              <TD>860</TD>
              <TD>40</TD>
          </TR>
          <TR>
              <TD>Na</TD>
              <TD>589.5</TD>
              <TD>10</TD>
          </TR>
          <TR>
              <TD>p</TD>
              <TD>950</TD>
              <TD>60</TD>
          </TR>
          <TR>
              <TD>b</TD>
              <TD>480</TD>
              <TD>30</TD>
          </TR>
      </TABLE>

    <br/>
    <h2>Data Archive</h2>
    <p>
       ???
    </p>

    <br/>
    <h2>References</h2>
    <br/>
    <cite>
      Suzuki, H. et al. (2017) Initial Inflight Calibration for Hayabusa2 Optical Navigation Camera (ONC) for Scientific Observations of Asteroid Ryugu (in review for Icarus).
    </cite>
    <br/>
    <br/>
    <cite>
        Kameda, S. et al. (2015) Detectability of hydrous minerals using ONC-T camera onboard the Hayabusa2 spacecraft, Advances in Space Research, Volume 56, Issue 7, Pages 1519-1524, ISSN 0273-1177, http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.asr.2015.06.037.
        (http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0273117715004743)
    </cite>
    <br/>
    <br/>

  </description>

  <history>
    <change name="Kaj Williams" date="2017-07-05">
      Original version
    </change>
    <change name="Kaj Williams and Ian Humphrey" date="2017-07-26">
      Added references and more text.
    </change>
  </history>

  <category>
    <missionItem>Hayabusa2</missionItem>
  </category>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input PDS formatted detached header file for ONC image.
        </brief>
        <description>
           This file is the PDS label (ending in .lbl) to the image data.  The
           image data are stored in  FITS format with the detached .lbl file
           describing generic access to the data.  The program,
           <em>hyb2onc2isis</em>, will also read the FITS file and extract
           the header contained therein.  Some FITS label values are transferred
           to the output ISIS files as well for completeness.
        </description>
        <filter>*.lbl *.LBL</filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TO">
         <type>cube</type>
         <pixelType>real</pixelType>
         <fileMode>output</fileMode>
         <brief>Output ISIS cube filename</brief>
         <description>
           Use this parameter to select the output filename of the ISIS cube
           generated by this application.
         </description>
         <filter>*.cub</filter>
       </parameter>

    </group>
    <group name="Parameters">
        <parameter name="TARGET">
            <type>string</type>
            <brief>Provide target name if absent or incorrect in input (FROM)
              label
            </brief>
            <description>
              <p>
                 This parameter may be necessary as some ONC EDR labels may
                 not contain correct values for the TARGET_NAME keyword. This
                 parameter can be used to provide the correct name of the target.
                 It may also be used to specify SKY as the target to support
                 projecting data to the celestial sphere.
              </p>
            </description>
            <internalDefault>Label Value</internalDefault>
        </parameter>
    </group>
  </groups>
</application>
