<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<application name="apolloremrx" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">
  <brief>
    Removes Reseaus from an Apollo image
  </brief>

  <description>
    This program will remove Reseaus from Apollo images.  
    The Reseaus are removed using either PATCH interpolation of the 
    surrounding pixels or by simply putting NULLs in the portion of the 
    image around the Reseau location of the input image.  The ACTION 
    parameter is used to tell the program which of these two actions to 
    take. RESVALID is used to determine whether the
    program will check the reseau valid flag for nominal reseaux before
    removing the reseau.  If RESVALID is NO, the program will not check
    the reseau valid flag for nominal reseaux and all the reseaux will be
    removed except invalid nominal positions.  If RESVALID is YES, the 
    program will check the reseau valid flag that is output from the 
    findrx program.  If the flag is 0, the program will not remove that
    reseau.  If the flag is 1, the reseau will be removed.  If the flag is
    -1, indicating an invalid nominal position, the reseau will not be
    removed in any case.   The "apollofindrx" program, which writes the Reseau
    locations, Reseau type, and a valid flag to the cube file label, must be
    run before "apolloremrx".
  </description>

  <category>
    <missionItem>Apollo</missionItem>
  </category>

  <seeAlso>
    <applications>
      <item>apollofindrx</item>
      <item>findrx</item>
      <item>remrx</item>
    </applications>
  </seeAlso>

  <history>
    <change name="Jacob Danton" date="2007-01-18">
      Original version
    </change>
  </history>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input file
        </brief>
        <description>
          The cube the reseaus will be removed from.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TO">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Output cube
        </brief>
        <description>
          The resultant cube containing the data with reseaus removed. (Leave blank to overwrite original)
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Options">
        <parameter name="WIDTH">
            <type>integer</type>
            <brief>
                Reseau width
            </brief>
            <description>
                The width of the Apollo reseau.
            </description>
            <default><item>5</item></default>
        </parameter>
        <parameter name="ACTION">
            <type>string</type>
            <brief>
                The way the reseaus will be removed
            </brief>
            <description>
                There are 2 options for removing the Reseaus.  The program 
                can replace pixels inside the SDIM x LDIM box with Null or 
                PATCH interpolation. Defaults to PATCH.
            </description>
            <default><item>PATCH</item></default>
            <list>
                <option value="PATCH">
                    <brief>
                       Replace values with PATCH interpolation
                    </brief>
                    <description>
                        This option uses PATCH interpolation to create new DN
                        values for the pixels inside the SDIM x LDIM box.
                    </description>
                </option>
                <option value="NULL">
                    <brief>
                       Replace values with NULLs
                    </brief>
                    <description>
                       This option will replace each value inside the SDIM x LDIM
                       box with the Isis::NULL value.  This allows the user to run 
                       another filter program to replace the NULL values.
                    </description>
                </option>
            </list>
        </parameter>

        <parameter name="RESVALID">
            <type>boolean</type>
            <brief>
                Check Reseau Valid Flag?
            </brief>
            <description>
                If this parameter is TRUE, the reseau valid flag will be
                checked before the reseau is removed.  If the reseau 
                valid flag is a 0 or -1, the reseau will not be removed.
                If the reseau valid flag is a 1, the reseau will be
                removed.  Reseaus with a valid flag=-1 are never removed.
                This flag indicates an invalid nominal position.
                If RESVALID is FALSE, the reseau valid flag will not be 
                checked for nominals and all the reseaus will be removed,
                except the invalid nominals. Defaults to FALSE.
            </description>
            <default><item>FALSE</item></default>
        </parameter>
    </group>
  </groups>
</application>

