<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="cnetextract" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">

  <brief>
    Extracts portions of an existing Control Network
  </brief>

  <description>
    <p>
      Extracts Control Points into a new Control Network from a specified
      Control Network in accordance to specified filters.
    </p>

    <p>
      Currently, the filters are divided into four categories: Exclusive
      Filters, Inclusive Filters, Cube Filters, and Lat/Lon Filters.
    </p>

    <p>
      <strong>Exclusive Filters</strong> prevent extraction. They are taken
      into consideration last and have the highest priority. This means that
      if any other filter creates a selected Exclusive Filter condition during
      processing, that Exclusive Filter will prevent the extraction. For
      example, if the Cube Filters CUBES, CUBELIST, and CUBEMEASURES are used
      along with the Exclusive Filter NOSINGLEMEASURES, then an input Control
      Point which contains only one cube in the CUBELIST will not be
      extracted, regardless of the number of Control Measures it had on input.
      This is because NOSINGLEMEASURES will see it as a Control Point with
      exactly one Control Measure and prevent its extraction. If only
      Exclusive Filters are used, all Control Points/Measures that do not have
      an exclusive property will be extracted.
    </p>

    <p>
      <strong>Inclusive Filters</strong> allow extraction. They only extract
      Control Points and/or Measures that are included in the Inclusive
      Filter. In addition, each Inclusive Filter is associated with an
      explicit property of the Control Point/Measure. If more than one
      Inclusive Filter is selected, only Control Points/Measures that contain
      all inclusive properties will be extracted.
    </p>

    <p>
      <strong>Cube Filters</strong> also allow extraction, however, they
      pertain to the cubes contained within the Control Points/Measures.
      Option RETAIN_REFERENCE will extract the Reference even if not in the
      Cube List.
    </p>

    <p>
      <strong>Lat/Lon Filters</strong> allow extraction as well, however, they
      only extract Control Points/Measures that lie in the lat/lon bounding
      box.
    </p>
    <p>
      A summary of the Control Points not extracted, listed by the filter which
      prevented them from being extracted, can be included in optional report
      files. See the PREFIX and filter keywords for more details. The following
      table lists the output file names, the corresponding filter for the
      output file, and a description of the contents of the output file.
      These output files will only be generated if PREFIX has been defined.
      <table border="1">
        <tr>
          <th><strong>OutputReport</strong></th>
          <th><strong>Filter</strong></th>
          <th>
            <strong>
              Reason for not extracting the points/measures in this report
            </strong>
          </th>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td align="center"><code>[PREFIX]IgnoredPoints.txt</code></td>
          <td align="center"><code>NOIGNORE</code></td>
          <td align="left"><code>These points are set to ignored.</code></td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td align="center"><code>[PREFIX]IgnoredMeasures.txt</code></td>
          <td align="center"><code>NOIGNORE</code></td>
          <td align="left">
            <code>
              These measures are set to ignored. Ignored reference measures are
              always extracted, however they are still listed in this report
              with the note: Ignored measure but extracted since it is Reference.
            </code>
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td align="center"><code>[PREFIX]SingleMeasurePoints.txt</code></td>
          <td align="center"><code>NOSINGLEMEASURES</code></td>
          <td align="left"><code>These points have only one measure.</code></td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td align="center"><code>[PREFIX]MeasurelessPoints.txt</code></td>
          <td align="center"><code>NOMEASURELESS and REFERENCE</code></td>
          <td align="left"><code>These points have no measures.</code></td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td align="center"><code>[PREFIX]NonReferenceMeasures.txt</code></td>
          <td align="center"><code>REFERENCE</code></td>
          <td align="left"><code>These measures are not reference measures.</code></td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td align="center"><code>[PREFIX]NonFixedPoints.txt</code></td>
          <td align="center"><code>FIXED</code></td>
          <td align="left"><code>These points are not fixed.</code></td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td align="center"><code>[PREFIX]NonConstrainedPoints.txt</code></td>
          <td align="center"><code>CONSTRAINED</code></td>
          <td align="left"><code>These points are not constrained.</code></td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td align="center"><code>[PREFIX]NonEditLockedPoints.txt</code></td>
          <td align="center"><code>EDITLOCKED</code></td>
          <td align="left"><code>These points are not editlocked.</code></td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td align="center"><code>[PREFIX]TolerancePoints.txt</code></td>
          <td align="center"><code>TOLERANCE</code></td>
          <td align="left">
            <code>
              These points have line and/or sample less than the given
              PIXELTOLERANCE.
            </code>
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td align="center"><code>[PREFIX]NonListedPoints.txt</code></td>
          <td align="center"><code>POINTSLIST</code></td>
          <td align="left">
            <code>
              These points are not in the given POINTLIST.
            </code>
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td align="center"><code>[PREFIX]NonCubePoints.txt</code></td>
          <td align="center"><code>CUBES</code></td>
          <td align="left">
            <code>
              These points have no measures corresponding to the given CUBELIST.
            </code>
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td align="center"><code>[PREFIX]NonCubeMeasures.txt</code></td>
          <td align="center"><code>CUBES, CUBEMEASURES, and RETAIN_REFERENCE</code></td>
          <td align="left">
            <code>
              These are measures for extracted points that do not correspond to
              cubes in the given CUBELIST. If RETAIN_REFERENCE is true,
              all reference measures for extracted points will be extracted,
              however any reference measure that does not correspond to cubes
              in the cubelist will still be listed in this report with the note:
              Reference not in the cubelist but extracted since RETAIN_REFERENCE=true.
            </code>
          </td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td align="center"><code>[PREFIX]LatLonOutOfRange.txt</code></td>
          <td align="center"><code>LATLON</code></td>
          <td align="left"><code>These points have a latitude and/or longitude that is not in the given MINLAT/MAXLAT or MINLON/MAXLON range.</code></td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td align="center"><code>[PREFIX]NoLatLonPoints.txt</code></td>
          <td align="center"><code>LATLON</code></td>
          <td align="left"><code>These points do not have a determineable latitude and/or longitude value.</code></td>
        </tr>
      </table>
    </p>
  </description>

  <history>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2009-07-22">
      Original version
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2009-07-31">
      Refactored for readability, added parameter defaults, and added detail to
      the application log.
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2009-08-11">
      Added an additional output progress bar.
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2009-08-21">
      Added the points kept to the print file.
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2009-08-28">
      Fixed TOLIST blank lines, added the POINTLIST option, and changed the
      CUBEPOINTS parameter to take a filename instead of a boolean.
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2009-09-29">
      Added the TOLERANCE parameter.
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2009-10-02">
      Changed the TOLERANCE keyword to extract points with an error greater
      than or equal to the TOLERANCE, instead of less than or eqaul to.
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2009-10-15">
      Fixed the TOLERANCE code.
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2009-11-02">
      Fixed the interface to be more clear.
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2009-11-09">
      Added the GROUND parameter.
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2010-01-20">
      Added the USENETWORK parameter to avoid the need for spiceinit prior
      to knowing which cubes are necessary for the extracted control network.
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2010-02-01">
      FROMLIST is now an option parameter, however, to be able to generate a
      TOLIST, the FROMLIST must be provided. Also did some code cleanup.
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2010-03-01">
      Changed NOSINGLEMEASURES to NOMEASURELESS and fixed a simple progress
      bug.
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2010-03-03">
      Fixed min/max lat/lon bounding issues.
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2010-03-08">
      Brought back NOSINGLEMEASURES while leaving NOMEASURELESS as is.
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2010-06-18">
      Added PREFIX and moved all detailed output from the print.prt to the
      PREFIX files for each filter parameter.
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2010-06-30">
      Rewrote documentation and reorganized keywords into groups.
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2010-11-08">
      Fixed for binary cnet conversion.
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2011-01-18">
      Altered to compile with the new Control redesign.
    </change>
    <change name="Jai Rideout" date="2011-04-12">
      Changed OUTNET to ONET for consistency.
    </change>
    <change name="Sharmila Prasad" date="2011-05-27">
      Added an option RETAIN_REFERENCE to extract the Reference measure even if
      it is not in the CUBELIST
    </change>
    <change name="Debbie A. Cook and Tracie Sucharski" date="2011-06-07">
      Change point types "Ground" to "Fixed" and "Tie" to "Free".
    </change>
    <change name="Stuart Sides" date="2011-10-07">
      Added documentation with Annie Howington-Kraus and Ella Lee.
    </change>
    <change name="Jeannie Backer" date="2012-06-22">
      Added and modified documentation for filters and PREFIX report files to
      better reflect how the program filters work. References #927.
    </change>
    <change name="Jeannie Backer" date="2012-07-11">
      Modified application to not create empty output files. If a file is not
      created, a comment will be printed in the results log. Fixes #253.
      Fixed bug in NOMEASURELESS and POINTLIST filters. These were not being
      properly handled by the program. Replaced summary keyword NoCubeMeasure
      with NonCubeMeasures for consitency with NonCubePoints. Modified and
      added new appTests to reflect changes. Fixes #955. Added webpage example.
      Added documentation to Makefiles. Updated xml documentation and clarified
      output reports for [PREFIX]IgnoredMeasures.txt and
      [PREFIX]NonCubeMeasures.txt Fixes #927.
    </change>
    <change name="Debbie A. Cook" date="2012-11-30">
      Changed to use TProjection instead of Projection.  References #775.
    </change>
    <change name="Moses P. Milazzo" date="2014-11-13">
      Added EditLocked and Constrained filters. References #255.
    </change>
    <change name="Kelvin Rodriguez" date="2016-08-16">
      removed redundant boolean statement (len == 0) which caused warnings in clang.
      Part of porting to OS X 10.11.
    </change>
    <change name="Ian Humphrey" date="2016-09-29">
      When using LATLON=true, control points that are out of the specified latitude and longitude
      ranges will now be properly recorded into the approriate output text files. See the internal
      history for cnetextract.cpp's ExtractLatLonRange() for more detailed change information.
    </change>
  </history>

  <category>
    <categoryItem>Control Networks</categoryItem>
  </category>

  <groups>

    <group name="Input Files">

      <parameter name="FROMLIST">
          <type>filename</type>
          <fileMode>input</fileMode>
          <internalDefault>No input cube list</internalDefault>
          <brief>
            List of ISIS cubes in the input Control Network
          </brief>
          <description>
          A text file containing one column of ISIS cube file names. Every cube
          used in the input control network should be contained in this list.
          </description>
          <filter>
            *.txt *.lis *.list
          </filter>
        </parameter>

        <parameter name="CNET">
          <type>filename</type>
          <fileMode>input</fileMode>
          <brief>
            Input Control Network filename
          </brief>
          <description>
            A filename containing control network points and measures to extract
            the ONET from.
            </description>
          <filter>
            *.net
          </filter>
        </parameter>

    </group>

    <group name="Output">

      <parameter name="PREFIX">
        <type>string</type>
        <internalDefault>Prefix of NO results reports</internalDefault>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <brief>
          A string used to enable output of optional report file(s) of excluded
          information
        </brief>
        <description>
          A short single word string used as a prefix on output report file(s)
          generated based on extraction criteria entered by the user.  If a PREFIX is
          provided, the Control Points and Control Measures not extracted will be placed
          into output report files with the given PREFIX.  If a
          PREFIX is not entered, no report files will be output. See each
          option in the
          "Filter" groups to see which report files are created for each given filter.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TOLIST">
          <type>filename</type>
          <fileMode>output</fileMode>
          <internalDefault>No output cube list</internalDefault>
          <brief>
            List of ISIS cubes in the output Control Network file
          </brief>
          <description>
          This optional output text file contains one column of ISIS cube file names associated
          with the ONET. This list can only include cubes that were provided in the FROMLIST.
          </description>
          <filter>
            *.txt *.lis *.list
          </filter>
        </parameter>

        <parameter name="ONET">
          <type>filename</type>
          <fileMode>output</fileMode>
          <brief>
            Output Control Network filename
          </brief>
          <description>
            The resultant Control Network file extracted from CNET.
            </description>
          <filter>
            *.net
          </filter>
        </parameter>
        <parameter name="NETWORKID">
        <type>string</type>
        <internalDefault>Parent Network Id</internalDefault>
        <brief>
            Set Networkid keyword to this value in the extracted Control Network
        </brief>
        <description>
            The Networkid keyword of the extracted Control Network will be set
            to this string value.  The Networkid is a single word identifier
            or name assigned to a Control Network. This string should
            be unique.
        </description>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="DESCRIPTION">
        <type>string</type>
        <default><item>cnetextracted</item></default>
        <brief>
            Set Description keyword to this value in the extracted Control Network.
        </brief>
        <description>
            The Description keyword of the extracted Control Network will be
            set to this string value.  This should be a brief description
            of the purpose of the extracted control network.
        </description>
      </parameter>

    </group>

    <group name="Exclusive Filters">

      <parameter name="NOIGNORE">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>False</item></default>
        <brief>
          Do not extract ignored Control Points and non-referernce ignored
          Control Measures
        </brief>
        <description>
          <p>
            When selected, no ignored Control Points in the input
            Control Net will be included in the output Control Network.
            Furthermore, any ignored Control Measures that are not reference
            measures will also be excluded from the output Control Network.
          </p>

          <p>
            When option PREFIX is used, two report files will be created,
            [PREFIX]IgnoredPoints.txt and [PREFIX]IgnoredMeasures.txt.
            These files list all Control Points and Control Measures from the
            input Control Network that were not extracted due to this filter.
            **Note** The [PREFIX]IgnoredMeasures.txt will include ignored
            control measures that are reference measures even though they
            will be extracted.
          </p>
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="NOMEASURELESS">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>False</item></default>
        <brief>
          Do not extract Control Points with exactly zero Control Measures
        </brief>
        <description>
  	      <p>
            When selected, all Control Points that are reduced to zero Control
            Measures (from other selected filters or have zero measures on
            input) will not be included in the output Control Network.
          </p>

          <p>
            When option PREFIX is used, report file [PREFIX]MeasurelessPoints.txt
            will also be created. Each Control Point it lists was not extracted
            due to this filter.
          </p>
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="NOSINGLEMEASURES">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>False</item></default>
        <brief>
          Do not extract Control Points with exactly one Control Measure
        </brief>
        <description>
  	      <p>
            When selected, all Control Points that are reduced to one Control
            Measure (from other selected filters or only have one measure on
            input) will not be included in the output Control Network.
          </p>

          <p>
            When option PREFIX is used, report file [PREFIX]SingleMeasurePoints.txt
            will also be created. Each Control Point it lists was not extracted
            due to this filter.
          </p>
        </description>
        <exclusions>
          <item>REFERENCE</item>
        </exclusions>
      </parameter>

    </group>

    <group name="Inclusive Filters">

      <parameter name="REFERENCE">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>False</item></default>
        <brief>
          Only extract reference Control Measures
        </brief>
        <description>
          <p>
            When selected, only reference Control Measures will be
            extracted into the output Control Network.
          </p>

          <p>
            When this filter is used, NOMEASURELESS will be selected
            automatically, and NOSINGLEMEASURES will be disabled.
          </p>

          <p>
            When option PREFIX is used, report files with the names
            [PREFIX]NonReferenceMeasures.txt and  [PREFIX]MeasurelessPoints.txt
            will also be created. The first file will contain each Control
            Measure that was not extracted due to this filter and the latter
            will list all measurless points not extracted due to this filter.
          </p>
        </description>
        <exclusions>
          <item>NOSINGLEMEASURES</item>
        </exclusions>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="FIXED">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>False</item></default>
        <brief>
          Only extract fixed Control Points
        </brief>
        <description>
          <p>
            When selected, only fixed Control Points will be extracted into the
            output Control Network file.
          </p>

          <p>
            When option PREFIX is used, report file [PREFIX]NonFixedPoints.txt will also be
            created. Each Control Point it lists was not
            extracted due to this filter.
          </p>
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="CONSTRAINED">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>False</item></default>
        <brief>
          Only extract constrained Control Points
        </brief>
        <description>
          <p>
            When selected, only constrained Control Points will be extracted into the
            output Control Network file.
          </p>

          <p>
            When option PREFIX is used, report file [PREFIX]NonConstrainedPoints.txt will also be
            created. Each Control Point it lists was not
            extracted due to this filter.
          </p>
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="EDITLOCKED">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>False</item></default>
        <brief>
          Only extract editlocked Control Points
        </brief>
        <description>
          <p>
            When selected, only editlocked Control Points will be extracted into the
            output Control Network file.
          </p>

          <p>
            When option PREFIX is used, report file [PREFIX]NonEditLockedPoints.txt will also be
            created. Each Control Point it lists was not
            extracted due to this filter.
          </p>
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TOLERANCE">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>False</item></default>
        <brief>
          Only extract Control Points with line or sample residual greater than
          PIXELTOLERANCE
        </brief>
        <description>
          <p>
            When selected, extract all Control Points which have a line or a
            sample residual greater than or equal to the PIXELTOLERANCE value.
          </p>

          <p>
            The PIXELTOLERANCE is compared to the keywords LineResidual and
            SampleResidual in the input Control Network.
          </p>

          <p>
            When option PREFIX is used, report file [PREFIX]TolerancePoints.txt
            will also be created. Each Control Point it lists was not
            extracted due to this filter.
          </p>
        </description>
        <inclusions>
          <item>PIXELTOLERANCE</item>
        </inclusions>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="PIXELTOLERANCE">
        <type>double</type>
        <default><item>10.0</item></default>
        <brief>
          Only extract Control Points with a line or sample residual greater
          than this value
        </brief>
        <description>
          Control Points which contain at least one Control Measure with a line
          or a sample residual error greater than or equal to this value will
          be extracted.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="POINTLIST">
       <type>filename</type>
       <fileMode>input</fileMode>
       <internalDefault>None</internalDefault>
       <brief>
         File containing Control Point Ids which will be extracted
        </brief>
       <description>
         <p>
           Use this parameter to select a text file that contains a list of
           Control Point Ids. All the Control Points with matching Ids will be
           extracted as long as another selected filter does not exclude the
           Control Point.
         </p>

         <p>
           When option PREFIX is used, report file [PREFIX]NonListedPoints.txt
           will also be created. Each Control Point it contains was not
           extracted due to this filter.
         </p>
       </description>
       <filter>
         *.lis
       </filter>
     </parameter>

    </group>

    <group name="Cube Filters">

      <parameter name="CUBES">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>False</item></default>
        <brief>
          Enable extraction of Control Points/Measures based on listed cubes
        </brief>
        <description>
          When selected, only Control Points which contain the cubes listed in
          CUBELIST will be extracted.
        </description>
        <inclusions>
          <item>CUBELIST</item>
          <item>CUBEMEASURES</item>
        </inclusions>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="CUBELIST">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Only extract Control Points containing the listed cubes
        </brief>
        <description>
          <p>
            Use this parameter to select a text file that contains a list of
            ISIS cubes. All the Control Points which contain at least one of
            these cubes will be extracted.
          </p>

          <p>
            When option PREFIX is used, report file [PREFIX]NonCubePoints.txt
            will also be created. Each Control Point it lists was not
            extracted due to this filter.
          </p>
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.lis
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="CUBEMEASURES">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>False</item></default>
        <brief>
          Only extract Control Measures containing a cube in CUBELIST
        </brief>
        <description>
          <p>
            When selected, extract all Control Measures from extracted Control
            Points that contain a cube in the CUBELIST list. This option can
            only be used when a file has been provided for CUBELIST.
          </p>

          <p>
            When this filter is used, NOMEASURELESS will be selected
            automatically.
          </p>

          <p>
            When option PREFIX is used with this filter, the report file
            [PREFIX]NonCubeMeasures.txt will also be created. Each Control
            Measure it lists was not extracted due to this filter.
          </p>
        </description>
        <inclusions>
          <item>RETAIN_REFERENCE</item>
        </inclusions>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="RETAIN_REFERENCE">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>False</item></default>
        <brief>
          Retain Reference even if not in the CUBELIST
        </brief>
        <description>
          <p>
            When selected, retain the Reference in the extracted Control Points
            even if it is not in the  the CUBELIST  list.
          </p>

          <p>
            When this filter is used, NOMEASURELESS will be selected
            automatically.
          </p>

          <p>
            When option PREFIX is used with the CUBEMEASURES filter, the
            report file [PREFIX]NonCubeMeasures.txt will also be created. This
            file will list the measures that are not extracted.  This will
            include non-reference measures that do not correspond to the
            cubelist. When RETAIN_REFERENCE is true, reference measures will
            be listed in this file, even though they will be extracted.
          </p>
        </description>
      </parameter>

    </group>

    <group name="Lat/Lon Filters">

      <parameter name="LATLON">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>False</item></default>
        <brief>
          Only extract Control Points in the lat/lon range
        </brief>
        <description>
  	      <p>
            When selected, all Control Points that are inside of the provided
            latitude and longitude ranges will be extracted. Control Points
            whose latitude and/or longitude cannot be computed will not be
            extracted.
          </p>

          <p>
            Fixed Points will use the lat/lon values provided in the input
            control network, while Free Points will calculate the lat/lon
            from the images provided by the FROMLIST. These calculated lat/lon
            values will be added to Free Points in the output control network
            for reference purposes. However, no Isis application will use
            these lat/lons that are added to Free Points.
          </p>

          <p>
            When option PREFIX is used, report files [PREFIX]LatLonOutOfRange.txt
            and [PREFIX]NoLatLonPoint.txt will also be created. Each Control
            Point they list was not extracted due to this filter.
          </p>

          <p>
            Control Points in [PREFIX]LatLonOutOfRange.txt did not fall within
            the provided lat/lon bound. Each Control Points listed in
            [PREFIX]NoLatLonPoint.txt do not have a determinable Latitude or
            Longitude.
          </p>

          <p>Note: This option is expensive.</p>
        </description>
        <inclusions>
          <item>MINLAT</item>
          <item>MAXLAT</item>
          <item>MINLON</item>
          <item>MAXLON</item>
        </inclusions>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="MINLAT">
        <type>double</type>
        <default><item>-90.0</item></default>
        <minimum inclusive="yes">-90.0</minimum>
        <maximum inclusive="yes">90.0</maximum>
        <brief>
          Minimum Control Point Latitude
        </brief>
        <description>
          Any Control Point with a latitude less than MINLAT will be removed.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="MAXLAT">
        <type>double</type>
        <default><item>90.0</item></default>
        <minimum inclusive="yes">-90.0</minimum>
        <maximum inclusive="yes">90.0</maximum>
        <greaterThanOrEqual><item>MINLAT</item></greaterThanOrEqual>
        <brief>
          Maximum Control Point Latitude
        </brief>
        <description>
          Any Control Point with a latitude greater than MAXLAT will be removed.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="MINLON">
        <type>double</type>
        <default><item>0.0</item></default>
        <minimum inclusive="yes">0.0</minimum>
        <maximum inclusive="yes">360.0</maximum>
        <brief>
          Minimum Control Point Longitude
        </brief>
        <description>
          <p>
            Any Control Point with a longitude less than MINLON will be
            removed.
          </p>

          <p>
            If MINLON is greater than MAXLON than the longitude range is
            assumed to cross the 0/360 longitude boundry, where points with
            longitude greater than MINLON or less than MAXLON will be
            included.
          </p>
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="MAXLON">
        <type>double</type>
        <default><item>360.0</item></default>
        <minimum inclusive="yes">0.0</minimum>
        <maximum inclusive="yes">360.0</maximum>
        <brief>
          Maximum Control Point Longitude
        </brief>
        <description>
          <p>
            Any Control Point with a longitude greater than MAXLON will be
            removed.
          </p>

          <p>
            If MAXLON is less than MINLON than the longitude range is assumed
            to cross the 0/360 longitude boundry, where points with longitude
            greater than MINLON or less than MAXLON will be included.
          </p>
        </description>
      </parameter>

    </group>

  </groups>
  <examples>
    <example>
      <brief>
        Example of cnetextract using the CUBES parameters.
      </brief>

      <description>
        This example shows how to use cnetextract to extract points using Cube
        filters. This will extract all points that contain at least one measure
        corresponding to the given cubes in the file list.lis (CUBES=true
        CUBELIST=list.lis). From these points, the only measures that are
        extracted will correspond to the cubelist (CUBEMEASURES=true).
        All reference measures will be extracted, whether they correspond to
        the cubelist or not (RETAIN_REFERENCE=true). Note that the
        RETAIN_REFERENCE option overrides the CUBEMEASURES option with
        respect to reference measures.
      </description>

      <terminalInterface>
        <commandLine>
          fromlist=list.lis cnet=cnet.net prefix=new tolist=newList.lis
          onet=newNet.net networkid=new description=new cubes=true
          cubelist=list.lis cubemeasures=true retain_reference=true
        </commandLine>
        <description>
          An example of how to run this program from the command line.
        </description>
      </terminalInterface>

      <guiInterfaces>
        <guiInterface>
          <image width="820" height="1239" src="assets/images/cnetextract-cube-filter-1640w-2478h.png">
          <brief>
            Example GUI
          </brief>
            <description>
              An example of how to run this program using the GUI. Note that the
              results summary can be seen in the log window.
            </description>
            <thumbnail width="103" height="155" src="assets/thumbs/cnetextract-cube-filter-thumb-205w-310h.png" caption="Example of GUI command"/>
          </image>
        </guiInterface>
      </guiInterfaces>

      <dataFiles>
        <dataFile path="assets/dataFiles/list.lis">
          <brief>
            FROMLIST = list.lis
          </brief>
          <description>
            This is the input list containing cubes that can be found in the
            input control network.
          </description>
          <parameterName>
            FROMLIST
          </parameterName>
        </dataFile>
        <dataFile path="assets/dataFiles/cnet.pvl">
          <brief>
            CNET = cnet.net
          </brief>
          <description>
            The input control network contains 18 points and a total of 37
            measures.
          </description>
          <parameterName>
            CNET
          </parameterName>
        </dataFile>
        <dataFile path="assets/dataFiles/newList.lis">
          <brief>
            TOLIST = newList.lis
          </brief>
          <description>
            This is the list of cubes contained in the FROMLIST that can be
            found in the output control network. Notice that one of the cubes
            listed in the FROMLIST is not included in the output TOLIST.
          </description>
          <parameterName>
            TOLIST
          </parameterName>
        </dataFile>
        <dataFile path="assets/dataFiles/newNet.pvl">
          <brief>
            ONET = newNet.net
          </brief>
          <description>
            The output control network contains 13 of the original 18 points.
            Five points were extracted (test0135 to test0139) since they did
            not contain either measures from any of the three cubes in the
            cubelist (see list.lis).  Also, notice that 19 of the original
            37 measures have been extracted. Each of these measures can be
            matched to a cube in the cubelist or is reference measure for one
            of the 13 output points.
          </description>
          <parameterName>
            ONET
          </parameterName>
        </dataFile>
        <dataFile path="assets/dataFiles/list.lis">
          <brief>
            CUBELIST = list.lis
          </brief>
          <description>
            This is a list of cubes from which we will filter.
          </description>
          <parameterName>
            CUBELIST
          </parameterName>
        </dataFile>
        <dataFile path="assets/dataFiles/newNonCubePoints.txt">
          <brief>
            newNonCubePoints.txt, created since PREFIX=new and CUBES=true
          </brief>
          <description>
            The output report for the CUBES filter lists the 5 points that were
            not extracted since they have no measures that correspond to cubes
            in the given cubelist. Notice the prefix of the file name "new" is
            taken from the value passed into the PREFIX parameter. Also, note
            that this file would not be created if the PREFIX parameter was
            left blank.
          </description>
          <parameterName>
            PREFIX, CUBES
          </parameterName>
        </dataFile>
        <dataFile path="assets/dataFiles/newNonCubeMeasures.txt">
          <brief>
            newNonCubeMeasures.txt, created since PREFIX=new,
            CUBEMEASURES=true, RETAIN_REFERENCE=true
          </brief>
          <description>
            Output report for CUBEMEASURES filter
            The output report for the CUBEMEASURES and RETAIN_REFERENCE filters
            lists the 24 measures from extracted points that don't correspond
            to cubes in the given cubelist. Notice that, since RETAIN_REFERENCE
            is selected, the reference measures listed in this report indicate
            that they are extracted. Also, notice the prefix of the file name
            "new" is taken from the value passed into the PREFIX parameter.
            This file would not be created if the PREFIX parameter was left
            blank.
          </description>
          <parameterName>
            PREFIX, CUBES, CUBEMEASURES, RETAIN_REFERENCE
          </parameterName>
        </dataFile>
        <dataFile path="assets/dataFiles/summaryLog.txt">
          <brief>
            Standard output results summary.
          </brief>
          <description>
            If run command line, this summary will be printed in the terminal
            window. If run in GUI, this summary will be printed in the log area.
            Notice that the report shows MeasurelessPoints even though the
            NOMEASURELESS parameter was not selected. However, this parameter is
            automatically selected when CUBEMEASURES is selected.
          </description>
        </dataFile>
      </dataFiles>

    </example>
  </examples>

</application>
