<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="cnetnewradii" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">
  <brief>
    Generate new radii from DEM for a ControlNet
  </brief>

  <description>
    <p>
      This application will go through an existing control network and copy it
      to a new control network updating either apriori or adjusted radii values
      using the given shape file. When it encounters a point type of Fixed or 
      Constrained it will use the control point latitude and longitude to update 
      the radius from the shape model file. The radius will be calculated based 
      on a bilinear interpolation of the closest pixels in the shape file.  The 
      AprioriRadius, AprioriRadiusSource and AprioriRadiusSourceFile will be 
      updated if GETLATLON=APRIORI.  The AdjustedRadius will be updated if 
      GETLATLON=ADJUSTED.  There are not keywords for AdjustedRadiusSource or
      AdjustedRadiusSourceFile.  
    </p>
    <p>
      If, for a particular point, the application fails to calculate a radius
      using the shape file, then the input radius value is kept and the point is
      set to Ignore=true.  The number of these failures are recorded in the
      application's log.  The Point IDs for the corresponding control points
      will be listed in the ERRORS log output file.  If the user did not enter
      a filename for this log and there are any points that failed, one will be
      created with the name "failures.log".
      <strong>Note:</strong>If a significant number of points in the control 
      network fail to find a new radius value, the user should make sure that 
      they have input the correct shape model for the input control network.
    </p>
  </description>

  <category>
    <categoryItem>Control Networks</categoryItem>
  </category>

  <history>
    <change name="Steven Koechle" date="2008-08-05">
      Original Version
    </change>
    <change name="Jeannie Walldren" date="2010-05-25">
      Modified to handle control points that fail to calculate a new radius as
      explained in the description. Added ERRORS parameter to list PointIDs of
      the control points that failed to calculate a new radius. Added filters
      for input and output parameters.
    </change>
    <change name="Jeannie Walldren" date="2010-05-27">
      Created examples.
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2011-01-19">
      Altered to compile with the new Control redesign.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2011-02-09">
      Updated to not try to project null lat,lon values
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2011-03-14">
      Updated for Control Point's removal of Set/GetSurfacePoint() and added
      the GetLatLon parameter.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2011-04-11">
      Changed the DEM parameter name to MODEL
    </change>
    <change name="Debbie A. Cook and Tracie Sucharski" date="2011-06-07">
      Changed the point type "Ground" to "Fixed"
    </change>
    <change name="Tracie Sucharski" date="2011-07-28">
      Change radii values for both Fixed and Constrained points.   Use bilinear
      interpolation to get the correct radius from the shape file.  This uses 
      the same interpolation as the camera.  Print error  if there are no Fixed
      or Constrained points in the network.  Change input parameter names to be
      consistent with those suggested on the Astrogeology wiki page.  Removed NETWORKID
      as user parameter since it should carry the ID from the input control net.
      Set Apriori as the default for the GETLATLON parameter.  Update examples
      documentation.
    </change>
    <change name="Tracie Sucharski" date="2011-10-04">
      Skip edit locked points, keep count for summary.  Added appTest for edit 
      locked points.
    </change>
  </history>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="CNET">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input ControlNet
        </brief>
        <description>
          Use this parameter to select the input control network.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.net
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="MODEL">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          User defined ISIS cube shape model.
        </brief>
        <description>
          A map projected ISIS cube which contains the radii of the target.
          The file can cover a larger area than the control points in the 
          network, but must minimally include all of the control point
          locations.
        </description>
        <defaultPath>$base/dems/</defaultPath>
        <filter>*.cub</filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="ONET">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Output ControlNet file
        </brief>
        <description>
          Use this parameter to specify the name of the output control network.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.net
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="ERRORS">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <internalDefault>No Error Output</internalDefault>
        <brief>
          Optional log file containing failures.
        </brief>
        <description>
          This file will contain the Point IDs of all control points whose
          radius could not be calculated from the shape model.  This happens 
          when the radius value is a special pixel or when the program fails to 
          set universal ground given the lat/lon values of the control point.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.log *.pvl *.txt
        </filter>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Parameters">
      <parameter name="GETLATLON">
        <type>string</type>
        <default>
          <item>APRIORI</item>
        </default>
        <brief>Source of the latitude, longitude used to set new radii</brief> 
        <description> 
          Specify which Surface Point to use when setting the new radii.
        </description> 
        <list>
          <option value="APRIORI">
            <brief>Use the Apriori Surface Point</brief>
            <description>
               Use the lat/lon values provided by the Apriori Surface Point
               when setting the new radii.
            </description>
          </option>
          <option value="ADJUSTED">
            <brief>Use the Adjusted Surface Point</brief>
            <description>
               Use the lat/lon values provided by the Adjusted Surface Point
               when setting the new radii. The lat/lon value of the Adjusted
               Surface Point is generated by bundle adjust.
            </description>
          </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>
    </group>
  </groups>

  <examples>
    <example>
      <brief>All fixed points successfully updated</brief>
      <description>
        Example of the use of cnetnewradii on a control network whose
        constrained and fixed points lat/lon values are all contained within the 
        given shape model.
      </description>
      <terminalInterface>
        <commandLine>
          cnet=../IN/inputcnet.net model=../IN/inputDEM1.cub
          onet=../OUT/ouputcnet1.net getlatlon=APRIORI
        </commandLine>
        <description>
          In this example, cnetnewradii will take the input control network and
          copy it to the output network with new radii values calculated for
          all constrained and fixed points using an interpolated  DN value from 
          the shape cube. The apriori values will be updated.  No error log will 
          be generated.
        </description>
      </terminalInterface>
      <guiInterfaces>
        <guiInterface>
          <image src="assets/images/cnetnewradiiGui1.jpg" width="719" height="550">
            <brief>
              Example GUI
            </brief>
            <description>
              Screen shot of GUI with parameters filled in to create control 
              network with new radii values.
            </description>
            <thumbnail caption="" src="assets/thumbs/cnetnewradiiGui1Thumb.jpg" width="200" height="153"/>
          </image>
        </guiInterface>
      </guiInterfaces>
      <dataFiles>
        <dataFile path="assets/inputcnet.pvl">
          <brief>Input ControlNet for cnetnewradii</brief>
          <description>
            Example of an input control network whose radii values will be 
            updated.
          </description>
          <parameterName>CNET</parameterName>
        </dataFile>
        <dataFile path="assets/outputcnet1.pvl">
          <brief>Output control network for cnetnewradii</brief>
          <description>
            Example of an output control network corresponding to the input 
            example with updated radii values.  Notice that radii values have 
            been updated for all contrained and fixed points.
          </description>
          <parameterName>ONET</parameterName>
        </dataFile>
      </dataFiles>
      <inputImages>
        <image src="assets/images/inputDEM1.jpg" width="716" height="550">
          <brief>Input shape file for cnetnewradii</brief>
          <description>
            Example of an input shape cube used by cnetnewradii to update the
            radii values of contrained and fixed points in the control network.
          </description>
          <thumbnail caption="SHAPE " src="assets/thumbs/inputDEM1Thumb.jpg" width="200" height="154"/>
          <parameterName>SHAPE</parameterName>
        </image>
      </inputImages>
    </example>
    <example>
      <brief>Some fixed points fail to be updated</brief>
      <description>
        Example of the use of cnetnewradii on a control network` that contains 
        some fixed points whose radius can not be calculated.
      </description>
      <terminalInterface>
        <commandLine>
          cnet=../IN/inputcnet.pvl model=../IN/inputDEM2.cub
          onet=../OUT/ouputcnet2.pvl errors=../OUT/failures.pvl
        </commandLine>
        <description>
          In this example, cnetnewradii will take the input control network and
          copy it to the output network with new radii values calculated for
          fixed points using the DN value recieved from the shape cube. The
          PointIDs of fixed points that fail to calculate a new radius value
          will be listed in the error log.
        </description>
      </terminalInterface>
      <guiInterfaces>
        <guiInterface>
          <image src="assets/images/cnetnewradiiGui2.jpg" width="719" height="550">
            <brief>
              Example GUI
            </brief>
            <description>
              Screen shot of GUI with parameters filled in to create control 
              network with new radii values.
            </description>
            <thumbnail caption="" src="assets/thumbs/cnetnewradiiGui2Thumb.jpg" width="200" height="153"/>
          </image>
        </guiInterface>
      </guiInterfaces>
      <dataFiles>
        <dataFile path="assets/inputcnet.pvl">
          <brief>Input control network for cnetnewradii</brief>
          <description>
            Example of an input control network whose radii values will be
            updated.
          </description>
          <parameterName>CNET</parameterName>
        </dataFile>
        <dataFile path="assets/failures.pvl">
          <brief>Output error log for cnetnewradii</brief>
          <description>
            Example of an output error log containing the PointIDs of all points
            that failed to calculate a new radius value.
          </description>
          <parameterName>ERRORS</parameterName>
        </dataFile>
        <dataFile path="assets/outputcnet2.pvl">
          <brief>Output control network for cnetnewradii</brief>
          <description>
            Example of an output control network corresponding to the input 
            example with updated radii values.  Notice that the fixed points
            that failed are set to Ignore=True and their original radii values
            are retained.
          </description>
          <parameterName>ONET</parameterName>
        </dataFile>
      </dataFiles>
      <inputImages>
        <image src="assets/images/inputDEM2.jpg" width="716" height="550">
          <brief>Input shape cube for cnetnewradii</brief>
          <description>
            Example of an input shape cube used by cnetnewradii to update the
            radii values of fixed points in the control network.
          </description>
          <thumbnail caption="SHAPE" src="assets/thumbs/inputDEM2Thumb.jpg" width="200" height="154"/> <parameterName>DEM</parameterName>
        </image>
      </inputImages>
    </example>
  </examples>

</application>
