<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="kerneldbgen" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">
  <brief>
    Creates a database of kernels
  </brief>

  <description>
    <p>
      This program is used to give the programmer and ISIS programs a database
      with which they can reference coverage times for ck and spk kernels. Output
      will thus be to a pvl file specified in the TO parameter. It should be noted
      that the user is encouraged to use system preferences when defining pathnames,
      for example $mgs or $base. If this is not possible, for example kernels are
      being referenced that are located in a user's development area, absolute
      pathnames should be used. Relative pathnames using ".", "..", or user-defined
      environment variables are highly discouraged.
    </p>
    <p>
      Kernels have different qualities. The lowest quality is nadir, which supplies
      what may be considered "placeholder" values. Generally, nadir kernels exist
      to fill in gaps and mimic the instrument pointing at -90 degrees. Since they
      only mimic pointing data, they cannot be used for SPKs, since these kernels
    specify positions rather than pointing.
    </p>
    <p>
      The second lowest quality kernel is predict. Predict kernels are based on
      the predicted location of spacecraft and thus are subject to error.
    </p>
    <p>
      Reconstructed kernels are of higher quality than predicts. They are
      supplemented with information as to the actual position of bodies and
      spacecraft.
    </p>
    <p>
      The highest quality kernels are smithed. These generally come from reconstructed
      kernels that have been corrected even further by an individual institution.
    </p>
    <p>
      The four levels of kernels listed above are the only ones that will be
      listed in the database. Kernels are ordered from the lowest quality at the
      top of the output file to the highest quality at the bottom of the output
      file within individual kernel qualities, kernels are listed from earliest to
      latest created file. This is done in anticipation of programs such as spiceinit
      which read from the bottom of the file for the best kernel.
    </p>
    <br />
    <p>
      This program's database is in pvl format, and as such order is
      significant. The last listed kernel file covering the timespan will be
      used. Because of this in combination with the individual needs of
      specific missions, ISIS arrays can be used to control kernel file order.
    </p>
    <p><pre>
      For example, using the pure string expression:

      "m01_sc_ext??_rec_nadir.bc ; m01_sc_ext??.bc"

      would result in the listing:

      m01_sc_ext10.bc
      m01_sc_ext10_rec_nadir.bc
      m01_sc_ext11.bc
      m01_sc_ext11_rec_nadir.bc
      m01_sc_ext12.bc
      m01_sc_ext12_rec_nadir.bc
      m01_sc_ext13.bc
      m01_sc_ext13_rec_nadir.bc

          while using the ISIS array expression:

          ("m01_sc_ext??_rec_nadir.bc", "m01_sc_ext??.bc")

          would result in the listing:

      m01_sc_ext10_rec_nadir.bc
      m01_sc_ext11_rec_nadir.bc
      m01_sc_ext12_rec_nadir.bc
      m01_sc_ext13_rec_nadir.bc
      m01_sc_ext10.bc
      m01_sc_ext11.bc
      m01_sc_ext12.bc
      m01_sc_ext13.bc
    </pre></p>
  </description>

  <category>
    <categoryItem>System</categoryItem>
  </category>

  <seeAlso>
    <applications>
      <item>spiceinit</item>
    </applications>
  </seeAlso>

  <history>
    <change name="Drew Davidson" date="2005-08-03">
      Original version
    </change>
    <change name="Drew Davidson" date="2005-08-03">
      Added relative pathnames to output database
    </change>
    <change name="Drew Davidson" date="2005-08-16">
      Added examples
    </change>
    <change name="Elizabeth Miller" date="2005-10-05">
      Moved from Geometry category to System
    </change>
    <change name="Brendan George" date="2005-11-03">
      Added application test
    </change>
    <change name="Elizabeth Miller" date="2005-11-21">
      Fixed constriction on filename size and fixed bug in appTest
    </change>
    <change name="Jacob Danton" date="2005-12-27">
      Made changes to SpiceDbGen to comply with changes in KernelDb
    </change>
    <change name="Brendan George" date="2006-10-05">
      Modified call to retrieve current time to refer to Time class, instead
      of Application class
    </change>
    <change name="Jeff Anderson" date="2006-10-24">
      Removed spaces between Spacecraft Clock Count and Leapsecond Kernel
      keywords
    </change>
    <change name="Stuart Sides" date="2006-11-21">
      Fixed bug where spk and ck kernel files were flagged as "Predict" instead
      of "Predicted"
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2008-08-01">
      Fixed bug where some ck kernels could not be loaded due to their size.
      Also added naif status calls, which will provide easy to read iExceptions to the
      user instead of a dump to the terminal window when a problem occurs.
    </change>
    <change name="Stuart Sides" date="2010-04-27">
      Modified to use a vector of filters for each quality of kernel instead of
      a single string
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2011-05-06">
      Added documentation for ISIS array input.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2013-02-15">
      Added the EXTRA option. Also, added basic support for kerneldb files being specified for
      SCLK/LSK parameters. Fixes #1023.
    </change>
    <change name="Stuart Sides" date="2015-03-29">
      Added three additional decimal places to the output of the TIME keyword in output
      kernel database file.  Fixes #2236.
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Combs" date="2018-01-11">
      Added STARTOFFSET and ENDOFFSET parameters to allow for slight editing to start and end times.
      Fixes #5272.
    </change>
  </history>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="TO">
        <type>filename</type>
        <default>
          <item>./kernels.????.db</item>
        </default>
        <brief>
          Location of the output file
        </brief>
        <description>
          This parameter may be used as a relative pathname to specify the
          location of an output PVL database containing data on all of kernels
          matched by kerneldbgen. It should be noted that version sequences
          may be included in the pathname, in which case a new version will be
          created.
        </description>
      </parameter>
    </group>
    <group name="Kernel Type">
      <parameter name="TYPE">
        <type>string</type>
        <default>
          <item>CK</item>
        </default>
        <brief>
          Kernel type
        </brief>
        <description>
          The kernel type specifies what sort of information the kernel contains.
          Since kerneldbgen is intended for use only in situations where the most
          recent kernel does not eclipse the content of previous kernels, there
          are only two options: Spacecraft pointing kernels (CK) and Spacecraft
          position kernels (SPK).
        </description>
        <list>
          <option value="CK">
            <brief>
              Spacecraft pointing kernels
            </brief>
            <description>
              The kernels to be listed in the output database will include
              spacecraft pointing data. In order to properly calculate times, a
              spacecraft clock kernel (SCLK)  and leapsecond kernel (LSK)
              must also be furnished via the dependency kernel group below.
            </description>
          </option>
          <option value="SPK">
            <brief>
              Spacecraft position kernels
            </brief>
            <description>
              The kernels to be listed in the output database will include
              spacecraft position data. Unlike calculations for pointing data,
              only the leapsecond kernel (LSK) needs to be provided.
            </description>
            <exclusions>
              <item>SCLK</item>
              <!--
              <item>NADIRFILTER</item>
              <item>NADIRDIR</item>
              -->
            </exclusions>
          </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>
    </group>
    <group name="Predict">
      <parameter name="PREDICTDIR">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>
          Directory where the predict quality kernels are located
        </brief>
        <description>
          This parameter specifies the path upon which the regular expression in
          "PREDICTFILTER" will operate. Since this parameter will be used
          explicitly in the "File" keyword of the generated database, it is
          recommended that only shortcuts known to the ISIS system and absolute
          pathnames are used. If left as "none" no predicted kernels will be
          included in the database
        </description>
        <default>
          <item>none</item>
        </default>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="PREDICTFILTER">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>
          Filter to identify predict quality kernels
        </brief>
        <default>
          <item>none</item>
        </default>
        <description>
          This parameter is used to specify the kernel or kernels to be
          identified as predicted. Any combination of kernel file names or
          regular expression may be specified. The value of "PREDICTDIR" is
          prepended to each element before being expanded. Each regular
          expression is evaluated then the results are sorted according
          to ASCII order and added to the list of available kernels.
        </description>
      </parameter>
    </group>
    <group name="Reconstructed">
      <parameter name="RECONDIR">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>
          Directory where the reconstructed quality kernels are located
        </brief>
        <description>
          This parameter specifies the path upon which the regular expression in
          "RECONFILTER" will operate. Since this parameter will be used
          explicitly in the "File" keyword of the generated database, it is
          recommended that only shortcuts known to the ISIS system and absolute
          pathnames are used. If left as "none" no reconstructed kernels will be
          included in the database.
        </description>
        <default>
          <item>none</item>
        </default>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="RECONFILTER">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>
          Filter to identify reconstructed quality kernels
        </brief>
        <description>
          This parameter is used to specify the kernel or kernels to be
          identified as reconstructed. Any combination of kernel file names or
          regular expression may be specified. The value of "RECONDIR" is
          prepended to each element before being expanded. Each regular
          expression is evaluated then the results are sorted according to ASCII
          order and added to the list of available kernels.
        </description>
        <default>
          <item>none</item>
        </default>
      </parameter>
    </group>
    <group name="Smithed">
      <parameter name="SMITHEDDIR">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>
          Directory where the smithed quality kernels are located
        </brief>
        <description>
          This parameter specifies the path upon which the regular expression in
          "SMITHEDFILTER" will operate. Since this parameter will be used
          explicitly in the "File" keyword of the generated database, it is
          recommended that only shortcuts known to the ISIS system and absolute
          pathnames are used. If left as "none" no smithed kernels will be
          included in the database
        </description>
        <default>
          <item>none</item>
        </default>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="SMITHEDFILTER">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>
           Filter to identify smithed quality kernels
        </brief>
        <description>
          This parameter is used to specify the kernel or kernels to be
          identified as smithed. Any combination of kernel file names or regular
          expression may be specified. The value of "SMITHED"DIR" is prepended
          to each element before being expanded. Each regular expression is
          evaluated then the results are sorted according to ASCII order and
          added to the list of available kernels.
        </description>
        <default>
          <item>none</item>
        </default>
      </parameter>
    </group>
    <group name="Offset">
      <parameter name="STARTOFFSET">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief>
          Seconds to subtract from each start time in the kernel.
        </brief>
        <minimum inclusive="yes">0.0</minimum>
        <description>
          This parameter is used to specify the amount of offset (in seconds) to apply to the 
          StartTime value for each kernel that is used to populate the db file. This value will be
          subtracted the value found in the kernel. If left as 0.0, no offset will be applied, and 
          the Time will be copied over as written in the kernel.
        </description>
        <default>
          <item>0.0</item>
        </default>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="ENDOFFSET">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief>
           Seconds to add to each end time in the kernel.
        </brief>
        <minimum inclusive="yes">0.0</minimum>
        <description>
          This parameter is used to specify the amount of offset (in seconds) to apply to the 
          EndTime value for each kernel that is used to populate the db file. This value will be
          added to the value found in the kernel. If left as 0.0, no offset will be applied, and the
          Time will be copied over as written in the kernel.
        </description>
        <default>
          <item>0.0</item>
        </default>
      </parameter>
    </group>
    <!-- Removed because NADIR kerels are not specifed by files, instead NADIR pointing is caluculated as normal to the surface from the current spacecraft position
    <group name="Nadir">
      <parameter name="NADIRDIR">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>
          Directory where the nadir quality kernels are located
        </brief>
        <description>
          This parameter specifies the path upon which the regular expression in
          "NADIRFILTER" will operate. Since this parameter will be used
          explicitly in the "File" keyword of the generated database, it is
          recommended that only shortcuts known to the ISIS system and absolute
          pathnames are used. If left as "none" no nadir kernels will be
          included in the database.
        </description>
        <default>
          <item>none</item>
        </default>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="NADIRFILTER">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>
          Filter to identify nadir quality kernels
        </brief>
        <description>
          This parameter is used to specify the kernel or kernels to be
          identified as predicted. Any combination of kernel file names or
          regular expression may be specified. The value of "PREDICTDIR" is
          prepended to each element before being expanded. Each regular
          expression is evaluated then the results are sorted according
          to ASCII order and added to the list of available kernels.


          This parameter can be used to specify a single kernel, but the intent
          is to specify a simple regular expression which, when expanded, will
          list all of the predicted kernels in the directory specified by
          "NADIRDIR"
        </description>
        <default>
          <item>none</item>
        </default>
      </parameter>
    </group>
    -->
    <group name="Dependency Kernels">
      <parameter name="SCLK">
        <type>filename</type>
        <brief>
          Spacecraft clock kernel
        </brief>
        <description>
          This parameter specifies a spacecraft clock kernel for use in
          determining spacecraft pointing data. An actual kernel may be used, or
          a pvl file of the form kernels.????.db that specifies SCLK data may
          be used, where ???? is the version sequence.
        </description>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name= "LSK">
        <type>filename</type>
        <brief>
          Leapsecond kernel
        </brief>
        <description>
          This parameter specifies a leapsecond kernel for use in
          determining spacecraft data. An actual kernel may be used, or
          a pvl file of the form kernels.????.db that specifies LSK data may
          be used, where ???? is the version sequence.
        </description>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name= "EXTRA">
        <type>filename</type>
        <brief>
          Other kernels
        </brief>
        <description>
          This parameter specifies additional kernels required to fully vet the CK/SPK kernels.
          An actual kernel may be used, or a pvl file of the form kernels.????.db that specifies
          LSK data may be used, where ???? is the version sequence.
        </description>
        <internalDefault>none</internalDefault>
      </parameter>
    </group>
  </groups>
  <examples>
    <example>
      <brief>
         Messenger ck kernels
      </brief>
      <description>
        Use the ck option to create a database of spacecraft pointing kernels.
        In this example, a database is being created for the pivot kernels
        pertaining to the Messenger spacecraft.
      </description>
      <terminalInterface>
        <commandLine>
          'to=pivot_kernels.????.db
          type = ck
          recondir = $Messenger/kernels/ck
          reconfilter= *_mdis_pivot.bc
          lsk = $Base/kernels/lsk/naif0008.tls
          sclk = $Messenger/kernels/sclk/messenger_167.tsc'
        </commandLine>
        <description>
          This command line argument will create the database pivot_kernels.0002.db,
          assuming "0001" is the highest version in the target directory. Note the
          use of single quotes around the invocation of kerneldbgen. This is
          done because this particular run uses several characters such as the
          wildcard (*) that would be interpreted by the shell.
        </description>
      </terminalInterface>




      <guiInterfaces>
        <guiInterface>
          <image width="440" height="625" src="assets/images/messengerCk.jpg">
            <brief>
              Example GUI
            </brief>
            <description>
              Screenshot of the GUI with parameters set to create a kernel database
              of Messenger pivot kernels. Unlike running from the command line, the
              program need not go through the shell. Consequently, the input does
              not need to include escape sequences or quotes.
            </description>
            <thumbnail width="220" height="312" caption="kerneldbgen gui"
             src="assets/thumbs/messengerCk.jpg" />
          </image>
        </guiInterface>
      </guiInterfaces>




      <inputImages>
        <image width="600" height="323" src="assets/images/terminalBefore.jpg">
          <brief>
            List of files before kerneldbgen has been run
          </brief>
          <description>
            As seen in this terminal snapshot, there are a number of files that will
            match the reconfilter in the directory specified by the recondir. The
            highest pivot_kernels version is 0001.
          </description>
          <thumbnail caption= "The directory before kerneldbgen"
           src="assets/thumbs/terminalBefore.jpg" width="200" height="108"/>
          <parameterName>RECONDIR</parameterName>
        </image>
      </inputImages>




      <outputImages>
        <image width="600" height="323" src="assets/images/terminalAfter.jpg">
          <brief>
            List of files after kerneldbgen has been run
          </brief>
          <description>
            None of the original files have been altered, but the versioning system
            has created a new version of the pivot_kernels database named
            pivot_kernels.0002.db. The content of this file is listed below.
          </description>
          <thumbnail caption= "The directory after kerneldbgen"
          src="assets/thumbs/terminalAfter.jpg" width="200" height="108"/>
          <parameterName>TO</parameterName>
        </image>
        <image width="750" height="483" src="assets/images/pivotDb.jpg">
          <brief>
            The database created by kerneldbgen
          </brief>
          <description>
            As seen here, the database has picked up all of the files that match the
            filter specified. Each time coverage interval is listed as a selection,
            and the dependency kernels is listed in a "dependency" group. Note that
            since the only type of filter specified was for Reconstructed kernels,
            that is the only type of kernel to appear in the database.
          </description>
          <thumbnail caption= "The database file"
          src="assets/thumbs/pivotDb.jpg" width="200" height="132"/>
          <parameterName>TO</parameterName>
        </image>
      </outputImages>
    </example>
    <example>
      <brief>
        MGS CK kernels
      </brief>
      <description>
      Use the ck option to create a database of pointing kernels. In
      this example, kernels are being created for Mars Odyssey, both predict
      and reconstructed quality. This example should be of interest because it shows
      both the creation of a database with multiple levels of quality, and it also
      shows the use of several different filters used in conjunction to pick up a
      variety of reconstructed kernel names
      </description>
      <terminalInterface>
        <commandLine>
          'to=kernels.????.db
          type = ck
          <!--nadirdir = $Odyssey/kernels/ck -->
          reconfilter= *_nadir.bc
          recondir = $Odyssey/kernels/ck
          reconfilter= m01_sc_ab*.bc;m01_sc_ext?.bc;m01_sc_map.bc;m01_sc_map?.bc;m01_sc_map??.bc;m01_sc_map?_v2.bc'
          lsk = $Base/kernels/lsk/naif0008.tls
          sclk = $Odyssey/kernels/sclk/ORB1_SCLKSCET.00113.tsc'
        </commandLine>
        <description>
          This command line argument will create the database kernels.0001.db,
          assuming that file does not already exist in the target directory. As in the
          previous example, the command line argument is surrounded by single quotes
          in order to escape characters that would otherwise be considered special by
          the shell.
        </description>
      </terminalInterface>




      <guiInterfaces>
        <guiInterface>
          <image width="440" height="625" src="assets/images/odysseyCk.jpg">
            <brief>
            Example GUI
            </brief>
            <description>
              Screenshot of the GUI with parameters set to create a kernel database
              mixed with nadir kernels and reconstructed kernels.
            </description>
            <thumbnail width="220" height="312" caption="kerneldbgen gui"
             src="assets/thumbs/odysseyCk.jpg" />
          </image>
        </guiInterface>
      </guiInterfaces>




      <inputImages>
        <image width="702" height="468" src="assets/images/odysseyBefore.jpg">
          <brief>
            List of files before kerneldbgen has been run
          </brief>
          <description>
            As seen in this terminal snapshot, there are a number of files that will
            match the reconfilter in the directory specified by the recondir. The
            highest pivot_kernels version is 0001.
          </description>
          <thumbnail caption= "The directory before kerneldbgen"
           src="assets/thumbs/odysseyBefore.jpg" width="200" height="133"/>
          <parameterName>RECONDIR</parameterName>
        </image>
      </inputImages>




      <outputImages>
        <image width="702" height="468" src="assets/images/odysseyAfter.jpg">
          <brief>
            List of files after kerneldbgen has been run
          </brief>
          <description>
            None of the original files have been altered, but the versioning system
            has created the first version of the kernel database, kernels.0001.db.
            The content of this file is listed as well.
          </description>
          <thumbnail caption= "The directory after kerneldbgen"
          src="assets/thumbs/odysseyAfter.jpg" width="200" height="108"/>
          <parameterName>TO</parameterName>
        </image>
      </outputImages>
      <dataFiles>
        <dataFile path="assets/cumindex.tab">
          <brief>
            kernels.0001.db
          </brief>
          <description>
            Here one can examine the results of the datafile. Note the ascending
            order of kernel quality.
          </description>
          <parameterName>TO</parameterName>
        </dataFile>
      </dataFiles>
    </example>





  </examples>
</application>
