<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="dawnfc2isis" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">

  <brief>Import PDS formatted Dawn FC EDR or RDR image cube into Isis format cube</brief>

  <description>
    <p>
    This application will import a PDS formatted Dawn Framing Camera (FC) level
    1 (EDR) or level 2 (RDR) radiometrically calibrated image into an Isis cube.
    The resulting cube ("TO" parameter) will function properly in other ISIS
    cartographic software such as "spiceinit" and "cam2map".   The Dawn FC EDRs
    and RDRs will be available for download from the PDS Small Bodies Node at
    http://pdssbn.astro.umd.edu/. </p>

    <p>
    Although allowed in PDS standards, Dawn EDR and RDR files are arranged in a
    rarely used spatial storage order.  That is,  the bottom line of the image
    is stored first within the image array object contained in the PDS file. 
    This
    application modifies the arrangement by reversing the line storage order in
    the output cube; however,  be aware that other
    non-ISIS software may not apply the reversal.
    Therefore a Dawn image may appear to be flipped from top-to-bottom when
    comparing to ISIS cubes.
    </p>

    <p>
    Please note that ancillary Dawn PDS products such as mosaics or other map
    projected RDRs should not be used as input to this program.  Instead use the
    general "pds2isis" program.
    </p>
  </description>

  <history>
    <change name="Janet Barrett" date="2010-03-10">
      Original version
    </change>
    <change name="Janet Barrett" date="2010-04-15">
      The program now automatically flips the image in the line direction.
    </change>
    <change name="Sharmila Prasad" date="2011-01-21">
      Changed the category
    </change>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2011-03-14">
        Removed tests on HorizontalPixelScale and VerticalPixelScale; Added
        optional TARGET parameter to allow TargetName specification.
    </change>
    <change name="Jeff Anderson" date="2011-07-26">
    	Changed the program to write the NaifFrameCode in the labels to include
    	the filter number.  This was done because the Dawn FC team provided a new
    	instrument kernel (IK) with band dependent focal lengths and optical
    	distortion parameters. The camera model then uses this update label
    	keyword to read the correct camera parameters.
    </change>
    <change name="Jeff Andersoni and Chris Isbell" date="2011-10-05">
      Improved the user documentation
    </change>
  </history>

  <category>
    <missionItem>Dawn</missionItem>
  </category>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Select a PDS Dawn EDR or RDR file
        </brief>
        <description>
          Use this parameter to select an existing Dawn EDR or RDR filename.
      	  This file must contain the PDS labels.  The program will apply a
          sanity check to make sure the labels match the expected Dawn PDS
          format and report a user error if they are unacceptable.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.img *.IMG
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TO">
         <type>cube</type>
         <fileMode>output</fileMode>
         <brief>
           Output Isis cube
         </brief>
         <description>
           Use this parameter to define the output ISIS cube filename
         </description>
         <filter>
           *.cub
         </filter>
       </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Parameters">
        <parameter name="TARGET">
            <type>string</type>
            <brief>Provide target name if it needs to be changed</brief>
            <description>
              In order for ISIS cartographic applications  to properly function
              a TARGET_NAME keyword and value must be present in the source PDS
              labels. During the cruise phase of the Dawn mission, preliminary
              versions of the Dawn PDS EDRs and RDRs at times did not contain
              the TARGET_NAME or it was left blank.   This parameter allows the
              user to correct that oversight by providing "MARS" or "VESTA" as
              the parameter value.  Also, star observations were made and
              recorded in the TARGET_NAME.  The various star names are not
              recognized by ISIS and this application will produce an unknown
              target error message. If you plan to use some of the ISIS sky
              projection programs such as "skymap" or "skypt" you can set the
              this parameter to "SKY".
              <p>
                If this parameter is not provided it will use the value in the
                PDS labels given by TARGET_NAME.
              </p>
            </description>
            <internalDefault>Label Value</internalDefault>
        </parameter>
    </group>

  </groups>
</application>
