<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="mimap2isis" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">

  <brief>Import PDS formatted Kaguya MI MAP file to ISIS cube format</brief>

  <description>
    <p>
      This program converts PDS formatted Kaguya MI MAP files to ISIS
      <def link="Cube">cube</def> format.
    </p>
    <p>
      The PDS formatted MI MAP file is a 9-band mosaic of derived data products.
      The Kaguya (SELENE) mission's Lunar Imager/Spectrometer (LISM) Multi-band
      Imager (MI) instrument acquired 5 bands of visible and 4 bands of
      near-infrared images. The MI images in the mosaic have been radiometrically
      calibrated, tone matched, projected to a simple cylindrical projection, and
      mosaicked.
    </p>
    <p>
      <b>Input:</b>
    </p>
    <p>
      The FROM parameter is used to specify a standard PDS file or a detached label
      file. Both the detached label and the associated image file must exist in the
      same working directory. The IMAGE parameter does not need to be defined, unless
      the program cannot find the image file specified in the label file upon the
      program's execution.
      <ul>
        <li>Standard PDS formatted file (attached label)</li>
        <li>Detached label file</li>
        <li>Image file without labels</li>
      </ul>
    </p>
    <p>
      <b>Output:</b>
    </p>
    <p>
      An ISIS formatted multi-band cube with corrected labels is output to the
      filename specified.
    </p>
    <p>
      <b>Default Settings:</b> The default settings normally result in successful
      ingestion of Kaguya MI MAP products. Occasionally, the user must modify
      default values to obtain an image that meets specific requirements. The
      program will apply a correction by changing the sign of the SAMPLE_PROJECTION_OFFSET
      keyword value. The modified label is written to a temporary detached label file
      and then used to import the Kaguya MI MAP file into ISIS.
    </p>
    <p>
      <b>Special Pixel Assignment:</b> The incoming special pixel values are assigned
      equivalent values for special pixels in ISIS. If any incoming pixel value falls
      within two different special pixel types, the special pixel with the higher priority
      is assigned. The precedence for special pixels in ISIS from highest to lowest is
      1)<b>NULL</b>, 2)<b>HRS</b>, 3)<b>LRS</b>, 4)<b>HIS</b>, and 5)<b>LIS</b>.
    </p>
    <p>
      The user may also specify a range of input pixel values to be assigned to specific
      ISIS special pixels. If the range of pixel values defined by the user for the
      different special pixels overlap, the special pixel with the highest priority is
      assigned. For example, if NULLMIN=0.0, NULLMAX=3.0, LISMIN=3.0, and LISMAX=5.0,
      the actual raw value 3.0 could be designated as NULL or LIS; however, the actual
      assignment is NULL (highest priority).
    </p>
    <p>
      <b>Processing Notes:</b> If the output MI MAP cubes are to be mosaicked using
      programs such as automos, then please be aware that you must set the matchbandbin
      option to false when mosaicking. This is required because the BaseBand keyword in
      each file will not always match and this will cause your mosaic to fail if you
      don't set the matchbandbin option to false.
    </p>
  </description>

  <history>
    <change name="Janet Barrett" date="2013-12-11">
      Original version. Created by modifying the pds2isis program.
      Fixes #1919.
    </change>
    <change name="Janet Richie" date="2013-12-12">
      Reviewed documentation. References #1919.
    </change>
    <change name="Janet Barrett" date="2014-01-16">
      Added additional translation for other keywords in the
      PDS label. Fixes #1959.
    </change>
    <change name="Adam Paquette" date="2016-08-04">
      Added seperate translation table for L3C labels.
      Fixes #2358.
    </change>
    <change name="Summer Stapleton" date ="2017-06-27">
      Added conditional to check whether default offsets and multipliers where changed from their
      default values and log them if so.
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Combs" date ="2018-01-19">
      Changed call to SetPdsFile to reflect changes to PvlToPvlTranslationManager. Fixes #4345,
      #4421.
    </change>
  </history>

  <category>
    <missionItem>Kaguya</missionItem>
  </category>

  <groups>

    <group name="Files">

      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input PDS file or PDS detached label
        </brief>
        <description>
          Specify a PDS file or PDS detached label file. If the
	  input file is a PDS detached label file and the companion image
	  file is not in the same directory, use the IMAGE parameter to
	  define the location and filename of the image, otherwise just
	  enter the label file name.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.lbl *.img
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="IMAGE">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Detached image file
        </brief>
        <description>
          Use this parameter if the pointer to the image data in the
          detached label file (FROM) is not correct.
        </description>
        <internalDefault>
          Cube data embedded with label or file pointer in label file
        </internalDefault>
        <filter>
          *.img
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TO">
         <type>cube</type>
         <fileMode>output</fileMode>
         <brief>
           Output cube file
         </brief>
         <description>
           Use this parameter to specify the output cube filename.
         </description>
         <filter>
           *.cub
         </filter>
       </parameter>

    </group>

    <group name="Special Pixels">

      <parameter name="SETNULLRANGE">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default>
          <item>NO</item>
        </default>
        <brief>Option to convert pixel values to NULL</brief>
        <description>
	  Specify if valid input pixel will be set to NULL. If this option is set to
	  "yes" or "true", a range of input raw pixels defined by the NULLMIN and NULLMAX
	  parameters are converted to <def>NULL</def> pixels. All other valid pixels
	  that do not fall within the ranges specified for LIS, LRS, HIS, and HRS pixels
	  are transferred to the output file unchanged. If the <def link="Bit Type">bit type</def>
	  of the input file is changed, the NULL and HRS <def link="Special Pixels">special
	  pixels</def> may be incorrectly set to valid pixel values. For example,
	  if a raw 8-bit file is output to 16 or 32-bit, the pixel values "0"
	  and "255" may be converted to actual values instead of retaining the
	  special pixel property. If the output file remains as 8-bit, then "0"
	  stays as NULL and "255" stays as HRS.
        </description>
        <inclusions>
          <item>NULLMIN</item>
          <item>NULLMAX</item>
        </inclusions>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="NULLMIN">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief> Minimum value for NULL</brief>
        <description>
          Specify the minimum pixel value to set to <def>NULL</def>. All values
          greater than or equal to NULLMIN and less than or equal to NULLMAX are
          converted to NULL.
        </description>
        <inclusions>
          <item>SETNULLRANGE</item>
        </inclusions>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="NULLMAX">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief> Maximum value for NULL </brief>
        <description>
          Specify the maximum pixel value to set to <def>NULL</def>. All values
          greater than or equal to NULLMIN and less than or equal to NULLMAX are
          converted to NULL.
        </description>
        <inclusions>
          <item>SETNULLRANGE</item>
        </inclusions>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="SETHRSRANGE">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default>
          <item>NO</item>
        </default>
        <brief>Option to convert pixel values to HRS</brief>
        <description>
	  Specify if valid input pixel value will be set to HRS. If this option
	  is set to "yes" or "true", a range of input raw pixels defined by the
	  HRSMIN and HRSMAX parameters are converted to HRS pixels. All other
	  valid pixels that do not fall within the ranges specified for LIS, LRS,
	  HIS, and NULL pixels are transferred to the output file unchanged. If
	  the <def link="Bit Type">bit type</def> of the input file is changed,
	  the NULL and HRS <def link="Special Pixels">special pixels</def> may be
	  incorrectly set to valid pixel values. For example, if a raw 8-bit file
	  is output to 16 or 32-bit, the pixel values "0" and "255" may be converted
	  to actual values instead of retaining the special pixel property. If the
	  output file remains as 8-bit, then "0" stays as NULL and "255" stays as HRS.
        </description>
        <inclusions>
          <item>HRSMIN</item>
          <item>HRSMAX</item>
        </inclusions>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="HRSMIN">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief> Minimum value for HRS</brief>
        <description>
          Specify the minimum pixel value to set to <def>HRS</def>. All values
          greater than or equal to HRSMIN and less than or equal to HRSMAX are
          converted to HRS.
        </description>
        <inclusions>
          <item>SETHRSRANGE</item>
        </inclusions>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="HRSMAX">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief> Maximum value for HRS</brief>
        <description>
          Specify the maximum pixel value to set to <def>HRS</def>. All values
          greater than or equal to HRSMIN and less than or equal to HRSMAX are
          converted to HRS.
        </description>
        <inclusions>
          <item>SETHRSRANGE</item>
        </inclusions>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="SETHISRANGE">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default>
          <item>NO</item>
        </default>
        <brief>Option to convert pixel values to HIS</brief>
        <description>
	  Specify if valid input pixel will be set to HIS. If this option is set
	  to "yes" or "true", a range of input raw pixels defined by the HISMIN
	  and HISMAX parameters are converted to HIS pixels. All other valid pixels
	  that do not fall within the ranges specified for LIS, LRS, HRS, and NULL
	  pixels are transferred to the output file unchanged.
        </description>
        <inclusions>
          <item>HISMIN</item>
          <item>HISMAX</item>
        </inclusions>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="HISMIN">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief> Minimum value for HIS</brief>
        <description>
          Specify the minimum pixel value to set to <def>HIS</def>. All values
          greater than or equal to HISMIN and less than or equal to HISMAX are
          converted to HIS.
        </description>
        <inclusions>
          <item>SETHISRANGE</item>
        </inclusions>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="HISMAX">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief> Maximum value for HIS</brief>
        <description>
          Specify the maximum pixel value to set to <def>HIS</def>. All values
          greater than or equal to HISMIN and less than or equal to HISMAX are
          converted to HIS.
        </description>
        <inclusions>
          <item>SETHISRANGE</item>
        </inclusions>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="SETLRSRANGE">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default>
          <item>NO</item>
        </default>
        <brief>Option to convert pixel values to LRS</brief>
        <description>
	  Specify if valid input pixel will be set to LRS. If this option is set
	  to "yes" or "true", a range of input raw pixels defined by the LRSMIN
	  and LRSMAX parameters are converted to LRS pixels. All other valid pixels
	  that do not fall within the ranges specified for LIS, HIS, HRS, and NULL
	  pixels are transferred to the output file unchanged.
        </description>
        <inclusions>
          <item>LRSMIN</item>
          <item>LRSMAX</item>
        </inclusions>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="LRSMIN">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief> Minimum value for LRS</brief>
        <description>
          Specify the minimum pixel value to set to <def>LRS</def>. All values
          greater than or equal to LRSMIN and less than or equal to LRSMAX are
          converted to LRS.
        </description>
        <inclusions>
          <item>SETLRSRANGE</item>
        </inclusions>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="LRSMAX">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief> Maximum value for LRS </brief>
        <description>
          Specify the maximum pixel value to set to <def>LRS</def>. All values
          greater than or equal to LRSMIN and less than or equal to LRSMAX are
          converted to LRS.
        </description>
        <inclusions>
          <item>SETLRSRANGE</item>
        </inclusions>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="SETLISRANGE">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default>
          <item>NO</item>
        </default>
        <brief>Option to convert pixel values to LIS</brief>
        <description>
	  Specify if valid input pixel will be set to LIS. If this option is set
	  to "yes" or "true", a range of input raw pixels defined by the LISMIN and
	  LISMAX parameters are converted to LIS pixels. All other valid pixels that
	  do not fall within the ranges specified for LRS, HIS, HRS, and NULL pixels
	  are transferred to the output file unchanged.
        </description>
        <inclusions>
          <item>LISMIN</item>
          <item>LISMAX</item>
        </inclusions>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="LISMIN">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief> Minimum value for LIS </brief>
        <description>
          Specify the minimum pixel value to set to <def>LIS</def>. All values greater
          than or equal to LISMIN and less than or equal to LISMAX are converted to LIS.
        </description>
        <inclusions>
          <item>SETLISRANGE</item>
        </inclusions>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="LISMAX">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief> Maximum value for LIS </brief>
        <description>
          Specify the maximum pixel value to set to <def>LIS</def>. All values greater
          than or equal to LISMIN and less than or equal to LISMAX are converted to LIS.
        </description>
        <inclusions>
          <item>SETLISRANGE</item>
        </inclusions>
      </parameter>

    </group>

  </groups>

</application>
