<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="slpmap" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">

  <brief>
    Creates cubes that have slope data or aspect data
  </brief>

  <description>
    This program will compute the slope or aspect of a cube.  Typically a digital terrian model is given as the input but other non-elevation datasets can be provided.  
    Horne's algorithm is used to compute the slope/aspect.   That is, given a 3x3 kernel:<pre>
   A  B  C
   D  E  F
   G  H  I</pre>
   it is convolved through the image and each output pixel is computed as follows:
<pre>
  <b>SLOPE EQUATION</b>
   [dz/dx] = ((C + 2F + I) - (A + 2D + G)) / (8 * X_PIXEL_RESOLUTION) 
   [dz/dy] = ((G + 2H + I) - (A + 2B + C)) / (8 * Y_PIXEL_RESOLUTION)

   slope = ATAN ( SQRT ( [dz/dx]^2 + [dz/dy]^2 ) )
   percentslope = slope / 90

  <b>ASPECT EQUATION</b>
   [dz/dx] = ((C + 2F + I) - (A + 2D + G)) / 8
   [dz/dy] = ((G + 2H + I) - (A + 2B + C)) / 8

   aspect = 90 - ATAN2 ([dz/dy], -[dz/dx])
   if (aspect &lt; 0) then aspect = aspect + 360
</pre>
  Therefore slope is typically a number betwen 0 and 90 degrees which is flat to vertical slope, respectively.  The aspect represents the direction (0 to 360) of the slope in pixel space.  
  From the center pixel E, 0 degrees is straight towards B, 45 towards C, 90 is towards F, 135 towards I, 180 towards H, and so on.  The user has the opportunity to output the slope in
  radians, degrees, or percent slope.  The aspect can be in degrees or radians.

  <p>
    The above slope equation assume the pixels are not square; hence X_PIXEL_RESOLUTION and Y_PIXEL_RESOLUTION.  That is, the x distance across the pixel is not equal to the y distance 
    from top to 
    the bottom of the pixel.   By default the program will attempt to remove any scaling difference by using the map projection information (PIXRES=AUTOMATIC).  This computation is done at
    every pixel so that the correct x-to-y ratio is computed.  This is important for global maps where the ratio deviates as you move away from the latitude and/or longitude of true scale in the 
    map projection.    If the image lacks a map projection then the user must provide the pixel resolution, assumed to be square via PIXRES=USER.  The user then provides a single value 
    (RESOLUTION) that will be applied to all pixels in the image and in both directions.  
  </p>
  <p>
    The second assumption is that the xy units are the same as the z (pixel) units.   By default the program assumes the units are the same but allows the user to scale the z units to the xy units
    using the CONVERSIONFACTOR parameter.
  </p>
  
  </description>

  <history>
    <change name="Brian Peck" date="2006-12-25">
      Original version
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2008-10-06">
      Changed slope and aspect algorithms
    </change>
    <change name="Jeff Anderson" date="2012-08-02">
     Changed the slope algorithm to compute the sample and line resolution
     at each pixel.  Previously the algorithm used the resolution at the
     center of the image. In projected images the resolution varies as you
     move away from the latitude and/or longitude of true scale.   Also, improved the
     documentation and added user options to output percent slope.
    </change>
  </history>

  <category>
   <categoryItem>Topography</categoryItem>
  </category>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input cube
        </brief>
        <description>
          Use this parameter to select input cube. All bands of the cube within the file
          will have the algorithm applied.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TO">
        <type>cube</type>
        <pixelType>real</pixelType>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Output cube
        </brief>
        <description>
          Use this parameter to define the filename of the resultant slope or aspect cube
        </description>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Output Options">
      <parameter name="OUTPUT">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>Type of output requested, slope, aspect, or percent slope</brief>
        <default><item>PERCENTSLOPE</item></default>
        <description>
          This determines the type of output pixels that will be created.  One of slope, aspect, or percent slope.
        </description>
      	<list>
      	  <option value="SLOPE">
      	    <brief>Create slope cube</brief>
      	    <description>
      	      This creates a slope cube.        
      	    </description>
      	  </option>
      	  <option value="ASPECT">
      	    <brief>Create aspect cube</brief>
      	    <description>
      	      This creates an aspect cube.  That is, the direction/azimuth of the slope.           
      	    </description>
            <exclusions>
              <item>PIXRES</item>
              <item>RESOLUTION</item>
              <item>CONVERSION</item>
            </exclusions>
      	  </option>
          <option value="PERCENTSLOPE">
            <brief>Create percent slope cube</brief>
            <description>
              This creates a slope cube whose pixel values are percentages (slope/90) instead of angles.
            </description>
            <exclusions>
              <item>UNITS</item>
            </exclusions>
          </option>
      	</list>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="UNITS">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>Units of the output image</brief>
        <default><item>DEGREES</item></default>
        <description>
          Units of the output pixels 
        </description>
        <list>
          <option value="RADIANS">
            <brief>Output pixels in radians</brief>
            <description>
              The output pixels will be in radians, between 0 and PI/2 for slope and 0 and 2PI for aspect.
            </description>
          </option>
          <option value="DEGREES">
            <brief>Output pixels in degrees</brief>
            <description>
              The output pixels wiil be in degrees, between 0 and 90 for slope and 0 and 360 for aspect
            </description>
          </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Scaling Options">
      <parameter name="CONVERSION">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief>Conversion from z units to spatial units</brief>
        <default><item>1.0</item></default>
        <description>
          Since the slope algorithm depends on cancelling out the units, the
          conversion factor from the z (input pixel) units to the xy (spatial) units needs to be considered.

          For example, if the
          xy units are meters and the z units are in kilometers the unit conversion factor should be 1000
          as we are converting z units to xy units.  

          The default is one which presumes the units are the same. 
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="PIXRES">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>Defines the pixel resolution (width and height) </brief>
        <default><item>AUTOMATIC</item></default>
        <description>
          This determines the how the resolution of the input pixels will be defined.
        </description>
        <list>
          <option value="AUTOMATIC">
            <brief>Automatically compute the resolution using the map projection</brief>
            <description>
              The program will use the map projection to automatically compute the resolution (X and Y) of each pixel in
              order to ensure the slope is computed properly.
            </description>
            <exclusions>
              <item>RESOLUTION</item>
            </exclusions>
          </option>
          <option value="USER">
            <brief>User defined pixel resolution</brief>
            <description>
              If the input cube does not have a map projection then this option can be used to define the
              resolution which is assumed to be square.   A single resolution is used for the entire image in both the
              X and Y directions.  Note:  If the pixel height varies significantly from the width,
              the slope will not be computed correctly.
            </description>
          </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="RESOLUTION">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief>Pixel resolution</brief>
        <description>
          Defines both the X and Y pixel resolution to be used across the entire image.  Note that if the pixel height varies significantly from the width, the slope
          will not be computed correctly.
         </description>
      </parameter>

    </group>
  </groups>

</application>
