<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="qnet" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">
  <brief>
    Create and edit control networks
  </brief>

  <description>
    <p>
      This program will create and edit control networks.  To run qnet, you will
      need to create a text file containing a list of all cubes in the control
      network. These cubes must be un-projected, level 1 cubes. Optionally, you 
      can also input an existing control network or when prompted for the 
      control network, select the "Cancel" button, and a new control network 
      will be created.  
    </p>

    <p>
      There are 3 core windows used in this application.
    </p>

    <h3>qnet window</h3>
     The main qnet window is similar to the qview application.  You will see
     many of the same tools, such as "Band Selection", "Zoom", "Pan",
     "Stretch" and "Find" along the right border. The "Tie" tool is the last
     button along the right toolbar. It will be the default tool selected when
     "qnet" is launched.
    <p>
      In this window, select the "Open network" button or the open action (from 
      File menu), and open the file containing the list of cubes in the network. 
      You will then be prompted for the control network file. If you are editing 
      an existing one, choose that file.  If you are creating a new control 
      network, choose the "Cancel" button.
    </p>
    <p>
      Cubes may be opened in the main qnet window selected from the list in
      the Control Network Navigator window.  Points on these cubes are color
      coded as follows:
    </p>
    <pre>
      <strong>green "+"</strong> control point 

      <strong>magenta "+"</strong> ground point

      <strong>yellow "+"</strong> ignore point 

      <strong>red "+"</strong> point currently being edited (i.e. in Qnet Tool window) 
      
      window) 
    </pre> 
      When the "Tie" tool is activated, the mouse buttons have the following 
      function in the cube viewports of the main qnet window:
    <pre>
      <strong>Left Button:</strong>  Modify the closest control point

      <strong>Middle Button:</strong>  Delete the closest control point 

      <strong>Right Button:</strong>  Create new control point
    </pre>

    <h3>Control Network Navigator window</h3>
    <p>
      The Control Network Navigator displays a list of cubes or points in the
      control network.  The user may choose to open cube(s) in the qnet window or
      filter the list on different attributes.
    </p>
    <p>
      <strong>Points -</strong> default list for the Control Network Navigator.  
      With this selected, the user may click any of the following buttons:
    </p>
    <pre>
      <strong>"View Cube(s)"</strong> to open all cubes containing the selected 
      point(s) 

      <strong>"Modify Point"</strong> (or <strong>double click</strong> list 
      item) to edit the point using the Qnet Tool 
      
      <strong>"Ignore Point(s)"</strong> to set selected points to "Ignore"
      
      <strong>"Delete Point(s)"</strong> to remove selected points from the 
      control network 
      
      <strong>"Filter"</strong> to list all points from the currently displayed
      list that meet the new filtering criteria selected.  **Note** If the 
      currently displayed list is already filtered, the new list will only 
      display points that meet the criteria of all filters previously chosen
      until the user resets the list.
      
      <strong>"Show All"</strong> to reset the displayed list to all points in 
      the network 
    </pre>  
    There are 9 filters for the points list which display the following:
    <pre>
      <strong>Error:</strong> points with bundle adjustment errors within the 
      user specified range 
      
      <strong>Point ID:</strong> points whose Point Id contains the user 
      specified string 
      
      <strong>Number of Measures:</strong> points that are contained in (at 
      least or no more than) the user specified number of images 
      
      <strong>Point Properties:</strong> points that have the user specified 
        property.  Note: If all of the measures in a point are ignored, then 
        this point will be returned in the ignored point filter.
      
      <strong>Range:</strong> points that lie within the user specified 
      latitudinal and longitudinal ranges 
      
      <strong>Distance:</strong> points that are within the user specified 
      distance of some other point in the control network 
      
      <strong>Measure Properties:</strong> points that contain at least one 
        measure that matches the selected ingore status and one of the selected 
        types 
      
      <strong>Goodness of Fit:</strong> points that contain at least one measure 
      whose Goodness of Fit is within the user specified range 

      <strong>Cube Name(s):</strong> points that contain at a measure whose 
      serial number matches that of the user chosen cube filename
    </pre>
    <p>
      <strong>Cubes -</strong> With this selected, the user may click any of the 
      following buttons:
    </p>
    <pre>
      <strong>"View Cube(s)"</strong> to open all selected cubes  
      
      <strong>"Filter"</strong> to list all cubes from the currently displayed
      list that meet the new filtering criteria selected.  **Note** If the 
      currently displayed list is already filtered, the new list will only 
      display cubes that meet the criteria of all filters previously chosen
      until the user resets the list.
      
      <strong>"Show All"</strong> to reset the list to all images in the network 
    </pre> 
    There are 3 filters for the cubes list which display the following:
    <pre>
      <strong>Cube Name:</strong> cubes whose file name contains the user 
      specified string 
      
      <strong>Number of Points:</strong> cubes containing (at least or no more 
      than) the user specified number of points 
      
      <strong>Distance:</strong> cubes that contain at least one pair of points 
      that are within the user specified distance from each other 
    </pre>
    
    <h3>Qnet Tool window</h3>
      This is the point editor window of qnet for modifying or creating a 
      point.  The window will display the cube that is the "Reference" cube 
      on the left and the next cube in the control point on the right. Only 
      the control measure on the right hand side can be moved.  The measure 
      can be adjusted by:
    <pre>
      move to the cursor position under the crosshair by clicking the left mouse button

      move 1 pixel at a time by using arrow keys on the keyboard 

      move 1 pixel at a time by using arrow buttons above the right view
    </pre>
    Other point editor functions / options include the following:
    <pre>

      <i>In the File menu:</i>
      <strong>
        
      </strong>
      <i>In the Registration menu:</i>
        <strong>Open registration template</strong> Set registration template. 
      
      <strong>View/edit registration template</strong> View, edit and save 
      registration templates.

      <strong>Save registartion chips</strong> Save the cube chips used
        to perform registration.  These are usually only used for debugging
        registration parameters.   

      <i>Along the left border of the window:</i>
        <strong>Geom:</strong>  Geom the right view to match the left view 
        
        <strong>Rotate:</strong>  Rotate the right view
    
      <i>Below the left view:</i>
        <strong>Blink controls:</strong>  Blink the left and right view in the
        left view window using the "Blink Start" button (with play icon) and 
        "Blink Stop" button (with stop icon).  The arrow keys above the right view 
        may be used to move the right view in order to update the blinking in real 
        time.
      
        <strong>Find:</strong>   Center the right view so that the same latitude / 
        longitude is under the crosshair as the left view. 
        
        <strong>Add Measure(s) to Point:</strong>  Add control measure(s) to the 
        current control point. 
      
      <i>Below the right view:</i>
        <strong>Register:</strong>  Sub-pixel register the the right view to
        the left view.
        
        <strong>Save Point:</strong>  Save the control measure under the right 
        view in the control network. 
    </pre>
  </description>

  <category>
    <categoryItem>Control Networks</categoryItem>
    <categoryItem>Display</categoryItem>
  </category>

  <history>
    <change name="Jeff Anderson, Elizabeth Miller, Stuart Sides, Tracie Sucharski" date="2006-11-01">
      Original version
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2007-07-23">
      Added to Control Networks category
    </change>
    <change name="Tracie Sucharski" date="2008-10-06">
      Refactor of underlying classes
    </change>
    <change name="Jeannie Walldren" date="2008-11-24">
      Changed the name of the "Tie Point Tool" window to "Qnet Tool". 
      
      Added "Close" command to the drop down File menu on the "Qnet Tool" 
      window's  menu bar.  
      
      Added Qt's wait cursor (i.e. clock or hourglass) to indicate that there is
      background activity when the "Filter" or "View Cube(s)" buttons have been
      clicked on the "Control Network Navigator" window. 
      
      Added message box when the user creates a new point and tries to give it a
      Point ID that already exists in the Control network.  Previously this
      resulted in a PROGRAMMER ERROR from ControlPoint. Now, the user will be
      alerted in a message box and prompted to enter a new value for the Point
      ID.  

      Replaced references to PointEdit class with ControlPointEdit.

      Added "Goodness of Fit" to "Qnet Tool" right and left measure info.
    </change>
    <change name="Jeannie Walldren" date="2008-11-26">
      Added "Goodness of Fit" filter to the tabs for the "Points" section of the 
      "Control Network Navigator" window.  This filter returns all points that 
      have at least one measure that falls inside the user specified range.

      Added "Number of Measures" to "Qnet Tool" window below "Point ID".

      Modified code to pre-set the Point ID value in the "New Point Dialog" 
      window to the last Point ID entered in the dialog box. This value is 
      highlighted so the user may begin typing over the name without needing to 
      backspace.

      Changed the "Qnet Tool" title bar to display the name of the ControlNet 
      file open.

      Added message box when saving an "Ignore" point in the "Qnet Tool" to ask 
      if user wants to set Ignore=false.

      Modified the "Distance" filter in the "Points" section of the "Control 
      Network Navigator" window to improve efficiency and accuracy.
    </change>
    <change name="Tracie Sucharski" date="2008-11-26">
      Removed plot tool and all polygon references-this funtionality will be in 
      qmos.
    </change>
    <change name="Jeannie Walldren" date="2008-12-03">
      Modified the "Distance" filter in the "Cubes" section of the "Control 
      Network Navigator" window to improve efficiency and accuracy, and to allow 
      the user to select a distance in meters or pixels.
    </change>
    <change name="Jeannie Walldren" date="2008-12-08">
      Added connection from "x" in upper right corner to "Exit" command under 
      the "File" menu of the main window.
    </change>
    <change name="Jeannie Walldren" date="2008-12-10">
      Added functionality to "Qnet Tool" can set, view, edit and save changes 
      for a template file.  This is located in the "Options" menu under 
      "Registration" as the "Set registration template" and "View/edit 
      registration template" actions.  Added "What's this?" descriptions to 
      "Qnet Tool" window actions.
    </change>
    <change name="Tracie Sucharski" date="2008-12-19">
      Added "Ignore Points" and "Delete Points" to the Control Navigator tool.
    </change>
    <change name="Jeannie Walldren" date="2008-12-29">
      Added question boxes when the "Delete Points" or "Ignore Points" buttons 
      are clicked in the Control Navigator to verify that the user wants to 
      delete or ignore the selected points.  Disabled "Ground Point" checkbox 
      in Qnet Tool window and added dialog window for determining 
      lat/lon/radius if user chooses to toggle the "Hold Point" checkbox to
      true.
    </change>
    <change name="Jeannie Walldren" date="2008-12-30">
      Modified Qnet Tool "Save Point" button to set the left and right measures
      to Ignore=False if the user chooses to set the point's Ignore=False.  
      Also, "Save Point" button will now update ChooserName and DateTime 
      keywords for altered measures.  Modified Control Network Navigator points
      list to set most recently edited point to the current item so that it may
      be easily deleted.
    </change>
    <change name="Jeannie Walldren" date="2008-12-31">
      Added keyboard shortcuts to buttons in Control Network Navigator window. 
      Added question box to Qnet Tool "Save Point" button to ask user whether 
      the reference measure should be replaced with the measure in the left
      viewport. 
    </change>
    <change name="Jeannie Walldren" date="2009-01-08">
      Updated user documentation.  Modified Control Network Navigator window to 
      filter on existing filtered list until user selects the "Show All" button,
      which will bring up all points in the control net or images in the serial
      number list.
    </change>
    <change name="Jeannie Walldren" date="2009-01-26">
      Added "Cube Name" filter to "Points" tab of Control Network Navigator 
      window.
    </change>
    <change name="Eric Hyer" date="2010-03-22">
      Discontinued forcing of gui style to windows
    </change>
    <change name="Eric Hyer" date="2010-05-20">
      Connected FindTool's recordPoint signal to AdvancedTrackTool's record slot
    </change>
    <change name="Jeannie Walldren" date="2010-06-14">
      Modified to uncheck "Held" in the QnetTool window if the "Cancel" button 
      is clicked in the Hold Point Dialog. Added a filter of Measure Properties 
      by Ignore Status to the Navigation Tool's Point Filters. Modified 
      Navigation Tool's Point Type filter to treat points as ignored if all 
      measures are ignored. Fixed bug that did not show proper colors of points 
      unless the QnetTool was open.  Updated documentation. 
    </change>
    <change name="Jeannie Walldren" date="2010-07-01">
      Modified to reopen the Navigation Tool whenever the Tie Tool on the tool 
      pad is activated. Modified to draw points selected in the QnetTool last 
      so they are always visible on top of the other points. Added some 
      documentation.
    </change>
    <change name="Tracie Sucharski" date="2011-">
      
    </change>
  </history>
</application>
