<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="qnet" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">
  <brief>
    Create and edit control networks
  </brief>

  <description>
    <p>
      This program will create and edit <def>control network</def>s.  Before running  qnet,
      you will need to create a text file containing a list of all cubes in the control
      network, 1 cube per line. These cubes must be un-projected, <def>level1</def> cubes.
      Optionally, you can also input an existing control network or when prompted
      for the control network, select the "Cancel" button, and a new control network 
      will be created.  
    </p>

    <p>
      In addition to selecting <def>control point</def>s between level 1 un-projected images,
      qnet may also be used to select ground control points, both Fixed  and
      Constrained points.   To select ground control points, you must select
      a ground source image.  This could be a Dem or shaded relief version
      of a Dem, a projected basemap or a level 1 image with updated camera
      pointing.  Optionally, a radius source file, Dem may also be entered 
      which would provide radii for the ground control point.  These files
      are entered from the <strong>File Menu</strong> on the main Qnet window.
      The ground source image is immediately displayed in the main Qnet
      window and new ground control points may be created by right-clicking
      on the ground source cube display.
    </p>

    <p>
      This program should be started by typing its name in a terminal, with no arguments. 
      This will start blank versions of the main Qnet window and the control network 
      navigator window.
      
      There are 3 core windows used in this application.
    </p>

    <h3>Qnet window</h3>
     The main qnet window is similar to the qview application.  You will see
     many of the same tools, such as "Band Selection", "Zoom", "Pan",
     "Stretch" and "Find" along the right border. The "Tie" tool is the last
     button along the right toolbar. It will be the default tool selected when
     "qnet" is launched.
    <p>
      In this window, select the "Open network" button or the open action (from 
      File menu), and open the file containing the list of cubes in the network. 
      You will then be prompted for the control network file. If you are editing 
      an existing one, choose that file.  If you are creating a new control 
      network, choose the "Cancel" button.
    </p>
    <p>
      Cubes may be displayed in the main qnet window throught two methods.
    <font size="-1"><ol>
      <li>Select a Point Id from those listed in the Control Network Navigator window,
         then single-click "View Cube(s)".</li>
      <li>In the Control Network Navigator window, change the combo-box selection
         from Points to Cubes, then double-click a cube filename, or single-click
         the cube filename, then single-click the "View Cube(s)" button.</li>
    </ol></font>
    </p>
    <p>
      Control Points will be drawn on the displayed cubes with the following colors:
    <font size="-1"><ul>
      <li><strong>green "+"</strong> control point</li>
      <li><strong>magenta "+"</strong> ground point</li>
      <li><strong>yellow "+"</strong> ignore point</li>
      <li><strong>red "+"</strong> point currently being edited (i.e. in Qnet Tool window)</li>
    </ul></font>
    </p>
      When the "Tie" tool is activated, the mouse buttons have the following 
      function in the cube viewports of the main qnet window:
    <font size="-1"><ul>
      <li><strong>Left Button:</strong>  Modify the closest control point</li>
      <li><strong>Middle Button:</strong>  Delete the closest control point</li>
      <li><strong>Right Button:</strong>  Create new control point</li>
    </ul></font>

    <h3>Control Network Navigator window</h3>
    <p>
      The Control Network Navigator displays a list of cubes or points in the
      control network.  The user may choose to open cube(s) in the qnet window,
      edit a control point or filter the point or cube lists on different attributes.
      By default, double-clicking on a Point Id in the point list will display
      that control point in the Qnet Tool window.  Double-clicking on a filename
      in the Cube list will display the chosen cube in the qnet main window.
    </p>
    <p>
      <strong>Points</strong> This is the default list for the Control Network Navigator.  
      When this is selected, the user may click any of the following buttons:
    </p>
    <p><font size="-1"><ul>
      <li><strong>"View Cube(s)"</strong> to open all cubes containing the selected 
      point(s)</li>
      <li><strong>"Modify Point"</strong> (or <strong>double click</strong> list 
      item) to edit the point using the Qnet Tool</li>
      <li><strong>"Ignore Point(s)"</strong> to set selected points to "Ignore"</li>
      <li><strong>"Delete Point(s)"</strong> to remove selected points from the 
      control network</li>
      <li><strong>"Filter"</strong> to list all points from the currently displayed
      list that meet the new filtering criteria selected.  **Note** If the 
      currently displayed list is already filtered, the new list will only 
      display points that meet the criteria of all filters previously chosen
      until the user resets the list.</li>
      <li><strong>"Show All"</strong> to reset the displayed list to all points in 
      the network</li>
    </ul></font></p>
    <blockquote>There are 9 filters for the points list which display the following:
      <blockquote>
      <p><font size="-1"><ul>
        <li><strong>Jigsaw Errors:</strong> points with bundle adjustment errors within
        the user specified range</li>
        <li><strong>Registration Errors:</strong> points with sub-pixel registration
        errors within the user specified range</li>
        <li><strong>Point ID:</strong> points whose Point Id contains the user 
        specified string</li>
        <li><strong>Number of Measures:</strong> points that are contained in (at 
        least or no more than) the user specified number of images.  The control point
        will contain at least the given number of <def>control measure</def>s.</li>
        <li><strong>Point Properties:</strong> points that have the user specified 
          property.  There are 3 options and any combination may be chosen.</li>
          <ul>
              <li>Filter by Point Type(s)</li>
              <li>Filter by Ignore Status
                    Note: If all of the measures in a point are ignored, then 
                          this point will be returned in the ignored point filter.</li>
              <li>Filter by Edit Lock Status</li>
          </ul>
        <li><strong>Range:</strong> points that lie within the user specified 
        latitudinal and longitudinal ranges</li>
        <li><strong>Distance:</strong> points that are within the user specified 
        distance of some other point in the control network</li>
        <li><strong>Measure Properties:</strong> points that contain at least one 
          control measure that matches the selected criteria</li>
          <ul>
            <li>Filter by Measure Type(s)</li>
            <li>Filter by Ignore Status</li>
            <li>Filter by Edit Lock Status</li>
          </ul>
        <li><strong>Goodness of Fit:</strong> points that contain at least one measure 
        whose Goodness of Fit is within the user specified range</li>
        <li><strong>Cube Name(s):</strong> points that contain at a measure whose 
        serial number matches that of the user chosen cube filename</li>
      </ul></font></p>
      </blockquote>
    </blockquote>
    <p>
      <strong>Cubes</strong> When this is selected, the user may click any of the 
      following buttons:
    </p>
    <p><font size="-1"><ul>
      <li><strong>"View Cube(s)"</strong> to open all selected cubes</li>
      <li><strong>"Filter"</strong> to list all cubes from the currently displayed
      list that meet the new filtering criteria selected. <br /> **Note** If the 
      currently displayed list is already filtered, the new list will only 
      display cubes that meet the criteria of all filters previously chosen
      until the user resets the list.</li>
      <li><strong>"Show All"</strong> to reset the list to all images in the network</li>
    </ul></font></p>
    <blockquote>There are 3 filters for the cubes list which display the following:
      <blockquote>
      <p><font size="-1"><ul>
        <li><strong>Cube Name:</strong> cubes whose file name contains the user 
             specified string</li>
        <li><strong>Number of Points:</strong> cubes containing (at least or no more 
              than) the user specified number of points</li>
        <li><strong>Distance:</strong> cubes that contain at least one pair of points 
            that are within the user specified distance from each other</li>
      </ul></font></p>
      </blockquote>
    </blockquote>
    
    <h3>Qnet Tool window</h3>
    <p>
      This is the point editor window of qnet for modifying or creating a control
      point.  This window will display information about the control point and
      two control measures are displayed.  Initially the measures displayed will
      be the "Reference" cube on the left and the next cube in the control point
      on the right. The measures displayed in the left and right side can be 
      chosen from the combo-boxes under the labels "Left Measure" and
      "Right Measure".  Only the control measure in the right view can be
      moved, so if you want to move the reference measure, you must display it
      in the right view. You can select the previous or next right measure with the
      shortcuts <strong>PageUp</strong> and <strong>PageDown</strong>, respectively.
    </p>
    <h4>Changing Measure Locations</h4>
      <p>
      The measure location can be adjusted by:
    <ul>
      <li>Move the cursor location under the crosshair by clicking the left mouse
          button</li>
      <li>Move 1 pixel at a time by using arrow keys on the keyboard</li>
      <li>Move 1 pixel at a time by using arrow buttons above the right view</li>
    </ul>
    </p>
    <h4>Other Point Editor Functions</h4>
      <p>Along the right border of the window:</p>
      <ul>
        <li><strong>Geom:</strong>   Geometrically match the right view to the left
            view</li>
        <li><strong>Rotate:</strong>   Rotate the right view using either the dial
            or entering degrees </li>
        <li><strong>Show control points:</strong>  Draw crosshairs at all control
             point locations visible within the view</li>
        <li><strong>Show crosshair:</strong>  Show a red crosshair across the entire
            view</li>
        <li><strong>Circle:</strong>  Draw circle which may help center measure
            on a crater</li>
      </ul>
      <p>Below the left view:</p>
      <ul>
        <li><strong>Blink controls:</strong>  Blink the left and right view in the
            left view window using the "Blink Start" button (with play icon) and 
            "Blink Stop" button (with stop icon).  Both arrow keys above the right view 
            and the keyboard arrow keys may be used to move the right view while
            blinking.</li>
        <li><strong>Find:</strong> Center the right view so that the same latitude / 
            longitude is under the crosshair as the left view. <strong>Shortcut: F</strong></li>
      </ul>
      <p>Below the right view:</p>
      <ul>
        <li><strong>Register:</strong>  Sub-pixel register the the right view to
            the left view. <strong>Shortcut: R</strong></li>
        <li><strong>Undo Registration:</strong> Undo the sub-pixel registration.
            <strong>Shortcut: U</strong></li>
        <li><strong>Save Measure:</strong>  Save the control measure under the
            right view to the edit control point. <strong>Shortcut: M</strong></li>
      </ul>
      <p>Along the bottom:</p>
      <ul>
        <li><strong>Add Measure(s) to Point:</strong>  Add control measure(s) to the 
            current control point.  A dialog will show all cubes in the network with
            those that fall at this control point's latitude and longitude highlighted.
            All cubes chosen will be added as control measures to this control point.
            <strong>Shortcut: A</strong></li>
        <li><strong>Save Point:</strong> Save the edit control point to the control
            network. <strong>Shortcut: P</strong></li>
      </ul>
    <h3>Measure Table window</h3>
    <p>This window will show all control measure data for the current edit control
       point.  The table can be sorted by clicking on any of the headers.</p>
  </description>

  <category>
    <categoryItem>Control Networks</categoryItem>
    <categoryItem>Display</categoryItem>
  </category>

  <history>
    <change name="Jeff Anderson, Elizabeth Miller, Stuart Sides, Tracie Sucharski" date="2006-11-01">
      Original version
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2007-07-23">
      Added to Control Networks category
    </change>
    <change name="Tracie Sucharski" date="2008-10-06">
      Refactor of underlying classes
    </change>
    <change name="Jeannie Walldren" date="2008-11-24">
      Changed the name of the "Tie Point Tool" window to "Qnet Tool". 
      
      Added "Close" command to the drop down File menu on the "Qnet Tool" 
      window's  menu bar.  
      
      Added Qt's wait cursor (i.e. clock or hourglass) to indicate that there is
      background activity when the "Filter" or "View Cube(s)" buttons have been
      clicked on the "Control Network Navigator" window. 
      
      Added message box when the user creates a new point and tries to give it a
      Point ID that already exists in the Control network.  Previously this
      resulted in a PROGRAMMER ERROR from ControlPoint. Now, the user will be
      alerted in a message box and prompted to enter a new value for the Point
      ID.  

      Replaced references to PointEdit class with ControlPointEdit.

      Added "Goodness of Fit" to "Qnet Tool" right and left measure info.
    </change>
    <change name="Jeannie Walldren" date="2008-11-26">
      Added "Goodness of Fit" filter to the tabs for the "Points" section of the 
      "Control Network Navigator" window.  This filter returns all points that 
      have at least one measure that falls inside the user specified range.

      Added "Number of Measures" to "Qnet Tool" window below "Point ID".

      Modified code to pre-set the Point ID value in the "New Point Dialog" 
      window to the last Point ID entered in the dialog box. This value is 
      highlighted so the user may begin typing over the name without needing to 
      backspace.

      Changed the "Qnet Tool" title bar to display the name of the ControlNet 
      file open.

      Added message box when saving an "Ignore" point in the "Qnet Tool" to ask 
      if user wants to set Ignore=false.

      Modified the "Distance" filter in the "Points" section of the "Control 
      Network Navigator" window to improve efficiency and accuracy.
    </change>
    <change name="Tracie Sucharski" date="2008-11-26">
      Removed plot tool and all polygon references-this funtionality will be in 
      qmos.
    </change>
    <change name="Jeannie Walldren" date="2008-12-03">
      Modified the "Distance" filter in the "Cubes" section of the "Control 
      Network Navigator" window to improve efficiency and accuracy, and to allow 
      the user to select a distance in meters or pixels.
    </change>
    <change name="Jeannie Walldren" date="2008-12-08">
      Added connection from "x" in upper right corner to "Exit" command under 
      the "File" menu of the main window.
    </change>
    <change name="Jeannie Walldren" date="2008-12-10">
      Added functionality to "Qnet Tool" can set, view, edit and save changes 
      for a template file.  This is located in the "Options" menu under 
      "Registration" as the "Set registration template" and "View/edit 
      registration template" actions.  Added "What's this?" descriptions to 
      "Qnet Tool" window actions.
    </change>
    <change name="Tracie Sucharski" date="2008-12-19">
      Added "Ignore Points" and "Delete Points" to the Control Navigator tool.
    </change>
    <change name="Jeannie Walldren" date="2008-12-29">
      Added question boxes when the "Delete Points" or "Ignore Points" buttons 
      are clicked in the Control Navigator to verify that the user wants to 
      delete or ignore the selected points.  Disabled "Ground Point" checkbox 
      in Qnet Tool window and added dialog window for determining 
      lat/lon/radius if user chooses to toggle the "Hold Point" checkbox to
      true.
    </change>
    <change name="Jeannie Walldren" date="2008-12-30">
      Modified Qnet Tool "Save Point" button to set the left and right measures
      to Ignore=False if the user chooses to set the point's Ignore=False.  
      Also, "Save Point" button will now update ChooserName and DateTime 
      keywords for altered measures.  Modified Control Network Navigator points
      list to set most recently edited point to the current item so that it may
      be easily deleted.
    </change>
    <change name="Jeannie Walldren" date="2008-12-31">
      Added keyboard shortcuts to buttons in Control Network Navigator window. 
      Added question box to Qnet Tool "Save Point" button to ask user whether 
      the reference measure should be replaced with the measure in the left
      viewport. 
    </change>
    <change name="Jeannie Walldren" date="2009-01-08">
      Updated user documentation.  Modified Control Network Navigator window to 
      filter on existing filtered list until user selects the "Show All" button,
      which will bring up all points in the control net or images in the serial
      number list.
    </change>
    <change name="Jeannie Walldren" date="2009-01-26">
      Added "Cube Name" filter to "Points" tab of Control Network Navigator 
      window.
    </change>
    <change name="Eric Hyer" date="2010-03-22">
      Discontinued forcing of gui style to windows
    </change>
    <change name="Eric Hyer" date="2010-05-20">
      Connected FindTool's recordPoint signal to AdvancedTrackTool's record slot
    </change>
    <change name="Jeannie Walldren" date="2010-06-14">
      Modified to uncheck "Held" in the QnetTool window if the "Cancel" button 
      is clicked in the Hold Point Dialog. Added a filter of Measure Properties 
      by Ignore Status to the Navigation Tool's Point Filters. Modified 
      Navigation Tool's Point Type filter to treat points as ignored if all 
      measures are ignored. Fixed bug that did not show proper colors of points 
      unless the QnetTool was open.  Updated documentation. 
    </change>
    <change name="Jeannie Walldren" date="2010-07-01">
      Modified to reopen the Navigation Tool whenever the Tie Tool on the tool 
      pad is activated. Modified to draw points selected in the QnetTool last 
      so they are always visible on top of the other points. Added some 
      documentation.
    </change>
    <change name="Tracie Sucharski" date="2010-11-09">
      Fixed a bug in the Navigator when using the double-click option on the
      Cube list.
    </change>
    <change name="Eric Hyer" date="2010-11-19">
      Implement drawing control measures in the edit window displays.
    </change>
    <change name="Eric Hyer" date="2010-11-22">
      Added functionality to stretch the control point editor displays.
    </change>
    <change name="Eric Hyer" date="2010-12-03">
      In the new point and measure dialogs, put selected items at top of the list.
    </change>
    <change name="Eric Hyer" date="2010-12-08">
      Organize the look of the control point editor and add icons.  Display the
      sub-pixel registration template filename.
    </change>
    <change name="Eric Hyer" date="2010-12-14">
      Added an editor for the sub-pixel registration template file.
    </change>
    <change name="Tracie Sucharski" date="2010-12-17">
      Converted from the Pvl control network keywords to the binary version.
    </change>
    <change name="Tracie Sucharski" date="2011-03-08">
      Implemented ground point selection.
    </change>
    <change name="Tracie Sucharski" date="2011-04-04">
      Implement the SetApriori dialog.  Use the reference measure's lat/lon
      when adding new measures.  Print progress when reading control network
      and initialize the cameras on the images.
    </change>
    <change name="Tracie Sucharski" date="2011-04-13">
      Allow the SetApriori dialog to stay open and fill values from the 
      current edit point.
    </change>
    <change name="Tracie Sucharski" date="2011-04-20">
      When saving measure, if the left measure equals the right measure,
      copy right into left.
    </change>
    <change name="Tracie Sucharski" date="2011-04-28">
      In the Maximum residual filter, sort points by residual in descending order.
      Fix bug in SetApriori dialog with edit locked points.
    </change>
    <change name="Tracie Sucharski" date="2011-05-05">
      Update values in point editor in response to input to the SetApriori dialog.
    </change>
    <change name="Tracie Sucharski" date="2011-05-20">
      Fixed bugs in the measure type filter and reference measures.
    </change>
    <change name="Tracie Sucharski" date="2011-06-08">
      Changed Control Point types Ground to Fixed and Tie to Free.
    </change>
    <change name="Tracie Sucharski" date="2011-06-15">
      When changes are made to a measure or point, change the text
      color in the Save buttons to red.
    </change>
    <change name="Tracie Sucharski" date="2011-06-27">
      Forgot to turn Save buttons to red after auto-registration or using
      the Find button.
    </change>
    <change name="Tracie Sucharski" date="2011-06-28">
      Create a table showing the control measures with their corresponding data for
      the current edit control point.
    </change>
    <change name="Tracie Sucharski" date="2011-07-05">
      Added control point type to editor as a combo box.  Added error checking for
      edit locked points and refresh measure table.
    </change>
    <change name="Tracie Sucharski" date="2011-07-07">
      Grey out the Open Ground and Open Dem in the File menu until the cube list
      and control network have been opened.
    </change>
    <change name="Tracie Sucharski" date="2011-07-12">
      Added point registration error filter to the Navigator.
    </change>
    <change name="Tracie Sucharski" date="2011-07-18">
      Allow ground file to be loaded on the left of the point editor.
    </change>
    <change name="Tracie Sucharski" date="2011-07-25">
      Fixed a bug when deleting points from the Navigator.  Add option to the
      SetApriori dialog for calculating the surface point.
    </change>
    <change name="Tracie Sucharski" date="2011-07-27">
      Fixed bug reading the radius from the Dem.
    </change>
    <change name="Tracie Sucharski" date="2011-08-03">
      Highlight thte reference measure in the file selection combo boxes.
      Implement bilinear interpolation when reading radius from the Dem.
    </change>
    <change name="Tracie Sucharski" date="2011-08-08">
      Fixed bug when creating a new control network, forgot to set the 
      Target which caused program to crash when creating a new ground point.
    </change>
    <change name="Tracie Sucharski" date="2011-09-15">
      Speed up the blinking and drawing of control points on the cube
      viewports for large control networks.  Add an option for displaying
      other points besides the current edit point in the editor displays.
      If a control point has sigmas, do not erase when the point has been
      re-located.  Fixed the blinking problem with the measure table.
    </change>
    <change name="Tracie Sucharski" date="2011-09-16">
      Fixed bug when adding measures to a point when a ground source file
      is opened.  Draw fixed and constrained points on the ground source
      display.  If creating a ground point and no images intersect the 
      point, print an error.  In the new point dialog display the 
      intersecting images at the stop of the file selection list.
    </change>
    <change name="Tracie Sucharski" date="2011-09-22">
      Fixed the problem with duplicate warnings when saving Ignored measures.
    </change>
    <change name="Tracie Sucharski" date="2011-09-29">
      Updated documentation.  Implemented the "What's This" functionality
      to the control point editor.
    </change>
    <change name="Tracie Sucharski" date="2011-10-21">
      Fixed bug that caused qnet to crash when creating a new control network.
    </change>
    <change name="Tracie Sucharski" date="2011-10-31">
      Changed the Save button on the qnet tool to save to current network,
      rather than a "Save As".
    </change>
    <change name="Tracie Sucharski" date="2011-11-09">
      Fixed problem caused by an image in the list which did not have any
      measure associated with it.
    </change>
    <change name="Tracie Sucharski" date="2011-12-05">
      Fixed bug with measure table not displaying all information when 
      table has been sorted.
    </change>
    <change name="Tracie Sucharski" date="2012-01-11">
      Add error checking for creating point with invalid latitude, longitude.
    </change>
    <change name="Tracie Sucharski" date="2012-05-07">
      Fixed following bugs:  error when attempting to geom when using a ground
      source as the reference measure, problem un-locking a measure even
      if the point is un-locked and when changing between geom and rotate options,
      chips were not resettting correctly.
    </change>
    <change name="Tracie Sucharski" date="2012-05-08">
      Fixed bug that resulted in seg fault when deleting a point by middle clicking
      on a cubeviewport after creating a ground point.
    </change>
    <change name="Tracie Sucharski" date="2012-06-12">
      Fix made on 2012-05-07 caused a bug which would not allow a new measure
      to be set as the reference measure.
    </change>
    <change name="Tracie Sucharski" date="2012-07-30">
      Fixed bug which caused program to crash when left clicking on a cube when
      there are no control points.
    </change>
    <change name="Tracie Sucharski" date="2012-09-28">
      Fixed bug that resulted in a qt assert error when loading or creating a new
      ground point if the ground source file had the Instrument group in the labels.
    </change>
    <change name="Tracie Sucharski" date="2012-10-05">
      Improved error checking for opening a ground source file with the same serial
      number as a cube in the cube list.  This is not allowed, so an error with suggested
      solution is printed.
    </change>
    <change name="Tracie Sucharski" date="2013-05-16">
      Fixed bugs when attempting to delete a point in an empty network, deleting all
      measures in a point.  Fixed repetitive warnings when the current edit point does
      not fall on the ground source.  Fixes #1491, #1493, #1655.
    </change>
    <change name="Tracie Sucharski" date="2013-12-06">
      Fixed following bugs: seg fault when selecting a new reference measure and moving
      the point, seg fault when moving edit locked points without un-locking.
      Also, improved error checking on ignored reference measures on constrained and
      fixed points.  Fixes #1603, #1624.
    </change>
    <change name="Ian Humphrey" date="2015-10-07">
      Updated icons. Fixes #1041.
    </change>
    <change name="Ian Humphrey" date="2015-11-19">
      Added shortcuts to Qnet Tool window for selecting right measures, registration, saving 
      measures, saving a point, adding a new measure, find, and saving the control network. Fixes
      #2324.
    </change>
    <change name="Makayla Shepherd" date="2017-01-04">
      Fixed an issue that caused the Control Network Navigator to go behind the qnet main window 
      when using Gnome or Cinnamon. Fixes #4541.
    </change>
  </history>
</application>
