<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="spiceinit" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">
  <brief>
    Update SPICE data (kernels, pointing, and position) for a camera cube
  </brief>

  <description>
    <p>
      This program searches the ISIS data areas in order to discern the SPICE kernels required
      for the camera cube. Cubes which have supported camera models in the ISIS system require
      spacecraft position, pointing, body shape and orientation, sun position, and other
      information in order to compute ground positions (latitude/longitude) and photometric
      viewing angles. This information is stored in SPICE kernels.
    </p>

    <p>
      The program uses the "SpacecraftName", "InstrumentId", "TargetName", "StartTime", and
      "StopTime" keywords from the cube's label to determine which kernels to use.   It attempts to
      find kernel files for the following keywords and writes them to the Kernels group:
    </p>

    <ul>
      <li>Leap Second (LS)</li>
      <li>Spacecraft Clock (SCLK)</li>
      <li>Target Position (TSPK)</li>
      <li>Target AttitudeShape (PCK)</li>
      <li>Instrument (IK)</li>
      <li>Instrument Addendum (IAK)</li>
      <li>Frame (FK)</li>
      <li>Spacecraft Position (SPK) </li>
      <li>Instrument Pointing (CK)</li>
      <li>Shape Model (DEM)</li>
    </ul>

    If you are unfamilar with SPICE terminology it is recommended you read the NAIF required
    reading at http://naif.jpl.nasa.gov/naif/doc_C.html

    <p>
      The program modifies the kernels group and writes the name of the SPICE files that need to
      be loaded by the camera models.  It has the option of pre-reading the data from the SPICE
      kernels and loading it as a binary table attached to the cube.  This can faciliate faster load
      times and allows the instrument pointing to be easily updated.
    </p>
    <p>
      As kernels are loaded they override the data in previously loaded kernels.
      The order in which kernels are loaded is:
      <ol>
        <li>Target Position</li>
        <li>Instrument Position</li>
        <li>Instrument Pointing</li>
        <li>Frame</li>
        <li>Target Attitude Shape</li>
        <li>Instrument</li>
        <li>Instrument Addendum</li>
        <li>Leap Second</li>
        <li>Spacecraft Clock</li>
        <li>Extra</li>
      </ol>

      The spiceinit program will always try to use the highest quality kernels possible. This
      only applies to kernels that are not specified manually. The
      kernel qualities are, from best to worst:
      <ol>
        <li>Smithed</li>
          This is considered the best quality kernel and will be used first when
          selected.  Smithed kernels have been improved or adjusted for accuracy
          by a mission team or for the purpose of a cartographic product.
          Consider the source, content and completeness of Smithed kernels
          when selecting this level of quality.
        <li>Reconstructed</li>
          These kernels are typically produced by a mission a few weeks after the target has been reached.
        <li>Predicted</li>
          These are preliminary kernels produced by a mission and are the
          best-estimates of where the spacecraft will be at any given time.
        <li>Nadir</li>
          This is the worst quality kernel and is used as a last resort because it
          assumes the spacecraft is always nadir-looking.
      </ol>
    </p>
    <p>
      The <b>InstrumentPositionQuality</b> and <b>InstrumentPointingQuality</b> keywords are
      added to the Kernels group to indicate the level of quality of the loaded kernels. At least
      one of the parameters CKPREDICTED, CKNADIR, CKRECON, or CKSMITHED must be entered.
      Furthermore, at least one of the parameters SPKPREDICTED,  SPKRECON, or SPKSMITHED must be
      entered.
    </p>
    <p>
       Please note: Kernel Files specified that reside in the current working directory will
       not have their paths expanded.  This is to allow variables like $msg/ to work correctly.
    </p>
    <p>
      The spiceinit program will also add the RayTraceEngine, OnError, and Tolerance keywords to the Kernels
      group if specified in the IsisPreferences file. If included, these keywords specify the ray-tracing engine to use and how to use it for shapemodels.
      Please see the IsisPreferences file for more details.

    </p>
    <p><b>Troubleshooting:</b> If spiceinit is failing with the error
      "No Camera Kernel found for the image ..." then try enabling the
      "CKPREDICTED" or "CKNADIR" option. A similar error exists for SPK kernels,
      and you can enable "SPKPREDICTED" to get past that error. "PREDICTED" and
      "NADIR" options typically have less accuracy than reconstructed and smithed
      kernels which is why they are disabled by default.
    </p>
  </description>

  <category>
    <categoryItem>Cameras</categoryItem>
  </category>

  <history>
    <change name="Debbie A. Cook" date="2000-06-08">
      Original Version
    </change>
    <change name="Stuart Sides" date="2003-11-05">
      Complete rewrite under ISIS 3.0 conversion.
    </change>
    <change name="Stuart Sides" date="2004-01-14">
      Modified to use an existing "Kernels" group instead of creating a
      new one. This was because the mission specific import program
      (e.g., moc2isis) was modified to create the "kernels" group and
      put the "NaifFrameCode" into it.
    </change>
    <change name="Stuart Sides" date="2004-01-23">
      Added new parameter "TEST." This parameter controls the
      testing of the final kernel list. If false the kernels will not be
      tested for completeness by creating a camera model.
    </change>
    <change name="Stuart Sides" date="2004-02-23">
      Added elevation model DEM capabilities.
    </change>
    <change name="Stuart Sides" date="2004-02-24">
      Completed capabilities to search for kernels of different qualities
      such as PREDICTED, NADIR, RECONSTRUCTED, and C-SMITHED.
    </change>
    <change name="Stuart Sides" date="2005-11-08">
      Added fix for framing cameras, so they would not need a stop time in
      the instrument group of the labels.
    </change>
    <change name="Elizabeth Miller" date="2005-11-14">
      Added appTest
    </change>
    <change name="Jacob Danton" date="2005-12-22">
      Added support for multiple files within the kernels
    </change>
    <change name="Jacob Danton" date="2005-12-27">
      Added a progress bar
    </change>
    <change name="Jacob Danton" date="2006-01-03">
      Fixed the xml description
    </change>
    <change name="Jacob Danton" date="2006-01-25">
      Changed the mission translation file name
    </change>
    <change name="Jacob Danton" date="2006-01-25">
      Changed the appTest to comply with changes in the String class.
    </change>
    <change name="Jeff Anderson" date="2006-03-27">
      Modified to write InstrumentPointing, InstrumentPosition, SunPosition, and BodyRotation
      information to SPICE tables in the cube.
    </change>
    <change name="Brendan George" date="2006-09-19">
        Added call to  modify the history of the cube
    </change>
    <change name="Brendan George" date="2006-10-19">
        Modifed to remove label entries for SPICE tables, if ATTACH is unchecked,
        and the input cube already has them.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2007-07-10">
       Combined Frame and InstrumentPointing. Changed to support new version of KernelDb. Cleaned
       up the code.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright and Steve Koechle" date="2007-07-10">
       Fixed problem where the allowed kernels were being set improperly.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2007-08-10">
       Fixed so that when no spacecraft pointing is found, but frame kernels are, and Nadir is
       allowed it still adds the Nadir keyword.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Koechle" date="2007-10-05">
       Added a check to see if the cube had an existing polygon, if so delete it.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Koechle" date="2007-10-25">
       Fixed Smithed enum, changed from C-Smithed.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Koechle" date="2007-12-14">
        Added error handling logic. If the user chose to use Nadir CK and
        another type, and the system found a file where the image falls in a gap
        (no pointing is available) Nadir would never be calculated. Fixed.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2008-02-13">
       Added time padding options
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2008-02-21">
       Added additional explanation of time padding options
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2008-02-22">
       Split the CK parameter into FK and CK, they are still combined in the label as
       InstrumentPointing.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2008-04-14">
       All found CK kernels will now be tested before giving an error
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2008-05-02">
        Fixed the propagation of the EXTRA Kernel.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2008-05-12">
      Removed references to CubeInfo
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2008-05-19">
      Fixed documentation
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2008-06-03">
      Furthered documentation.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Koechle" date="2008-06-17">
      Added CK check and throw more appropriate error
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2008-09-12">
      Added the removal of StartPadding and EndPadding keywords from previous
      spiceinit runs, and added some double inited tests.  NOTE: Whenever
      adding new keywords, run spiceinit twice on the same cube in your test,
      dumping out both labels to verify that the keyword is not being
      duplicated.
    </change>
    <change name="Tracie Sucharski" date="2009-03-12">
      If spice is put into a Table, append the kernel name to the Kernel group
      keyword to keep track of original spice kernels.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Koechle" date="2009-05-12">
      Added CameraVersion into the Kernel labels
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2009-07-09">
      Error messages from the camera are now reported
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2009-07-21">
      Fixed handling of user-entered CK kernels
    </change>
    <change name="Janet Barrett and Steven Lambright" date="2011-05-25">
      Added support for storing text spice kernel values in the cube labels
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright and Jai Rideout" date="2011-08-30">
      Added support for using a spiceinit web service
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2011-10-05">
      As a result of our test and review team, I have updated the documentation
      to match the recommendations of Laz Kestay and Ken Edmundson. Fixes
      #423.
    </change>
    <change name="Jai Rideout" date="2011-11-18">
      Fixed bug in writing tables to the cube that were retrieved from the web
      service.
    </change>
    <change name="Debbie A. Cook" date="2012-07-06">
       Updated Spice members to be more compliant with ISIS coding standards.
       References #972.
    </change>
    <change name="Jeannie Backer" date="2013-02-26">
      Added ability to load multiple ck database files from the system using a
      conf file. Changed methods to lower camel case to comply with Isis3
      standards. Added web example. References #924.
    </change>
    <change name="Tammy Becker" date="2014-03-31">
      Made a few documentation modifications regarding kernel quality
      keywords and shapemodel keyword. References #1849.
    </change>
    <change name="Kimberly Oyama" date="2014-04-27">
      Added assets directory for web example. Updated Documentation. Fixes #1849.
    </change>
    <change name="Tyler Wilson" date="2016-12-19">
      Changed the URL for the spice server to https://services.isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/cgi-bin/spiceinit.cgi
      and the default port to 443 (it was originally 80).  This is due to the recent https migration implementation
      from within the Department of the Interior, which was causing people on the outside of the DOI network
      to get an unrecognized server response error when attempting to download spice data.  Fixes #4552.
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Combs" date="2017-06-01">
      Removed examples with links leading to missing images. Created two new examples:
      one with default settings and another with a user-chosen ShapeModel.
    </change>
    <change name="Kristin Berry" date="2017-06-06">
      Updated spiceinit to retain ShapeModel-related keywords set by the ShapeModelFactory and add them to the kernel
      group. Like other keywords in the kernels group, if they are present at the beginning of a spiceinit run (if we are re-spiceiniting)
      they are removed.
    </change>
    <change name="Kristin Berry" date="2017-08-06">
      Updated spiceinit to remove code dealing with the CubeSupported Pvl Keyword, from the ShapeModel group in the IsisPreferences file,
      which has been removed.
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Combs" date="2018-01-11">
      Made change to camera construction error throw for better reporting on uninstantiated cameras.
      Fixes #5163.
    </change>
    <change name="Jesse Mapel" date="2020-02-26">
      Changed PCK selection to use the same qualities as CK so that target body parameters
      derived from bundle adjustment can be used alongside CKs derived from bundle adjustment.
      Fixes #3669.
    </change>
  </history>

  <oldName>
    <item>levinit</item>
    <item>naiflab</item>
    <item>spicelab</item>
  </oldName>

  <groups>
    <group name="Input Files">
      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          The input cube for which the Kernels group will be updated.
        </brief>
        <description>
          The input cube for which the Kernels group will be updated. InstrumentPointing,
          InstrumentPosition, BodyRotation, and SunPosition tables will also be added to the cube.
        </description>
        <filter>*.cub</filter>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Spice Data">
      <parameter name="WEB">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>false</item></default>
        <brief>
          Use the ISIS SPICE Web Service
        </brief>
        <description>
          This option uses the ISIS SPICE Website to get the most up to
          date kernels available. The ATTACH parameter must be enabled for this option. Manually
          specifying kernel files is not allowed when this option is used. This service may
          be temporarily unavailable when new Isis releases are being
          distributed. Any mismatch in Isis version will cause this option to fail; only
          the most recent version of ISIS is supported. An active internet
          connection is required to use this service. Running with this option is slower than downloading the SPICE data locally (download all of $ISIS3DATA) and running spiceinit
          with the local data. This data can take up a lot of space. The size of the download
          will depend heavily on the mission and instrument of your input file.
        </description>
        <exclusions>
          <item>ATTACH</item>
          <item>LS</item>
          <item>PCK</item>
          <item>TSPK</item>
          <item>IK</item>
          <item>SCLK</item>
          <item>CK</item>
          <item>FK</item>
          <item>SPK</item>
          <item>IAK</item>
          <item>EXTRA</item>
        </exclusions>
        <inclusions>
          <item>URL</item>
          <item>PORT</item>
        </inclusions>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="ATTACH">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>TRUE</item></default>
        <brief>
          Attach SPICE data to cube
        </brief>
        <description>
          This option attaches binary tables to the cube which contain the
          instrument position (SPK) and orientation (CK), as well as the sun
          position and body/target orientation. This is the prefered
          initialization option as it allows the pointing to be updated by
          further programs.
        </description>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Instrument Orientation Kernel (CK) quality">
      <parameter name="CKSMITHED">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>FALSE</item></default>
        <brief>
          Use smithed (corrected) pointing kernels if available
        </brief>
        <description>
          Allow the use of pointing kernels marked as Smithed. If this parameter is selected,
          smithed kernels may be used to cover the time requirements of the image. Please
          consider the source, content, and completeness of a smithed ck-kernel before
          selecting. The keyword InstrumentPointingQuality=Smithed will be added to the Kernels
          group if this quality kernel is loaded.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="CKRECON">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>TRUE</item></default>
        <brief>
          Use reconstructed pointing kernels if available
        </brief>
        <description>
          Allow the use of pointing kernels marked as Reconstructed. This is the default option.
          If reconstructed kernels cannot be found for the given time range, the program will fail.
          The keyword InstrumentPointingQuality=Reconstructed will be added to the Kernels group
          if this quality kernel is loaded.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="CKPREDICTED">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>FALSE</item></default>
        <brief>
          Use predicted pointing kernels if available
        </brief>
        <description>
          Allow the use of pointing kernels marked as Predicted. The program will check the
          reconstructed kernels for the given time range first. If the time range is not found,
          spiceinit will check for predicted kernels. If predicted kernels cannot be found for
          the given time range, the program will fail. The keyword
          InstrumentPointingQuality=Predicted will be added to the Kernels group if this quality
          kernel is loaded.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="CKNADIR">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>FALSE</item></default>
        <brief>
          Compute nadir pointing if no other kernels exist
        </brief>
        <description>
          This option will create nadir pointing data. The higher quality kernels will be checked
          first. If the given time range cannot be found, spiceinit will use a nadir kernel. The
          keyword InstrumentPointingQuality=Nadir will be added to the Kernels group if this
          quality kernel is loaded.
        </description>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Instrument Position Kernel (SPK) quality">
      <parameter name="SPKSMITHED">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>FALSE</item></default>
        <brief>
          Use smithed (corrected) position kernels if available
        </brief>
        <description>
          Allow the use of position kernels marked as Smithed. If this parameter is turned on,
          smithed kernels may be used to cover the time requirements of the image. If a smithed
          kernel cannot be found, spiceinit will look for a reconstructed kernel for the given
          time frame. Please consider the source, content, and completeness of a smithed spk-kernel
          when selected. The keyword InstrumentPositionQuality=Smithed will be added to the
          Kernels group if this quality kernel is loaded.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="SPKRECON">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>TRUE</item></default>
        <brief>
          Use reconstructed position kernels if available
        </brief>
        <description>
          Allow the use of position kernels marked as Reconstructed. This is the default
          option. If no lower quality options are selected and spiceinit cannot find
          reconstructed kernels for the given time frame, the program will fail. The keyword
          InstrumentPositionQuality=Reconstructed will be added to the Kernels group if this
          quality kernel is loaded.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="SPKPREDICTED">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>FALSE</item></default>
        <brief>
          Use predicted pointing kernels if available
        </brief>
        <description>
          Allow the use of pointing kernels marked as Predicted. The program will check the
          reconstructed kernels for the given time range first. If the time range is not found,
          spiceinit will check for predicted kernels. If predicted kernels cannot be found for
          the given time range, the program will fail The keyword
          InstrumentPositionQuality=Predicted will be added to the Kernels group if this quality
          kernel is loaded.
        </description>
      </parameter>

    </group>

    <!--
    <group name="Kernel Database">
      <parameter name="DEFAULT">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>TRUE</item></default>
        <brief>
          Search the ISIS default database files for appropriate kernels
        </brief>
        <description>
          Allows the program to search kernel databases in the ISIS
          preference "BASE" and the mission specific ISIS preference
          (e.g., "MGS") for kernels file to satisfy the kernel label
          requirements.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="DATABASE">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <internalDefault>none</internalDefault>
        <brief>
          User defined kernel database file.
        </brief>
        <description>
          Kernel database to be used to find kernels for the
          input file. All kernels found in the user database will override any
          found in the default database.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.db
        </filter>
      </parameter>
    </group>
    -->

    <group name="User Override of System Kernels">
      <parameter name="LS">
        <type>filename</type>
        <internalDefault>none</internalDefault>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          User defined leap second kernel file.
        </brief>
        <description>
          NAIF kernel file to be used for the leap second in place of the automated leap second
          kernel. The LS kernel will be referenced in the keyword LeapSecond by the resulting
          Kernel group. If none is specified, spiceinit will use the latest kernel configuration
          file or kernel database file to find the appropriate kernel(s) for the given input file.
        </description>
        <defaultPath>
          $base/kernels/lsk/
        </defaultPath>
        <filter>*.tls</filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="PCK">
        <type>filename</type>
        <internalDefault>none</internalDefault>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          User defined target attitude and shape kernel file.
        </brief>
        <description>
          NAIF kernel file to be used for the target attitude and shape in place
          of the automated attitude and shape kernel. The PCK kernel will be
          referenced in the keyword TargetAttitudeShape by the resulting Kernel
          group.  If none is specified, spiceinit will use the latest kernel
          configuration file or kernel database file to find the appropriate kernel(s)
          for the given input file.
        </description>
        <defaultPath>
          $base/kernels/pck/
        </defaultPath>
        <filter>*.tpc</filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TSPK">
        <type>filename</type>
        <internalDefault>none</internalDefault>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          User defined target position kernel file.
        </brief>
        <description>
          NAIF kernel file to be used for the target position in place of the
          automated position kernel. The TSPK kernel will be referenced in the
          keyword TargetPosition by the resulting Kernel group.  If none is
          specified, spiceinit will use the latest kernel configuration file or kernel
          database file to find the appropriate kernel(s) for the given input
          file.
        </description>
        <defaultPath>
          $base/kernels/spk/
        </defaultPath>
        <filter>*.bsp</filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="IK">
        <type>filename</type>
        <internalDefault>none</internalDefault>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          User defined instrument kernel file.
        </brief>
        <description>
          NAIF kernel file to be used for the instrument in place of the
          automated instrument kernel. The IK kernel will be referenced in the
          keyword Instrument by the resulting Kernel group.  If none is
          specified, spiceinit will use the latest kernel configuration file or kernel
          database file to find the appropriate kernel(s) for the given input
          file.
        </description>
        <defaultPath>
          $ISIS3DATA
        </defaultPath>
        <filter>*.ti</filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="SCLK">
        <type>filename</type>
        <internalDefault>none</internalDefault>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          User defined spacecraft clock kernel file.
        </brief>
        <description>
          NAIF kernel file to be used for the spacecraft clock in place of the
          automated spacecraft clock kernel. The SCLK kernel will be referenced
          in the keyword Instrument by the resulting Kernel group.  If none is
          specified, spiceinit will use the latest kernel configuration file or kernel
          database file to find the appropriate kernel(s) for the given input
          file.
        </description>
        <defaultPath>
          $ISIS3DATA
        </defaultPath>
        <filter>*.tsc</filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="CK">
        <type>filename</type>
        <internalDefault>none</internalDefault>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          User defined spacecraft pointing kernel file.
        </brief>
        <description>
          NAIF kernel file to be used for the spacecraft pointing in place of
          the automated spacecraft pointing kernel. The CK kernel will be
          referenced in the keyword InstrumentPointing by the resulting Kernel
          group. If none is specified, spiceinit will use the latest kernel
          configuration file or kernel database file to find the appropriate kernel(s)
          for the given input file.
        </description>
        <defaultPath>
          $ISIS3DATA
        </defaultPath>
        <filter>*.bc</filter>
      </parameter>

       <parameter name="FK">
         <type>filename</type>
         <internalDefault>none</internalDefault>
         <fileMode>input</fileMode>
         <brief>
           User defined frames kernel file.
         </brief>
         <description>
           NAIF kernel file to be used for the instrument frame in place of the
           automated frames kernel. The FK kernel will be referenced in the
           keyword InstrumentPointing by the resulting Kernel group.
           Note: If you enter a filename for CK some instruments may require a
           frame kernel as well. If none is specified, spiceinit will use the
           latest kernel configuration file or kernel database file to find the
           appropriate kernel(s) for the given input file.
         </description>
         <defaultPath>
           $ISIS3DATA
         </defaultPath>
         <filter>*.tf</filter>
       </parameter>


      <parameter name="SPK">
        <type>filename</type>
        <internalDefault>none</internalDefault>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          User defined spacecraft position kernel file.
        </brief>
        <description>
          NAIF kernel file to be used for the spacecraft position in place of
          the automated spacecraft position kernel. The SPK kernel will be
          referenced in the keyword InstrumentPosition by the resulting Kernel
          group. If none is specified, spiceinit will use the latest kernel
          configuration file or kernel database file to find the appropriate kernel(s)
          for the given input file.
        </description>
        <defaultPath>
          $ISIS3DATA
        </defaultPath>
        <filter>*.bsp</filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="IAK">
        <type>filename</type>
        <internalDefault>none</internalDefault>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          User defined instrument addendum kernel file.
        </brief>
        <description>
          NAIF formatted kernel file to be used for the ISIS specific instrument
          addendum kernel, in place of the automated. The IAK kernel will be
          referenced in the keyword InstrumentAddendum by the resulting Kernel
          group. If none is specified, spiceinit will use the latest kernel
          configuration file or kernel database file to find the appropriate kernel(s)
          for the given input file.
        </description>
        <defaultPath>
          $ISIS3DATA
        </defaultPath>
        <filter>*.ti</filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="EXTRA">
        <type>filename</type>
        <internalDefault>none</internalDefault>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          User defined extra kernel file.
        </brief>
        <description>
          Optional extra NAIF formatted kernel file. The EXTRA kernel will be
          referenced in the keyword Extra by the resulting Kernel group.
        </description>
        <defaultPath>
          $ISIS3DATA
        </defaultPath>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Shape Model Parameters ">
      <parameter name="SHAPE">
        <type>string</type>
        <default><item>SYSTEM</item></default>
        <brief>
          Select the definition of the shape model
        </brief>
        <description>
          ISIS camera models can use a shape model (a  projected ISIS cube that defines the radii
          for a global or regional area).  You can choose to select a shape model or to use the
          definition of the ellipsoid found in the planetary constants (PCK) file.
        </description>
        <list>
          <option value="ELLIPSOID">
            <brief>Use triaxial ellipsoid from PCK</brief>
            <description>
               The camera will use the radii defined in the planetary constants file (PCK) when
               determining intersections of the body surface. The ShapeModel keyword will be set
               to NULL for an ellipsoid.
            </description>
            <exclusions>
              <item>MODEL</item>
            </exclusions>
          </option>
          <option value="RINGPLANE">
            <brief>Use the targets equatorial ring plane</brief>
            <description>
               The camera will use the targets equatorial ringplane for surface intersections.
               The ShapeModel keyword will be set to RINGPLANE.
            </description>
            <exclusions>
              <item>MODEL</item>
            </exclusions>
          </option>
          <option value="SYSTEM">
            <brief>Search system for a default shape model</brief>
            <description>
              This option will search the default system data area ($ISIS3DATA/base/dems) for a
              shape model that matches the target of the input cube.  If none are found, then no
              shape model will be used and the default ellipsoid parameters found in the
              planetary constants (PCK) file define the shape. The filename and path of the shape
              model loaded will be found in the cube labels Kernels Group in the <b>ShapeModel</b>
              keyword.
            </description>
            <exclusions>
              <item>MODEL</item>
            </exclusions>
          </option>
          <option value="USER">
            <brief>User specified shape model file</brief>
            <description>
               The camera will use shape model defined by the parameter MODEL.  The filename and
               path of the shape model loaded will be found in the cube labels Kernels Group in
               the <b>ShapeModel</b> keyword.
            </description>
          </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="MODEL">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          User defined ISIS cube shape model.
        </brief>
        <description>
          A map projected ISIS cube which contains the radii of the target.  The file can cover
          more than the input cube (FROM) but must minimally cover the data in the input cube.
          The filename and path of the shape model loaded will be found in the cube labels Kernels
          Group in the <b>ShapeModel</b> keyword.
        </description>
        <defaultPath>$base//dems/</defaultPath>
        <filter>
	  *.cub
	  *.bds
	</filter>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Time Parameters">
      <parameter name="STARTPAD">
        <type>double</type>
        <minimum inclusive="true">0.0</minimum>
        <brief>
            Time padding (in seconds) to load from the kernels before the start time of the image
        </brief>
        <description>
          When the kernels for an image are loaded, by default only what the image requires is
          loaded.  By setting this option, the loaded kernels start at the specified amount of
          time before the image start time. Using this option for framing cameras could
          significantly decrease the accuracy of the NAIF information because this will cause
          the information to be interpolated between the STARTPAD and ENDPAD.
        </description>
        <default><item>0.0</item></default>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="ENDPAD">
        <type>double</type>
        <minimum inclusive="true">0.0</minimum>
        <brief>
            Time padding (in seconds) to load from the kernels after the end time of the image
        </brief>
        <description>
          When the kernels for an image are loaded, by default only what the image requires is
          loaded.  By setting this option, the loaded kernels end at the specified amount of time
          after the image end time. Using this option for framing cameras could significantly
          decrease the accuracy of the NAIF information because this will cause the information
          to be interpolated between the STARTPAD and ENDPAD.
        </description>
        <default><item>0.0</item></default>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Spice Service Parameters">
      <parameter name="URL">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>The Spice Service URL</brief>
        <description>
          This is where a request for SPICE data is sent. The default is the USGS SPICE server.
        </description>
        <default><item>https://services.isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/cgi-bin/spiceinit.cgi</item></default>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="PORT">
        <type>integer</type>
        <brief>The Spice Service Port</brief>
        <description>
          This is the port on which a request for SPICE data is sent.
        </description>
        <default><item>443</item></default>
        <minimum inclusive="yes">0</minimum>
      </parameter>
    </group>
  </groups>

  <examples>
    <example>
      <brief>
        Example of spiceinit using default parameters.
      </brief>
      <description>
        This example shows how to use spiceinit using the default parameters. That is, the SPICE
        data will be attached to the cube labels (attach=yes). Only reconstructed kernel types
        will be allowed for CK and SPK kernels, the default system kernels will be found in
        the kernel database files, and no time parameters will be set.

        Because there is no default elevation model for Titan, spiceinit will set
        the ShapeModel keyword to "Null".
      </description>
      <terminalInterface>
        <commandLine>
          from=v1545949478_1.cub
        </commandLine>
        <description>
          An example of how to run this program with default parameters from the command line.
        </description>
      </terminalInterface>
      <guiInterfaces>
        <guiInterface>
          <image width="625" height="800" src="assets/images/spiceinit_example1.jpg">
          <brief>
            Example GUI
          </brief>
            <description>
              An example of how to run this program using the GUI. Note, the
              updated Kernel group can be seen in the log window.
            </description>
            <thumbnail width="239" height="300" src="assets/thumbs/spiceinit_thumb1.jpg" caption="Example of GUI command"/>
          </image>
        </guiInterface>
      </guiInterfaces>
      <dataFiles>
        <dataFile path="assets/dataFiles/v1545949478_1_after.pvl">
          <brief>
            Cube labels after spiceinit.
          </brief>
          <description>
            This is the label of the input cube after spiceinit has been
            run. The following groups were added to the cube's labels:
            <pre>
              Group = Kernels
                NaifFrameCode             = -82370
                LeapSecond                = $base/kernels/lsk/naif0012.tls
                TargetAttitudeShape       = ($base/kernels/pck/pck00009.tpc,
                                             $cassini/kernels/pck/cpck27Mar2017.tpc)
                TargetPosition            = (Table, $base/kernels/spk/de405.bsp)
                InstrumentPointing        = (Table, $cassini/kernels/ck/06357_06362ra.bc,
                                             $cassini/kernels/fk/cas_v40_usgs.tf)
                Instrument                = Null
                SpacecraftClock           = $cassini/kernels/sclk/cas00170.tsc
                InstrumentPosition        = (Table,
                                             $cassini/kernels/spk/070208R_SCPSE_06356_0700-
                                             8.bsp)
                InstrumentAddendum        = $cassini/kernels/iak/vimsAddendum03.ti
                ShapeModel                = Null
                InstrumentPositionQuality = Reconstructed
                InstrumentPointingQuality = Reconstructed
                CameraVersion             = 1
              End_Group

              Object = Table
                Name                = InstrumentPointing
                StartByte           = 6373579
                Bytes               = 4352
                Records             = 68
                ByteOrder           = Lsb
                TimeDependentFrames = (-82000, 1)
                ConstantFrames      = (-82370, -82000)
                ConstantRotation    = (0.99991568332482, 0.0014510663863786,
                                       -0.012904287946602, 0.012904407824453,
                                       -7.32810212777781e-05, 0.99991673197751,
                                       0.0014499999195506, -0.99999894451756,
                                       -9.19999948958952e-05)
                CkTableStartTime    = 220528381.47991
                CkTableEndTime      = 220529079.47551
                CkTableOriginalSize = 4096
                FrameTypeCode       = 3
                Description         = "Created by spiceinit"
                Kernels             = ($cassini/kernels/ck/06357_06362ra.bc,
                                       $cassini/kernels/fk/cas_v40_usgs.tf)

                Record Information
                .
                .
                .

              End_Object

              Object = Table
                Name                 = InstrumentPosition
                StartByte            = 6377931
                Bytes                = 6496
                Records              = 116
                ByteOrder            = Lsb
                CacheType            = HermiteSpline
                SpkTableStartTime    = 220528381.47991
                SpkTableEndTime      = 220529079.47551
                SpkTableOriginalSize = 4096.0
                Description          = "Created by spiceinit"
                Kernels              = $cassini/kernels/spk/070208R_SCPSE_06356_07008.bsp

                Record Information
                .
                .
                .

              End_Object

              Object = Table
                Name                = BodyRotation
                StartByte           = 6384427
                Bytes               = 128
                Records             = 2
                ByteOrder           = Lsb
                TimeDependentFrames = (10044, 1)
                CkTableStartTime    = 220528381.47991
                CkTableEndTime      = 220529079.47551
                CkTableOriginalSize = 2
                FrameTypeCode       = 2
                PoleRa              = (39.4827, 0.0, 0.0)
                PoleDec             = (83.4279, 0.0, 0.0)
                PrimeMeridian       = (186.5855, 22.5769768, 0.0)
                PoleRaNutPrec       = (0.0, 0.0, 0.0, 0.0, 0.0, 0.0, 0.0, 0.0, 0.0)
                PoleDecNutPrec      = (0.0, 0.0, 0.0, 0.0, 0.0, 0.0, 0.0, 0.0, 0.0)
                PmNutPrec           = (0.0, 0.0, 0.0, 0.0, 0.0, 0.0, 0.0, 0.0, 0.0)
                SysNutPrec0         = (353.32, 28.72, 177.4, 300.0, 316.45, 345.2, 29.8,
                                       706.64, 57.44)
                SysNutPrec1         = (75706.7, 75706.7, -36505.5, -7225.9, 506.2, -1016.3,
                                       -52.1, 151413.4, 151413.4)
                Description         = "Created by spiceinit"
                Kernels             = ($base/kernels/spk/de405.bsp,
                                       $base/kernels/pck/pck00009.tpc,
                                       $cassini/kernels/pck/cpck27Mar2017.tpc)
                SolarLongitude      = 312.76943291256

                Record Information
                .
                .
                .

              End_Object

              Object = Table
                Name                 = SunPosition
                StartByte            = 6384555
                Bytes                = 112
                Records              = 2
                ByteOrder            = Lsb
                CacheType            = Linear
                SpkTableStartTime    = 220528381.47991
                SpkTableEndTime      = 220529079.47551
                SpkTableOriginalSize = 2.0
                Description          = "Created by spiceinit"
                Kernels              = $base/kernels/spk/de405.bsp

                Record Information
                .
                .
                .

              End_Object

              Object = NaifKeywords
                BODY606_RADII                    = (2575.0, 2575.0, 2575.0)
                BODY_FRAME_CODE                  = 10044
                CLOCK_ET_-82_1545949478_COMPUTED = 802c35fdfd49aa41
                CLOCK_ET_-82_1545950172_COMPUTED = d3ea3269034aaa41
                INS-82370_TRANSX                 = (0.0, 1.0, 0.0)
                INS-82370_TRANSY                 = (0.0, 0.0, 1.0)
                INS-82370_ITRANSS                = (0.0, 1.0, 0.0)
                INS-82370_ITRANSL                = (0.0, 0.0, 1.0)
              End_Object
              End

            </pre>
          </description>
          <parameterName>
            FROM
          </parameterName>
        </dataFile>
      </dataFiles>
    </example>

    <example>
      <brief>
        Example of spiceinit using a ShapeModel chosen by the user.
      </brief>
      <description>
        This example shows how to use spiceinit using a ShapeModel chosen by the user.

        In this example, the input cube is of Mars, so we can use a ShapeModel
        from $ISIS3DATA that was created specifically for use with Mars data.
      </description>
      <terminalInterface>
        <commandLine>
          from=hi2isis_RED0.cub shape=user model=$ISIS3DATA/base/dems/ulcn2005_lpo_0005.cub
        </commandLine>
        <description>
          An example of how to run this program with a chosen ShapeModel.
        </description>
      </terminalInterface>
      <guiInterfaces>
        <guiInterface>
          <image width="625" height="800" src="assets/images/spiceinit_example2.jpg">
          <brief>
            Example GUI
          </brief>
            <description>
              An example of how to run this program using the GUI. Note, the
              updated Kernel group can be seen in the log window.
            </description>
            <thumbnail width="239" height="300" src="assets/thumbs/spiceinit_thumb2.jpg" caption="Example of GUI command"/>
          </image>
        </guiInterface>
      </guiInterfaces>
      <dataFiles>
        <dataFile path="assets/dataFiles/hi2isis_RED0_after.pvl">
          <brief>
            Cube labels after spiceinit.
          </brief>
          <description>
            This is the label of the input cube after spiceinit has been
            run. The following groups were added to the cube's labels:
            <pre>
              Object = Table
                Name                = InstrumentPointing
                StartByte           = 3343625
                Bytes               = 1152
                Records             = 18
                ByteOrder           = Lsb
                TimeDependentFrames = (-74000, -74900, 1)
                ConstantFrames      = (-74690, -74000)
                ConstantRotation    = (0.9999703083413, 0.0, -0.0077059999872177,
                                       8.81584889031119e-06, 0.99999934560434,
                                       0.0011439900269605, 0.0077059949444447,
                                       -0.0011440239949305, 0.99996965396507)
                CkTableStartTime    = 217006138.39688
                CkTableEndTime      = 217006140.07063
                CkTableOriginalSize = 5001
                FrameTypeCode       = 3
                Description         = "Created by spiceinit"
                Kernels             = ($mro/kernels/ck/mro_sc_psp_061114_061120.bc,
                                       $mro/kernels/fk/mro_v15.tf)

                Record Information
                .
                .
                .

              End_Object

              Object = Table
                Name                 = InstrumentPosition
                StartByte            = 3344777
                Bytes                = 168
                Records              = 3
                ByteOrder            = Lsb
                CacheType            = HermiteSpline
                SpkTableStartTime    = 217006138.39688
                SpkTableEndTime      = 217006140.07063
                SpkTableOriginalSize = 5001.0
                Description          = "Created by spiceinit"
                Kernels              = $mro/kernels/spk/mro_psp1.bsp

                Record Information
                .
                .
                .

              End_Object

              Object = Table
                Name                = BodyRotation
                StartByte           = 3344945
                Bytes               = 128
                Records             = 2
                ByteOrder           = Lsb
                TimeDependentFrames = (10014, 1)
                CkTableStartTime    = 217006138.39688
                CkTableEndTime      = 217006140.07063
                CkTableOriginalSize = 2
                FrameTypeCode       = 2
                PoleRa              = (317.68143, -0.1061, 0.0)
                PoleDec             = (52.8865, -0.0609, 0.0)
                PrimeMeridian       = (176.63, 350.89198226, 0.0)
                Description         = "Created by spiceinit"
                Kernels             = ($base/kernels/spk/de405.bsp,
                                       $base/kernels/pck/pck00009.tpc)
                SolarLongitude      = 136.5654319332

                Record Information
                .
                .
                .

              End_Object

              Object = Table
                Name                 = SunPosition
                StartByte            = 3345073
                Bytes                = 112
                Records              = 2
                ByteOrder            = Lsb
                CacheType            = Linear
                SpkTableStartTime    = 217006138.39688
                SpkTableEndTime      = 217006140.07063
                SpkTableOriginalSize = 2.0
                Description          = "Created by spiceinit"
                Kernels              = $base/kernels/spk/de405.bsp

                Record Information
                .
                .
                .

              End_Object

              Object = NaifKeywords
                BODY499_RADII                            = (3396.19, 3396.19, 3376.2)
                BODY_FRAME_CODE                          = 10014
                INS-74699_FOCAL_LENGTH                   = 11994.9988
                INS-74699_PIXEL_PITCH                    = 0.012
                CLOCK_ET_-74999_848201292:03460_COMPUTED = 7549cb7480dea941
                INS-74602_TRANSX                         = (-96.9459, -3.4e-05, 0.012)
                INS-74602_TRANSY                         = (60.0469, -0.012, -3.4e-05)
                INS-74602_ITRANSS                        = (4981.07, -0.2353, -83.333)
                INS-74602_ITRANSL                        = (8092.92, 83.333, -0.2353)
                INS-74699_OD_K                           = (-0.0048509, 2.41312e-07,
                                                            -1.62369e-13)
              End_Object
              End
            </pre>
          </description>
          <parameterName>
            FROM
          </parameterName>
        </dataFile>
      </dataFiles>
    </example>
  </examples>
</application>
