<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="hidtmgen" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">

  <brief>
    Generates PDS products from a DTM and/or orthorectified images.
  </brief>

  <description>
    <p>
      This application is designed to produce a set of PDS products from an ISIS Digital Terrain
      Model (DTM) cube and/or a list of MRO HiRISE orthorectified images. The purpose of this 
      program is to:
      <ol>
        <li>
          Export the input cubes to PDS-formatted images.
        </li>
        <li>
          Modify the output label to include extra information.
        </li>
      </ol>
    </p>
    <p>
      The input DTM file for this program must have been generated using a set of
      HiRISE stereo pair images. If both input orthorecitfied files and an input DTM have
      been provided by the user, they should all have the same original stereo pair source.
      These files are usually generated using Socet Set and require some processing before
      they are passed into this program. In some cases, restrictions to the input file names
      are enforced. See the documentation for the DTM and ORTHOTOLIST parameters for details.
    </p>

    The table below indicates the requirements for program parameters under the
    indicated conditions.
    <table border="1">
      <tr>
        <th>DEFAULTNAMES</th>
        <th>Input file type</th>
        <th>Required Parameters</th>
        <th>Required PARAMSPVL Keywords</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td rowspan="3">FALSE</td>
        <td>Both DTM and ORTHOFROMLIST provided</td>
        <td>
          The following parameters are enabled:
          <ul>
            <li>DTMTO (required)</li>
            <li>DTM_PRODUCT_ID (required)</li>
            <li>ORTHOTOLIST (required)</li>
            <li>ORTHOPRODUCTIDLIST (required)</li>
            <li>PARAMSPVL (required)</li>
          </ul>
        </td>
        <td>
          <ul>
            <li>DATA_SET_ID</li>
            <li>DATA_SET_NAME</li>
            <li>PRODUCER_INSTITUION_NAME</li>
            <li>PRODUCER_ID</li>
            <li>PRODUCER_FULL_NAME</li>
            <li>PRODUCING_INSTITUTION</li>
            <li>PRODUCT_VERSION_ID</li>
            <li>RATIONALE_DESC</li>
            <li>SOFTWARE_NAME</li>
            <li>DTM_SOURCE_PRODUCT_ID</li>
          </ul>
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>DTM provided only</td>
        <td>
          The following parameters are enabled:
          <ul>
            <li>DTMTO (required)</li>
            <li>DTM_PRODUCT_ID (required)</li>
            <li>PARAMSPVL (required)</li>
          </ul>
        </td>
        <td>
          <ul>
            <li>DATA_SET_ID</li>
            <li>DATA_SET_NAME</li>
            <li>PRODUCER_INSTITUION_NAME</li>
            <li>PRODUCER_ID</li>
            <li>PRODUCER_FULL_NAME</li>
            <li>PRODUCING_INSTITUTION</li>
            <li>PRODUCT_VERSION_ID</li>
            <li>RATIONALE_DESC</li>
            <li>SOFTWARE_NAME</li>
            <li>DTM_SOURCE_PRODUCT_ID</li>
          </ul>
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>ORTHOFROMLIST provided only</td>
        <td>
          The following parameters are enabled:
          <ul>
            <li>ORTHOTOLIST (required)</li>
            <li>ORTHOPRODUCTIDLIST (required)</li>
            <li>PARAMSPVL (required)</li>
          </ul>
        </td>
        <td>
          <ul>
            <li>DATA_SET_ID</li>
            <li>DATA_SET_NAME</li>
            <li>PRODUCER_INSTITUION_NAME</li>
            <li>PRODUCER_ID</li>
            <li>PRODUCER_FULL_NAME</li>
            <li>PRODUCING_INSTITUTION</li>
            <li>PRODUCT_VERSION_ID</li>
            <li>RATIONALE_DESC</li>
            <li>SOFTWARE_NAME</li>
            <li>ORTHO_SOURCE_DTM_ID</li>
          </ul>
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td rowspan="3">TRUE</td>
        <td>Both DTM and ORTHOFROMLIST provided</td>
        <td>
          The following parameters are enabled:
          <ul>
            <li>OUTPUTDIR (optional - defaults to current working directory)</li>
             <li>
               Ortho input file name requirements - each file must have orbit/target IDs for
               itself, as described in the documentation for the ORTHOFROMLIST parameter.
            </li>
            <li>OUTPUTDIR (optional - defaults to current working directory)</li>
            <li>ORTHOSEQUENCENUMBERLIST (required)</li>
            <li>PARAMSPVL (required)</li>
          </ul>
        </td>
        <td>
          <ul>
            <li>DATA_SET_ID</li>
            <li>DATA_SET_NAME</li>
            <li>PRODUCER_INSTITUION_NAME</li>
            <li>PRODUCER_ID</li>
            <li>PRODUCER_FULL_NAME</li>
            <li>PRODUCING_INSTITUTION</li>
            <li>PRODUCT_VERSION_ID</li>
            <li>RATIONALE_DESC</li>
            <li>SOFTWARE_NAME</li>
            <li>DTM_SOURCE_PRODUCT_ID</li>
          </ul>
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>DTM provided only</td>
        <td>
          The following parameters are enabled:
          <ul>
            <li>OUTPUTDIR (optional - defaults to current working directory)</li>
            <li>PARAMSPVL (required)</li>
          </ul>
        </td>
        <td>
          <ul>
            <li>DATA_SET_ID</li>
            <li>DATA_SET_NAME</li>
            <li>PRODUCER_INSTITUION_NAME</li>
            <li>PRODUCER_ID</li>
            <li>PRODUCER_FULL_NAME</li>
            <li>PRODUCING_INSTITUTION</li>
            <li>PRODUCT_VERSION_ID</li>
            <li>RATIONALE_DESC</li>
            <li>SOFTWARE_NAME</li>
            <li>DTM_SOURCE_PRODUCT_ID</li>
          </ul>
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>ORTHOFROMLIST provided only</td>
        <td>
          The following parameters are enabled:
          <ul>
             <li>
               File name requirements - input orthorectified file names must have orbit/target IDs for
               itself, as described in the documentation for the ORTHOFROMLIST parameter.
            </li>
            <li>OUTPUTDIR (optional - defaults to current working directory)</li>
            <li>ORTHOSEQUENCENUMBERLIST (required)</li>
            <li>PARAMSPVL (required)</li>
          </ul>
        </td>
        <td>
          <ul>
            <li>DATA_SET_ID</li>
            <li>DATA_SET_NAME</li>
            <li>PRODUCER_INSTITUION_NAME</li>
            <li>PRODUCER_ID</li>
            <li>PRODUCER_FULL_NAME</li>
            <li>PRODUCING_INSTITUTION</li>
            <li>PRODUCT_VERSION_ID</li>
            <li>RATIONALE_DESC</li>
            <li>SOFTWARE_NAME</li>
            <li>ORTHO_SOURCE_DTM_ID</li>
          </ul>
        </td>
      </tr>
    </table>

  </description>

  <category>
    <missionItem>Mars Reconnaissance Orbiter</missionItem>
  </category>

  <seeAlso>
    <applications>
      <item>
        hirdrgen
      </item>
      <item>
        isis2pds
      </item>
    </applications>
  </seeAlso>

  <history>
    <change name="Mackenzie Boyd" date="2011-05-13">
      0riginal Version.
    </change>
    <change name="Tracie Sucharski" date="2012-12-06">
      Changed to use TProjection instead of Projection. References #775.
    </change>
    <change name="Lynn Weller" date="2012-01-22">
      Application category name changed from Import and Export to Mars Reconnaissance Orbiter. 
      Fixes mantis ticket #951.
    </change>
    <change name="Jeannie Backer" date="2013-09-11">
      Modified the code to add SOURCE_PRODUCT_ID values individually when they are generated by the
      program. Otherwise, if the user enters a value for SOURCE_PRODUCT_ID as a string, they must
      include braces for array values. Fixed code to read the PRODUCT_VERSION_ID from the
      PARAMSPVL file if the user has not entered a value. Added PRODUCT_VERSION_ID value to params
      default file. Fixed spelling in error message and user documentation. Changed IString objects
      to QStrings. Brought code closer to ISIS coding standards. Improved code test coverage. 
      Fixes ticket #757, #946.
    </change>
    <change name="Jeannie Backer" date="2015-10-02">
      Backwards Compatibility Issue:  The command line parameters were changed to generalize this
      program's capabilities, as requested by the HiRISE mission representatives. This will impact
      processing scripts/pipelines.

      Modified the program to be able to process any number of orthorectified input files. 
      Also, a DTM is no longer a required input for this program. Updated the output file names and
      keyword values generated when DEFAULTNAMES=TRUE. The following parameters were added,
      removed, or replaced:
      1. ORTHO1, ORTHO2, ORTHO3, and ORTHO4 replaced with ORTHOFROMLIST.
      2. ORTHO1TO, ORTHO2TO, ORTHO3TO, and ORTHO4TO replaced with ORTHOTOLIST.
      3. ORTHO1_PRODUCT_ID, ORTHO2_PRODUCT_ID, ORTHO3_PRODUCT_ID,
          and ORTHO4_PRODUCT_ID replaced with ORTHOPRODUCTIDLIST.
      4. PRODUCER_FULL_NAME, RATIONALE_DESC, and PRODUCT_VERSION_ID
          removed since they are required in the PARAMSPVL input file.
      5. ORTHOSEQUENCENUMBERLIST added to be able to generate default names for
          orthorectified files. 
      Fixes ticket #801
    </change>
  </history>
  
  <groups>
    <group name="Output Options">

      <parameter name="DEFAULTNAMES">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>TRUE</item></default>
        <brief>
          Indicates whether the program will generate the output file names and PRODUCT_IDs. 
          Input names must match expected form.
        </brief>
        <description>
          <p>
            This parameter is used for convenience so that output file names and PRODUCT_IDs
            do not need to be specified by the user. 

            If this parameter is selected, then the parameters DTMTO, ORTHOTOLIST,
            DTM_PRODUCT_ID, and ORTHOPRODUCTIDLIST are disabled since the program will use
            the default output values for these.

            See the table in the main description of this program for specific requirements.

            If this parameter is selected, the names of the output files will match the
            corresponding PRODUCT_IDs (minus the file path and extension).

            The values for each PRODUCT_ID is generated using the name of the input cube, the
            corresponding sequence number (for orthorectified output images), and other cube
            attributes. For this reason, input orthorectified file names of a certain form are
            required. See the documentation for the ORTHOFROMLIST parameter for specifications.
            Also, certain keyword values are provided by the PARAMSPVL file. See the 
            documentation for PARAMSPVL  for specifications.
          </p>

          <pre>
The output PRODUCT_IDs used when DEFAULTNAMES=TRUE are explained below.

For DTMs files the form is 
<strong>DTems_xxxxxx_xxxx_xxxxxx_xxxx_vnn</strong>
    <strong>e</strong> is the code for the type of elevation data 
          <em>E</em> for areoid elevations 
          <em>R</em> for radii (hidtmgen does not currently support this option)
    <strong>m</strong> is the map projection code 
          <em>E</em> for equirectangular
          <em>P</em> for polar stereographic
    <strong>s</strong> is the grid spacing (i.e. map scale) code
          <em>A</em> for 0.25 m 
          <em>B</em> for 0.5 m 
          <em>C</em> for 1.0 m 
          <em>D</em> for 2.0 m
          etc. 
          <em>Z</em> is used if no match is found, a 10% tolerance on the 
             resolution value is used to catch values that are close. 
    <strong>xxxxx_xxxx_yyyyy_yyyy</strong> is the orbit (five digit) number 
          and target (four digit) codes
          for the stereo pairs used to create this DTM
    <strong>v</strong> is the code for the producing institution 
          <em>U</em> for USGS 
          <em>A</em> for University of Arizona 
          <em>C</em> for CalTech 
          <em>N</em> for NASA Ames 
          <em>J</em> for JPL 
          <em>O</em> for Ohio State 
          <em>Z</em> for other 
    <strong>nn</strong> is the 2 digit product version ID number 

For orthorectified image files, the form is 
<strong>pSP_xxxxxx_xxxx_ccc_s_nn_ORTHO</strong>
    <strong>p</strong> is the code for the mission phase
          <em>E</em> for Extended Science Phase
          <em>P</em> for Primary Science Phase
    <strong>xxxxxx_xxxx</strong> is the orbit number and target code for this ORTHO
    <strong>ccc</strong> is the color content code
          <em>RED</em> for visible RED, 1 band image
          <em>IRB</em> for 3 band enhanced color (IR, RED, BG)
    <strong>s</strong> is the grid spacing (i.e. map scale) code
          <em>A</em> for 0.25 m 
          <em>B</em> for 0.5 m 
          <em>C</em> for 1.0 m 
       	  <em>D</em> for 2.0 m
          etc. 
          <em>Z</em> is used if no match is found, a 10% tolerance on the 
             resolution value is used to catch values that are close. 
    <strong>nn</strong> is a sequence number to distinguish between orthorectified images
          from the same HiRISE observation that may be created from different DTMs.
    <strong>ORTHO</strong> indicates that the image has been orthorectified

NOTE: The first 15 characters of the product ID pSP_xxxxxx_xxxx are taken
      directly from the first 15 characters of the input ortho file name.

          </pre>
        </description>
        <exclusions>
          <item>DTMTO</item>   
          <item>ORTHOTOLIST</item>   
          <item>DTM_PRODUCT_ID</item>   
          <item>ORTHOPRODUCTIDLIST</item>   
        </exclusions>
        <inclusions>
          <item>OUTPUTDIR</item>
          <item>ORTHOSEQUENCENUMBERLIST</item>
        </inclusions>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="OUTPUTDIR">
        <type>string</type>
        <default><item>./</item></default>
        <brief>
          Directory for output products.
        </brief>
        <description>
          The directory where output image files will be written. This parameter only applies when 
          DEFAULTNAMES=TRUE. The default is the current working directory.
        </description>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="DTM Parameters">

      <parameter name="DTM">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>The name of the input DTM file.</brief>
        <description>
          The name of the DTM file to be exported. The given file must be an ISIS cube
          whose label contains a mapping group. This DTM, usually created using Socet Set, must be
          generated from a stereo pair of MRO HiRISE images. The user may specify the corresponding
          output file name using the DTMTO parameter. Otherwise, the output file name can
          be generated by hidtmgen by setting DEFAULTNAMES=TRUE.
          <b> Note: </b> DTM is not a required parameter. The user may choose to only export a list 
          orthorectified images.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
        <internalDefault>None</internalDefault>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="DTMTO">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <brief>DTM output file name.</brief>
        <description>
          The name of the exported DTM file. 
          This parameter is required when DTM has been provided and DEFAULTNAMES=FALSE.
        </description>
        <filter> *.IMG </filter> 
        <internalDefault>Automatic</internalDefault>
        <inclusions>
          <item>DTM</item>
        </inclusions>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="DTM_PRODUCT_ID">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>User specified ID for the output DTM product.</brief>
        <description>
          The PRODUCT_ID for the output DTM product. 
          This parameter is required when DTM has been provided and DEFAULTNAMES=FALSE.
        </description>
        <internalDefault>None</internalDefault>
        <inclusions>
          <item>DTM</item>
        </inclusions>
      </parameter>

      </group>

    <group name="Orthorectified Cube Parameters">
        
      <parameter name="ORTHOFROMLIST">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          A list file names for input orthorectified cubes.
        </brief>
        <description>
          A list of orthorectified images to be exported. The given files in this list must be ISIS 
          cubes from the MRO HiRISE camera that have been orthorectified to the input DTM, if 
          provided. The user may specify the corresponding output file names using the ORTHOTOLIST 
          parameter. Otherwise, these output file names can be generated by hidtmgen by setting
          DEFAULTNAMES=TRUE. In this case, the name of each input image file in this list must
          begin with the prefix pSP_######_####_ where p is the code for the mission phase and
          the #'s represent the orbit number followed by the target code for this image.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.txt *.lis *.lst
        </filter>
        <internalDefault>Automatic</internalDefault>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="ORTHOTOLIST">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          An ordered list of output file names for PDS products corresponding to the list of input orthorectified cubes.
        </brief>
        <description>
          An ordered list of output PDS file names. It is expected that the order of the  file
          names in this list will correspond to the orthorectified cubes in the ORTHOFROMLIST.
          Each file in this list should have a full path to the output location where the PDS
          file will be created. 

          Note that the DEFAULTNAMES and OUTPUTDIR options may be
          selected instead of ORTHOTOLIST if the user prefers to specify only the location of the
          output PDS files (and not the file names). 

          This parameter is required when ORTHOFROMLIST has been provided and DEFAULTNAMES=FALSE.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.txt *.lis *.lst
        </filter>
        <internalDefault>Automatic</internalDefault>
        <inclusions>
          <item>ORTHOFROMLIST</item>
        </inclusions>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="ORTHOPRODUCTIDLIST">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          An ordered list of user specified PRODUCT_ID values corresponding to each of the
          orthorectified input images given in the ORTHOFROMLIST.
        </brief>
        <description>
          An ordered list of strings representing the PRODUCT_ID values that correspond to each of the
          input orthorectified images given in the ORTHOFROMLIST. This parameter is required when
          ORTHOFROMLIST has been provided and DEFAULTNAMES=FALSE.

        </description>
        <filter>
          *.txt *.lis *.lst
        </filter>
        <internalDefault>Automatic</internalDefault>
        <inclusions>
          <item>ORTHOFROMLIST</item>
        </inclusions>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="ORTHOSEQUENCENUMBERLIST">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          An ordered list of user specified sequence numbers corresponding to each of the
          orthorectified input images given in the ORTHOFROMLIST.
        </brief>
        <description>
          An ordered list of two digit sequence numbers that correspond to each of the input images
          given in the ORTHOFROMLIST. These sequence numbers are used to distinguish between
          orthorectified images from the same HiRISE observation that may be created from different
          DTMs. This parameter is required when ORTHOFROMLIST has been provided and
          DEFAULTNAMES=TRUE.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.txt *.lis *.lst
        </filter>
        <internalDefault>Automatic</internalDefault>
        <inclusions>
          <item>ORTHOFROMLIST</item>
        </inclusions>
      </parameter>

    </group>

      
    <group name="Label Information">

      <parameter name="PARAMSPVL">
        <type>filename</type>
        <default><item>$mro/templates/labels/hidtmgenDefaults.pvl</item></default>
        <brief>
          PVL-formatted file containing required keyword values.
        </brief>
        <description>
          This should be a PVL-formatted file that contains the keywords indicated below.
          <br/>
          <br/>
           Keywords that are always required:<br/>
          <ul>
            <li>DATA_SET_ID</li>
            <li>DATA_SET_NAME</li>
            <li>PRODUCER_INSTITUION_NAME</li>
            <li>PRODUCER_ID</li>
            <li>PRODUCER_FULL_NAME</li>
            <li>PRODUCING_INSTITUTION*</li>
            <li>PRODUCT_VERSION_ID**</li>
            <li>RATIONALE_DESC</li>
            <li>SOFTWARE_NAME</li>
          </ul>
          <pre>
<strong>*</strong>  The <strong>PRODUCING_INSTITUTION</strong> value must be a single character code: 
       <em>U</em> for USGS 
       <em>A</em> for University of Arizona 
       <em>C</em> for CalTech 
       <em>N</em> for NASA Ames 
       <em>J</em> for JPL 
       <em>O</em> for Ohio State 
       <em>Z</em> for other 
<strong>**</strong> The <strong>PRODUCT_VERSION_ID</strong> must be a real number (i.e. double 
   precision) value. When DEFAULTNAMES=TRUE this number will be used
   to generate the 2 digit version ID code used as the last two digits
   of the output DTM's PRODUCT_ID.
        <strong>Case 1:</strong> If the number given is greater than 10,
                the first two digits will be used for the output code.
        <strong>Case 2:</strong> If it is of the form N.0 (where N is between 0 and 9),
                the output code will be 0N.
        <strong>Case 3:</strong> If it is of the form N.M (where N and M are between
                0 and 9), the output code will be NM.
        <strong>Case 4:</strong> If it is less than 1.0, the output code will be 0N,
                where N is the first significant digit
                (i.e the first non-zero from the left).
   Note that except for the special case of N.0, the most significant
   digits are used. 

          </pre>
          Keywords that are required under particular circumstances:<br/>
          <ul>
            <li>DTM_SOURCE_PRODUCT_ID (required if DTM provided) *</li>
            <li>ORTHO_SOURCE_DTM_ID (required if DTM was not provided) **</li>
          </ul>
          <pre>
*  The <strong>DTM_SOURCE_PRODUCT_ID</strong> is an array that indicates the source of the input DTM.
   If the user enters a DTM, this value must be an array containing the PRODUCT_IDs
   of the stereo pair used to generate the DTM.

** The <strong>ORTHO_SOURCE_DTM_ID</strong> is the PRODUCT_ID of the DTM used to generate the given
   orthorectified input cubes.

          </pre>
        </description>
      </parameter>

    </group>

    <group name="Output Data Options">

      <parameter name="ENDIAN">
        <type>string</type>
        <default>
          <item>LSB</item>
        </default>
        <brief>Endianness of the output bytes for all output files.</brief>
        <description>
          This parameter is used to select the output data storage order. The output can be
	        streamed starting with the most significant byte (MSB) or starting
	        with the least significant bytes (LSB). The choice should be made by
	        the user depending upon the format read by the system architecture
	        from which they plan to read the raw data.
        </description>
        <list>
          <option value="LSB">
            <brief>Least significant byte.</brief>
            <description>
              The least significant byte will be the first byte output.
            </description>
          </option>
          <option value="MSB">
            <brief>Most significant byte.</brief>
            <description>
            The most significant byte will be the first byte output.
            </description>
          </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="NULL">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>true</item></default>
        <brief>Dedicates a DN value for null pixels in output DTM product.</brief>
        <description>
          If set to true, the minimum value of the raw output data will be
          reserved for null pixels. The actual value used for null pixels will
          be denoted in the print.prt file as well as displayed onscreen.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="LRS">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>false</item></default>
        <brief>Dedicates a DN value for LRS pixels in output DTM product.</brief>
        <description>
          If set to true, then an output DN value is set aside for the LRS input pixels.
          The actual DN value used for LRS pixels will be denoted in the print.prt
          file as well as displayed onscreen.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="LIS">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>false</item></default>
        <brief>Dedicates a DN value for LIS pixels in output DTM product.</brief>
        <description>
          If set to true, then an output DN value is set aside for the LIS input pixels.
          The actual DN value used for LIS pixels will be denoted in the print.prt
          file as well as displayed onscreen.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="HIS">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>false</item></default>
        <brief>Dedicates a DN value for HIS pixels in output DTM product.</brief>
        <description>
          If set to true, then an output DN value is set aside for the HIS input pixels.
          The actual DN value used for HIS pixels will be denoted in the print.prt
          file as well as displayed onscreen.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="HRS">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>false</item></default>
        <brief>Dedicates a DN value for HRS pixels in output DTM product.</brief>
        <description>
          If set to true, then an output DN value is set aside for the HRS input pixels.
          The actual DN value used for HRS pixels will be denoted in the print.prt
          file as well as displayed onscreen.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="DTMBITTYPE">
        <type>string</type>
        <default>
          <item>32BIT</item>
        </default>
        <brief>Bit type of output DTM file.</brief>
        <description>
          Bit type of output:
          <ul>
            <li>8-bit (0=black, 255=white)</li>
            <li>16-bit unsigned (0=black, 65535=white)</li>
            <li>16-bit signed (-32767=black, 32768=white)</li>
            <li>32-bit (1.17549435e-38=black, 3.40282347e+38=white)</li>
          </ul>
        </description>
        <list>
          <option value="8BIT">
            <brief>Output 8-bit data in DTM product.</brief>
            <description>
              Pixels are in 8-bit data range (0 to 255).
            </description>
          </option>         
          <option value="U16BIT">
            <brief>Output 16-bit unsigned data in DTM product.</brief>
            <description>
              Pixels are in the 16-bit data range (0 to 65535).
            </description>
          </option>
          <option value="S16BIT">
            <brief>Output 16-bit signed data in DTM product.</brief>
            <description>
              Pixels are in 16-bit signed data range (-32768 to 32767).
            </description>
          </option>
          <option value="32BIT">
            <brief>Output 32-bit data in DTM product.</brief>
            <description>
              Pixels are in the 32-bit floating point data range
              (-3.40282347e+38 to 3.40282347e+38).
            </description>
         </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="ORTHOBITTYPE">
        <type>string</type>
        <default>
          <item>8BIT</item>
        </default>
        <brief>Bit type of orthorectified output files.</brief>
        <description>
          Bit type of output:
          <ul>
            <li>8-bit (0=black, 255=white)</li>
            <li>16-bit unsigned (0=black, 65535=white)</li>
            <li>16-bit signed (-32767=black, 32768=white)</li>
            <li>32-bit (1.17549435e-38=black, 3.40282347e+38=white)</li>
          </ul>
        </description>
        <list>
          <option value="8BIT">
            <brief>Output 8-bit data in orthorectified PDS products.</brief>
            <description>
              Pixels are in 8-bit data range (0 to 255).
            </description>
            <!--<exclusions>
              <item>ENDIAN</item>
            </exclusions>!-->
          </option>         
          <option value="U16BIT">
            <brief>Output 16-bit unsigned data in orthorectified PDS products.</brief>
            <description>
              Pixels are in the 16-bit data range (0 to 65535).
            </description>
          </option>
          <option value="S16BIT">
            <brief>Output 16-bit signed data in orthorectified PDS products.</brief>
            <description>
              Pixels are in 16-bit signed data range (-32768 to 32767).
            </description>
          </option>
          <option value="32BIT">
            <brief>Output 32-bit data in orthorectified PDS products.</brief>
            <description>
              Pixels are in the 32-bit floating point data range
              (-3.40282347e+38 to 3.40282347e+38).
            </description>
         </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>
    </group>

  </groups>
</application>
