<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="apollopanstitcher" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">

  <brief>
    Stitches together the typically eight individual scans of an Apollo Panoramic Image
  </brief>

  <description>
    This program uses the Selection and CentroidApolloPan classes to find the centers of the fiducial marks along the image segments.  Conjugate fiducial marks between segments are used
	to calculate transformations to unite the segments.  The transformation math model is limited to three parameters (2 transformations and 1 rotation) because it is unlikely the
	film is undergoing any measureable dimensional changes during the scanning.  Thus, the intent of this program is to stitch together the image that would have been produced had there
	been a large enough scanner, and not to correct for any film degradation or other systematic error sources.  Those corrections are left to the camera model.
  </description>

  <history>
    <change name="Orrin Thomas" date="2011-10-03">
      Created
    </change>
    <change name="Orrin Thomas" date="2012-07-13">
      Application name changed from apollopansticher to apollopanstitcher
    </change>
    <change name="Raad A. Saleh" date="2012-08-08">
      Program has been modified to accept long (more than 128 characters) file names without error.
      This fixes Mantis ticket # 1024. 
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2012-12-26">
      Fixed a bug that caused this program to produce erroneous outputs a small percentage of
      the times it was run (less than 3% failure rate). The bad outputs looked valid - visually -
      but the stitching was incorrect (pixels would be in the wrong place). This was a general
      failure, not caused by a particular input or set of parameter values. Fixes #1053.
    </change>
    <change name="Lynn Weller" date="2012-01-22">
      Application category name changed from Import and Export to Apollo.  Fixes mantis ticket #951.
    </change>
  </history>

  <category>
    <missionItem>Apollo</missionItem>
  </category>

   <groups>
     <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="TO">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Output image 
        </brief>
        <description>
          Use this parameter to specify the name of the output cube.
        </description>
        <pixelType>real</pixelType>
      </parameter>
    </group>
    <group name="File Base Name">
      <parameter name="FILE_BASE">
        <type>string</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Apollo Panoramic Image Base Name
        </brief>
        <description>
          Base Name of the eight subscans of an Apollo Panoramic image. For example, given the base name: "AS15_P_0330-", the first image would be expected to be "AS15_p_0330-0001.cub", the second
		"AS15_P_0330-0002.cub", etc.
        </description>
      </parameter>
    </group>    
    <group name="Resolution">
     <parameter name="MICRONS">
       <type>double</type>
       <brief>
	 Pixels size in microns
       </brief>
       <description>
	 The scanner resolution (dot size) in microns.
       </description>  
     </parameter>  
    </group>
  </groups>
</application>
