<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="pds2isis" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation=
"http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">

  <brief>Import PDS or ISIS2 image into ISIS cube format</brief>

  <description>
    <p>
      This program converts a PDS or ISIS2 formatted file to an ISIS3
      <def link="Cube">cube</def> format.  The standard PDS image is defined in
      the "FROM" parameter, and not the "IMAGE" parameter.  If the PDS file has
      a detached label file and an image file, both are required to exist in the
      working directory.  If the label is detached, the detached label filename
      is defined as the input file for the "FROM" parameter.  The "IMAGE" parameter
      does not need to be defined, unless the program fails to find the image file
      specifed in the label file upon the program's execution.

      The default settings normally work for most PDS products, but occasionally
      the user may need to modify the default values in order to obtain an image
      that meets their specific requirements.
     </p>
     <p>
      The incoming <def link="Special Pixels">special pixel</def> values in the
      PDS file are assigned equivalent values for special pixels in ISIS.  The
      order of precedence for special pixels in ISIS from highest to lowest
      priority is the following:
      <blockquote>
      <ol>
        <li><def>NULL</def></li>
	<li><def>HRS</def></li>
	<li><def>LRS</def></li>
	<li><def>HIS</def></li>
	<li><def>LIS</def></li>
      </ol>
      </blockquote>
      If any incoming <def link="Digital Number">pixel value</def> falls within
      two different special pixel types, the <def link="Special Pixels">special
      pixel</def> with the higher priority is assigned.  The user may also
      specify a range of pixel values to be assigned to the different special pixels.
      If the range of pixel values defined by the user for the different special
      pixels overlap, the special pixel with the highest priority is assigned.  For
      example, if NULLMIN=0.0, NULLMAX=3.0, LISMIN=3.0, and LISMAX=5.0, the actual
      raw value 3.0 can be assigned as a NULL or LIS, but is translated to NULL because
      NULL has a higher priority than LIS.
    </p>
    <p>
      It should be noted if any incoming <def link="Digital Number">pixel values</def>
      are equal to one of the ISIS <def link="Special Pixels">special pixel</def>
      values for the corresponding bit type, those pixels will be special in the
      output cube. The special pixel values for each bit type can be found
      <a href="https://github.com/USGS-Astrogeology/ISIS3/wiki/SpecialPixels">here</a>.
      This is most commonly an issue with 8-bit data. If you are working with
      an 8-bit image and need either 0 or 255, either convert the data to 16-bit
      or use Stretch after ingestion.
    </p>
    <p>
      The conversion of images from ISIS2 to ISIS3
      follows the same rules as PDS images, except that the label information
      is propagated to the output file.
     </p>
     <p>
      The best option to convert files from ISIS2 to ISIS is to maintain all the
      input file settings, and do not change the <def link="Bit Type">bit type</def>
      or change any incoming pixel values to <def link="Special Pixels">special pixels</def>.
      When an ISIS2 <def>Level1</def> image is imported into ISIS3, it is
      important to note the label information is not propagated from the ISIS2 to
      the ISIS cube file. For an ISIS2 <def>Level2</def> image or mosaic file,
      a limited set of label information is transferred to the ISIS labels that
      include the "Instrument," "<def link="Band">BandBin</def>," and
      "<def link="Map Projection">Mapping</def>" groups.
    </p>
  </description>

  <history>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="1997-05-01">
      Original version.
    </change>
    <change name="Stuart Sides" date="2003-05-15">
      Wrote for Isis 3.
    </change>
    <change name="Stuart Sides" date="2003-05-16">
      Modified schema location from "astrogeology" to "isis.astrogeology."
    </change>
    <change name="Stuart Sides" date="2003-06-04">
      Fixed Makefile.
    </change>
    <change name="Stuart Sides" date="2003-10-10">
      Converted to use new IsisImport instead of IsisPdsImport.
    </change>
    <change name="Stuart Sides" date="2004-02-20">
      Converted to use the new IsisImportPds class and added
      import labels to the output cube.
    </change>
    <change name="Brendan George" date="2006-09-28">
        Documentation fixes.
    </change>
    <change name="Stuart Sides" date="2007-01-25">
        Added ability to transfers Isis2 instrument and bandbin
        information.
    </change>
   <change name="Tracie Sucharski" date="2007-04-10">
       Added LatitudeType2 group to translation table to handle CTX cubes.
       Additonal changes to projection translation tables for other possible
       values for Longitude direction, latitude type.  If the min or max
       longitude values are greater than 180, change longitude domain to 360.
       Only call TranslateIsis2Labels if pds file is an Isis2 cube.
   </change>
   <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2007-08-07">
       Added support for copying some PDS labels, if they exist, into the output.
   </change>
   <change name="Steven Koechle" date="2007-08-29">
       Added special pixel ranges. Added examples.
   </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2008-05-13">
      Removed references to CubeInfo.
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2008-09-15">
      Fixed problem with special pixel range functionality and documentation.
      Added HIS and LIS range options.
    </change>
    <change name="Stuart Sides" date="2012-08-08">
      Added translations for BAND_BIN_CENTER, BAND_BIN_WIDTH, and BAND_BIN_FILTER_NUMBER from
      NIMS RDR products fixes #1029.
    </change>
    <change name="Ella Mae Lee" date="2012-11-09">
      Improve the documentation, document capability to import ISIS2 images,
      fixes #1172.
    </change>
    <change name="Kimberly Oyama" date="2012-11-21">
      Added app tests for BIP and BIL formatted input. References #819.
    </change>
    <change name="Tyler Wilson" date ="2016-02-25">
     Added an app test for opening Galileo NIMS qubes saved in VAX format.  Modified the filter
     tag on FROM parameter in this document to also recognize *.qub files.  All changes
     relating to converting VAX to IEEE were made in ProcessImport, ProcessImportPds.
     References:  #2368.
    </change>
    <change name="Summer Stapleton" date="2017-06-27">
     Added conditional to check whether default offsets and multipliers where changed from their
     default values and log them if so.
    </change>

  </history>

  <category>
    <categoryItem>Import and Export</categoryItem>
  </category>

  <groups>

    <group name="Files">

      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input PDS, PDS label, or ISIS2 file
        </brief>
        <description>
          Specify a PDS file, PDS label file, or ISIS2 cube file.  If the
	  input file is a PDS detached label file and the companion image
	  file is not in the same directory, use the parameter "IMAGE" to
	  define the location and filename of the image, otherwise just
	  enter the label file name.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.lbl *.img *.qub
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="IMAGE">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Detached image file
        </brief>
        <description>
          Use this parameter if the pointer to the image data in the
          detached label file (FROM) is incorrrect.
        </description>
        <internalDefault>
          Cube data embedded with label or file pointer in label file
        </internalDefault>
        <filter>
          *.img
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TO">
         <type>cube</type>
         <fileMode>output</fileMode>
         <brief>
           Output cube file
         </brief>
         <description>
           Use this parameter to specify the output cube filename.
         </description>
         <filter>
           *.cub
         </filter>
       </parameter>

    </group>

    <group name="Special Pixels">

      <parameter name="SETNULLRANGE">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default>
          <item>NO</item>
        </default>
        <brief>Option to convert pixel values to NULL</brief>
        <description>
	  If this option is set to "yes" or "true", a range of input raw pixels
	  defined by the NULLMIN and NULLMAX parameters are converted to <def>NULL</def>
	  pixels.  All other valid pixels that do not fall within the ranges
	  specified for LIS, LRS, HIS, and HRS pixels are transferred to the output file
	  unchanged.  If the <def link="Bit Type">bit type</def> of the input
	  file is changed, the NULL and HRS <def link="Special Pixels">special
	  pixels</def> may be incorrectly set to valid pixel values.  For example,
	  if a raw 8-bit file is output to 16 or 32-bit, the pixel values "0"
	  and "255" may be converted to actual values instead of retaining the
	  special pixel property.  If the output file remains as 8-bit, then "0"
	  stays as NULL and "255" stays as HRS.
        </description>
        <inclusions>
          <item>NULLMIN</item>
          <item>NULLMAX</item>
        </inclusions>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="NULLMIN">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief> Minimum value for NULL</brief>
        <description>
          Minimum pixel value to set to <def>NULL</def>.  All values greater than or equal to
	  NULLMIN and less than or equal to NULLMAX are converted to NULL.
        </description>
        <inclusions>
          <item>SETNULLRANGE</item>
        </inclusions>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="NULLMAX">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief> Maximum value for NULL </brief>
        <description>
          Maximum pixel value to set to <def>NULL</def>.  All values greater than or equal to
	  NULLMIN and less than or equal to NULLMAX are converted to NULL.
        </description>
        <inclusions>
          <item>SETNULLRANGE</item>
        </inclusions>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="SETHRSRANGE">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default>
          <item>NO</item>
        </default>
        <brief>Option to convert pixel values to HRS</brief>
        <description>
	  If this option is set to "yes" or "true", a range of input raw pixels
	  defined by the HRSMIN and HRSMAX parameters are converted to HRS
	  pixels.  All other valid pixels that do not fall within the ranges
	  specified for LIS, LRS, HIS, and NULL pixels are transferred to the output file
	  unchanged.  If the <def link="Bit Type">bit type</def> of the input
	  file is changed, the NULL and HRS <def link="Special Pixels">special
	  pixels</def> may be incorrectly set to valid pixel values.  For example,
	  if a raw 8-bit file is output to 16 or 32-bit, the pixel values "0"
	  and "255" may be converted to actual values instead of retaining the
	  special pixel property.  If the output file remains as 8-bit, then "0"
	  stays as NULL and "255" stays as HRS.
        </description>
        <inclusions>
          <item>HRSMIN</item>
          <item>HRSMAX</item>
        </inclusions>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="HRSMIN">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief> Minimum value for HRS</brief>
        <description>
          Minimum pixel value to set to <def>HRS</def>.  All values greater than or equal to
	  HRSMIN and less than or equal to HRSMAX are converted to HRS.
        </description>
        <inclusions>
          <item>SETHRSRANGE</item>
        </inclusions>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="HRSMAX">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief> Maximum value for HRS</brief>
        <description>
          Maximum pixel value to set to <def>HRS</def>.  All values greater than or equal to
	  HRSMIN and less than or equal to HRSMAX are converted to HRS.
        </description>
        <inclusions>
          <item>SETHRSRANGE</item>
        </inclusions>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="SETHISRANGE">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default>
          <item>NO</item>
        </default>
        <brief>Option to convert pixel values to HIS</brief>
        <description>
	  If this option is set to "yes" or "true", a range of input raw pixels
	  defined by the HISMIN and HISMAX parameters are converted to HIS
	  pixels.  All other valid pixels that do not fall within the ranges
	  specified for LIS, LRS, HRS, and NULL pixels are transferred to the
	  output file unchanged.
        </description>
        <inclusions>
          <item>HISMIN</item>
          <item>HISMAX</item>
        </inclusions>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="HISMIN">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief> Minimum value for HIS</brief>
        <description>
          Minimum pixel value to set to <def>HIS</def>.  All values greater than or equal to
	  HISMIN and less than or equal to HISMAX are converted to HIS.
        </description>
        <inclusions>
          <item>SETHISRANGE</item>
        </inclusions>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="HISMAX">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief> Maximum value for HIS</brief>
        <description>
          Maximum pixel value to set to <def>HIS</def>.  All values greater than or equal to
	  HISMIN and less than or equal to HISMAX are converted to HIS.
        </description>
        <inclusions>
          <item>SETHISRANGE</item>
        </inclusions>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="SETLRSRANGE">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default>
          <item>NO</item>
        </default>
        <brief>Option to convert pixel values to LRS</brief>
        <description>
	  If this option is set to "yes" or "true", a range of input raw pixels
	  defined by the LRSMIN and LRSMAX parameters are converted to LRS
	  pixels.  All other valid pixels that do not fall within the ranges
	  specified for LIS, HIS, HRS, and NULL pixels are transferred to the
	  output file unchanged.
        </description>
        <inclusions>
          <item>LRSMIN</item>
          <item>LRSMAX</item>
        </inclusions>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="LRSMIN">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief> Minimum value for LRS</brief>
        <description>
          Minimum pixel value to set to <def>LRS</def>.  All values greater than or equal to
	  LRSMIN and less than or equal to LRSMAX are converted to LRS.
        </description>
        <inclusions>
          <item>SETLRSRANGE</item>
        </inclusions>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="LRSMAX">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief> Maximum value for LRS </brief>
        <description>
          Maximum pixel value to set to <def>LRS</def>.  All values greater than or equal to
	  LRSMIN and less than or equal to LRSMAX are converted to LRS.
        </description>
        <inclusions>
          <item>SETLRSRANGE</item>
        </inclusions>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="SETLISRANGE">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default>
          <item>NO</item>
        </default>
        <brief>Option to convert pixel values to LIS</brief>
        <description>
	  If this option is set to "yes" or "true", a range of input raw pixels
	  defined by the LISMIN and LISMAX parameters are converted to LIS
	  pixels.  All other valid pixels that do not fall within the ranges
	  specified for LRS, HIS, HRS, and NULL pixels are transferred to the
	  output file unchanged.
        </description>
        <inclusions>
          <item>LISMIN</item>
          <item>LISMAX</item>
        </inclusions>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="LISMIN">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief> Minimum value for LIS </brief>
        <description>
          Minimum pixel value to set to <def>LIS</def>.  All values greater than or equal to
	  LISMIN and less than or equal to LISMAX are converted to LIS.
        </description>
        <inclusions>
          <item>SETLISRANGE</item>
        </inclusions>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="LISMAX">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief> Maximum value for LIS </brief>
        <description>
          Maximum pixel value to set to <def>LIS</def>.  All values greater than or equal to
	  LISMIN and less than or equal to LISMAX are converted to LIS.
        </description>
        <inclusions>
          <item>SETLISRANGE</item>
        </inclusions>
      </parameter>

    </group>

  </groups>

  <examples>
    <example>
      <brief>
        Convert PDS file to ISIS format with pds2isis
      </brief>
      <description>
        The example ingests a PDS formatted file, and outputs an ISIS cube file
	using the default settings for the program.
      </description>
      <terminalInterface>
        <commandLine>
	   from=input.img to=out.cub
        </commandLine>
        <description>
	   This example shows the use of pds2isis to create an ISIS cube file.
        </description>
      </terminalInterface>

      <guiInterfaces>
        <guiInterface>
          <image width="450" height="550" src="assets/images/pds2isisGUI.jpg">
            <brief>
	       Example GUI
            </brief>
            <description>
	       Screenshot shows the pds2isis GUI with the parameter settings.
            </description>
            <thumbnail width="164" height="200" caption="Pds2isis GUI"
             src="assets/thumbs/pds2isisGUI.jpg" />
          </image>
        </guiInterface>
      </guiInterfaces>

      <dataFiles>
        <dataFile path="assets/input.img">
          <brief>
	     The PDS formatted input file
          </brief>
          <description>
	      This is a PDS image with attached labels.
          </description>
          <parameterName>FROM</parameterName>
        </dataFile>
      </dataFiles>

      <outputImages>
        <image width="458" height="550" src="assets/images/out.jpg">
          <brief>
	      The ISIS output cube file
          </brief>
          <description>
	      This screenshot displays the ouput of the pds2isis application.
          </description>
          <thumbnail caption= "The ISIS image cube after conversion"
          src="assets/thumbs/out.jpg" width="167" height="200"/>
          <parameterName>TO</parameterName>
        </image>
      </outputImages>
    </example>
  </examples>

</application>
