<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="marci2isis" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">

    <brief>
      Import an MRO MARCI image to an Isis cube
    </brief>

    <description>
        This program takes an image from the Mars Reconnaissance Orbiter Color Imager
        and produces an Isis cube containing the image data.
    </description>

    <history>
      <change name="Steven Lambright " date="2007-10-02">
        Original Version
      </change>
      <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2008-03-18">
        Checks if input file is rdr.
      </change>
      <change name="Steven Lambright " date="2008-11-19">
        The COLOROFFSET keyword in the output instrument group labels
        is now properly set when no color offset is used.
      </change>
    </history>

    <category>
      <missionItem>Mars Reconnaissance Orbiter</missionItem>
    </category>

    <groups>
      <group name="Files">
        <parameter name="FROM">
          <type>filename</type>
          <fileMode>input</fileMode>
          <brief>
            Input file
          </brief>
          <description>
            The EDR to be processed
          </description>
          <filter>
            *.img
          </filter>
        </parameter>

        <parameter name="TO">
          <type>cube</type>
          <pixelType>real</pixelType>
          <fileMode>output</fileMode>
          <brief>
            Even bands of the output cube
          </brief>
          <description>
            This should be the base filename of resultant cube. The output will actually be two cubes,
            with "even" and "odd" added to the filename.
          </description>
          <filter>
            *.cub
          </filter>
        </parameter>
      </group>

      <group name="Settings">
        <parameter name="COLOROFFSET">
          <type>boolean</type>
          <brief>Add padding to align bands</brief>
          <description>
            The result of how MARCI takes pictures leaves a filter height offset in adjacent filters. This will correct that offset
            by adding padding to the top of the image file, aligning color images correctly.
          </description>
          <default><item>true</item></default>
          <inclusions><item>COLOROFFSET_SIZE</item></inclusions>
        </parameter>
           
        <parameter name="COLOROFFSET_SIZE">
          <type>integer</type>
          <brief>Amount of filter heights to pad with for COLOROFFSET</brief>
          <description>
            The filters are offset by a certain number of filters, which is a multiple of their height. It appears
            the filters are all offset by twice their height, or two filter heights. One filter height can be explained by
            the method of taking pictures: the first filter on the first framelet is one higher than the second filter on
            the first framelet.  
          </description>
          <default><item>2</item></default>
          <minimum inclusive="false">0</minimum>
        </parameter>
           
        <parameter name="FLIP">
          <type>string</type>
          <brief>Flip the framelets for pictures taken on ascending orbits</brief>
          <description>This corrects pictures taken on an ascending orbit</description>
          <default><item>AUTO</item></default>
          <list>
            <option value="AUTO">
            <brief>Auto-detect whether or not this correction is needed</brief>
              <description>
              This option will look at the correlation between the first framelet's data and the second framelet's data. 
              If there is a better correlation between the end of the first framelet and the end of the second
              framelet compared to the beginning of the second framelet, the framelets will be flipped. This only
              correlates the first filter's data.
              </description>
            </option> 
            <option value="YES">
              <brief>Flip the framelets</brief>
              <description>
                On ascending orbits, the framelets are aligned incorrectly. This option will mirror the framelets to correct this problem.
              </description>
            </option>
               
            <option value="NO">
              <brief>Don't modify original data</brief>
              <description>
                This will prevent any modification of the original data and should be used on descending orbits.
              </description>
            </option>
          </list>
        </parameter>
      </group>
    </groups>
    
    <examples>
      <example>
        <brief>
          Importing a MARCI EDR
        </brief>
        <description>
          This example covers importing a typical MARCI EDR using the various FLIP options.
        </description>
        <terminalInterface>
          <commandLine>
            FROM=T02_001000_1199_MC_00N230W.IMG TO=T02_001000_1199_MC_00N230W.cub FLIP=AUTO|YES|NO  
          </commandLine>
          <description>
            This is the command line for running this program with a typical EDR. FLIP should be AUTO, YES, or NO.
          </description>
        </terminalInterface>
        <guiInterfaces>
          <guiInterface>
            <image width="719" height="550" src="assets/images/gui.jpg">
              <brief>Running with default options</brief>
              <description>
                This is what the interface should look like when running this example with FLIP set to AUTO.
              </description>
              <thumbnail width="200" height="153" src="assets/thumbs/gui.jpg" caption="Running this program" />
            </image>
          </guiInterface>
        </guiInterfaces>
        <outputImages>
          <image src="assets/images/T02_001000_1199_MC_00N230W.auto.jpg" width="282" height="550">
            <brief>The output images (combined), using AUTO flip, cropped and colorized for this example</brief>
            <description>
              Since this particular input image had a RED, GREEN, and ORANGE filter, it was possible to display the image
              in color. To give a better picture of the outputs, because MARCI takes long strips of data, this image was
              cropped at line 2800 to a height of 1000 pixels. This image was created with FLIP set to AUTO, which decided to
              flip the data.
            </description>
            <thumbnail src="assets/thumbs/T02_001000_1199_MC_00N230W.auto.jpg" caption="Output Image" width="103" height="200" />
          </image>
          <image src="assets/images/T02_001000_1199_MC_00N230W.noflip.jpg" width="282" height="550">
            <brief>The output images (combined), using NO flip, cropped and colorized for this example</brief>
            <description>
              Since this particular input image had a RED, GREEN, and ORANGE filter, it was possible to display the image
              in color. To give a better picture of the outputs, because MARCI takes long strips of data, this image was
              cropped. In order to show the same feature as the flipped image, the crop was at line 5800 to a height of 1000 pixels. 
              This image was created with FLIP set to NO, because AUTO flipped the data. When you look closely, especially compared
              to the flipped data, the features in this data are distorted.
            </description>
            <thumbnail src="assets/thumbs/T02_001000_1199_MC_00N230W.noflip.jpg" caption="Output Image Without FLIP" width="103" height="200" />
          </image>
        </outputImages>
      </example>
    </examples>
</application>
