<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="tonematch" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">
  <brief>
    Matches the tone of two, single-band images
  </brief>

  <description>
    <p>This application matches the tone of two single-band images. It is very similar to the 
    equalizer application, but is only used on two images and only works on single band images. 
    The user can choose whether to match the tone of the entire image, or perform overlap matching
    using the projection information. The default behavior is to match the tones of the entire
    area of the input cube and the match cube.
    </p>

    <p>First, tonematch collects statistics on each individual cube. It then uses this data to 
    find a linear regression between the pixel values of the input cube and the match cube. The
    linear regression provides offset and gain values that are applied to the input cube, creating
    the output cube whose tone is equal to that of the match cube.
    </p>
  </description>

  <category>
    <categoryItem>Radiometric and Photometric Correction</categoryItem>
  </category>

  <seeAlso>
    <applications>
      <item>equalizer</item>
    </applications>
  </seeAlso>

  <history>
    <change name="Jeff Anderson" date="1998-01-12">
      Original version
    </change>
    <change name="Elizabeth Ribelin" date="2005-08-29">
        Documented and refactored
    </change>
    <change name="Elizabeth Miller" date="2005-11-22">
      Added appTest and poverlap option
    </change>
    <change name="Elizabeth Miller" date="2006-02-10">
      Moved to Photometry and Radiometry group in documentation
    </change>
    <change name="Kimberly Oyama" date="2013-01-14">
      Output the statistics used for the linear regression to the log. Updated documentation to 
      correctly describe the POVERLAP option and to explain that this application only works on
      single band cubes. Fixes #1383.
    </change>
  </history>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input single band cube 
        </brief>
        <description>
          The pixels of the input cube will be altered using the base and multiplier found 
           in the linear regression to make the tone of the output and match cubes equal.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="MATCH">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Match Cube (single band)
        </brief>
        <description>
          The match cube will be used to find the tone that the output cube should have.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TO">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Output cube
        </brief>
        <description>
          The resultant cube containing the tonematched image.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="OUTSTATS">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Output text file containing thorough equalization-related
          statistics
        </brief>
        <description>
          This file will contain the statistics of the overlapping area along with the computed
          equalizing factors (OFFSET and GAIN). Since the output statistics are of the overlapping
          area, the POVERLAP option must be selected. Specifying this output file is optional.
        </description>
        <internalDefault>None</internalDefault>
        <filter>
          *.txt *.pvl *.lis *.lst
        </filter>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Option">
      <parameter name="POVERLAP">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <brief>
          Projection Overlap
        </brief>
        <description>
          This parameter allows the user to match the tone of the overlapping area of the cubes
          instead of matching the tone of the entire area of both cubes. If this option is set to
          TRUE, both cubes must have the same projection parameters and must overlap.
        </description>
        <default><item>FALSE</item></default>
        <inclusions><item>OUTSTATS</item></inclusions>
      </parameter>
    </group>
  </groups>
</application>
