<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="hijitreg" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">

  <brief>
       Characterize HiRISE image jitter with co-registration
  </brief>

  <description>
      <p>
        This program co-registers two HiRISE image overlaping sections.  The
        section of overlap of each image is determined by their relative positions
        in the HiRISE focal plane assembly.   Its intended use is to characterize
        spacecraft jitter, but may also have other uses, such as determining
        relative gains and zero-level offsets of adjacent CCDs, this from the
        linear regression data computed for each registration chip.
      </p>
      <p>
        hijitreg requires the two images provided in FROM and MATCH have
        some portion of overlap.  This is typically adjacent CCDs, such as RED4
        and RED5 but individual CCD channels can be processed as well.
        The appropriate channel will need to be provided, however.  For example,
        RED4_0 and RED5_1 are overlapping channel files, but RED4_1 and
        RED3_1 are not.  Furthermore, this application can be used to
        characterize offsets of the color sets as well.  I will describe these
        scenarios in more detail below. 
      </p>
      <p>
        The offsets are determined using HiRISE focal plane locations for
        each CCD.  Adjacent CCDs are designed to have at least 48 pixels
        of overlap between them.
        However, it has been determined the amount of overlap can vary under
        most viewing conditions.  Thus, hijitreg can utilize the same sample and
        line offset information used by <i>hiccdstitch</i> to adjust each CCD's
        relative position within the HiRISE focal plane.  hijitreg then makes the
        appropriate localized adjustments to determine the final overlap used to
        characterize the two image sections.  See the documentation for the
        SHIFTDEF parameter for <i>hiccdstitch</i> for further details.
     </p>
      <p>
          The type of registration algorithm and appropriate parameters for its
          use is determined by the REGDEF parameter.  This follows the Isis
          standard.  Below is an example of the PVL-format that is expected
          in the file provided.
      </p>
     <pre>
         Object = AutoRegistration
           Group = Algorithm
             Name         = MaximumCorrelation
             Tolerance    = 0.7
           EndGroup

           Group = PatternChip
             Samples = 17
             Lines   = 45
           EndGroup

           Group = SearchChip
             Samples = 30
             Lines   = 70
           EndGroup
         EndObject
     </pre>
     <p>
         A chip registration grid is defined across the MATCH image using the
         parameters ROWS  and COLUMNS.   If the user does not provide
         values for the grid size, it will be automatically computed as
         follows:  ROWS = (line overlap - 1) / search chip lines + 1.  The
         default for COLUMNS is set to 1.  This default condition assumes
         processing of overlapping regions that are approximately 48 pixels.
         However, if you specify 0, then the computation for 
         COLUMNS is the same as it is for ROWS only using sample overlap.
         Conceptually,  the chip grid defined by ROWS and COLUMNS will be
         laid on top of both images with even spacing between the rows (or
         columns) and but no row will touch the top or bottom of the image.
         That is, the grid is internal to the image.
     </p>
     <p>
         At each grid intersection, a translation will be computed.  This is done
         by centering the search chip at the grid intersection for the image to
         be translated (FROM) and centering the pattern chip at the grid
         intersection for the  held image (MATCH).  The pattern chip is walked
         through the search chip to find the best registration (if any).   The
         details of how this is done is described in the document "Automatic
         Registation in Isis 3.0".  The local translation is recorded at all grid
         intersections that had a successful registration.  It will be written to
         the FLATFILE if requested.  The average and standard deviation of the
         local translations is computed and reported as well..
     </p>
     <p>
         Some tips to improve odds of a successful registration.  In general
         don't go too small with the pattern chip size, 17x45 is the nomimal
         starting point.  Also, the larger the translation, the larger the search
         chip size will need to be.  So if your translation is only a couple of
         pixels keep the search chip slightly bigger than the pattern 
         (e.g., 25x55 vs 17x45).  However if the translation is large you will
         need to expand the search area.  For example,  if the translation is
         roughly 45 pixels and your pattern is 20x20 the search area should
         be 20+2*45 or 110x110.
     </p>
     <p>
         <b>A word of caution.</b>  In testing, we found that some of the correlations
         reported were wildly huge.  This indicates that the best fitting offset is
         at the very edge of the search chip.  When using the MaximumCorrelation
         algorithm, they should be between -1 and 1.  There is a keyword added
         to the log file called <i>NSuspects</i> that indicates the number of
         occurances of this condition.  If this is not 0, then chances are this
         issue occured.  This may only apply to the MaximumCorrelation
         algorithm.

         To rectify this problem,
         examine the RegLine and RegSamp values and compare with the FromLine
         and FromSamp, respectively.  If the registering sample or line is near
         the search chip threshold (i.e., FromSamp+(SearchChip/Samples/2) or
         FromLine+(SearchChip/Lines/2)) then increase the size of the search
         chip dimensions appropriately.
     </p>
     <p>
         A typical command line run of hijitreg will look like:
         <PRE>
          hijitreg FROM=AEB_000002_0050_RED5.cub MATCH=AEB_000002_0050_RED4.cub \
                      REGDEF='$mro/calibration/hijitreg.p1745.s3070.def' \
                      SHIFTDEF='$mro/calibration/hiccdstitch.000002_0050_RED.def' \
                      FLATFILE=AEB_000002_0050_RED5.dat
         </PRE>
         To register RED to IR or BG images, you will typically need to insure
         that, at a minumum, the summing modes are equivalent.  If they are not,
         you must run <i>enlarge</i> or <i>reduce</i>, whichever makes sense,
         and then use <i>editlab</i> to change the /IsisCube/Instrument/Summing
         keyword to the appropriate mode.  The keyword values in both images
         must be the same number.  Note that both samples and lines must be
         increased or decreased in order to yield appropriate results.
         Once equivalent summing modes are achieved, you will likely have to get
         the images lined up using sample and line offsets.  This is done via the 
         SHIFTDEF parameter.  Further adjustments should be considered.  For
         example, now a much large portion of the images are overlapping.  You
         may wish to specify 3 columns, evenly spaced, to register.  Set the
         COLUMNS and ROWS parameters appropriately.
     </p>
  </description>

  <category>
      <missionItem>Mars Reconnaissance Orbiter</missionItem>
  </category>  

  <seeAlso>
      <applications>
          <item>autoregtemplate</item>
          <item>coreg</item>
      </applications>
      <documents>
          <document>
              <title>Automatic Registration in Isis 3.0</title>
          </document>
      </documents>
  </seeAlso>

  <history>
     <change name="Kris Becker" date="2006-05-04">
         Original Version
     </change>
     <change name="Kris Becker" date="2006-05-31">
         Added CNETFILE parameter to provide easier input into transform
         applications such as the 1-D transform anticipated to operate on
         the results of this application.
     </change>
     <change name="Kris Becker" date="2006-06-16">
          Added specification of reference image in the control net file to
          support subsequent use (e.g., 1-D transform). 
      </change>
    <change name="Brendan George" date="2006-09-28">
        Documentation fixes
    </change>
    <change name="Brendan George" date="2006-10-03">
        Modified calls to get current time to use Time class, instead of
        Application class
    </change>
    <change name="Brendan George" date="2006-12-08">
        Modified to conform to changes made to SerialNumber
    </change>
    <change name="Janet Barrett" date="2007-02-23">
        Added support for noproj'ed files. The files are required to
	have a summing mode of 1. Support for noproj'ed files with
	other summing modes will be added later. Noproj'ed files are
	also required to have 20000 samples. This will be fixed later.
    </change>
    <change name="Janet Barrett" date="2007-08-08">
        Modified program so that noproj'ed files are no longer 
	required to have a summing mode of 1. Support was also added
	for noproj'ed IR and BG files.
    </change>
    <change name="Janet Barrett" date="2007-11-21">
        Modified program to look at the PixelPitch keyword in the
	Instrument group of noproj'ed images to determine what the
	summing mode is. The PixelPitch value is divided by .012
	to calculate the summing mode.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2008-06-23">
        Updated to properly check AutoReg::Register()'s return status
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Koechle" date="2008-08-18">
	Updated to work with Geos 3.0.0
    </change>
    <change name="Travis Addair" date="2009-08-10">
        Auto registration parameters are now placed into the print file.
    </change>
  </history>

  <groups>
    <group name="Input Files">
      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          HiRISE image that will have line/sample offsets computed for
        </brief>
        <description>
          This cube will be registered to the MATCH cube and corresponds to
          the search chip (the larger sized chip).   This file can be either a stitched
          CCD or an individual CCD channel.  If a channel is provided, be sure it
          one that shares common overlap with the MATCH cube.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="MATCH">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          HiRISE image that will contain the pattern to match the FROM image
        </brief>
        <description>
          This HiRISE cube will be held fixed in the registration process. The
          FROM cube will be translated to match this cube. 
          It corresponds to the pattern chip (the smaller sized chip).
          This file can be either a stitched
          CCD or an individual CCD channel.  If a channel is provided, be sure it
          one that shares common overlap with the FROM cube.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="REGDEF">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          The Auto Registration template
        </brief>
        <description>
          The registration template for correlations. Default will be MaximumCorrelation function
          with a tolerance of 0.7, a search chip of 30X70 pixels, and a pattern chip of 17X45 pixels.
          There may also be other templates available in the default MRO directory as well as
          the base templates directory, $base/templates/autoreg.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.def
        </filter>
        <default><item>$mro/calibration/hijitreg.p1745.s3070.def</item></default>
        <defaultPath>$mro/calibration</defaultPath>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="SHIFTDEF">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <internalDefault>None</internalDefault>
        <brief>
          Pvl file containing absolute shifts for CCD lines and samples.
        </brief>
        <description>
            <p>
                For convenience and consistancy, the same offset file used in
                the <i>hiccdstitch</i> application can be used here to specify line and
                sample offsets for each HiRISE CCD.   The documentation below
                is the same as it is for <i>hiccdstitch</i>.
            </p>
            <p>
                This file contains groups for each CCD that requires a 
                modification to its placement into the HiRISE
                focal plane.  The name of each group is the CCD name for
                which the shift in line or sample is needed.  For example, the
                leftmost CCD, CCD 0 is named "RED0", the next "RED1" and
                so on.  <i>hiccdstitch</i> searches for names of groups that match
                the stitched input cube files and will apply offsets to the
                default sample and line location of where the CCD is mapped to
                in the focal plane.
            </p>
            <p>
                Offsets for both line and sample can be supplied.  None, one or
                both can be provided for any CCD.  Negative values shift the 
                image left if a sample offset is given or up if a line offset is given.
                Positive values in sample and line shift the image right and down,
                respectively.
            </p>
            <p>
                These shifts are absolute shifts and only apply to
                the specified CCD and are not propagated to subsequent CCDs
                left to right in the focal plane layout.  (HiRISE CCD arrangement
                is always left to right as far as <i>hijitreg</i> is concerned.)
             </p>
            <p>
                Below is an example of the format of the input file for the
                SHIFTDEF file:
            </p>
            <pre>
            Object = Hiccdstitch
              Group = RED0
                SampleOffset     = -10
                LineOffset       = 5
              End_Group

              Group = RED3
                SampleOffset     = 13
                LineOffset       = -5
              End_Group

              Group = RED5
                LineOffset       = 22
              End_Group

               Group = IR11
                SampleOffset     = -4
                LineOffset       = 2
              End_Group

              Group = BG12
                SampleOffset     = 12
              End_Group
            End_Object
            End
            </pre>
            <p>
                The only keywords that hiccdstitch reads from this file
                are <b>SampleOffset</b> and <b>LineOffset</b>.  All
                other keywords are ignored.  Note that groups named
                by CCD name must exist as well as all specified groups
                must be contained within the <b>Hiccdstitch</b> object.
            </p>
            <p>
                Note that this file is an optional parameter.  If it is not
                provided, then all CCD files provided are mapped to
                focal plane positions as specified in the HiRISE
                Instrument Operations Handbook.  The size
                of a HiRISE pixel is 0.012 millimeters and the measurements
                in the handbook are also in millimeters.
            </p>
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.def
        </filter>
        <defaultPath>$mro/calibration</defaultPath>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Input Parameters">
      <parameter name= "ROWS">
          <type>integer</type>
          <brief>
              Number of Rows of grid points to use.
          </brief>
          <description>
              The number of rows of grid points to use in the registration
               process.  If not entered, it will default to
               ROWS = (lines of overlap - 1) / search chip lines + 1.
          </description>
          <internalDefault>Automatic</internalDefault>
          <minimum inclusive="true">1</minimum>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name= "COLUMNS">
          <type>integer</type>
          <brief>
              Number of Columns grids points to register.
          </brief>
          <description>
              The number of columns of grid points to use in the registration process.
              If not entered, the default is set to 1.  This assumes we are registering
              adjacent CCD overlap.  The user can have the application compute the
              number of grid columns similar to how ROWS is done.  To use this
              option, set COLUMNS = 0.  The application will then compute
              the number of grid columns as 
              COLUMNS = (samples of overlap - 1) / search chip samples + 1.
          </description>
          <default><item>1</item></default>
          <minimum inclusive="true">0</minimum>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Output">
        <parameter name="FLATFILE">
          <type>filename</type>
          <fileMode>output</fileMode>
          <brief>
               Text file of registration data
          </brief>
          <description>
              <p>
               This file will contain the data collected from the application. 
               Data pertaining to the input images that may have relevance
               to the analysis is provided in free form.  This includes lines,
               samples, offsets, CPMM number, summing, TDI mode, overlap
               and timing information.    In addition, there is registration data
               included such as sample and line spacing (which is typically
               a single column), registration algorithm and tolerances and
               the results of the correlation processing.
              </p>
              <p>
               In addition to the above general information, a table of information
               follows where each row contains registration information for each
               chip.  There are 12 columns of data for each chip (row).    Below is
               a description of each column:
              </p>
              <p>
                  <TABLE BORDER="1">
                      <CAPTION>Column description for FLATFILE data</CAPTION>
                      <TR>
                        <TH>Heading</TH>
                        <TH>Column Description</TH>
                      </TR>
                      <TR>
                         <TD>FromTime</TD>
                         <TD>
                           The time the line in the FROM image was observed
                           (scanned) expressed in ephemeris time
                         </TD>
                      </TR>
                      <TR>
                          <TD>FromSamp</TD>
                          <TD>
                              Image sample in the FROM file of the center of
                              the correlation chip
                          </TD>
                      </TR>
                      <TR>
                          <TD>FromLine</TD>
                          <TD>
                              Image line in the FROM file of the center of the
                              correlation chip
                          </TD>
                      </TR>
                      <TR>
                         <TD>MatchTime</TD>
                         <TD>
                           The time the line in the MATCH image was observed
                           (scanned) expressed in ephemeris time
                         </TD>
                      </TR>
                      <TR>
                          <TD>MatchSamp</TD>
                          <TD>
                              Image sample in the MATCH file of the center of
                              the correlation chip
                          </TD>
                      </TR>
                      <TR>
                          <TD>MatchLine</TD>
                          <TD>
                              Image line in the MATCH file of the center of the
                              correlation chip
                          </TD>
                      </TR>
                      <TR>
                          <TD>RegSamp</TD>
                          <TD>
                               Best registering sample in the FROM file resulting
                               from the correlation.
                          </TD>
                      </TR>
                      <TR>
                          <TD>RegLine</TD>
                          <TD>
                              Best registering line in the FROM file resulting
                              from the correlation
                          </TD>
                      </TR>
                      <TR>
                          <TD>RegCorr</TD>
                          <TD>
                              Correlation coefficient of the best registering sample
                              and line in the FROM file.  This will typically be between
                              1.0 and -1.0.  <B>NOTE:</B>  At times these values can
                              be wildly huge, as indicated by the <i>NSuspects</i>
                              log file keyword.  This typically indicates the specified
                              search chip is not large enough.  Inspect the
                              registering sample and line to determine which size
                              to increase and rerun the correlation.
                          </TD>
                      </TR>
                      <TR>
                          <TD>B0_Offset</TD>
                          <TD>
                              This is the offset in the linear regression analysis of the
                              best registering chip
                          </TD>
                      </TR>
                      <TR>
                          <TD>B1_Slope</TD>
                          <TD>
                              This is the slope in the linear regression analysis of the
                              best registering chip
                          </TD>
                      </TR>
                      <TR>
                          <TD>B_RCorr</TD>
                          <TD>
                              This is the correlation coefficient resulting from the linear
                              regression analysis of the best registering chip in the FROM
                              image compared to the corresponding area from the MATCH
                              chip.  The Linear Regression equation is:
                              <PRE>
                                  <i>y = B0_Offset + B1_Slope * x</i>
                              </PRE>
                              Here, <i>y</i> is the output FROM Dn and <i>x</i> is the
                              FROM input Dn.   In theory, one could use <i>poly</i> to
                              apply this to the FROM image and it will adjust FROM 
                              to look closer to MATCH in brightness levels.
                          </TD>
                      </TR>
                  </TABLE>
              </p>
              <p>
                  Linear regression analysis is performed on each chip.  The best
                  registering sample and line is computed at the sub-pixel level (this
                  can be modified in the REGDEF file).  The best registered chip
                  is read from the FROM file at the subpixel level and compared
                  with the correlated search chip in the MATCH file.
              </p>

          </description>
          <internalDefault>None</internalDefault>
          <filter>
            *.txt *.lis *.lst
          </filter>
        </parameter>

        <parameter name="CNETFILE">
          <type>filename</type>
          <fileMode>output</fileMode>
          <brief>
             Crontrol net file for input into transform applications
          </brief>
          <description>
             This file will contain the ControlNet created in the hijitreg application.  The data
             will be in Pvl format.  This option is required if the subsequent transformations of
             the FROM files is desired.  hijitreg is specifically designed to apply a 1-D
             transform that shifts each line in the line and sample direction as indicated in
             the control net.
           </description>
          <internalDefault>None</internalDefault>
          <filter>
          *.txt *.lis *.lst
          </filter>
        </parameter>
    </group>
  </groups>
</application>
