<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="qview" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">
  <brief>
    Display and analyze cubes
  </brief>

  <description>
    <p>
      This program will display cubes and allow for interactive analysis. Although the program
      comprises a number of individual tools to perform analysis on your data, only the Spatial
      Plot Tool is discussed here until further notice.
    </p>
    <h3>Spatial Plot Tool</h3>
    <p>
      This tool is used for analyzing manually selected pixel DN values. It works with two
      different modes: linear and rotated rectangle. It is also capable of handling three different
      modes of interpolation: Nearest Neighbor, BiLinear and Cubic Convolution.
    </p>
    <h4>Linear</h4>
    <p>
      This mode involves drawing a
      line across an open cube. The selection is started by clicking and holding the mouse where
      you would like to start your calculations, at which point you may drag the mouse in any
      direction and release the click to establish the end of your selection.
    </p>
    <p>
      The tool calculates the length of the line in pixels, rounding to the nearest full pixel
      value. It then divides the actual length of the line by this rounded length to achieve a
      step-size. <strong>Please note:</strong> This step size may be slightly bigger or smaller
      than a pixel length, but this difference becomes negligible for larger selections. For
      example, if the length of the drawn line was 2.91 pixels, the tool would round the length to
      3 and the step-size would be 2.91/3 (or 0.97).
    </p>
    <p>
      A plot window will be generated with the calculated DN values of the pixels. The first value
      to be calculated is the value where the original mouse click was made. At each increment,
      according to step size, the tool calculates the value along the line until it reaches where the
      mouse-click was released. This means that for a line with a rounded length of 3, the plot would show a
      total of 4 plotted DN values. <strong>Please note:</strong> For a line with a rounded length of
      <i>n</i>, the tool will calculate <i>n</i> + 1 values.
    </p>
    <!--
    <image src="assets/image/LinearSelection.png" height="400" />
    <image src="assets/image/LinearPlot.png" height="400" />
    <p>
      The images above include an example of the line as drawn in the cube view and the
      associated plot window. Marking has been added to delineate where mouse clicks were made and
      the DN values were calculated. The mouse was first clicked at dileneation marked "1" on the
      cube, and was released at "4". The number from the cube view correlates with the "Pixel
      Number" on the plot.
    </p>
    -->
    <h4>Rotated Rectangle</h4>
    <p>
      This mode of the Spatial Plot Tool involves drawing a
      rectangle across an open cube. The selection starts by clicking and holding the mouse
      where you would like to start your calculations, at which point you may drag the mouse in any
      direction and release the click to establish one edge of your selection. You may then
      drag the mouse away from this original line to expand in the other direction. A single mouse
      click establishes your final selection. <strong>Please note:</strong> The tool will lock
      angles to be perpendicular and so your selections will always be a perfect rectangle.
    </p>

    <p>
      Similar to the linear mode of this tool, the lengths of the lines in pixels are rounded to the
      nearest full pixel value, and then the lengths are divided by their rounded lengths to establish
      a step-size. <strong>Please note:</strong>
      The step-size along one edge of the selection may differ from the step-size of the
      perpendicular edge, this becomes negligible for larger selections. For
      example, if the length of the line in one direction was 2.91 pixels, the step-size would be 2.91/3
      (or 0.97), whereas if the length of the line in the perpendicular direction was 4.92, the step
      size would be 4.92/5 (0.98).
    </p>
    <p>
      A plot window will be generated with the calculated DN values. This is done by calculating the
      value where the original mouse click was made, then continuing in the direction of that
      first-drawn line, calculating the DN value at each step-sized increment until it reaches where
      the original mouse-click was released. The tool will then calculate the average of these
      values. This average becomes the first value in the plot.
    </p>
    <p>
      The tool will then shift a step-size along the perpendicular edge, and calculate the average DN
      value along a line running parallel to the first-drawn line. This average becomes the second
      value in the plot. The tool continues this pattern until it has reached the opposite edge of
      the rectangle as the first-drawn line.
    </p>
    <!--
    <image src="assets/image/RRSelection.png" height="400" />
    <image src="assets/image/RRSelectionMarked.png" height="400" />
    <image src="assets/image/RRPlot.png" height="400" />
    <p>
      The first image is the original selection. The second image
      is the same view that has been marked for reference purposes. Finally, the last image
      is the associated plot window. The original mouse click was made at delineation
      "1" within the cube view, the original mouse release was made at "5", and the final
      mouse click was made at "15". The Spatial Plot Tool calculates the average of the DN values at
      delineations 1-5, and this value is stored as "Pixel Value" 1 in the plot window, while the
      averages of 6-10 are stored in 2, and 7-15 are stored in 3.
    </p>
    -->
    <h4>Interpolations</h4>
    <p>
      Spatial Plot Tool makes use of Nearest Nieghbor, BiLinear and Cubic Convolution interpolations
      when calculating the DN values at particular points. <strong>Do be aware that when the tool is
      calculating a DN value at a particular point, it is calculating the interpolated DN value at
      that point.</strong>
    </p>
  </description>

  <category>
    <categoryItem>Display</categoryItem>
  </category>

  <history>
    <change name="Jeff Anderson" date="2004-12-01">
      Original version
    </change>
    <change name="Jeff Anderson" date="2006-01-06">
      Port to Qt4 and add blink tool
    </change>
    <change name="Elizabeth Miller" date="2006-07-26">
      Fixed bug with filename expansion and added the MeasureTool
    </change>
    <change name="Brendan George" date="2006-09-19">
      Documentation fixes
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2007-09-11">
      Added new rubber band functionality
    </change>
    <change name="Sharmila Prasad" date="2009-10-19">
      Added Mosaic Tracking info like image index, serial number and file name
      in the Advanced Tracking window to have the ability to track mosaic
      origin.
    </change>
    <change name="Jeannie Walldren" date="2010-03-08">
      Modified FindTool.  If a user enters a line/sample in the Image tab, then
      the corresponding lat/lon is displayed in the Ground tab.  Added Record
      button to FindTool to record clicked or typed point in the
      AdvancedTrackTool window.
    </change>
    <change name="Sharmila Prasad" date="2010-03-19">
      "qview" now has the ability to handle exceptions. The status bar now
      displays a default NoWarning icon with "Ready" message. If an
      exception is caught, the icon changes to Warning and displays the error
      message. Clicking on the Warning icon will display a dialog window with
      the details of the most recent error occured. Closing the dialog or any
      other mouse activity will reset the Warning status.
    </change>
    <change name="Eric Hyer" date="2010-03-22">
      Discontinued forcing of gui style to windows
    </change>
    <change name="Sharmila Prasad" date="2010-03-24">
      Enable FindTool for images without camera and/or projection
    </change>
    <change name="Sharmila Prasad" date="2011-02-16">Added columns Local
     Emission and  Incidence Angles for Advanced Tracking Tool
    </change>
    <change name="Sharmila Prasad" date="2011-03-18">
      Connect the viewport's close signal to the all windows/subwindows like
      plottool and histogram tools as well.
    </change>
    <change name="Sharmila Prasad" date="2011-05-11">
      Added options for SaveAs to save cube as fullImage, Export AsIs or Export
      FullResolution options
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright, Jai Rideout and Tracie Sucharski" date="2012-01-18">
      Re-implemented all of the plotting functionality in order to improve the
      user interface and capabilities. Added best fit lines and a scatter plot.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2012-03-22">
      Added the sun shadow and feature nomenclature tools.
    </change>
    <change name="Tracie Sucharski" date="2012-04-24">
      Added the stereo tool which calculates spot elevations and elevation profiles
      from pairs of stereo images.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2012-05-29">
      Fixed prompts for saving edited files on closing so they are functional once again.
      Fixes #854.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright and Kimberly Oyama" date="2012-06-11">
      Updated the nomenclature tool to include the option to choose from three
      types of extent displays (4 arrows, 8 arrows, or a box) and the option
      to display all features or only IAU approved features.
    </change>
    <change name="Kimberly Oyama and Steven Lambright" date="2012-06-22">
      Updated the Advanced Track Tool to include a help menu and a help dialog that opesn with the
      tool and when the user opens it through the help menu. Fixes #772.
    </change>
    <change name="Kimberly Oyama and Steven Lambright" date="2012-06-26">
      Fixed query range problems with the nomenclature tool. It can now handle longitudinal ranges
      that encompass the 0/360 line. Fixes #958.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2012-06-28">
      The special pixel colorization tool's settings won't be forgotten when restretching.
      Also, images that are opened after using this tool will now take on the appropriate
      colors. Fixes #684.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2012-06-29">
      Improved handling of special pixels in the statistics tool so that they are reported
      correctly. Fixes #199.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2012-07-03">
      Added M/KM options to the spatial plot tool. Fixes #853.
    </change>
    <change name="Tracie Sucharski" date="2012-07-30">
      Added the match tool which allows registration (control points) to be edited
      between cubes without a camera model.
    </change>
    <change name="Tracie Sucharski" date="2012-10-01">
      Fixed bug in the match tool which caused qview to to print error messages and possibly
      crash when closing cube viewports either individually or from the File Menu.
    </change>
    <change name="Tracie Sucharski" date="2013-01-08">
      Add the AlphaCube to the labels of and exported cropped cube.  Fixes #706.
    </change>
    <change name="Tracie Sucharski" date="2013-01-08">
      Fixed bug when saving a cube viewport that is displayed at full resolution,  the application
      would seg fault.  Fixes #1386.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2013-01-24">
      Fixed spatial plot tool functionality on single line images. Fixes #997.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2013-01-31">
      Improved upon the accuracy of the find tool's sync scale option. Fixes #953.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2013-02-12">
      The red boxes that indicate the current selection (i.e. the rubber band) shown
      while creating plots, updating stretches, and other actions should now only draw
      on cubes (viewports) that are relevant to the action being performed. Fixes #1035.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2013-02-07">
      The plot tables should no longer have multiple rows with the same X value. Also, fixed a crash
      related to closing the plot table windows. Fixes #710. Fixes #818.
    </change>
    <change name="Kimberly Oyama and Stuart Sices" date="2013-12-30">
      Changed the character that is used as a token when parsing the list of file names used when
      the socket is already open. Fixes #1551.
    </change>
    <change name="Ian Humphrey" date="2014-07-30">
      Modified spectral plot tool to more accurately compute statistics for rectangular and
      polygonal selections. Fixes #2071.
    </change>
    <change name="Ian Humphrey" date="2014-07-31">
      Added configurePlotCurves() method to PlotWindow. User can activate configure dialog on
      single curve with right-click or activate dialog with combo box of all curves using the
      toolbar button. Added What's This for SpatialPlotTool and removed the configure toolbar button
      for ScatterPlotWindow. Fixes #2089.
    </change>
    <change name="Ian Humphrey" date="2015-10-07">
      Updated icons. Fixes #1041.
    </change>
    <change name="Ian Humphrey" date="2015-11-19">
      Added shortcuts to Match Tool window for selecting right measures, registration, undo
      registration, saving measures, saving the point, and saving the control network. Fixes #2324.
    </change>
    <change name="Ian Humphrey" date="2017-05-10">
      Fixed initial loading of viewport and Fit to viewport zoom to correctly zoom to the center
      of the image. Fixes #4756.
    </change>
    <change name="Adam Paquette" date="2017-05-19">
      Readded help menu for the 2D and 3D plot tools. Now properly display in both tools.
      Fixes #2126.
    </change>
    <change name="Summer Stapleton" date="2018-03-14">
      Included documentation for Spatial Plot Tool in this .xml. References #5281.
    </change>
    <change name="Amy Stamile" date="2022-08-26">
      Added latitude and longtitude grid display.
    </change>
  </history>
</application>
