<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="qview" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">
  <brief>
    Display and analyze cubes
  </brief>

  <description>
    This program will display cubes and allow for interactive analysis.
  </description>

  <category>
    <categoryItem>Display</categoryItem>
  </category>

  <history>
    <change name="Jeff Anderson" date="2004-12-01">
      Original version
    </change>
    <change name="Jeff Anderson" date="2006-01-06">
      Port to Qt4 and add blink tool
    </change>
    <change name="Elizabeth Miller" date="2006-07-26">
      Fixed bug with filename expansion and added the MeasureTool
    </change>
    <change name="Brendan George" date="2006-09-19">
      Documentation fixes
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2007-09-11">
      Added new rubber band functionality
    </change>
    <change name="Sharmila Prasad" date="2009-10-19">
      Added Mosaic Tracking info like image index, serial number and file name
      in the Advanced Tracking window to have the ability to track mosaic
      origin.
    </change>
    <change name="Jeannie Walldren" date="2010-03-08">
      Modified FindTool.  If a user enters a line/sample in the Image tab, then
      the corresponding lat/lon is displayed in the Ground tab.  Added Record
      button to FindTool to record clicked or typed point in the
      AdvancedTrackTool window.
    </change>
    <change name="Sharmila Prasad" date="2010-03-19">
      "qview" now has the ability to handle exceptions. The status bar now
      displays a default NoWarning icon with "Ready" message. If an
      exception is caught, the icon changes to Warning and displays the error
      message. Clicking on the Warning icon will display a dialog window with
      the details of the most recent error occured. Closing the dialog or any
      other mouse activity will reset the Warning status.
    </change>
    <change name="Eric Hyer" date="2010-03-22">
      Discontinued forcing of gui style to windows
    </change>
    <change name="Sharmila Prasad" date="2010-03-24">
      Enable FindTool for images without camera and/or projection
    </change>
    <change name="Sharmila Prasad" date="2011-02-16">Added columns Local
     Emission and  Incidence Angles for Advanced Tracking Tool
    </change>
    <change name="Sharmila Prasad" date="2011-03-18">
      Connect the viewport's close signal to the all windows/subwindows like
      plottool and histogram tools as well.
    </change>
    <change name="Sharmila Prasad" date="2011-05-11">
      Added options for SaveAs to save cube as fullImage, Export AsIs or Export
      FullResolution options
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright, Jai Rideout and Tracie Sucharski" date="2012-01-18">
      Re-implemented all of the plotting functionality in order to improve the
      user interface and capabilities. Added best fit lines and a scatter plot.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2012-03-22">
      Added the sun shadow and feature nomenclature tools.
    </change>
    <change name="Tracie Sucharski" date="2012-04-24">
      Added the stereo tool which calculates spot elevations and elevation profiles
      from pairs of stereo images.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2012-05-29">
      Fixed prompts for saving edited files on closing so they are functional once again.
      Fixes #854.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright and Kimberly Oyama" date="2012-06-11">
      Updated the nomenclature tool to include the option to choose from three
      types of extent displays (4 arrows, 8 arrows, or a box) and the option
      to display all features or only IAU approved features.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2012-06-28">
      The special pixel colorization tool's settings won't be forgotten when restretching.
      Also, images that are opened after using this tool will now take on the appropriate
      colors. Fixes #684.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2012-06-29">
      Improved handling of special pixels in the statistics tool so that they are reported
      correctly. Fixes #199.
    </change>
  </history>
</application>
