<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="kernfilter" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">

  <brief>
    Filter a cube through a kernel
  </brief>

  <description>
    This program uses a kernel gathered from an input file to filter a cube. 
    The intent of the program is to allow a flexible, user-defined kernel to
    be applied to an image. This program is not recommended for cubes with 
    significant numbers of special pixels as it will create more special pixels. 
    A group of pre-made kernels has been provided, but the procedure to 
    create a custom kernel is outlined below. 
      <p/> A kernel follows
    the rules and regulations of the Isis PVL (parameter value language). This
    means that several keywords must be inserted into the text document which
    will become the custom kernel. Any text editor should allow you to create a
    kernel, though the program will only read files with the .txt extension. In
    addition, there are some specifications that must be met. <p/> A sample
    kernel file will appear in the form
    <pre> 
    Group=Kernel 
      Samples=2 
      Lines=1 
      Weight=1 
      Data= (1, -1)
    EndGroup
    </pre> 
    The "group" keyword should equal Kernel (Group=Kernel). This lets the 
    program know that it is the users intent that the text file is used as a 
    kernel.
    <p/>
    The "lines" and "samples" keywords should match the amount of data that
    is supplied in the data keyword. In this example, there are 2 samples 
    worth of data and 1 line worth. The keywords above thus reflect these 
    values.
    <p/>
    The "weight" is applied to all of the values in the kernel. It is 
    often set to a fraction that allows for averaging, but it is a value
    that is used differently by each type of filter simulated by the 
    kernel. Since the above filter uses no averaging, the weight is simply 1.
    <p/>
    The "data" defines a set of multiplicative constants. These multiplicative
    constants are the weights that the kernfilter will use on the input image.
    In our example, assume that the DNs being examined are 10 and 20. The 
    first DN (10) would be multiplied by the first weight (1). The second DN 
    (20) would be multiplied by the second weight (-1). The two products (10 
    and -20) would then be added together and the resultant sum (-10) would 
    be output.  The set of data should be enclosed in parentheses. For 
    organizational purposes, one may insert as much or as little white space
    as they desire but they must separate each constant with a comma.
    <p/>
    Finally, the document should be finished with the keyword "EndGroup" to
    signify that no more information is provided.
  </description>

  <history>
    <change name="Drew Davidson" date="2004-07-26">
      Original version
    </change>
    <change name="Drew Davidson" date="2004-07-27">
      Added application test
    </change>
    <change name="Drew Davidson" date="2004-08-16">
      Added examples
    </change>
    <change name="Elizabeth Miller" date="2006-07-24">
      Moved kernel files to the $base/templates/kernels folder
    </change>
    <change name="Mackenzie Boyd" date="2009-07-27"> 
      Added error checking for kernel input, modified special pixel handling to
      null resultant pixel, added example, added application test, changed
      pixel type to real.
    </change>
  </history>

  <category>
    <categoryItem>Filters</categoryItem>
  </category>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input cube to be filtered
        </brief>
        <description>
          Use this parameter to select the filename. All bands within the file
          will be filtered.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TO">
        <type>cube</type>
        <pixelType>real</pixelType>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Output cube
        </brief>
        <description>
          This file will contain the results of the filter
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub 
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="KERNEL">
         <type>filename</type>
         <fileMode>input</fileMode>
         <defaultPath>$base/templates/kernels/</defaultPath>
         <brief>
           The kernel that describes the filter to be applied
         </brief>
         <description>
           Use this parameter to select the file to be used as the kernel.    
           The input kernel is by default found in the "kernels" directory and
           includes several examples that can be used to filter images.
         </description>
         <filter>
           *.txt
         </filter>
       </parameter>

    </group>
  </groups>
  
  <examples>
    <example>
      <brief>
       Using the highpassCircle5x5.txt kernel
      </brief>
      <description>
        This example assumes that a kernel named "highpassCircle5x5.txt" (which         
        is provided with the program) exists in the "kernels" file that is 
        created by default. The program does not actually run a highpass 
        algorithm on the cube. Instead, it weighs the pixels with a common 
        algorithm that adds all of the weighted pixel values together and 
        outputs that sum as the center pixel of the boxcar. The weights, which 
        are provided by the user-specified parameter "kernel" define the 
        characteristics of that final sum. In this example, the kernel 
        "highpassCircle5x5.txt" (which is provided with the program) is 
        selected. The kernel weights are as follows:
        <pre>
        0  -1  -1  -1   0
       -1  -1  -1  -1  -1
       -1  -1  24  -1  -1     x .04
       -1  -1  -1  -1  -1
        0  -1  -1  -1   0 
      </pre> 
       Thus, the highpass filter is simulated. The center pixel will be
       multiplied by 24. Then this value will be added to the values of its 
       surrounding pixels (all of these values will either have a sign change
       since they were multiplied by -1 in this filter or they will be 0, since
       0 and -1 are the only weight values that the filter holds, except for the
       center pixel). Finally, after all of the addition has been done, the final
       sum of all of the weights that were multiplied by either 24, or -1, or 0, 
       will be multiplied by .04, which equals 1/25. The reason all of the pixels
        are multiplied by 1/25 is that there are 25 spots in the 5 by 5 kernel, 
        and thus the image will be normalized.
      </description>
      <terminalInterface>
        <commandLine> 
          from= peaks.cub to=highpass.cub kernel=highpassCircle5x5.txt     
        </commandLine>
        <description> 
          The kernfilter program has been loaded with a kernel that will 
          simulate a circular highpass filter with a 5 x 5 boxcar.
        </description>
      </terminalInterface>
      
      <guiInterfaces>
        <guiInterface>   
          <image width="440" height="625" 
            src="assets/images/kernHighpassGui.jpg">
            <brief>
              Example GUI
            </brief>
            <description>
              Screenshot of the GUI with parameters set to simulate the highpass
              filter with a 5 x 5 circular boxcar.
            </description>
            <thumbnail width="220" height="312" caption="kernfilter gui" 
            src="assets/thumbs/kernHighpassGui.jpg" />
          </image>
        </guiInterface>
      </guiInterfaces>
      
      <inputImages>
        <image width="500" height="500" src="assets/images/peaks.jpg">
          <brief>
            Input image before kernfilter.
          </brief>
          <description>
            This is the unfiltered image. Note the low frequency data (albedo) 
            in the image. The highpass filter that this kernel mimics is 
            intended to filter this type of data out. 
          </description>
          <thumbnail caption= "The image before the filter" 
            src="assets/thumbs/peaks.jpg" width="200" height="200"/>
          <parameterName>FROM</parameterName>
        </image>
      </inputImages>
      
      <outputImages>
        <image width="500" height="500" src="assets/images/kernHighpass.jpg">
          <brief>
            Output image after kernfilter
          </brief>
          <description>
            The filtered image. Just as an actual 5 x 5 circular highpass
            filter would do, this kernel has removed albedo, allowing the user
            to see more terrain. Since a 5x5 filter is considered relatively small,
            features which are considered relatively small will still be visible.
          </description>
          <thumbnail caption= "The image after the filter" 
            src="assets/thumbs/kernHighpass.jpg" width="200" height="200"/>
          <parameterName>TO</parameterName>
        </image>
      </outputImages>
    </example>
    
    <example>
      <brief>
        Using the smoothPyramid5x5.txt kernel 
      </brief>
      <description>
        This example assumes that a kernel named "smoothPyramid5x5.txt" (which
          is provided with the program) exists in the "kernels" file that is created
          by default. The program simulates a smoothing algorithm that takes an
          average of the DNs in the boxcar. The kernel weights pixels that are
          nearest to the center higher than those at the edges of the boxcar.
          The kernel weights are as follows
        <pre> 
          1  2  3  2 1 
          2  4  6  4  2
            3  6  9  6  3      x  1/81 
          2  4  6  4  2 
          1  2  3  2  1
        </pre> 
        The pixels in the boxcar are assigned weights that inversely reflect     
        their distance from the center of the boxcar. The pixel at the very 
        center will be multiplied by 9 and then added to all of the values that 
        were multiplied by the other weights in the boxcar. Note that all of the 
        weights add up to 81. This is why the final output is divided by 81; it 
        allows the center pixel to be an average of the weights. Thus, the blur 
        appears as though a smoothing algorithm applying weight in a pyramidal 
        fashion had been applied.    
      </description>
      <terminalInterface>
        <commandLine>         
            from= peaks.cub to=smooth.cub 
            kernel=smoothPyramid5x5.txt
        </commandLine>
        <description>       
          This example has loaded the smoothPyramid5x5.txt kernel, which will
          smooth the input image using weights that are dispersed in a pyramidal 
          fashion. The boxcar is 5 x 5.
        </description>
      </terminalInterface>
   
      <guiInterfaces>
        <guiInterface>
          <image width="440" height="625" src="assets/images/kernSmoothGui.jpg">
            <brief>
              Example GUI
            </brief>
            <description>           
              Screenshot of the GUI with parameters set to perform the smoothing       
              filter with a 5 x 5 boxcar.
            </description>
            <thumbnail width="220" height="312" caption="kernfilter gui" 
              src="assets/thumbs/kernSmoothGui.jpg" />
          </image>
        </guiInterface>
      </guiInterfaces>
 
      <inputImages>
        <image width="500" height="500" src="assets/images/peaks.jpg">
          <brief>
            Input image before kernfilter.
          </brief>
          <description>
            This is the image as it was taken originally with no smoothing. 
          </description>
          <thumbnail caption= "The image before the filter" 
            src="assets/thumbs/peaks.jpg" width="200" height="200"/>
          <parameterName>FROM</parameterName>
        </image>
      </inputImages>
      
      <outputImages>
        <image width="500" height="500" src="assets/images/kernSmooth.jpg">
          <brief>
            Output image after kernfilter
          </brief>
          <description>
            The image after the filter. Although possibly hard to detect, everything 
            about the pictures is a little blurred, and smoother, than in the 
            original. A larger filter size would further increase this effect.
          </description>
          <thumbnail caption= "The image after the filter" 
            src="assets/thumbs/kernSmooth.jpg" width="200" height="200"/>
          <parameterName>TO</parameterName>
        </image>
      </outputImages>
    </example>

    <example>
      <brief>
        Using the derivativeNWtoSE2x2.txt kernel
      </brief>
      <description>
        This example assumes that a kernel named "derivativeNWtoSE2x2.txt" 
        (which is provided with the program) exists in the "kernels" file that 
        is created by default. This program serves the purpose of bringing out 
        areas of high contrast. It does so by finding the difference of 2 pixels
        on a diagonal from each other. The weights are as follows
        <pre> 
          1   0 
          0  -1  x 1.0
        </pre> 
        The top left pixel receives the value of itself minus the pixel down
        right of itself. The other two pixesl do not matter. Anywhere where is
        significant change from the top left to the bottom right then shows it
        with brighter or darker pixels than the surrounding gray where there was
        little difference and the DNs are at or close to zero.
      </description>
      <terminalInterface>
        <commandLine>
            from=peaks.cub to=derivative.cub kernel=derivativeNWtoSE2x2.txt
          </commandLine>
          <description>
            The kernfilter program has been loaded with a kernel that will find 
          the difference between 2 diagonal pixels.
          </description>
      </terminalInterface>
      <guiInterfaces> 
        <guiInterface>
          <image width="723" height="353" src="assets/images/kernDerivativeGui.jpg">
            <brief>
                Example GUI
            </brief>
            <description>          
              Screenshot of the GUI with parameters set to perform the
              derivative from NW to SE with a 2x2 boxcar.
            </description>
            <thumbnail width="362" height="178" caption="kernfilter gui" 
              src="assets/thumbs/kernDerivativeGui.jpg" />
          </image>
        </guiInterface>
      </guiInterfaces>
 
      <inputImages>
        <image width="500" height="500" src="assets/images/peaks.jpg">
          <brief>
              Input image before kernfilter.
            </brief>
            <description>
              This is the image as it was taken originally. 
            </description>
            <thumbnail caption= "The image before the filter" 
            src="assets/thumbs/peaks.jpg" width="200" height="200"/>
            <parameterName>FROM</parameterName>
        </image>
      </inputImages>
      
      <outputImages>
        <image width="500" height="500" src="assets/images/kernDerivative.jpg">
          <brief>
              Output image after kernfilter
          </brief>
          <description>
            The processed image now appears to have a light source in the 
            northwest and shadows and bright spots in areas of significant 
            contrast in the original. 
          </description>
          <thumbnail caption="The image after the filter" 
              src="assets/thumbs/kernDerivative.jpg" width="200" height="200"/>
          <parameterName>TO</parameterName>
        </image>
      </outputImages>
    </example> 
  </examples>
</application>
