<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="mosrange" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation=
"http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">
  <brief>
    Compute the lat/lon range of a set of camera images for mosaicking
  </brief>

  <description>
    <p>
      <i>mosrange</i> computes and outputs the <def link="Latitude">latitude</def>
      and <def link="Longitude">longitude</def> ranges of a set of <def link="Level1">Level1</def>
      images (i.e. non-projected), as well as the <def link="Pixel Resolution"> pixel
      resolution</def> and the <def link="Oblique Pixel Resolution"> oblique pixel resolution</def>.
      It creates a <a href="../cam2map/cam2map.html" target="_blank">cam2map</a> ready map file
      with the extents of the latitude/longitude ranges of the image set.
    </p>

    <p>
      The user can select the type of <def link="Map Projection">map projection</def>
      preferred by two different ways. The PROJECTION parameter allows direct 
      specification of an ISIS supported projection.  Or, the user can select a 
      map file from the ISIS map template system that contains the projection name.  
      If none of these options are used, then <b>Equirectangular</b> is the default.
    </p>

    <p>
      <i>mosrange</i> provides better control over the values of the latitude/longitude 
      ranges by providing a PRECISION parameter.  This parameter specifies the 
      maximum number of digits of precision for many of the Mapping group parameters 
      used to project images.
    </p>
    
    <p>
      ONERROR, ERRORLOG, and ERRORLIST parameters offer better error handling and
      diagnostics when problems are encountered processing the input file list.
      ONERROR dictates whether <i>mosrange</i> will abort or continue when an error
      occurs. If ONERROR=FAIL (default behavior), <i>mosrange</i> aborts upon error
      without generating a map file. If ONERROR=CONTINUE, <i>mosrange</i> produces
      an output map file with data collected from all successfully processed images.
      A detailed list of files that fail and their associated errors are written to
      the ERRORLOG file if provided. A simple list of failed files is written to the
      ERRORLIST file if provided.
    </p>
 
    <p>
      The primary use of <i>mosrange</i> is to provide a quick, simple and batchable means of
      creating map files for projections.
    </p>
    
    <p>
      An example of the output generated is:
    </p>
<pre>
Group = Mapping
  ProjectionName          = Equirectangular
  TargetName              = Mercury
  <def link="Equatorial Radius" >EquatorialRadius</def>        = 2440000.0  &lt;meters&gt;   
  <def link="Polar Radius" >PolarRadius</def>             = 2440000.0 &lt;meters&gt;
  <def link="Latitude Type">LatitudeType</def>            = <def link="Planetocentric Latitude">Planetocentric</def>
  <def link="Longitude Direction">LongitudeDirection</def>      = <def link="Positive East Longitude">PositiveEast</def>
  <def link="Longitude Domain">LongitudeDomain</def>         = 360
  <def link="Pixel Resolution">PixelResolution</def>         = 505.3668 &lt;meters/pixel&gt; 
  <def link="Oblique Pixel Resolution">ObliquePixelResolution</def> = 791.251 &lt;meters/pixel&gt;
  <def>Scale</def>                   = 84.2676 &lt;pixels/degree&gt;
  MinPixelResolution      = 483.45317995544 &lt;meters&gt;
  MaxPixelResolution      = 527.28051834369 &lt;meters&gt;
  CenterLongitude         = 165.9728
  CenterLatitude          = -13.6612
  MinimumLatitude         = -21.5164
  MaximumLatitude         = -5.806
  MinimumLongitude        = 133.7863
  MaximumLongitude        = 198.1593

  # Actual Parameters without precision applied
  PreciseCenterLongitude  = 165.97281458717
  PreciseCenterLatitude   = -13.661167089917
  PreciseMinimumLatitude  = -21.516314016725
  PreciseMaximumLatitude  = -5.806020163109
  PreciseMinimumLongitude = 133.78639979231
  PreciseMaximumLongitude = 198.15922938202
End_Group
End
 </pre>
  </description>

  <category>
    <categoryItem>Map Projection</categoryItem>
  </category>

  <history>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2006-03-26">
      Original version
    </change>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2008-06-27">
      Removed references to CubeInfo due to refactor
    </change>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2009-08-13">
        Added parameters  LATTYPE, LONDIR and LONDOM;  Now computes pixel Scale 
        in pixels/degree;  added additional parameters to the output map file so 
        it is more compliant with projection requirements based upon input 
        parameters and established mapping group keywords.
    </change>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2009-09-18">
        Added TargetName to output map file.
    </change>
    <change name="Mackenzie Boyd" date="2010-07-19">
        Modified program to have output go to print.prt file in addition to 
        other outputs.
    </change>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2010-11-02">
        Added more detail to error reporting so the offending file can be 
        more readily identified.
    </change>
    <change name="Kris Becker, Lynn Weller" date="2012-01-22">
        Updated the documentation
    </change>
    <change name="Debbie A. Cook" date="2012-07-06">
       Updated Spice members to be more compliant with Isis coding standards. References #972.
    </change>
    <change name="Debbie A. Cook" date="2012-10-11">
       Updated to use new Target class. References Mantis tickets #775 and #1114.
    </change>
    <change name="Tyler Wilson" date="2016-08-25">
       Updated to use updated Camera/CameraPointInfo classes which include improved approximations
       to Pixel/Detector/Line/Sample resolutions, as well as providing the ability for developers
       to order the fields in CSV/Pvl output.  References #476.
    </change>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2019-03-11">
        Added ERRORLOG, ERRORLIST and ONERROR flags to provide better control
        error behavior and provide diagnostics when problems are encountered
        processing input file list.
    </change>
    <change name="Ken Edmundson" date="2023-09-07">
        Moved Kris Becker's 2019-03-11 changes from UofA code base to USGS. Updated documentation.
        Cleaned up unnecessary blank lines and commented code in mosrange.cpp. References #3606.
    </change>
 </history>
  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROMLIST">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input cube file list to compute range for
        </brief>
        <description>
          Use this parameter to select the filename of a cube with
          camera labels.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.lis
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="MAP">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <defaultPath>$ISISROOT/appdata/templates/maps</defaultPath>
        <internalDefault>None</internalDefault>
          <filter>*.map *.cub</filter>
        <brief>
          An existing MAP file that will be used to determine the name of the 
          projection
        </brief>
        <description>
            If this file is given, only the ProjectionName keyword is used to 
            determine the type of projection desired.  If you know the type 
            already as well as the proper spelling required by ISIS, then you 
            may use PROJECTION as an alternative to this file.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TO">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <internalDefault>None</internalDefault>
        <filter>*.map</filter>
        <brief>
          Output map projection file generated from the list
        </brief>
        <description>
          This file will contain a map projection file suitable for projecting 
          the given set of images.  This file will contain all the parameters 
          suitable for using directly in cam2map.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="LOG">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <internalDefault>None</internalDefault>
        <brief>
          Writes the specifics for each file to this file
        </brief>
        <description>
            Each input file will have its geometry computed and the results can 
            be written to this file.
        </description>
      </parameter>
    </group>
    <group name="Mapping">
      <parameter name="PROJECTION">
        <type>string</type>
        <default><item>None</item></default>
        <internalDefault>None</internalDefault>
        <brief>
           Name of projection you want to create
        </brief>
        <description>
          Use this named projection as the type of projection you wish to 
          create.  It should be the complete valid name as required by the 
          cam2map application.   This name can also be provided in the MAP 
          parameter if you do not know the proper spelling/format required for 
          ISIS projections.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="LATTYPE">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>
          Latitude type
        </brief>
        <description>
          The latitude type for the projection.  It can either be Planetocentric or Planetographic.
           PLANETOCENTRIC is the default.
        </description>
        <default>
          <item>PLANETOCENTRIC</item>
        </default>
        <list>
          <option value="PLANETOCENTRIC">
            <brief>
              Planetocentric
            </brief>
            <description>
              Sets the latitude type in the mapping template to Planetocentric.
            </description>
          </option>
          <option value="PLANETOGRAPHIC">
            <brief>
              Planetographic
            </brief>
            <description>
              Sets the latitude type in the mapping template to Planetographic.
            </description>
          </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="LONDIR">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>
          Longitude Direction
        </brief>
        <description>
          The longitude direction for the projection.  It can have a direction of Positive East 
          or Positive West.  POSITIVEEAST is the default.
        </description>
        <default>
          <item>POSITIVEEAST</item>
        </default>
        <list>
          <option value="POSITIVEEAST">
            <brief>
              PositiveEast Longitude Direction
            </brief>
            <description>
              Sets the longitude direction in the mapping template to PositiveEast.
            </description>
          </option>
          <option value="POSITIVEWEST">
            <brief>
              PositiveWest Longitude Direction
            </brief>
            <description>
              Sets the longitude direction in the mapping template to PositiveWest.
            </description>
          </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="LONDOM">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>
          Longitude Domain
        </brief>
        <description>
          The longitude domain for the projection.  It can either have a domain of 180 or 360.  
          360 is the default.
        </description>
        <default>
          <item>360</item>
        </default>
        <list>
          <option value="360">
            <brief>
              0 to 360 Degree Longitude Domain
            </brief>
            <description>
              Sets the longitude domain in the mapping template to 360 degrees.
            </description>
          </option>
          <option value="180">
            <brief>
              -180 to 180 Degree Longitude Domain
            </brief>
            <description>
              Sets the longitude domain in the mapping template to 180 degrees.
            </description>
          </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>
        
      <parameter name="PRECISION">
        <type>integer</type>
        <default><item>12</item></default>
        <brief>
           Digits of precision to use for latitude/longitude specifications
        </brief>
        <description>
            <p>
                This parameter provides some control over how the Latitude and 
                Longitude min/max values are written to the map file.  Note that 
                this is useful for creating easy values to use in subsequent 
                applications that may require these values.  If these values are not 
                specified, about 12 digits of precision will be used.
            </p>
            <p>
                Note that you can use a negative number which has the effect of 
                rounding the whole integral number.  A value of 0 will produce 
                an integral whole number, effectively removing the decimal 
                portion of the numbers.  A positive number will truncate up
                (maximums using the ceil function) or down (minimums using the 
                floor function) range values such as MinimumLatitude and 
                MaximumLatitude.  The pixel resolution is rounded using same 
                technique (with the rint fuction).
            </p>
                <TABLE  border="1" cellpadding="3" cellspacing="2" 
                       summary="This table shows the different effect of the PRECISION 
                        parameter on select data values.">
                <TR>
                  <TH colspan="3">PRECISION Examples</TH>
                </TR>
                    <TR>
                      <TH>Value</TH>
                      <TH align="center">PRECISION</TH>
                      <TH>Result</TH>
                    </TR>
                    <TR>
                       <TD>118.08747089457</TD>
                       <TD align="center">12 (Default)</TD>
                       <TD>118.08747089457</TD>
                    </TR>
                    <TR>
                       <TD>118.08747089457</TD>
                       <TD align="center">5</TD>
                       <TD>118.0875</TD>
                    </TR>
                   <TR>
                       <TD>118.08747089457</TD>
                       <TD align="center">1</TD>
                       <TD>118.1</TD>
                    </TR>
                    <TR>
                       <TD>118.08747089457</TD>
                       <TD align="center">0</TD>
                       <TD>118.0</TD>
                    </TR>
                    <TR>
                       <TD>118.08747089457</TD>
                       <TD align="center">-1</TD>
                       <TD>120.0</TD>
                    </TR>
                   <TR>
                       <TD>118.08747089457</TD>
                       <TD align="center">-2</TD>
                       <TD>100.0</TD>
                    </TR>
                  <TR>
                       <TD>118.08747089457</TD>
                       <TD align="center">-3</TD>
                       <TD>0.0 (Bad!)</TD>
                    </TR>
                </TABLE>
        </description>
      </parameter>
    </group>
    
    <group name="Errorhandling">
      <parameter name="ONERROR">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>
          Define behavior when a file error occurs
        </brief>
        <description>
          This flag is provided to specify what action is to be
          taken should an error occur processing the input file
          list. A detailed list of errors for each file will be
          recorded to ERRORLOG if a file name is provided. A list
          containing the file names that failed will be written
          to ERRORLIST if provided. If ONERROR=FAIL, a single
          error will result in an abort. FAIL is the default
          (to preserve existing behavior).
        </description>
        <default>
          <item>FAIL</item>
        </default>
        <list>
          <option value="CONTINUE">
            <brief>
              Continue processing all the input file list if an error occurs
            </brief>
            <description>
              Continue to produce an output map file with data collected from
              any number of successfully processed images when one or more
              errors are encountered with the input processing list. This option
              will cause the application to continue processing all files and
              generate a mapping file if at least one is successful.
            </description>
          </option>
          <option value="FAIL">
            <brief>
              Terminate the application when an error occurs
            </brief>
            <description>
              If any file produces an error when determining mapping statistics,
              ONERROR=FAIL will cause the application to abort with an error
              without generating a map file. The filename and detailed error are
              written to ERRORLOG if provided. The filename alone is written to
              ERRORLIST if provided.
            </description>
          </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="ERRORLOG">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <internalDefault>None</internalDefault>
        <brief>
          Writes detailed information for each failed file to a PVL file
        </brief>
        <description>
            Each file that encounters an error will produce the issue
            that cased the error. The ERRORLOG file can be specified to
            get a detailed account of why each file failed to successfully
            complete. Data collected from this process will be written
            to the specified ERRORLOG in the form of a PVL object.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="ERRORLIST">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <internalDefault>None</internalDefault>
        <brief>
          Record filename of each cube that failed to this file
        </brief>
        <description>
            The filename of each cube that encountered an error will be
            written to this file if provided. The ERRORLIST file can be
            used to difference against the input list to determine all
            the successful files included in the mapping statistics.
        </description>
      </parameter>
    </group>
  </groups>
</application>
