<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="mosrange" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">
  <brief>
    Compute the lat/lon range of a set camera images for mosaicking
  </brief>

  <description>
    This program computes and outputs the latitude/longitude range of a set of 
    images in camera space, as well as the pixel resolution.  It creates a 
    cam2map ready map file with the extents of the latitude/longitude ranges of 
    the image set.  

    mosrange provides better control over the values of the latitude/longitude 
    ranges by providing a PRECISION parameter.  This parameter specifies the 
    maximum nuber of digits precision for many of the Mapping group parameters 
    used to project images.

    Its primary use is to provide a quick, simple and batchable means of 
    creating map files for projections.
    
    An example of the output generated is:
<pre>
Group = Mapping
  ProjectionName          = Equirectangular
  TargetName              = Moon
  EquatorialRadius        = 2440000.0  &lt;meters&gt;   
  PolarRadius             = 2440000.0 &lt;meters&gt;
  LatitudeType            = Planetocentric
  LongitudeDirection      = PositiveEast
  LongitudeDomain         = 360
  PixelResolution         = 505.3668 &lt;meters/pixel&gt;
  Scale                   = 84.2676 &lt;pixels/degree&gt;
  MinPixelResolution      = 483.45317995544 &lt;meters&gt;
  MaxPixelResolution      = 527.28051834369 &lt;meters&gt;
  CenterLongitude         = 165.9728
  CenterLatitude          = -13.6612
  MinimumLatitude         = -21.5164
  MaximumLatitude         = -5.806
  MinimumLongitude        = 133.7863
  MaximumLongitude        = 198.1593

  # Actual Parameters without precision applied
  PreciseCenterLongitude  = 165.97281458717
  PreciseCenterLatitude   = -13.661167089917
  PreciseMinimumLatitude  = -21.516314016725
  PreciseMaximumLatitude  = -5.806020163109
  PreciseMinimumLongitude = 133.78639979231
  PreciseMaximumLongitude = 198.15922938202
End_Group
End
 </pre>
  </description>

  <category>
    <categoryItem>Map Projection</categoryItem>
  </category>

  <history>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2006-03-26">
      Original version
    </change>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2008-06-27">
      Removed references to CubeInfo due to refactor
    </change>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2009-08-13">
        Added parameters  LATTYPE, LONDIR and LONDOM;  Now computes pixel Scale 
        in pixels/degree;  added additional parameters to the output map file so 
        it is more compliant with projection requirements based upon input 
        parameters and established mapping group keywords.
    </change>
    <change name="Kris Becker" date="2009-09-18">
        Added TargetName to output map file.
    </change>
</history>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROMLIST">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input cube file list to compute range for
        </brief>
        <description>
          Use this parameter to select the filename of a cube with
          camera labels.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.lis
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="MAP">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <defaultPath>$base/templates/maps</defaultPath>
        <internalDefault>None</internalDefault>
          <filter>*.map *.cub</filter>
        <brief>
          An existing MAP file that will be used to determine the name of the 
          projection
        </brief>
        <description>
            If this file is given, the ProjectionName keyword is used to 
            determine the type of projection desired.  If you know the type 
            already as well as the proper spelling required by ISIS, then you 
            may use PROJECTION as an alternative to this file.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TO">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <internalDefault>None</internalDefault>
        <filter>*.map</filter>
        <brief>
          Output map projection file generated from the list
        </brief>
        <description>
          This file will contain a map projection file suitable for projecting 
          the given set of images.  This file will contain all the parameters 
          suitable for using directly in cam2map.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="LOG">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <internalDefault>None</internalDefault>
        <brief>
          Writes the specifics for each file to this file
        </brief>
        <description>
            Each input file will have its geometry computed and the results can 
            be written to this file for a looksee.
        </description>
      </parameter>
    </group>
    <group name="Mapping">
      <parameter name="PROJECTION">
        <type>string</type>
        <default><item>None</item></default>
        <internalDefault>None</internalDefault>
        <brief>
           Name of projection you want to create
        </brief>
        <description>
          Use this named projection as the type of projection you wish to 
          create.  It should be the complete valid name as required by the 
          cam2map application.   This name can also be provided in the MAP 
          parameter if you do not know the proper spelling/format required for 
          ISIS projections.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="LATTYPE">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>
          Latitude type
        </brief>
        <description>
          The latitude type for the projection.  It can either be Planetocentric or Planetographic.
           PLANETOCENTRIC is the default.
        </description>
        <default>
          <item>PLANETOCENTRIC</item>
        </default>
        <list>
          <option value="PLANETOCENTRIC">
            <brief>
              Planetocentric
            </brief>
            <description>
              Sets the latitude type in the mapping template to Planetocentric.
            </description>
          </option>
          <option value="PLANETOGRAPHIC">
            <brief>
              Planetographic
            </brief>
            <description>
              Sets the latitude type in the mapping template to Planetographic.
            </description>
          </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="LONDIR">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>
          Longitude Direction
        </brief>
        <description>
          The longitude direction for the projection.  It can have a direction of Positive East 
          or Positive West.  POSITIVEEAST is the default.
        </description>
        <default>
          <item>POSITIVEEAST</item>
        </default>
        <list>
          <option value="POSITIVEEAST">
            <brief>
              PositiveEast Longitude Direction
            </brief>
            <description>
              Sets the longitude direction in the mapping template to PositiveEast.
            </description>
          </option>
          <option value="POSITIVEWEST">
            <brief>
              PositiveWest Longitude Direction
            </brief>
            <description>
              Sets the longitude direction in the mapping template to PositiveWest.
            </description>
          </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="LONDOM">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>
          Longitude Domain
        </brief>
        <description>
          The longitude domain for the projection.  It can either have a domain of 180 or 360.  
          360 is the default.
        </description>
        <default>
          <item>360</item>
        </default>
        <list>
          <option value="360">
            <brief>
              0 to 360 Degree Longitude Domain
            </brief>
            <description>
              Sets the longitude domain in the mapping template to 360 degrees.
            </description>
          </option>
          <option value="180">
            <brief>
              -180 to 180 Degree Longitude Domain
            </brief>
            <description>
              Sets the longitude domain in the mapping template to 180 degrees.
            </description>
          </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>
        
      <parameter name="PRECISION">
        <type>integer</type>
        <default><item>12</item></default>
        <brief>
           Digits of precision to use for latitude/longitude specifications
        </brief>
        <description>
            <p>
                This parameter provides some control over how the Latitude and 
                Longitude min/max values are written to the map file.  Note that 
                this is useful for creating easy values to use in subsequent 
                applications that may require these values.  If these values are not 
                specified, about 12 digits of precision will be used.
            </p>
            <p>
                Note that you can use a negative number which has the effect of 
                rounding the whole integral number.  A value of 0 will produce 
                an integral whole number, effectively removing the decimal 
                portion of the numbers.  A positive number will truncate up
                (maximums using the ceil function) or down (minimums using the 
                floor function) range values such as MinimumLatitude and 
                MaximumLatitude.  The pixel resolution is rounded using same 
                technique (with the rint fuction).
            </p>
        </description>
      </parameter>
    </group>
  </groups>
</application>
