<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="cnetref" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">

  <brief>
    The application cnetref finds the best reference for a Control
    Point based on criteria like Emission Angle or Incidence Angle or
    Resolution or Interest 
  </brief>

  <description>
    <p> The application cnetref finds the best reference for a <def>Control 
    Point</def> based on user specified Criteria. </p> 

    <p> Application takes in as input the <def>Control Net</def> CNET and its 
    corresponding images list FROMLIST. FROMLIST contains the filenames of all 
    the images that are part of the input Control Net.</p>  
    
    <p> The resulting output Control Net is placed in the user specified file 
    ONET. The Id and Description for the output Control Net can be specified in 
    NETWORKID and DESCRIPTION parameters respectively. If the values are not 
    entered then the information is taken from the input Control 
    Net.</p>

    <p>Best Reference for the Control Point can be chosen based on the
    following four CRITERIAs. For all the criterias, picking the best Reference 
    is skipped if the Control Point is not Free or if either the Control 
    Point or the Reference is EditLocked. <br/><br/>
    <b>1.  EMISSION </b>: Of all the valid Control Measures in a Control 
    Point, the Control Measure with the least Emission Angle will be chosen as 
    the Reference.<br/><br/> 
    <b>2. INCIDENCE</b>: Of all the valid Control Measures in a Control 
    Point, the Control Measure with the least Incidence Angle will be chosen as 
    the Reference.<br/><br/>
    <b>3. RESOLUTION</b>: Of all the valid Control Measures in a Control 
    Point, the Control Measure with the best Resolution TYPE will be 
    chosen as the Reference. All the images in the Control Net must have the 
    resolution in the same units.
    <br/> The best Resolution can be chosen from the following TYPEs:<br/>
      <b>a. HIGH</b> - The Control Measure with the Highest Resolution will be 
      chosen as the Reference.<br/> 
      <b>b. LOW</b> - The Control Measure with the Least Resolution will be 
      chosen as the Reference.<br/> 
      <b>c. MEAN</b> - The Mean Resolution is calculated from the Resolution  
      all the images within each Control Point. The Control Measure closest to 
      the Mean Resolution will be chosen as the Reference.<br/> 
     <b> d. NEAREST</b> - The Control Measure with the Resolution closest to 
      this user specified value  in RESVALUE will be chosen as the 
      Reference. 
      <br/> 
      <b>e. RANGE</b> - The first Control Measure in the MINRES - MAXRES 
      Range will be chosen as the Reference. <br/><br/>
    <b>4. INTEREST</b>: Of all the valid Control Measures in a Control 
    Point, the Control Measure with the best Interest will be chosen as the 
    Reference. This option uses an interest operator to find the most 
    interesting point in the area near each Control Point of a Control Net. The 
    area is defined by the keywords DeltaLine and DeltaSample. The application 
    starts by finding the best Interest for each valid Control Measure in a 
    Control Point. Then the Control Measure with the best Interest among all the 
    valid Control Measures in the Control Point is chosen as the Reference. 
    After the new Reference is chosen, all the Control Measures are aligned to 
    the new Reference's location. The movement of the Control Point can be 
    limited to the Overlaps by enabling LIMIT and entering the list in 
    OVERLAPLIST. The Overlaplist contains the Serial Number and their 
    intersections. The intersections information can be got from the application 
     <b>findimageoverlaps</b>. If an exact match of the Control 
    Measure's Serial Number in the overlaplist fails then this option finds 
    image overlaps by getting intersection of the individual image footprints. 
    If the overlapslist is not specified, then the Point can be moved in the 
    area defined by DeltaLine and DeltaSample. 
    </p>
    <p>
    The Interest operator reads in a chip of size Delta Samples and Lines from 
    each Control Measure(<def>Cube</def>) in a point.  If the Overlap list is 
    included then the overlap polygon is taken into consideration when the chip 
    reads the cube. For each pixel in the chip, it extracts a sub chip of box 
    size (Samples, Lines) around the pixel. It first checks the pixel for 
    validity as specified in the DEFFILE. If the pixel passes the above tests, 
    then the Interest is calculated for the box around the pixel using the 
    chosen algorithm. This way it calculates the interest for all the pixels in 
    the chosen area (chip) around the Control Measure and the best Interest 
    (highest value) is chosen among them. The best Interest is calculated for 
    all the Control Measures in a Control Point.                                                        
    <br/> The application then selects the best Interest of all the valid 
    Control Measures in the Control Point and chooses it as the Reference. It 
    then moves all the other valid Control Measures to the chosen Reference by 
    mapping the Reference Lat/Lon to a sample, line in the Control Measure. It 
    then creates a new Control Net using these new "more interesting" Control 
    Points. If the BestReferenceIndex is not calculated because no Interest was 
    calculated for all the Control Measures or if the BestReferenceIndex's 
    Interest is invalid(less than the threshold Interest) then the Control Point 
    is set to be ignored. <br/> 
    <br/>Interest Algorithm could be:  <br/>
    <b>1. Standard Deviation</b><br/> 
    <b>2. Gradient</b> <br/> <br/>
     The options for the Interest Operator is defined in PVL group in the 
     DEFFILE. The DEFFILE should have the Operator Group relevant for the 
      Interest Operator plugin. It defines the algorithm(Name) to be used to calculate 
      the interest, the box size (Samples, Lines) and the distance (DeltaSamp, 
      DeltaLine) the algorithm is allowed to move the point from the current 
      position. It defines the minimum interest (MinimumInterest) value for the 
      interest to be considered a best interest. If the point must be static 
      then set the DeltaSamp and DeltaLine to zero. 
      <br/> All the keywords in the Operator Group are required for this 
      Criteria.<br/>
      <b>Example:</b><br/> </p>
      <p><div style="font-family: Arial, Helvetica, Geneva, sans-serif; font-size:95%">
      <table border="0" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="0">
      <tr><th colspan="3" align="left">Group = Operator</th></tr>
      <tr><td width="25"></td><td align="left">Name </td>
        <td>= StandardDeviation</td></tr>
      <tr><td width="25"></td><td align="left">Samples </td>
        <td>= Positive Integer</td></tr>
      <tr><td width="25"></td><td align="left">Lines </td>
        <td>= Positive Integer</td></tr> 
      <tr><td width="25"></td><td align="left">DeltaLine  </td>
        <td>= Positive Integer</td></tr> 
      <tr><td width="25"></td><td align="left">DeltaSample</td>
        <td>= Positive Integer</td></tr> 
      <tr><td width="25"></td><td align="left">MinimumInterest </td>
        <td>= Double</td></tr>
      <tr><th colspan="3" align="left">EndGroup</th><td></td></tr> 
      </table></div> 
      <br/> 

    <b>Note:  </b><br/> 1.If Control Measures with no camera is encountered, 
     then the application is halted and no ouput Control Net is generated.
    <br/> 2. The values Samples, Lines, DeltaLine, DeltaSamp, MinimumInterest 
    for the Operator are entirely dependent on the images in the Control Net. 
    Recommended preprocessing would be to run "gradient" filter or "svfilter" 
    and run "hist" to get the image stats and set the values for the Operator 
    accordingly. <br/><br/>
    For all the criterias except Interest, the application first validates each 
    measure for the properties specified in the "ValidMeasure" PvlGroup in 
    DEFFILE. The Validity test is optional for all the Criterias.<br/></p> 

    <p>Validation is little different if using the Interest Critera. The 
    Interest Operator while finding Interest for a Valid Control Measure, first 
    Validates each Sample, Line location in the DeltaSample, DeltaLine area 
    of the Control Measure and then calculates the Interest for that location. 
    This way the expensive Interest calculation is bypassed for an invalid 
    Sample, Line location. Validity test is also performed after moving the 
    Control Measure to the new location of the BestReference chosen after the 
    Interest operation for all the Control Measures in the Control Point.  If 
    the moved Control Measure fails the Validity test, then it is set to be 
    Ignored. </p> 

    <p>Following is the format for the Pvl DEFFILE file with the 
    defaults for Control Measure validation:   
   <br/></p> 

    <p><div style="font-family: Arial, Helvetica, Geneva, sans-serif; font-size:95%">
         <table border="0"><tr><td width="40"></td><td>
          <table border="0" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="0">
          <tr><th colspan="3" align="left">Group=ValidMeasure </th></tr>
          <tr><td width="25"></td><td align="left">MinDN 
          </td>
              <td>= Default is Min DN value (depends on the pixel size of the 
                image)
              </td></tr>
          <tr><td></td><td align="left">MaxDN </td>
              <td>= Default is Max DN value (depends on the pixel size of the 
                image) </td></tr> 
          <tr><td></td><td align="left">MinEmission </td>
              <td>= 0 (Default)</td></tr>
          <tr><td></td><td align="left">MaxEmission </td>
              <td>= 135 (Default) </td></tr> 
          <tr><td></td><td align="left">MinIncidence </td>
              <td>= 0 (Default) </td></tr>
          <tr><td></td><td align="left">MaxIncidence </td>
              <td>= 135 (Default) </td></tr> 
          <tr><td></td><td align="left">MinResolution </td>
              <td>= 0 (Default) </td></tr>
          <tr><td></td><td align="left">MaxResolution </td>
              <td>= Max Double</td></tr> 
          <tr><td></td><td align="left">PixelsFromEdge</td>
              <td>= 0 (Default) OR</td></tr> 
          <tr><td></td><td align="left">MetersFromEdge</td>
              <td>= 0 (Default) </td></tr> 
          <tr><th colspan="3" align="left">EndGroup</th><td></td></tr> 
          </table></td></tr>
    </table>
    </div>
    <br/>
    </p>
    If the Control Measure does not pass the validity test, then it will be 
    be Ignored. If the number of Valid Control Measures in a Control Point is 
    less than 2, then the Control Point is Ignored.<br/> <br/> 
    If the "Required" parameters are not entered or misspelled, then the 
    application will throw an error. If "Optional" parameters are not entered 
    then the Control Measure will not be validated against that option.
    <br/> 
    <p>The entire Control Net processing can be logged in an output LOG 
      file. Log information such as Control Point and Control Measure details 
    and change statistics are placed in LOG file if specified in PVL. Following 
    is the format of the Log File:</p>
       <p><div style="font-family: Arial, Helvetica, Geneva, sans-serif; font-size:95%">
         <table border="0"><tr><td width="40"></td><td>
          <table border="0" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="0">
            <tr><td colspan="4"  align="left">Object = PointDetails</td></tr>
            <tr><td width="10"></td>
            <td colspan="3"  align="left">PointId = </td></tr>
            <tr><td colspan="4"><br/></td></tr>
            <tr><td width="10"></td>
            <td colspan="3"  align="left">Group = MeasureDetails</td></tr>
            <tr><td colspan="2"></td><td colspan="2">
            <table border="0" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="0" >
            <tr><td width="10"></td> 
            <td  align="left">SerialNum </td><td align="left">=</td></tr>
            <tr><td width="10"></td> 
            <td  align="left">EmissionAngle </td><td>=</td></tr>      
            <tr><td width="10"></td>  
            <td  align="left">IncidenceAngle </td><td>=</td></tr> 
            <tr><td width="10"></td> 
            <td  align="left">Resolution</td><td>=</td></tr>
            <tr><td width="10"></td>
            <td  align="left">DNValue </td><td>=</td></tr> 
            <tr><td width="10"></td>  
            <td  align="left">SampleResidual </td><td>=</td></tr> 
            <tr><td width="10"></td>  
            <td  align="left">LineResidual </td><td>=</td></tr>      
            <tr><td width="10"></td>
            <td  align="left">ResidualMagnitude</td><td>=</td></tr>      
            <tr><td width="10"></td> 
            <td  align="left">SampleShift </td><td>=</td></tr>      
            <tr><td width="10"></td> 
            <td  align="left">LineShift </td><td>=</td></tr>      
             <tr><td width="10"></td> 
            <td  align="left">PixelShift </td><td>=</td></tr>      
            <tr><td width="10"></td>
            <td  align="left">Reference </td><td>=</td></tr>      
            </table></td></tr> 

            <tr><td width="10"></td> <td colspan="3"  align="left">EndGroup</td></tr>
            
            <tr><td colspan="4"><br/></td></tr>

            <tr><td width="10"></td> 
              <td colspan="3">Group = MeasureDetails</td></tr>      
            <tr><td colspan="2"></td><td colspan="2">
            <table border="0" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="0" >
            <tr><td width="10"></td> 
            <td  align="left">SerialNum </td><td>=</td></tr>      
            <tr><td width="10"></td> 
            <td  align="left">OriginalLocation </td><td>=</td></tr>      
            <tr><td width="10"></td>  
            <td  align="left">EmissionAngle </td><td>=</td></tr>      
            <tr><td width="10"></td> 
            <td  align="left">IncidenceAngle </td><td>=</td></tr>      
            <tr><td width="10"></td>  
            <td  align="left">Resolution </td><td>=</td></tr>      
            <tr><td width="10"></td>
            <td  align="left">DNValue </td><td>=</td></tr>      
            <tr><td width="10"></td>  
            <td  align="left">SampleResidual </td><td>=</td></tr>      
            <tr><td width="10"></td> 
            <td  align="left">LineResidual </td><td>=</td></tr>      
            <tr><td width="10"></td> 
            <td  align="left">ResidualMagnitude </td><td>=</td></tr>      
            <tr><td width="10"></td>  
            <td  align="left">SampleShift </td><td>=</td></tr>      
            <tr><td width="10"></td> 
            <td  align="left">LineShift </td><td>=</td></tr>      
            <tr><td width="10"></td> 
            <td  align="left">PixelShift </td><td>=</td></tr>  
           </table></td></tr>
            <tr><td width="10"></td>
            <td colspan="3"  align="left">EndGroup</td></tr>

            <tr><td colspan="4"><br/></td></tr>


           <tr><td width="10"></td> 
              <td colspan="3"  align="left">Group = 
                ReferenceChangeDetails</td></tr>  
            <tr><td colspan="2"></td><td colspan="2">
            <table border="0" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="0" >
            <tr><td width="10"></td>  
            <td  align="left">PrevSerialNumber </td><td>=</td></tr>      
            <tr><td width="10"></td>  
            <td  align="left">PrevIncAngle </td><td>=</td></tr>      
            <tr><td width="10"></td> 
            <td  align="left">PrevLocation </td><td>=</td></tr>      
            <tr><td width="10"></td> 
            <td  align="left">NewSerialNumber </td><td>=</td></tr>      
            <tr><td width="10"></td> 
            <td  align="left">NewLeastIncAngle </td><td>=</td></tr>      
            <tr><td width="10"></td> 
            <td  align="left">NewLocation </td><td>=</td></tr>
            </table></td></tr>     
            <tr><td width="10"></td>
            <td colspan="3"  align="left">EndGroup</td></tr> 

            <tr><td colspan="4"><br/></td></tr>

          <tr><td colspan="4"  align="left">EndObject</td></tr></table>
    </td></tr> </table></div>

    </p> 
  </description>

  <category>
    <categoryItem>Control Networks</categoryItem>
  </category>

  <history>
    <change name="Stuart Sides" date="2005-08-20">
      Original version
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Koechle" date="2008-09-25">
      Tweaked to compile and run with current version of Isis
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2008-11-04">
      Added support for image overlap files, new optional parameter "OVERLAPLIST"
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2008-11-14">
      "OVERLAPLIST" is now a required parameter.
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Koechle" date="2009-01-20">
      Fixed Memory Leaks, Changed Deletion of cubes to use an iterator
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Koechle" date="2009-04-24">
      If a control measure fails SetUniversalGround it is now ignored.
    </change>
    <change name="Travis Addair" date="2009-08-11">
      Interest operator parameters are now placed into the print file.
    </change>
    <change name="Sharmila Prasad" date="2010-03-30">
      Added Emission Angle criteria in the interest operator plugin for the
      best interest point to be considered. Also Check that the best interest
      point has DN value in the Valid Min and Max DN range.
    </change>
    <change name="Sharmila Prasad" date="2010-04-20">
      Logging and documentation-specify output log file for the results to be
      sent to else printed to print.prt. If images with no camera is
      encountered, the application is closed.
    </change>
    <change name="Sharmila Prasad" date="2010-05-04">
      Make the overlap list optional incase a control network has no overlap
      list. Added a checkbox to indicate whether the overlap list is available or
      not and modified the app accordingly
    </change>
    <change name="Sharmila Prasad" date="2010-05-10">
      Renamed to cnetref
    </change>
    <change name="Sharmila Prasad" date="2010-05-11">
      Calculate interest for Control Points with no Reference point and Control 
      Points with Measures less than 2. Include Min and Max Incidence Angle 
      filter and make parameters NETWORKID and DESCRIPTION optional..
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2010-05-27">
      Using an overlap list should be much more accurate and restrictive now.
      Added MINRES and MAXRES parameters. Fixed potential segmentation fault.
      Restored program's history.
    </change>
    <change name="Sharmila Prasad" date="2010-06-10">
      Find reference based on Emission, Incidence angles or interest or 
      Resolution. Added new parameters to accomodate the new options
    </change>
    <change name="Sharmila Prasad" date="2010-06-11">
      Added documentation and tests
    </change>
    <change name="Sharmila Prasad" date="2010-06-18">
      Added documentation, display error for Interest option with no DefFile.
    </change>
    <change name="Sharmila Prasad" date="2010-06-18">
      Use Standard Options Pixels/Meters from Edge
    </change>
    <change name="Sharmila Prasad" date="2010-10-06">
      Made changes for binary control net
    </change>
    <change name="Sharmila Prasad" date="2010-10-15">
      Use single copy of Control Net
    </change>
    <change name="Sharmila Prasad" date="2010-10-18">
      Input DefFile Validation before any processing
    </change>
    <change name="Sharmila Prasad" date="2010-10-22">
      Reset apriori for source==Reference
    </change>
    <change name="Sharmila Prasad" date="2010-10-27">
      Log, if Reference changed and apriorisource==Reference
    </change>
    <change name="Sharmila Prasad" date="2010-11-09">
      Update documentation regarding Template DefFile
    </change>
    <change name="Sharmila Prasad" date="2010-12-29">
      Updated for binary control net and fixed the app tests accordingly
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2011-01-19">
      Altered to compile with the new Control redesign.
    </change>
    <change name="Sharmila Prasad" date="2011-02-24">
      Fixed the app tests
    </change>
    <change name="Sharmila Prasad" date="2011-05-14">
      Added ability to validate Measure by Sample/Line Residuals and Residual 
      Magnitude
    </change>
    <change name="Sharmila Prasad" date="2011-05-24">
      Helper function to edit DefFile
    </change>
    <change name="Debbie A. Cook and Tracie Sucharski" date="2011-06-07">
      Changed point types "Ground" to "Fixed" and "Tie" to "Free"
    </change>
    <change name="Sharmila Prasad" date="2011-07-29">
      Improved the Log messages
    </change>
    <change name="Sharmila Prasad" date="2011-08-03">
      Fixed the statistics
    </change>
    <change name="Sharmila Prasad, Bonnie Redding, Mark Rosiek" date="2011-10-06">
      Updated the documentation and added missing tests for criteria resolution 
    </change>
    <change name="Sharmila Prasad" date="2011-11-23">
      Updated the documentation. Edited to work for control nets with Reference 
      not set. Fixes #589 and #584 
    </change>
    <change name="Debbie A. Cook" date="2013-02-11">
      Changed selection of reference by mean resolution to use the first measure for points 
      with only 2 measures.  References #775.
    </change>
    <change name="Kimberly Oyama and Steven Lambright" date="2013-02-25">
      Changed error handling such that, when an error occurs, this program will not choose that
      measure as reference instead of throwing an error and stopping. References #825.
    </change>
</history>

<groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROMLIST">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          List of Input cubes in the Control Net
        </brief>
        <description>
         This file contains all the the cube filenames which are 
          associated with the input Control Net.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.lis
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="CNET">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input Control Net
        </brief>
        <description>
          This file must contain Control Net with valid Control Points and 
          Control Measures
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.net
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="ONET">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Output Control Net
        </brief>
        <description>
          This file will contain the new adjusted Control Net
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="LOG">
        <type>filename</type>
         <internalDefault>None</internalDefault>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <brief>Optional output log file</brief>
        <description>
          This file stores log information such as Control Point and Control 
          Measure details and change statistics in PVL. 
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.*
        </filter>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Information">
        <parameter name="NETWORKID">
          <internalDefault>None</internalDefault>
          <type>string</type>
          <brief>
              Output Control Net ID
          </brief>
          <description>
              The ID or name of the output Control Net. This 
              string should be unique. If not specified, the ID is taken from 
              the input Control Net.
          </description>
        </parameter>

        <parameter name="DESCRIPTION">
        <type>string</type> 
         <internalDefault>None</internalDefault>
        <brief>
            The description of the Output Control Net.
        </brief>
        <description>
            A string describing purpose of this Output Control Net. If not specified, the ID is taken from 
            the input Control Net.
        </description>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Reference">
        <parameter name="CRITERIA">
        <type>string</type>
        <default>
          <item>EMISSION</item>
        </default>
        <brief>Criteria in choosing the best Reference in a Control Point 
          </brief>
        <description>
          This parameter lets the user choose one of the four ways to choose the 
          best Reference in a Control Point.
        </description>

        <list>
          <option value="EMISSION">
            <brief>Reference is chosen based on the Best Emission Angle </brief>
            <description>
              This option chooses a valid Control Measure with the least 
              Emission Angle (closer to zero) among all the other Control 
              Measures in a Control Point as the best Reference.
            </description>
            <exclusions>
              <item>LIMIT</item>
              <item>OVERLAPLIST</item>
              <item>TYPE</item>
              <item>RESVALUE</item>
              <item>MINRES</item>
              <item>MAXRES</item>
           </exclusions>
          </option>

          <option value="INCIDENCE">
            <brief>Reference is chosen based on the Best Incidence Angle 
              </brief>
            <description>
              This option chooses a valid Control Measure with the least 
              Incidence Angle (closer to zero) among all the other Control 
              Measures in a Control Point as the best Reference.
            </description>
            <exclusions>
              <item>LIMIT</item>
              <item>OVERLAPLIST</item>
              <item>TYPE</item>
              <item>RESVALUE</item>
              <item>MINRES</item>
              <item>MAXRES</item>
           </exclusions>
          </option>

           <option value="INTEREST">
            <brief>Reference is chosen based on the Best Interest </brief>
            <description>
              This option finds the most interesting area near each Control 
              Point of a Control Net depending on the best Interest. The 
              Control Measure with the best Interest (highest value) among all 
              other Control Measures in a Control Point will be chosen as the 
              Reference. Interest is calculated by an interest algorithm 
              Standard Deviation or Gradient. 
            </description>
            <exclusions>
              <item>TYPE</item>
              <item>RESVALUE</item>
              <item>MINRES</item>
              <item>MAXRES</item>
            </exclusions> 
          </option>

          <option value="RESOLUTION">
            <brief> Reference is chosen based on the Resolution</brief>
            <description>
              This option chooses the Reference based on the Control Measure's 
              Resolution. There are different ways as to how the Resolution will 
              be chosen as the best value.
            </description>
            <exclusions>
              <item>LIMIT</item>
              <item>OVERLAPLIST</item>
           </exclusions>
            <inclusions>
              <item>TYPE</item>
            </inclusions>
          </option>
        </list> 
          </parameter> 

      <parameter name="DEFFILE">
          <type>filename</type>
          <fileMode>input</fileMode>
          <internalDefault>None</internalDefault>
          <brief>
          PVL file containing the options for which a Control Measure 
          has to be validated and/or operator plugin if Interest criteria is 
          chosen. 
          </brief>
          <description>
          PVL file containing the options for which a Control Measure 
          has to be validated and/or operator plugin if Interest criteria is 
          chosen. Refer to documentation for DEFFILE format.
          </description>
          <filter>
            *
          </filter>

          <helpers >
            <helper name="H1">
              <function>View</function>
              <brief>View DefFile</brief>
              <description>
                This helper button will print the definition file to the session
                log of the application
              </description>
              <icon>$ISIS3DATA/base/icons/labels.png</icon>
            </helper>
            <helper name="H2">
              <function>Edit</function>
              <brief>Edit DefFile</brief>
              <description>
                This helper button opens an editor to able to edit the DefFile
              </description>
              <icon>$ISIS3DATA/base/icons/labels.png</icon>
            </helper>
          </helpers>

        </parameter>

      </group> 

    <group name="Interest">
        <parameter name="LIMIT">
          <type>boolean</type>
          <internalDefault>false</internalDefault>
          <brief>
          Limit the movement of all Control Measures to be within their 
          overlaps 
          </brief>
          <description>
           Limit the movement of all Control Measures to be within their 
          overlaps. The application makes sure that when enabled, even if the 
            point moves it will be within the defined overlap area. Uncheck 
            LIMIT if there is no overlap list for example Control Net from 
            seedgrid application or if it is ok if  the point moves beyond the 
            overlap area. 
          </description>
          <inclusions>
            <item>OVERLAPLIST</item>
          </inclusions>
        </parameter>
  
        <parameter name="OVERLAPLIST">
          <type>filename</type>
          <internalDefault>None</internalDefault>
          <fileMode>input</fileMode>
          <brief>This is the list of image overlaps corresponding to this 
            Control Net 
          </brief>
          <description>
            Use this parameter to select the filename which contains the
            overlap list. You can obtain this file by running the application 
            "findimageoverlaps."
          </description>
          <filter>
            *
          </filter>
        </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Resolution">
        <parameter name="TYPE">
          <type>string</type>
          <default><item>HIGH</item></default>
          <brief>Choose the Resolution type</brief>
          <description>
            This parameter lets the user choose the different Resolution choices 
            available
          </description>
          <list>
            <option value="HIGH">
            <brief>Reference is chosen based on Highest Resolution
                </brief>
              <description>This option chooses a valid Control Measure with the 
              highest Resolution 
              </description>
              <exclusions>
                <item>RESVALUE</item>
                <item>MINRES</item>
                <item>MAXRES</item>
              </exclusions>
            </option>
            
            <option value="LOW">
            <brief>Reference is chosen based on Least Resolution
                </brief>
              <description>
              This option chooses a valid Control Measure with the lowest 
              Resolution 
              </description>
              <exclusions>
                <item>RESVALUE</item>
                <item>MINRES</item>
                <item>MAXRES</item>
              </exclusions>
            </option>

            <option value="MEAN">
            <brief>Reference is chosen based on Mean of all the Resolutions
            </brief>
              <description>
                This option first calculates the Mean of the Resolution of all 
                the Control Measures in a Control Point and then chooses the 
                Control Measure with the Resolution closest to the Mean on the 
                higher Resolution side as Control Point Reference.
              </description>
              <exclusions>
                <item>RESVALUE</item>
                <item>MINRES</item>
                <item>MAXRES</item>
              </exclusions>
            </option>

            <option value="NEAREST">
              <brief>Reference is chosen based on Nearness to RESVALUE</brief> 
                <description> This option chooses the Control Measure whose 
                Resolution is closest to the user specified value in RESVALUE 
                as Control Point Reference.
              </description>
              <exclusions>
                <item>MINRES</item>
                <item>MAXRES</item>
              </exclusions>
            </option>

            <option value="RANGE">
              <brief>Reference is chosen if within MINRES, MAXRES Range</brief>
              <description>
              This option chooses the first Control Measure whose Resolution is 
              within the specified Resolution Range MINRES, MAXRES as Control 
              Point Reference. 
              </description>
              <exclusions>
                <item>RESVALUE</item>
              </exclusions>
            </option>
          </list>
        </parameter>
      
      <parameter name="RESVALUE">
        <type>double</type>
          <internalDefault>0</internalDefault>
          <brief>Resolution Number</brief>
          <description>
            This parameter is associated with the parameter NEAREST and holds 
            the Resolution value. The Control Measure closest to this value is 
            chosen as the Control Point Reference. 
          </description>
        </parameter>

      <parameter name="MINRES">
        <type>double</type> 
        <internalDefault>0</internalDefault>
        <brief>Minimum Image Resolution
        </brief>
        <description>
          This parameter is associated with parameters RANGE and MAXRES and 
          represents the Minimum Resolution for a Control Measure to be 
          considered to be a Control Point Reference.
        </description>
      </parameter>
      
      <parameter name="MAXRES">
        <type>double</type> 
        <internalDefault>0</internalDefault>
        <brief>Maximum Image Resolution
        </brief>
        <description>
          This parameter is associated with parameters RANGE and MINRES and 
          represents the Maximum Resolution for a Control Measure to be 
          considered to be a Control Point Reference. 
        </description>
      </parameter>
      </group>
  </groups>
</application>
