<?xml version="1.0"?>
<application name="stats" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">
  <brief>
    Generates statistics about a cube
  </brief>

  <description>
    <p>
      This program computes a set of statistics for the pixels in each selected <def link="Band">band</def>
      of an image <def link="Cube">cube</def>, and outputs the results of each band. By default, all bands are
      processed. The <i>stats</i> program generates statistics that will help you find new insights
      in your data to make more accurate predictions and achieve better outcomes.
    </p>


    <h4>
      Output:
    </h4>

    <p>
      The statistics are output to both the screen and the print.prt file in PVL format. Additionally,
      if the user specifies a file using the TO parameter, the statistics are written to that file in
      PVL format (default) or as a comma delimited text file (FLAT file), as specified by the FORMAT parameter.
      For multi-band images, each band has its own statistics information that will be appended to the
      output file.  The contents of the PVL file can be read using the <i>getkey</i> program. The
      comma delimited text file can be imported into Excel or other applications.  The statistics
      calculated and reported are as follows:
    </p>

    <pre>
Average                 Total pixels

Standard deviation      Valid pixels

Variance                Over valid maximum pixels

Median                  Under valid minimum pixels

Mode                    Null pixels

Skew                    Low representation saturation (LRS) pixels

Minimum                 High representation saturation (HRS) pixels

Maximum                 Low instrument saturation (LIS) pixels

Sum                     High instrument saturation (HIS) pixels
    </pre>

    <p>
      If the output file exists and the APPEND parameter is set to "no," the contents will be
      overwritten.
    </p>

    <h4>
      How to Specify Bands:
    </h4>

    <p>
      You may process one or a few specific bands if you indicate the band(s) in which you desire
      to gather statistics. A <def link="Band">band</def> may be specified by simply placing a
      plus sign and the band number after the input filename (e.g., peaks.cub+3). For several
      bands, commas and hyphens are used to communicate effectively with the program as in the
      following example: peaks.cub+2,4-6.
    </p>

  </description>

  <category>
    <categoryItem>Math and Statistics</categoryItem>
  </category>

  <history>
    <change name="Jeff Anderson" date="2002-06-17">
      Original version written as "histo"
    </change>
    <change name="Stuart Sides" date="2002-07-24">
      Changed name to "stats" and added logging mechanism
    </change>
    <change name="Jeff Anderson" date="2002-12-30">
      Added TO parameter which allows the user to create an output file that can
      be read using the getkey program
    </change>
    <change name="Jeff Anderson" date="2002-12-30">
      Tested for bands which contain only special pixels in order to prevent
      divide by zero errors.
    </change>
    <change name="Jeff Anderson" date="2002-12-31">
      Added the name of the input cube to the log and label file
    </change>
    <change name="Kim Sides" date="2003-05-13">
     Added application test
    </change>
    <change name="Stuart Sides" date="2003-05-16">
      Modified schema location from astrogeology... to isis.astrogeology..."
    </change>
    <change name="Stuart Sides" date="2003-05-30">
      Made changes to application test truth files to reflect -O1 optimization
    </change>
    <change name="Stuart Sides" date="2003-05-30">
      Added modifications to apptest by Kim
    </change>
    <change name="Stuart Sides" date="2003-07-29">
      Modified filename parameters to be cube parameters where necessary
    </change>
    <change name="Stuart Sides" date="2003-11-07">
      Modified results pvl to not include the results group
    </change>
    <change name="Jacob Danton" date="2006-01-23">
        Fixed appTest to comply to changes in iString
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2008-05-06">
      Added Above Range, Below Range reports
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2008-05-13">
      Removed references to CubeInfo
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2008-08-15">
      A bug where the VALIDMIN,VALIDMAX were ignored was fixed;
      these should always be used.
    </change>
    <change name="Stacy Alley" date="2009-01-16">
      Added the Format option for the output file.
    </change>
    <change name="Sharmila Prasad" date="2011-03-31">
      Added Band Keyword - displays the first physical band used to get the
      stats
    </change>
    <change name="James Alexander Crough" date="2011-06-17">
      Changed the behavior of the program to process all bands of a cube, or,
      if an input cube attribute is specified, only those bands will be
      processed. Previously, the program only processed the first band.
    </change>
    <change name="Kimberly Oyama" date="2013-11-12">
      Fixed spelling error in FORMAT=FLAT brief. Documentation updated
      and reviewed.  Fixes #1681.
    </change>
    <change name="Jeffrey Covington" date="2015-02-19">
      Updated documentation of FORMAT and APPEND parameters as well as
      general edits for clarity. Also added undocumented output statistics
      to the list in the description.
    </change>
    <change name="Austin Sanders" date="2020-06-04">
      Updated to fill columns with N/A in cases where images contained only
      special or invalid pixels.
    </change>
  </history>

  <oldName>
    <item>average</item>
    <item>avg_sd</item>
    <item>bandstats</item>
  </oldName>

  <seeAlso>
    <applications>
    <item>getkey</item>
    </applications>
  </seeAlso>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input cube
        </brief>
        <description>
  	  This specifies the input <def link="Cube">cube</def>. The default is
	  to calculate statistics for each band in the input cube, but this can be
	  overridden using the band specifier (e.g., file.cub+3).
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TO">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Output file that contains the statistics
        </brief>
        <internalDefault>
          No output file is created
        </internalDefault>
        <description>
          This text file will contain the statistics for each individual band.
	  If it is written in PVL format (default), the values can be read using the
	  <i>getkey</i> program. This is useful for developing scripts. If it is
          written as a comma delimited text file (FLAT) the output can be easily
          imported into spreadsheet applications like Excel.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.txt
        </filter>
      </parameter>

       <parameter name="FORMAT">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>
          Output file format (PVL or comma delimited text)
        </brief>
        <description>
          This is the format type for the output file. <def>PVL</def> format is the
	  default. The format is ignored unless the TO parameter is specified.
        </description>
        <default><item>PVL</item></default>
        <list>
          <option value="PVL">
            <brief>
              Format the output file specified by TO as PVL.
            </brief>
            <description>
              Output the results to a PVL formatted file specified by TO. This format
              can be read using the <i>getkey</i> program.
            </description>
          </option>
          <option value="FLAT">
            <brief>
              Format the output file specified by TO as a comma delimited text file.
            </brief>
            <description>
              Output the results to a comma delimited text file specified by TO.
              This file format can easily be imported into spreadsheet applications
              like Excel.
            </description>
          </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="APPEND">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <brief>
          Append results to output file specified by TO.
        </brief>
        <description>
          <p>
            If this option is not selected, the output from the <i>stats</i>
	    application is appended to the output file. If this option is
	    set to "NO" or "FALSE," any information in the TO file is
	    overwritten.
          </p>
          <p>
            Note: This will append the formatted results to the end of the TO
            file without regard to the formatting of the current contents.
          </p>
        </description>
        <default><item>TRUE</item></default>
      </parameter>

    </group>

    <group name="Settings">
      <parameter name="VALIDMIN">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief>
          Minimum valid DN value
        </brief>
        <internalDefault>
          No minimum DN value
        </internalDefault>
        <description>
          The statistics will exclude any <def link="Digital Number">DN</def>
	  values below this value.
        </description>
      </parameter>

       <parameter name="VALIDMAX">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief>
          Maximum valid DN value
        </brief>
        <internalDefault>
          No maximum DN value
        </internalDefault>
        <description>
          The statistics will exclude any <def link="Digital Number">DN</def>
	  values above this value.
        </description>
      </parameter>
    </group>
  </groups>

  <examples>
  <example>
      <brief>Calculate statistics for all bands in a cube</brief>
      <description>
        This example shows the statistics computed for all bands in
	the input cube. When no band is specified by the user, <i>stats</i>
	default behavior is to calculate statistics for all bands in a cube.
      </description>
      <terminalInterface>
        <commandLine>
          from=peaks.cub to=peaks0_stats.log
        </commandLine>
        <description>
          Command to run stats in the command line mode using all bands in
	  peaks.cub and output the results to peaks0_stats.log.
        </description>
      </terminalInterface>
      <dataFiles>
        <dataFile path="assets/peaks0_stats.log">
          <brief>
            Output from stats application
          </brief>
          <description>
            This is the results captured in "peaks0_stats.log" by the
            redirection of standard output.
          </description>
          <parameterName></parameterName>
        </dataFile>
      </dataFiles>
    </example>

    <example>
      <brief>Calculate statistics for a single band from an input cube</brief>
      <description>
        This example shows the statistics computed from band 3 of the input
	cube.  A band may be specified by simply placing the plus sign and
	the band number after the input filename.
      </description>
      <terminalInterface>
        <commandLine>
          from=peaks.cub+3 to=peaks1_stats.log
        </commandLine>
        <description>
          Command to run stats in the command line mode using the third band
	  of peaks.cub and output the results to peaks1_stats.log.
        </description>
      </terminalInterface>
      <dataFiles>
        <dataFile path="assets/peaks1_stats.log">
          <brief>
            Output from stats application
          </brief>
          <description>
            This is the results captured in "peaks3_stats.log" by the
            redirection of standard output.
          </description>
          <parameterName></parameterName>
        </dataFile>
      </dataFiles>
    </example>
    <example>
      <brief>Calculate statistics for multiple bands from an input cube</brief>
      <description>
        This example shows the statistics computed for selected bands of a cube.
	In addition to the plus suffix, the comma and hyphen are used to specify
	multiple bands from the input cube to process.
      </description>
      <terminalInterface>
        <commandLine>
          from=peaks.cub+2,4-6 to=peaks2_stats.log
        </commandLine>
        <description>
          Command to run stats in the command line mode using the second, fourth,
	  fifth, and sixth bands of peaks.cub and output the results to
	  peaks2_stats.log.
        </description>
      </terminalInterface>
      <dataFiles>
        <dataFile path="assets/peaks2_stats.log">
          <brief>
            Output from stats application
          </brief>
          <description>
            This is the results captured in "peaks2_stats.log" by the
            redirection of standard output.
          </description>
          <parameterName></parameterName>
        </dataFile>
      </dataFiles>
    </example>
  </examples>
</application>
