<?xml version="1.0"?>
<application name="framestitch" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">
  <brief>
    Stitches even and odd frames from push frame <def link="Cube">cubes</def> back into a single cube.
  </brief>

  <description>
    <p>
      This program combines the even and odd frames from push frame <def link="Cube">cubes</def> back
      into a single interwoven <def link="Cube">cube</def>. It can also optionally flip the frame order
      so that adjacent ground features appear adjacent between frames. This program
      is designed to be run before processing the data in another software package
      as it removes the camera information from the output <def link="Cube">cube</def>.
    </p>
    <p>
      When many push frame images are ingested into ISIS, their frames are separated
      into two different cubes, one with even frames and one with odd frames. In the
      odd frame cube, the lines for the even frames are Null and in the even frame cube,
      the lines for the odd frames are null. This makes processing in other applications
      difficult because each image only has half the data and covers half the ground.
      The footprint for each image is also composed of multiple disjoint pieces and can
      be difficult to work with.
    </p>
  </description>

  <category>
    <categoryItem>Geometry</categoryItem>
  </category>

  <history>
    <change name="Jesse Mapel" date="2022-04-22">
      Original version
    </change>
  </history>

  <seeAlso>
    <applications>
    <item>marciflip</item>
    </applications>
  </seeAlso>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="EVEN">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Even frame cube
        </brief>
        <description>
          This specifies the input <def link="Cube">cube</def> containing even frames.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="ODD">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Odd frame cube
        </brief>
        <description>
          This specifies the input <def link="Cube">cube</def> containing odd frames.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TO">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Output file that contains all frames
        </brief>
        <description>
          The output filename for the <def link="Cube">cube</def> containing the
          combined frames from the input even and odd <def link="Cube">cubes</def>.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Settings">
      <parameter name="FLIP">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <brief>
          Flip the frame order
        </brief>
        <description>
          <p>
            If true, the order of the frames in the output cube will be reversed.
            So the firt frame in the output cube will be the last frame in the input
            cubes and the last frame in the output cube will be the first frame in
            the input cubes.
          </p>
          <p>
            This option can be used to correct for adjacent ground points not being
            adjacent between frames. This occurs when the flight direction and the
            increasing line direction on the detector are opposite each other.
          </p>
          <p>
            This option can also be used to undo any flipping in the input cubes.
          </p>
        </description>
        <default><item>FALSE</item></default>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="FRAMEHEIGHT">
        <type>integer</type>
        <brief>
          The number of lines in each frame
        </brief>
        <description>
          <p>
            The number of lines in each frame.
          </p>
          <p>
            If not entered, then the program will attempt to count the number of
            adjacent NULL and non-NULL lines in each image to determine a frame size.
          </p>
        </description>
        <internalDefault>Camera</internalDefault>
        <minimum>1</minimum>
      </parameter>
    </group>
  </groups>

</application>
