<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<application name="mdisproc" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">
  <brief>
    Runs a raw Messenger cube through ingestion and calibration
  </brief>

  <description>
      Runs a raw Messenger cube through ingestion and/or calibration.
     With the optional CDR on, the final output will be a re-exported cdr img.
  </description>

  <history>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2008-08-12">
      Original version
    </change>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2008-08-21">
      Fixed the trim option and added a test for it.
    </change>
  </history>

  <category>
    <missionItem>Messenger</missionItem>
  </category>

  <groups>

    <group name="Files">

      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input Messenger img
        </brief>
        <description>
          Input filename to be ingested, calebrated, and possibly re-exported into a cdr.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.QUB *.imq *.ima *.img *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TO">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <internalDefault>Automatic</internalDefault>
        <brief>
          Final output filename.
        </brief>
        <description>
          Output filename from the last enabled processing sequence. By
          default the filename will be generated from the input filename with an
          .cdr.IMG extension.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="BANDS">
        <type>string</type>
        <internalDefault>All</internalDefault>
        <brief>
          Process a subset of bands
        </brief>
        <description>
          This parameter allows the user to specify a sub-set of
          bands to process.  Enter bands separated by commas (no spaces
          allowed).  For example, 1,3,8 or 1-3,9 or 5
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="REMOVE">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <brief>Remove Intermediate Files</brief>
        <description>
            This option allows the user to decide whether the intermediate files 
            created in the thmproc application are to be deleted.  The default value
            is TRUE.
        </description>
        <default><item>TRUE</item></default>
      </parameter>

    </group>

    <group name="Level Processing">

      <parameter name="INGESTION">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default>
          <item>YES</item>
        </default>
        <brief>
          Import and initialize a Messenger RDR file.
        </brief>
        <description>
          Process the input file through all level0 steps. This includes mdis2isis.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="CALIBRATION">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>YES</item></default>
        <brief>
          Process the input file through the calibration phase.
        </brief>
        <description>
          Process the input file through level1. This includes mdiscal.
        </description>
        <inclusions>
          <item>TRIM</item>
          <item>DARKCURRENT</item>
          <item>IOF</item>
        </inclusions>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TRIM">
        <type>integer</type>
        <brief>Trim off poor left pixles</brief>
        <description>
          Removes the first few pixels of each line of the final cdr prouct.
        </description>
        <default><item>3</item></default>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="CDR">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>FALSE</item></default>
        <brief>Export the calibrated image to cdr</brief>
        <description>
          <p>Exports the calibrated cube back into cdr format.</p>
          <p>If only this step needs to be ran, use mdis2pds instead.</p>
        </description>
        <inclusions>
          <item>BITS</item>
        </inclusions>
      </parameter>

    </group>

    <group name="Calibration">
      <parameter name="DARKCURRENT">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>Dark current calibration method</brief>
        <description></description>
        <default><item>MODEL</item></default>
        <list>
          <option value="NONE">
            <brief>No correction</brief>
            <description>
                No dark current correction will be applied
              </description>
          </option>
          <option value="STANDARD">
            <brief>Do a median dark current correction</brief>
              <description>
                  This will use the median of the three leftmost pixels to as 
                  the dark current, on a line by line basis. 
              </description>
          </option>
          <option value="LINEAR">
            <brief>Use a linear fit</brief>
            <description>
              This will fit a line to the leftmost pixel values, which should be 
              dark current data, through the lines. The equation derived from 
              these pixels will be used to calculate the dark current 
              correction, on a line by line basis.
            </description>
          </option>
          <option value="MODEL">
            <brief>Use pre-developed model</brief>
             <description>
               Messenger has independent dark models, developed on-ground. 
               This will use the most recent of these models to correct the dark
               current.
              </description>
          </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>
     <parameter name="IOF">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>True</item></default>
        <brief>
          Convert to I/F units
        </brief>
        <description>
            <p>
            This option when set wil convert the output to I/F from radiance values.  
            To convert from radiance to I/F (also known as radiance factor, the ratio 
            of measured radiance to that which would be measured from a white 
            perfectly Lambertian surface), the following expression should is applied: 
            <PRE>
I_over_F(f) = L(f) * PI * (SOLAR_DISTANCE/149597870.691)**2 / F(f)                
            </PRE> 
            where L(f) is calibrated radiance calculated for some filter f,
            SOLAR_DISTANCE is that value for distance of the target object from
            the center of the sun in kilometers (as indicated by the keyword
            SOLAR_DISTANCE), 149597870.691 is the number of kilometers in 1 AU
            and F(f) is effective average solar irradiance sampled under the
            filter bandpass.
            </p>
            <p>
                If the observed target is not of a valid body as recognized by 
                NAIF, the output is left in radiance.
            </p>
        </description>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="CDR">
      <parameter name="BITS">
          <type>integer</type>
          <default><item>32</item></default>
          <brief>
            Number of bits for the output DN
          </brief>
          <description>
            The number of bits to compress the input data to. The valid data as
            well as the five special pixel values (NULL, LIS, LRS, HIS, HRS) will be
            compressed into this number of bits. The output data type will be
            automaticity choosen using this value. A value of 8 will create 
            unsigned byte output files. Values from 9 to 16 will create unsigned
            word output files. Unused bits in the unsigned word output file will be
            set to zero.
          </description>
          <minimum inclusive="yes">8</minimum>
          <maximum inclusive="yes">32</maximum>
        </parameter>
    </group>

  </groups>

</application>
