<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<application name="dawnvir2isis" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">

  <brief>
       Import PDS formatted Dawn VIR EDR or RDR image cube into ISIS format cube 
  </brief>

  <description>
      This program will import a PDS formatted Dawn Visual and InfraRed Mapping
      Spectrometer (VIR) level 1A (EDR) or level 1B (RDR) image into an ISIS 
      cube.  It supports ingestion of detached PDS labels.  The file containing 
      the label needs to be provided in the FROM parameter.   This is typically 
      a file ending with a .LBL suffix.   If it is not the actual image data, it 
      will search for a file with the same base name and suffix with .QUB. 
  </description>

  <history>
    <change name="Janet Barrett" date="2010-03-31">
      Original version
    </change>
    <change name="Janet Barrett" date="2010-11-15">
      Added capability to read detached labels
    </change>
      <change name="Kris Becker" date="2011-03-09">
          Updated documentation
      </change>
     <change name="Kris Becker" date="2011-03-14">
          Removed HorixontalPixelScale and VerticalPixelScale compliancy test; 
          Added optional TARGET parameter to allow TargetName specification 
     </change>
     <change name="Kris Becker" date="2011-06-29">
          Added ingestion of PDS table data file for camera model support
     </change>
     <change name="Kris Becker" date="2011-10-02">
          Updated documentation.
     </change>
  </history>

  <category>
    <categoryItem>Import and Export</categoryItem>
  </category>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input PDS formatted Dawn VIR EDR (1A) or RDR (1B) file (or detached 
          label file) 
        </brief>
        <description>
          Use this parameter to select the existing Dawn VIR EDR or RDR 
          filename. This file must contain a PDS label, with the actual image 
          data either attached (within FROM file) or detached (separate file). 
          For the detached case, the image data filename will automatically be 
          obtained from the PDS image pointer keyword (^IMAGE =...). To 
          override the existing pointer value, use this application's IMAGE 
          parameter to specify the file containing the binary image data. 
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.qub *.QUB *.lbl *.LBL *.img
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="IMAGE">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Detached data file (if not attached in FROM file)
        </brief>
        <description>
          Use this parameter, if desired, to override the image pointer 
          (^IMAGE =...) value in the detached PDS label (FROM). Or, if the 
          existing pointer value is not resolved as an existing file, this 
          application will search for an image file with the same FROM path and 
          base name, only now with extension .QUB.  
        </description>
        <internalDefault>
          Cube data embedded with label or file pointer in label file.
        </internalDefault>
        <filter>
          *.img *.qub *.QUB
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="HKFROM">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          VIR 1A/1B housekeeping (HK) data (label)
        </brief>
        <description>
            <p>
                Housekeeping label file describing the HKTABLE. This parameter
                is optional but the relevant label file must exist and be accessible 
                by this application. Without a user entry here, the application will 
                derive an expected label filename (two options) as follows. 
            </p>
            <p>
                To start, the HKFROM filename is derived by using the FROM base 
                filename, and replacing the .extension with _HK.LBL. If this 
                file does not exist, the application then replaces, within the 
                derived filename, the string '_1B_' with '_1A_', and attempts a 
                second search for the file.  This second attempt is relevant 
                since table data for 1A (uncalibrated) images can be used with 
                1B (calibrated) images.
            </p>
            <p>
                 For example (again, without a user HKFROM entry), if the input 
                 image label file (FROM) is VIR_IR_1B_1_358284474_1.LBL, then 
                 the housekeeping file name first derived is    
                 VIR_IR_1B_1_358284474_1_HK.LBL. If deemed nonexistent, the 
                 second derived file name is VIR_IR_1A_1_358284474_1_HK.LBL. 
                 Otherwise, user input is required for the HKFROM parameter.
            </p>
            <p>
                  Note this file is assumed to exist in the same directory as 
                   the image data (FROM). Otherwise, the user must provide the 
                   full path and filename. 
            </p>
        </description>
        <internalDefault>Derived from input image (FROM)</internalDefault>
        <filter>
          *.LBL *.TAB
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="HKTABLE">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Detached housekeeping (HK) table data file
        </brief>
        <description>
            <p>
                This parameter is provided in the event where the table data is not 
                readily determined from the input file.  As described in the HKFROM 
                parameter, this filename is typically contained with the KHFROM 
                label.  If for some reason, it cannot be resolved/found, this 
                parameter allows the user to provide it directly.
            </p>
            <p>
                This table contains data that is required in order for the 
                camera model to work properly.  Uncalibrated (1A) tables can be 
                used for calibrated (1B) table.
            </p>
        </description>
        <internalDefault>
          Deterministic from input label file (HKFROM)
        </internalDefault>
        <filter>
          *.img *.qub *.QUB
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TO">
         <type>cube</type>
         <fileMode>output</fileMode>
         <brief>
           Output Isis cube
         </brief>
         <description>
           Use this parameter to select the output filename of the ISIS cube 
           generated by this application.
         </description>
         <filter>
           *.cub
         </filter>
       </parameter>

    </group>
    <group name="Parameters">
        <parameter name="TARGET">
            <type>string</type>
            <brief>Provide target name if absent or incorrect in input (FROM) 
              label 
            </brief>
            <description>
              <p>
               This parameter may be necessary as some Dawn EDR labels may 
                not contain incorrect values for the TARGET_NAME keyword. 
              </p>
              <p>
                Dawn had a long cruise period before arriving at Vesta in 
                August 2011. During cruise, a Mars flyby and various stellar 
                observations occurred. Proper specification of the 
                TARGET_NAME is critical. 
              </p>
              <p>
                With many star observations being made by Dawn, and in order to 
                properly instantiate the ISIS camera model, the target must be 
                either a recognized NAIF body or defined as <i>Sky</i>. NAIF 
                bodies provide the means to map image coordinates to 
                latitude/longitude values. 
              </p>
              <p>
                <i>Sky</i> is a special instantiation within ISIS providing the 
                ability to map image coordinates to RA/DEC coordinates. If not 
                defined here (TARGET), the default is to honor the TARGET_NAME 
                value in the existing EDR label. For some observed targets, 
                <i>Sky</i> is required in order to properly instantiate the camera 
                model orignally validated by the <b>spiceinit</b> ISIS 
                application.
              </p>
            </description>
            <internalDefault>Label Value</internalDefault> 
        </parameter>
    </group>
  </groups>
</application>
