<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="mar10cal" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">

  <brief>
    Radiometrically calibrates a Mariner10 image
  </brief>

  <description>
    <p>
    mar10cal performs radiometric corrections to images acquired by the Mariner 10
    vidicon cameras.

    MAR10CAL performs a dark curent correction and linearization of
    Mariner 10 images.  Key documents to refer to:

      MVM 73 TV Subsystem Calibration Report, M. Benesh and M. Morrill,
        JPL 615-148, 1973.
      Acquisition and Description of Mariner 10 Television Science Data
        at Mercury, G.E. Danielson, K.P. Klaasen, J.L. Anderson, Jour.
        Geophys. Research, Vol. 80, No. 17, pp 2357-2393, 1975 (and other
        articles in this issue).

    It should be noted that the flat field and sensitivity fluctuates as
    a function of vidicon temperature (especially for camera A).
    The camera heater was  not functioning during encounters 2 and 3
    and thus these encounters use a different calibration than the
    1st encounter.  Reliable non-linearity correction is thus available
    only for encounter 1 images.

    CAUTION:  the program will process the encounter 2 and 3 images but
    	the results are not reliable for any quantitative applications
    	such as albedo measurements (absolute or relative) or
    	photoclinometry.

    The situation is not hopeless, much effort has gone into deriving a
    fix for the 2nd and 3rd encounter frames and a future update of mar10cal
    will incorporate this work.

    </p>
  </description>

  <history>
    <change name="Mark Robinson" date="1991-09-18">
      Original version
    </change>
    <change name="Tracie Sucharski" date="2009-04-15">
        Converted to Isis

         Isis2 Change History:
                 Oct 25 1991 -  Tammy Becker, USGS,Flagstaff, Converted
                                       to DOIO and TAE
                 Mar 01 1995 Tracie Sucharski,  Converted to ISIS/UNIX
                 Nov 21 1995 Tracie Sucharski,  Changed name of coefficient file
                 Feb 08 1996 Tracie Sucharski,  Print name of calibration files
                                 used to terminal and print.prt.
                 Mar 05 1996 Tracie Sucharski,  Added blemish removal option
                 Mar 29 1996 TLS, New and improved equation
                 Apr 23 1996 TLS, Added user parameter of EXPOFF, also bomb
                               neatly if EXPOSURE on labels is 0.
                 Apr 29 1996 TLS, Added new RFFCOEF values.
                 May 02 1996 TLS, Added user parameter ABSCOEF
                 May 03 1996 TLS, Changed name of WAVECOEF to RFFCOEF(Relative
                               Filter Factor Coefficient)
                 May 16 1996 TLS, Get rid of Relative Filter Factor, corrected
                               abscoef values.
                 May 17 1996 TLS, Add new dark current files.
                 May 28 1996 TLS, If input pixel - dark current is &lt;, set
                               output pixel to NULL.  Also add new coefficient
                               file.
    </change>
    <change name="Travis Addair" date="2010-09-03">
      First commit, added exception handling, finished conversion.
    </change>
    <change name="Travis Addair" date="2010-09-20">
      Fixed minor process inconsistencies with Isis 2, clean up code, added
      tests.
    </change>
  </history>

  <category>
    <missionItem>Mariner</missionItem>
  </category>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Level 0 Mariner 10 image
        </brief>
        <description>
          An uncalibrated Mariner 10 image.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TO">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <pixelType>real</pixelType>
        <brief>
          Level 1 Mariner 10 image
        </brief>
        <description>
          The resultant radiometrically calibrated cube
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="COEFCUBE">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <pixelType>real</pixelType>
        <brief>
          Coefficient file
        </brief>
        <internalDefault>Internal Default</internalDefault>
        <description>
          <p>
           A cube file containing the calibration coefficients.  This
           file should have eight bands, bands 1-4 are the coefficients
           for inverting the third order equation, bands 5-6 are the
           minimum and maximum values to process.  Bands 5-6 are only
           used if the MASK parameter is set to "YES".  If MASK is set,
           pixels with values outside of this range are set to NULL in
           the output.  The mask assures that only pixels with dns in
           the range of the prelaunch fit are calibrated, dns outside
           this range are interpolations and may contain large errors.
           In most cases the default should be used and the files
           derived from the prelaunch calibration flat fields
           will be used.  These files are named -

           $ISISMAR10DATA/mariner_10_"First 3 letters of FILTER_NAME"_
           	"INSTRUMENT_ID"_coef.cub.

           See also
           1) Robinson et al., Jour. Geophys. Res., 97, p.18265-18274,
           	1992.
           2) Robinson and Lucey, Science, 275, p. 197-200, 1997.
           3) Robinson et al., abstracts of Lunar Planetary Sci. Conf.
                   XXVIII, p. 1187-1188, Lunar and Planetary Inst,
                   Houston, TX, 1997.
          </p>
        </description>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="DCCUBE">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <pixelType>real</pixelType>
        <brief>
          Dark Current file
        </brief>
        <internalDefault>Internal Default</internalDefault>
        <description>
          This parameter allows the user to use an alternate dark
          current file. In most cases, the default should be used for
          this parameter to indicate the derived dark current file is
          to be used.  The name of the derived dark current file is
          $ISISDATA/mariner10//mariner_10_"InstrumentId"_dc.cub.  The
          InstrumentId wil have a value of "A" or "B".
        </description>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Calibration Parameters">
      <parameter name="MASK">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>True</item></default>
        <brief>
          Use a range of values to decide whether to process a pixel
        </brief>
        <description>
           If TRUE, bands 5-6 of the coefficient cube are the minimum and
           maximum values to process.  Any values outside of this range
           are set to NULL in the output file.  Caution should be used in
           setting MASK to FALSE - the resulting dns may have less
           than optimal radiometric integrity.
        </description>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="BLEMMASK">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <default><item>True</item></default>
        <brief>
          Apply blemish removal mask
        </brief>
        <description>
           Apply blemish removal mask.
        </description>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="XPARM">
        <type>double</type>
        <default><item>75.0</item></default>
        <brief>
          Approximation for iterative solution
        </brief>
        <description>
          Approximation for iterative solution.
        </description>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="ABSCOEF">
        <type>double</type>
        <internalDefault>Internal Default</internalDefault>
        <brief>
          Absolute sensitivity coefficient
        </brief>
        <description>
           <p>
           After dark removal and linearity correction an absolute
           coefficent needs to be applied to put the data in units of
           radiance.  These coefficents (1 for each camera-filter
           combination) are still being refined.  The values are being
           derived by forcing global mosaics (photometrically
           corrected) to Earth based measurements.

           for futher explanation see;

           1) Robinson and Lucey, Science, 275, p. 197-200.
           2) Robinson et al., abstract of Lunar Planetary Sci. Conf.
                   XXVIII, p. 1187-1188, 1997.

           </p>
        </description>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="EXPOFF">
        <type>double</type>
        <internalDefault>Camera A = 0.316 msec   Camera B = 3.060 msec</internalDefault>
        <brief>
          Exposure offset (added to exposure)
        </brief>
        <description>
          <p>
          Offset to be added to Exposure time.  If the default of
          NULL is used the following values are added to the offset:

            Camera A EXPOFF = 0.316 msecs
            Camera B EXPOFF = 3.060 msecs

          These values are taken directly from the Benesh and Morrill
          JPL calibration document.  They state that there are some
          unknowns with these values... Read the section on their
          page 38.
          </p>
        </description>
      </parameter>

    </group>
  </groups>
</application>
