<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="ratio" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">
  <brief>
    Divide two cubes
  </brief>

  <description>
    This program divides two cubes.  It operates in one of two manners: 1) the
    denominator cube must have the same number of bands as the numerator cube
    or 2) the denominator cube must have exactly one band.  In the former case,
    corresponding bands are divided, for example, band one is divided by
    band one, band two by band two, and so on.  In the later case, all bands
    in the numerator cube are divided by the single band in the denominator
    cube.
    Special pixels values are handled identically in both cases.  Whenever a
    special pixel occurs, in either the numerator or denominator, the output
    pixel is set to NULL.  Likewise, if the denominator is zero, the output
    is set to NULL.
  </description>

  <category>
    <categoryItem>Math and Statistics</categoryItem>
  </category>

  <history>
    <change name="Eric Eliason" date="1990-09-01">
      Original version
    </change>
    <change name="Jeff Anderson" date="2002-06-17">
      Converted to Isis 3.0
    </change>
    <change name="Kim Sides" date="2003-05-13">
      Added application test
    </change>
    <change name="Stuart Sides" date="2003-05-16">
      Modified schema location from astogeology... to isis.astrogeology..."
    </change>
    <change name="Stuart Sides" date="2003-07-22">
      Changed NUM, DEN and To from type filename to type cube
    </change>
    <change name="Stuart Sides" date="2003-07-29">
      Modified filename parameters to be cube parameters where necessary
    </change>

  </history>

  <oldName>
    <item>ratio</item>
    <item>cosi</item>
  </oldName>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="NUMERATOR">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Numerator cube
        </brief>
        <description>
  	      The numerator cube.  All pixels in this cube will be divided by
          corresponding pixels in the denominator cube.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="DENOMINATOR">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Denominator cube
        </brief>
        <description>
          The denominator cube.  The number of bands in this cube must
          match the numerator cube or be exactly one.  In the former case,
          a band-by-band division occurs.  In the later, each numerator
          band is divided by the single denominator band.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TO">
        <type>cube</type>
        <pixelType>Real</pixelType>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Output cube
        </brief>
        <description>
          The output cube containing the results of the ratio.  A NULL
          pixel will be output when either of the numerator or denominator
          pixels is special.  Similarly, a NULL will be output if the
          denominator pixel is zero.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>
    </group>
  </groups>

  <examples>
    <example>
      <brief>Dividing one band by one band</brief>
      <description>
        This example presents dividing one band in a cube by a single band.
        In this case, we divide band 5 by band 4 in peaks.cub and
        generate a single band
        output cube.  Note that the file (peaks.cub) does not have to be
        the same name for NUMERATOR and DENOMINATOR so long as the
        spatial size (samples and lines) match between the given files.
      </description>
      <terminalInterface>
        <commandLine>
          numerator=peaks.cub:5 denominator=peaks.cub:4 to=ratio.cub
        </commandLine>
        <description></description>
      </terminalInterface>
    </example>

    <example>
      <brief>Dividing multiple bands by one band</brief>
      <description>
        This example presents dividing all bands in a cube by an individual
        band.  In this case, the seven bands in peaks.cub are divided
        by band 4 and the results output to ratio.cub.
      </description>
      <terminalInterface>
        <commandLine>
          numerator=peaks.cub denominator=peaks.cub:4 to=ratio.cub
        </commandLine>
        <description>
        </description>
      </terminalInterface>
    </example>
  </examples>

</application>
