<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="phoemplocal" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">
 
  <brief>
    Fit empirical photometric functions to Hapke model at a single point
  </brief>
  
  <description>
    <p>
    This program finds lunar-Lambert or Minnaert photometric functions
    to approximate a more realistic but complex Hapke model. The fit
    is performed at a single geometry rather than for a range of phase 
    angles.  The user specifies the <def link="Phase Angle">phase</def>,
    <def link="Incidence Angle">incidence</def> and <def 
    link="Emission Angle">emission</def> angles of the mean ground plane (datum), 
    as well as the root mean squared (RMS) slope relative to the datum.  
    Artificial data are then created, with slopes drawn from an isotropic 
    Gaussian distribution relative to the datum.  The simpler model is fit at 
    these orientations (phase, incidence, and emission angles) to the 
    Hapke model by adjusting the limb-darkening and the overall brightness 
    so that the sum-squared-residual between the two 
    is minimized.  Both the parameter (which, for both types of simple model, 
    mainly controls limb darkening) and the brightness (normalized as an 
    empirical phase curve) are reported.
    </p>
    <p>
    Phoemplocal requires the user to input a set of parameters for the Hapke
    model, and the results for a single point are returned by the program.
    The input parameter values and the results for the limb-darkening parameter (L), 
    best fit multiplier, and the RMS error of fit are reported to an output file. 
    The results can be used for photoclinometry application.
    </p>
  </description>

  <category>
    <categoryItem>Radiometric and Photometric Correction</categoryItem>
  </category>
  
  <oldName>
    <item>pho_emp_local</item>
  </oldName>

  <seeAlso>
    <applications>
      <item>photomet</item>
    </applications>
  </seeAlso>

  <history>
    <change name="Randy Kirk" date= "1999-11-16">
        USGS Flagstaff Original Version
    </change>
    <change name="Janet Barrett"  date="2003-01-13">
      Ported pho_fit_local from the VAX and renamed it 
      pho_emp_local in isis2
    </change>
    <change name="Sharmila Prasad" date="2011-08-04">
      Isis3 Original version, pho_emp_local ported from isis2 to isis3 
      phoemplocal 
    </change>
    <change name="Randy Kirk" date="2011-09-25">
      Updated documentation for the phoemplocal program
    </change>
    <change name="Ella Mae Lee" date="2013-01-28">
      Updated documentation for phoemplocal, and added glossary links and
      examples, fixes #450
    </change>
    <change name="Lynn Weller" date="2013-02-25">
      Removed links to applications imbedded in text and replaced with
      italicized application name.  Added application links to the
      "Related Objects and Documents" section of the documentation.
      Fixes mantis ticket #1525.
    </change>
  </history>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="TO">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <brief>
            Output text filename
        </brief>
        <internalDefault>
          None Specified
        </internalDefault>
        <description>
          The output file will contain the <def link="Phase Angle">phase angle</def>, 
	  best-fit limb darkening parameter, best-fit brightness both in absolute units
          and relative to the zero phase model and RMS residual to the fit.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.txt *.pvl
        </filter>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="APPEND">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <brief>
          Option to append results to output file
        </brief>
        <description>
          If this option is selected, the results will be appended to an existing
	  file specified as the "TO" file.  If "APPEND" is not selected, the output
	  information defaults and overwrites the existing "TO" file.
        </description>
        <default><item>FALSE</item></default>
      </parameter>
    </group>

     <group name="User Note">
       <parameter name="NOTE">
        <type>string</type>
        <brief>
            User note to add to the output text file
        </brief>
        <internalDefault>None Specified</internalDefault>
        <description>
          The text entered by the user is added to the output file. The note 
	  should include some helpful information that lets the user know
	  what types of data the results would be applied to, such as 
	  the planet and instrument filter.  The input parameter settings
	  should also be included in the note as a record. 
        </description>
       </parameter>
    </group>

     <group name="Hapke">
      <parameter name="PHTNAME">
        <type>combo</type>
        <internalDefault>HAPKEHEN</internalDefault>
        <default>
          <item>HAPKEHEN</item>
        </default>
        <brief>
          Surface photometric model
        </brief>
        <description>
          A Hapke (1981; 1984; 1986) photometric model is always used as the model
          to which empirical functions are fitted. The options correspond to variants
          of the Hapke model with different types of model for the single particle
          phase (scattering) function.
        </description>

        <list>
          <option value="HAPKEHEN">
            <brief> 
              Henyey-Greenstein photometric model
            </brief>
            <description>
              This is the two-parameter version of the Henyey-Greenstein single
              particle phase function, with parameters HG1 and HG2.
            </description>
            <exclusions>
              <item>BH</item>
              <item>CH</item>
            </exclusions>
          </option>
          <option value="HAPKELEG">
            <brief> 
              Hapke Legendre photometric model
            </brief>
            <description>
              This is a two-term Legendre Polynomial expansion of the single
              particle phase function, with parameters BH and CH.
            </description>
            <exclusions>
              <item>HG1</item>
              <item>HG2</item>
            </exclusions>
          </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="WH">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief>
          Single scattering albedo
        </brief>
        <description>
          The Hapke single-scattering <def link="Albedo">albedo</def> of surface 
	  particles, see Hapke (1981).  Not to be confused with albedo WHA of the 
	  atmospheric particles.
        </description> 
        <internalDefault>None Specified</internalDefault>
        <minimum inclusive="no">0.0</minimum>
        <maximum inclusive="yes">1.0</maximum>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="HH">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief>
          Hapke opposition surge width
        </brief>
        <description>
          The Hapke opposition surge width. The width parameter for the
          opposition effect for the surface if hapkehen or hapkeleg is used,
          see Hapke (1984).
        </description> 
        <internalDefault>None Specified</internalDefault>
        <minimum inclusive="yes">0.0</minimum>
       </parameter>

      <parameter name="B0">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief>
          Hapke opposition surge strength
        </brief>
        <description>
          The Hapke opposition surge strength. The magnitude of the opposition 
	  effect for the surface if hapkehen or hapkeleg is used, see Hapke (1984).
        </description>
        <internalDefault>None Specified</internalDefault>
        <minimum inclusive="yes">0.0</minimum>
       </parameter>

      <parameter name="THETA">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief>
          Surface roughness in degrees
        </brief>
        <description>
          The small scale surface roughness value in degrees. "Macroscopic roughness"
          of the surface as it affects the photometric behavior, used for hapkehen
          or hapkeleg. This is the root mean squared (RMS) slope at scales larger 
	  than the distance photons penetrate the surface but smaller than a pixel,
	  see Hapke (1986).  The roughness correction is evaluated if theta is given 
	  any value other than 0.0, but is extremely slow.
        </description>
        <internalDefault>None Specified</internalDefault>
        <minimum inclusive="yes">0.0</minimum>
        <maximum inclusive="yes">90.0</maximum>
      </parameter> 

      <parameter name="HG1">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief>
          Hapke Henyey-Greenstein coefficient
        </brief>
        <description>
          Asymmetry parameter used in Hapke Henyey-Greenstein model
          for the scattering phase function of single particles in the
          surface.  See Hapke (1981).  The two-parameter Henyey-Greenstein
          function is:
          <blockquote>
          P(phase)=(1-hg2) * (1-hg1**2)/(1+hg1**2+2*hg1*cos(phase))**1.5
          + hg2  * (1-hg1**2)/(1+hg1**2-2*hg1*cos(phase))**1.5
          </blockquote>
        </description>
        <internalDefault>None Specified</internalDefault>
        <minimum inclusive="no">-1.0</minimum>
        <maximum inclusive="no">1.0</maximum>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="HG2">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief>
          Hapke Henyey-Greenstein coefficient
        </brief> 
        <description>
          The Hapke Henyey-Greenstein coefficient for a single particle phase
          function.  The second parameter of the two-parameter Henyey-Greenstein
          model for the scattering phase function of single particles in the
          surface.  This parameter controls the proportions in a linear
          mixture of ordinary Henyey-Greenstein phase functions with asymmetry
          parameters equal to +hg1 and -hg1.  See HG1 for the full formula.
        </description>
        <internalDefault>None Specified</internalDefault>
        <minimum inclusive="yes">0.0</minimum>
        <maximum inclusive="yes">1.0</maximum>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="BH">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief>
          Hapke Legendre coefficient
        </brief>
        <description>
          The Hapke Legendre coefficient for a single particle phase
          function.  A two-term Legendre polynomial is used for the scattering
          phase function of single particles in the surface:
          <blockquote>
          P(phase) = 1 + bh * p1(cos(phase)) + ch * p2(cos(phase)) <br/>
          </blockquote>
          Where p1 and p2 are the first and second order Legendre polynomials.
          Bh is not to be confused with the Legendre coefficient bha of the
          phase function for atmospheric particles, used when
          atmname=anisotropic1 or anisotropic2.
        </description>
        <internalDefault>None Specified</internalDefault>
        <minimum inclusive="no">-1.0</minimum>
        <maximum inclusive="no">1.0</maximum>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="CH">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief>
          Hapke Legendre coefficient
        </brief>
        <description>
          The Hapke Legendre coefficient for a single particle phase
          function.  A two-term Legendre polynomial is used for the scattering
          phase function of single particles in the surface: <br/>
          <blockquote>
          P(phase) = 1 + bh * p1(cos(phase)) + ch * p2(cos(phase))
          </blockquote>
          Where p1 and p2 are the first and second order Legendre
          polynomials.
        </description>
        <internalDefault>None Specified</internalDefault>
        <minimum inclusive="no">-1.0</minimum>
        <maximum inclusive="no">1.0</maximum>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Empirical">
      <parameter name="MODEL">
        <type>combo</type>
        <internalDefault>LunarLambert</internalDefault>
        <brief>
          Photometric function to fit to the Hapke model
        </brief>
        <description>
          Specify a photometric function to fit to the Hapke model. The
          lists of brightness and limb-darkening values can be used with the
          LunarLambertEmpirical or MinnaertEmpirical photometric functions in
          the photometric normalization program <i>photomet</i>.
        </description>
        <list>
          <option value="LUNARLAMBERT">
            <brief>
              LunarLambert photometric function
            </brief>
            <description>
              Fit the LunarLambert photometric function to the Hapke Model to
              derive the parameters for the LunarLambertEmpirical photometric
              function. The LunarLambertEmpirical model as defined by
              McEwen (1991) and used by the program Photomet is
              <blockquote>
                func=b(phase) * ((1-l(phase))*u0 + 2*l(phase)*u0/(u0+u))
              </blockquote>
              where phase is the <def link="Phase Angle">phase angle</def>, and
              u0 and u are the
              cosines of the <def link="Incidence Angle">incidence</def> and
              <def link="Emission Angle">emission</def> angles respectively.
            </description>
          </option>
          <option value="MINNAERT">
            <brief>
              Minnaert photometric function
            </brief>
            <description>
              Fit the Minnaert photometric function to the Hapke Model to
              derive the parameters for the MinnaertEmpirical photometric
              function. The MinnaertEmpirical model as defined by
              McEwen (1991) and used by the program <i>photomet</i> is
              <blockquote>
              func=b(phase) * u0**k(phase) * u**(k(phase)-1)
              </blockquote>
              where phase is the <def link="Phase Angle">phase angle</def>,
              and u0 and u are the cosines of the
              <def link="Incidence Angle">incidence</def> and
              <def link="Emission Angle">emission</def> angles, respectively.
            </description>
          </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Atmospheric Scattering Model">
      <parameter name="ATMNAME">
        <type>combo</type>
        <internalDefault>NONE</internalDefault>
        <default>
          <item>NONE</item>
        </default>
        <brief>
           Atmospheric scattering model to be used
	</brief>
        <description>
          If an option other than NONE is selected, an atmospheric scattering
          and surface photometric properties are included as
          part of the physical model to which the empirical model is fitted.
          Six available atmospheric models are categorized into three
          classes that differ in their treatment of the single particle
          scattering function for atmospheric particles. Each of these classes
          of model can be evaluated to a first order (faster) or second order
          (more accurate) approximation. Atmospheric scattering in all these
          models both attenuates the surface signal and adds its own (uniform)
          contribution to the image <def link="Radiance">radiance</def>.
          Therefore, unless NONE is selected, it makes sense to also set
          ADDOFFSET=YES so that the additive contribution of the atmosphere
          will be modeled by an additive constant in the fit.  This approach 
	  is useful in preparing for photoclinometry (shape from shading), 
	  for which images are normally preprocessed by subtracting a uniform 
	  haze component that corresponds to the additive term in the fit with 
	  ADDOFFSET=YES.
	 </description>
        <list>  
          <option value="NONE">
            <brief>
              No atmospheric scattering model
            </brief>
            <description>
              The <def link="Radiance">radiance</def> from the Hapke surface
              is not modified by atmospheric scattering.
            </description>
            <exclusions>
              <item>TAU</item>
              <item>WHA</item>
              <item>HGA</item>
              <item>HNORM</item>
              <item>ADDOFFSET</item>
              <item>BHA</item>
            </exclusions>
          </option>
          <option value="ISOTROPIC1">
            <brief>
              First order isotropic
            </brief>
            <description> 
              Atmospheric particles are assumed to scatter light isotropically.
              The effects of this scattering are calculated exactly to first
              order.
            </description> 
            <inclusions> 
              <item>TAU</item>
              <item>WHA</item>
              <item>HNORM</item>
              <item>ADDOFFSET</item>
            </inclusions>
            <exclusions>
              <item>HGA</item>
              <item>BHA</item>
            </exclusions>
          </option>
          <option value="ISOTROPIC2">
            <brief>
              Second order isotropic
            </brief>
            <description>
              Atmospheric particles are assumed to scatter light isotropically.
              The effects of this scattering are calculated exactly to second
              order.
            </description>
            <inclusions> 
              <item>TAU</item>
              <item>WHA</item>
              <item>HNORM</item>
              <item>ADDOFFSET</item>
            </inclusions>
            <exclusions>
              <item>HGA</item>
              <item>BHA</item>
            </exclusions>
          </option>
          <option value="ANISOTROPIC1">
            <brief>
              First order anisotropic
            </brief>
            <description>
              Atmospheric particles are assumed to scatter light according
              to a Legendre polynomial model with a single term. The effects
              of this scattering are calculated exactly to first order.
            </description>
            <inclusions> 
              <item>TAU</item>
              <item>WHA</item>
              <item>BHA</item>
              <item>HNORM</item>
              <item>ADDOFFSET</item>
            </inclusions>
            <exclusions>
              <item>HGA</item>
            </exclusions>
          </option>
          <option value="ANISOTROPIC2">
            <brief>
              Second order anisotropic
            </brief>
            <description>
              Atmospheric particles are assumed to scatter light according to
              a Legendre polynomial model with a single term. The effects of
              this scattering are calculated exactly to second order.
            </description>
            <inclusions> 
              <item>TAU</item>
              <item>WHA</item>
              <item>BHA</item>
              <item>HNORM</item>
              <item>ADDOFFSET</item>
            </inclusions>
            <exclusions>
              <item>HGA</item>
            </exclusions>
          </option>
          <option value="HAPKEATM1">
            <brief>
              First order Henyey-Greenstein
            </brief>
            <description>
              Atmospheric particles are assumed to scatter light according to
              a single parameter Henyey-Greenstein function (see the description
              of the surface scattering parameter HG1 for the equation that
              combines two such functions for surface particles). The effects
              of this scattering are approximated by using a first order solution
              for multiple scattering by isotropic particles and making a
              correction to the distribution of singly scattered radiation. The
              model is called HAPKEATM1 because this correction for the single
              particle phase function is similar to the one developed by Hapke
              (1981) for surface scattering.
            </description>
            <inclusions> 
              <item>TAU</item>
              <item>WHA</item>
              <item>HGA</item>
              <item>HNORM</item>
              <item>ADDOFFSET</item>
            </inclusions>
            <exclusions>
              <item>BHA</item>
            </exclusions>
          </option>
          <option value="HAPKEATM2">
            <brief>
              Second order Henyey-Greenstein
            </brief>
            <description>
              Atmospheric particles are assumed to scatter light according to
              a single parameter Henyey-Greenstein function (see the description
              of the surface scattering parameter HG1 for the equation that
              combines two such functions for surface particles). The effects
              of this scattering are approximated by using a second order solution
              for multiple scattering by isotropic particles and making a
              correction to the distribution of singly scattered radiation. The
              model is called HAPKEATM2 because this correction for the single
              particle phase function is similar to the one developed by Hapke
              (1981) for surface scattering.
            </description>
            <inclusions> 
              <item>TAU</item>
              <item>WHA</item>
              <item>HGA</item>
              <item>HNORM</item>
              <item>ADDOFFSET</item>
            </inclusions>
            <exclusions>
              <item>BHA</item>
            </exclusions>
          </option>
        </list>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TAU">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief>
          Normal atmospheric optical depth
        </brief>
        <description>
          This is the normal atmospheric optical depth.
        </description>
        <internalDefault>None Specified</internalDefault>
        <minimum inclusive="yes">0.0</minimum>
       </parameter>

      <parameter name="WHA">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief>
          Single-scattering albedo
        </brief>
        <internalDefault>None Specified</internalDefault>
        <description>
          This is the single-scattering <def link="Albedo">albedo</def> of atmospheric
          particles, not to be confused with the albedo WH of surface particles.
        </description>
        <minimum inclusive="no">0.0</minimum>
        <maximum inclusive="yes">1.0</maximum>
       </parameter>

      <parameter name="HGA">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief>
          Henyey-Greenstein coefficient for atmospheric particles
        </brief>
        <description>
          Parameter used in the Henyey-Greenstein single particle phase
          function for atmospheric particles when ATMNAME=HAPKEATM1 or
          ATMNAME=HAPKEATM2. This is the asymmetry parameter for a single
          term Henyey-Greenstein model:
          <blockquote>
          p(phase) = (1-hga**2)/(1+hga**2+2*hga*cos(phase))**1.5
          </blockquote>
          Not to be confused with corresponding parameter HG1 for the
          surface particles.
        </description>
        <internalDefault>None Specified</internalDefault>
        <minimum inclusive="no">-1.0</minimum>
        <maximum inclusive="no">1.0</maximum>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="BHA">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief>
          Atmospheric particle Legendre coefficient
        </brief>
        <internalDefault>None Specified</internalDefault>
        <description>
          Coefficient of the first order Legendre polynomial in the
          single particle phase function for atmospheric scattering.
          When ATMNAME=ANISOTROPIC1 or ATMNAME=ANISOTROPIC2, a two-term
          Legendre polynomial expansion is used to represent the
          scattering phase function of single particles in the atmosphere:
          <blockquote>
          p(phase) = 1 + bha * p1(cos(phase))
          </blockquote>
          Where, P1 is the first order Legendre polynomial, and not to be
          confused with the corresponding parameter BH for the surface.
        </description>
        <minimum inclusive="yes">-1.0</minimum>
        <maximum inclusive="yes">1.0</maximum>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="HNORM">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief>
          Atmospheric shell thickness
        </brief>
        <description>
          Atmospheric shell thickness normalized to planet radius, used
          to correct the path lengths of atmospheric transmission for the
          spherical geometry of the planet. Default 0.003 is for Mars.
        </description>
        <internalDefault>None Specified</internalDefault>
        <minimum inclusive="yes">0.0</minimum>
       </parameter>

      <parameter name="ADDOFFSET">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <brief>
          Allow additive offset in fit
        </brief>
        <default>
          <item>false</item>
        </default>
        <description>
          If true, the additive contribution of the atmosphere will be modeled
          by an additive constant in the fit of the empirical function at each
          phase angle.
        </description>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Mean Ground Plane (Datum) Geometry">
      <parameter name="EMISSION">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief>
          Emission angle
        </brief>
        <description>
          This is the <def link="Emission Angle">emission angle</def> of the 
	  ground plane obtained from a representative point on an image.  The
	  emission angle is the measurement between the local vertical and 
	  the vector from the point on the ground to the spacecraft.
        </description>
        <internalDefault>None Specified</internalDefault>
        <minimum inclusive="yes">0.0</minimum>
        <maximum inclusive="yes">90.0</maximum>
       </parameter>

      <parameter name="PHASE">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief>
          Phase angle
        </brief>
        <description>
          This is the <def link="Phase Angle">phase angle</def> obtained from
	  a representative point on an image.  The phase angle is a measurement
	  between the vector from the representative point to the sun and the 
	  vector from that point to the spacecraft.
        </description>
        <internalDefault>None Specified</internalDefault>
        <minimum inclusive="yes">0.0</minimum>
        <maximum inclusive="yes">180.0</maximum>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="INCIDENCE">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief>
          Incidence angle
        </brief>
        <description>
          This is the <def link="Incidence Angle">incidence angle</def> of the 
	  ground plane obtained from a representative point on an image.  The 
	  incidence angle is the measurement between the local vertical and 
	  the vector from the point on the ground to the sun.
        </description>
        <internalDefault>None Specified</internalDefault>
        <minimum inclusive="yes">0.0</minimum>
        <maximum inclusive="yes">90.0</maximum>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="RMS_SLOPE">
        <type>double</type>
        <brief>
          Root mean squared slope
        </brief>
        <description>
          The fit will be performed over a set of synthesized data with
          different orientations. Each component (E-W and N-S) of slope
          of these data points is normally distributed with a mean of 
          zero and a standard deviation given by this parameter. The fit
          results should be only weakly dependent on this parameter.
        </description>
        <internalDefault>None Specified</internalDefault>
        <minimum inclusive="yes">0.0</minimum>
        <maximum inclusive="yes">90.0</maximum>
      </parameter>
    </group>

    <group name="Random Number Generator">
      <parameter name="SEED">
        <type>boolean</type>
        <brief>
          User specified seed
        </brief>
        <default><item>false</item></default>
        <description>
          If enabled, this program uses the user defined number as the starting
          seed for the random number generator which is used to generate 
          slopes at which the fit is performed, allowing the same random number
          sequence to be used multiple times for testing purposes. If disabled,
          the random number sequence will be initialized from the system clock
          and the numbers will be different each time the program is run.
        </description>
        <inclusions>
          <item>SEED_NUMBER</item>
        </inclusions>
      </parameter>
      <parameter name="SEED_NUMBER">
        <type>integer</type>
        <brief>
          Starting seed number
        </brief>
        <description>
          Starting seed number for random number generator
        </description> 
        <internalDefault>None Specified</internalDefault>
      </parameter>
    </group>
  </groups>

  <examples>
     <example>
      <brief>Create a PVL file with phoemplocal</brief>
      <description>
        This example shows the GUI and the input setting for each parameter name
	in the <i>phoemplocal</i> program.  
      </description>
      <terminalInterface>
        <commandLine>
           to=my_phoemplocal.pvl note="This is a test, wh.52, hh=.17 b0=.025 theta=30 
	   hg1=.213 hg2=1 for lunarlambert empirical model and no atmosphere" wh=.52 
	   hh=.17 b0=.025 theta=30 hg1=.213 hg2=1 model=lunarlambert emission=15 phase=30 
	   incidence=30 rms_slope=.5
        </commandLine>
        <description>
         Run <i>phoemplocal</i> to generate a PVL file with the parameter values for the
         LunarLambertEmpirical photometric model and no atmospheric scattering.
        </description>
      </terminalInterface>
      <guiInterfaces>
        <guiInterface>
          <image src="assets/images/phoemplocal_gui.png" width="464" height="750">
            <brief>phoemplocal GUI</brief>
            <description>
              Screenshot of GUI version of the application.  The parameter values
              are entered by the user, and the results are output to a text file.
            </description>
            <thumbnail src="assets/thumbs/phoemplocal_gui_thumb.png" caption="phoemplocal GUI" width="92" height="150"/>
          </image>
        </guiInterface>
      </guiInterfaces>
      <dataFiles>
        <dataFile path="assets/my_phoemplocal.pvl">
          <brief>Output PVL file</brief>
          <description>
            The output <def>PVL</def> file contains the photometric parameter settings
	    for the LunarLambertEmpirical photometric function.  The contents of this 
	    file can be used as input for photoclinometry application.
          </description>
          <parameterName>
            TO
          </parameterName>
        </dataFile>
      </dataFiles>
    </example>
   </examples>

</application>
