<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<application name="findgaps" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNmaespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">

  <brief>
    Finds the gaps in a given Cube.
  </brief>

  <description>
    <p>This program finds gaps in the line direction of an image, and will report the gap
    information or expand the gap based on user parameters or default settings. Gaps are areas where
    the entire line consists of NULL pixel values or pixel values statistically below the threshold
    setting of the CORTOL parameter.  This program ignores single line gaps.If the LOG parameter is
    specified, the starting and last line    of each gap as well as the band number is recorded and
    placed into a log filename (.pvl, .txt)    entered by the user. If the output cube or TO
    parameter is not specified, then the program only    identifies the gaps.</p>

    <p>The CORTOL parameter should be set to "0.0" to only identify an entire line of "NULL" pixels
    as a gap. If the CORTOL parameter is set to a value greater than "0.0," then the statistics of
    the current line are compared against the statistics of the previous line to determine if the
    line should be considered a gap. This option is useful if random lines are much brighter or
    darker than the adjacent lines.</p>
  </description>

  <category>
    <categoryItem>Utility</categoryItem>
  </category>

  <history>
    <change name="Christopher Austin" date="2007-11-26">
      Original version
    </change>
    <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2008-05-12">
      Removed references to CubeInfo 
    </change>
    <change name="Kimberly Oyama and Steven Lambright" date="2012-06-15">
      Added the option to nullify a gap and add a buffer of null lines above and below each gap and
      output these results to a cube. If no output cube is specified results will only be output to
      a log file (.pvl, .prt, or .txt) or vice versa. Neither output affects the other. Fixes #582.
    </change>
  </history>

  <groups>
    <group name="Files">
      <parameter name="FROM">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>input</fileMode>
        <brief>
          Input cube file
        </brief>
        <description>
          Input cube file to be checked for line gaps.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="TO">
        <type>cube</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <default>
          <item>none</item>
        </default>
        <brief>
          Output cube file
        </brief>
        <description>
          The resulting cube with a null buffer above and below each gap. Enter "TO=none"
          if you do not want to output a modified cube.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.cub
        </filter>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="LOG">
        <type>filename</type>
        <fileMode>output</fileMode>
        <default>
          <item>none</item>
        </default>
        <brief>
          The output file of the list of gaps (.pvl, .prt, or .txt).
        </brief>
        <description>
          The output file to which all of the gap information is written. If left as the default,
          no log file will be created/updated. This file will not be affected by the nulled lines
          that are included in the output cube.
        </description>
        <filter>
          *.txt *.prt *.pvl
        </filter>
      </parameter>
    </group>

     <group name="Correlation Coefficient Tolerance" >
      <parameter name="CORTOL">
        <type>double</type>
        <default><item>0.0</item></default>
        <brief>Correlation Tolerance</brief>
        <description>
          This parameter determines how similar one line can be to the next and still be considerd
          part of a gap. A higher tolerance will result in gaps that are
          more similar to the surrounding area (possibly valid data). A tolerance
          closer to zero will result in gaps that are more different from the
          surrounding area (CORTOL=0.0 will give you gaps of null data).
        </description>
      </parameter>
    </group>

     <group name="Buffer Size (Lines)" >
      <parameter name="ABOVE">
        <type>integer</type>
        <default><item>7</item></default>
        <brief>Number of nulled lines above gaps.</brief>
        <description>
          This parameter specifies how many lines above the gap are set to null in the output
          cube.
        </description>
      </parameter>

      <parameter name="BELOW">
        <type>integer</type>
        <default><item>7</item></default>
        <brief>Number of nulled lines below gaps</brief>
        <description>
          This parameter specifies how many lines below the gap are set to null in the output
          cube.
        </description>
      </parameter>
    </group>
  </groups>

  <examples>
    <example>
      <brief>Finds Image Gaps</brief>
      <description>
        This example shows how findgaps works on the cube
        I02025005RDR.cub.
      </description>

      <terminalInterface>
         <commandLine>FROM=I02025005RDR.cub
           TO=cubeResults.cub
           LOG=logFileResults.txt
           ABOVE=10
           BELOW=10
        </commandLine>
        <description>
          Searches I02025005RDR.cub for gaps based on the default
          Correlation Tolerance of CORTOL=0.0
        </description>
      </terminalInterface>

      <inputImages>
        <image src="assets/images/I02025005RDR.jpg" width="320" height="750">
          <brief>A section of the input cube</brief>
          <description>
            This image shows three null gaps.
          </description>
          <thumbnail caption="I02025005RDR.cub" src="assets/images/I02025005RDR.jpg"
                     width="86" height="200"/>
            <parameterName>FROM</parameterName>
        </image>
      </inputImages>

      <outputImages>
        <image src="assets/images/cubeResults.jpg" width="320" height="750">
          <brief>The same section as that shown for the input image.</brief>
          <description>
            This is the image cubeResults.cub that has null lines above and below each gap. You can
            see that 10 lines above and below the gap have been nulled out. The narrow strip of
            valid data in the middle of the image has been set to null due to the ABOVE and BELOW
            parameter settings. Reduce the value for ABOVE and BELOW to minimize the lines being set
            to NULL. 
          </description>
          <thumbnail caption="cubeResults.cub" src="assets/images/cubeResults.jpg"
                     width="86" height="200"/>
            <parameterName>TO</parameterName>
        </image>
      </outputImages>

      <dataFiles>
        <dataFile path="assets/logFileResults.txt">"
                             "
          <brief>logFileResults.txt</brief>
          <description>
            <p> In the case of no gaps, the LOG output file
            parameter will be empty. </p>
            <p> When there are gaps in the cube image, then the gap information is reported in the
            LOG file if it is specified. In this example, that file is logFileResults.txt, as shown
            here. Each gap is displayed as a group consisting of the band number, the starting line
            number, the correlation coefficient that defined the line as gap, and the last line for
            a particular gap. 
            </p>
          </description>
        </dataFile>
      </dataFiles>
      
    </example>
  </examples>
  
</application>
