<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<application name="blobdump" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:noNamespaceSchemaLocation="http://isis.astrogeology.usgs.gov/Schemas/Application/application.xsd">
  <brief>
      Program to output a selected blob out to a file
  </brief>

  <description>
      <p>
          This program takes a cube with a blob in it, and strings to identify which 
          blob, and reads that blob out to a file specified by the user.
      </p>

       <p>
          Helper button has been provided in the GUI mode for the NAME and TYPE 
          parameters.  The helper button will sequentially fill in the name and
          type of each blob when pressed, clear the field to blank after the 
          last blob has been reached, and then wrap back to the 
          beginning.
      </p>
  </description>

  <category>
      <categoryItem>Import and Export</categoryItem>
  </category>

  <history>
      <change name="Brendan George" date="2006-06-23">
          Original version
      </change>

      <change name="Steven Lambright" date="2007-07-27">
          Changed category from Utility to Import and Export
      </change>
      
      <change name="Travis Addair" date="2009-03-03">
          Added helper button to sequentially place one blob into the NAME and 
          TYPE parameters each time it is pressed
      </change>
  </history>

  <groups>
      <group name="Files">
          <parameter name="FROM">
              <type>cube</type>
              <fileMode>input</fileMode>
              <brief>
                  Input Cube
              </brief>
              <description>
                  This is the cube containing the blob to be output.
              </description>
              <filter>*.cub</filter>
          </parameter>

          <parameter name="TO">
              <type>filename</type>
              <fileMode>output</fileMode>
              <brief>
                  Output file
              </brief>
              <description>
                  This is the output file the blob will be written as
              </description>
          </parameter>
      </group>

      <group name="Blob Specifications">
          <parameter name="NAME">
              <type>string</type>
              <brief>
                  The name of the blob
              </brief>
              <description>
                  This is the name of the blob to be output. It is generally mission-specific, and 
                  does not refer to which subclass of blob created it. In the cube's labels, this
                  will be the information to the right of the equals sign after the keyword "Name"
              </description>
              <helpers>
                <helper name="H1">
                  <function>helperButtonGetBlobList</function>
                  <brief>Retrieve Blob names</brief>
                  <description>
                     This button will, each time it is pressed, generate the 
                     name and type of a blob in the input cube and put it in 
                     the appropriate field in the GUI, clear to blank after the
                     last blob is hit, and then wrap back to the beginning.  
                  </description>
                  <icon>$ISIS3DATA/base/icons/exec.png</icon>
               </helper>
            </helpers>
          </parameter>

          <parameter name="TYPE">
              <type>string</type>
              <brief>
                  The type of blob to be grabbed
              </brief>
              <description>
                  This is the blob type, and generally refers to the subclass of Blob that created the
                  blob, for example, "OriginalLabel", "Polygon", "Table", or "History". This appears in
                  the cube label as the information to the right of the "Object" entry.
              </description>
          </parameter>
      </group>
  </groups>
</application>
